<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1750–1775</title>
                <title type="short">1750–1775</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1750" to="1775">1750–1775</date>: Diplomatic Struggles in the
                    Colonial Period</head>
                <p>Colonial era diplomacy focused on two issues: the European balance of power and
                    the colonists’ appropriation of land from the Native Americans. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="FrenchandIndianWar2.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>French and Indian War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Rivalry in Europe, between the French and the British in particular, often
                    influenced the course of events in their North American colonies.In an effort to
                    increase their political and economic power, the British and the French competed
                    to acquire the better share of the available land and control over the new
                    trading opportunities the colonies presented.</p>
                <p>At the same time, the European colonial governments tried to find ways to coexist
                    with the original inhabitants of North America, often making alliances with some
                    tribes while alienating others. Sometimes, as in the case of the French and
                    Indian War (which in Europe was referred to as the Seven Years’ War), European
                    politics regarding balances of power resulted in conflict in the colonies. As
                    wars in Europe became more heated, fighting broke out between the French and the
                    British in the American colonies. Both sides called upon Native American allies
                    to assist them, exacerbating tensions between the tribes, as well as tensions
                    between the tribes and colonists. Ultimately, the British Government found it
                    necessary to pour additional troops and resources into protecting its
                    possessions in the Americas and taxed their colonists to pay for these
                    resources. These taxes eventually became a rallying cry for the American
                    independence movement.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="incidents">
                <head>Incidents leading up to the French and Indian War, <date from="1753" to="1754"
                        >1753–54</date>
                </head>
                <p>The French and Indian War, the North American phase of the larger Seven Years’
                    War, began after a series of incidents in the upper Ohio River valley, which the
                    French and British governments both claimed as their territory. Military forces
                    assembled by both imperial powers built forts in the region and attempted to
                    capture each others’ forts. These skirmishes, which included an expedition led
                    by George Washington, ultimately led to the escalation of a wider, full-scale
                    war between Great Britain and France.</p>
                <p>Wanting to limit British influence along their frontier, the French built a
                    string of forts from <placeName>Lake Erie</placeName> towards the forks of the
                    Ohio (present-day Pittsburgh).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lakeerie.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Lake Erie, Pennsylvania</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Since the colony of Virginia also claimed this region, Virginian lieutenant
                    governor Robert Dinwiddie sent Major <persName>George Washington</persName> with
                    a small expedition to order the removal of the French forts in late 1753.
                    Washington arrived at Fort Le Boeuf, about 15 miles inland from present-day
                    Erie, Pennsylvania, and delivered his message. The commander of the fort,
                    Jacques Legardeur de Saint-Pierre, received Washington and his men courteously,
                    but denied the validity of English claims to the contested region. Washington
                    then returned hastily to Virginia, arriving in early 1754, and delivered the
                    French reply to Governor Dinwiddie. Dinwiddie and the legislature agreed that
                    French rejection of British demands constituted a hostile act, and that the
                    French must be driven from their frontier forts on British-claimed land.
                    Dinwiddie sent Captain William Trent of the Virginia militia to construct a fort
                    at the strategically important forks of the Ohio River and to convince the local
                    Indians to ally against the French. Dinwiddie also promoted Washington to the
                    rank of Lieutenant Colonel and ordered an expedition to compel the French to
                    surrender their forts.</p>
                <p>While French and British officials maneuvered military forces about, they also
                    attempted to curry favor with American Indians living in the region. The most
                    important group, the Mingoes, were part of the Iroquois Confederation, which was
                    allied with Great Britain. British officials claimed the Iroquois Confederacy
                    had granted a Native American named Tanaghrisson the title of ‘Half-King’ over
                    the Mingoes and other Native communities under Iroquois rule. However, many
                    Indians in the upper Ohio Valley were concerned about British colonists
                    encroaching upon their land, and did not acknowledge either British or Iroquois
                    authority. Although many of them also feared French power and bore grudges
                    against the French from previous wars, the Indians of the upper Ohio valley
                    believed a French alliance to be the lesser of two evils. Consequently, they
                    were amenable to supplying French forces with additional men and intelligence
                    about British movements.</p>
                <p>Aided by such reports, the French soon learned of the British fort that William
                    Trent and his small group of men were constructing, and French forces moved
                    swiftly to compel its surrender on April 17, 1754. The French destroyed the
                    unfinished fort, building in its place the much more formidable Fort
                    Duquesne.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fortduquesne.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Fort Duquesne</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Further south, <persName>George Washington</persName>, accompanied by
                    Tanaghrisson, surprised an encampment of French soldiers in southwestern
                    Pennsylvania on May 24, 1754. A brief fight ensued, and afterwards the wounded
                    French leader, Ensign Joseph de Jumonville, attempted to explain through
                    translators that the French expedition was on a peaceful mission to warn British
                    forces about their incursions into French-claimed territory. Although accounts
                    of the incident differ, it seems that Tanaghrisson, who bore an intense personal
                    hatred of the French stemming from earlier war experiences, intervened in the
                    negotiations and killed Jumonville. Expecting further French incursions,
                    Washington then hastily constructed a fort and prepared to defend his forces,
                    but a combined French and Indian force forced his surrender on July 3.</p>
                <p>Once he heard of Washington’s defeat, Lieutenant-Governor Dinwiddie immediately
                    passed on the news to his superiors in London and called for aid from
                    neighboring colonies. Only North Carolina responded, but refused to make any
                    expenditures outside its own borders. However, British Prime Minister Thomas
                    Pelham-Holles, Duke of Newcastle, reacted swiftly to the news, and planned a
                    quick strike against the French forts before they could be reinforced. King
                    George II approved Newcastle’s plan to send General Edward Braddock to quickly
                    seize French frontier forts.</p>
                <p>Other political leaders wanted a bigger war, and so they publicly announced
                    Newcastle’s plans and changed the original plan so that Braddock would command
                    more forces and order the fractious North American colonies to provide
                    additional support against the French. Once the plans had been publicly
                    announced, the French government moved quickly to dispatch reinforcements to
                    North America and further pursued negotiations to diplomatically isolate the
                    British government by winning over its traditional European allies. Once
                    military forces were under way, war was inevitable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="french-indian-war">
                <head>French and Indian War/Seven Years’ War, <date from="1754" to="1763"
                        >1754–63</date>
                </head>
                <p>The French and Indian War was the North American conflict in a larger imperial
                    war between Great Britain and France known as the Seven Years’ War. The French
                    and Indian War began in 1754 and ended with the Treaty of Paris in 1763. The war
                    provided Great Britain enormous territorial gains in North America, but disputes
                    over subsequent frontier policy and paying the war’s expenses led to colonial
                    discontent, and ultimately to the American Revolution.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="French_and_Indian_War_map.gif" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Map from the French and Indian War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The French and Indian War resulted from ongoing frontier tensions in North
                    America as both French and British imperial officials and colonists sought to
                    extend each country’s sphere of influence in frontier regions. In North America,
                    the war pitted France, French colonists, and their Native allies against Great
                    Britain, the Anglo-American colonists, and the Iroquois Confederacy, which
                    controlled most of upstate New York and parts of northern Pennsylvania. In 1753,
                    prior to the outbreak of hostilities, Great Britain controlled the 13 colonies
                    up to the Appalachian Mountains, but beyond lay New France, a very large,
                    sparsely settled colony that stretched from Louisiana through the Mississippi
                    Valley and Great Lakes to Canada. (See <ref
                        target="/milestones/1750-1775/incidents">Incidents Leading up to the French
                        and Indian War</ref> and <ref target="/milestones/1750-1775/albany-plan"
                        >Albany Plan</ref>)</p>
                <p>The border between French and British possessions was not well defined, and one
                    disputed territory was the upper Ohio River valley. The French had constructed a
                    number of forts in this region in an attempt to strengthen their claim on the
                    territory. British colonial forces, led by Lieutenant Colonel George Washington,
                    attempted to expel the French in 1754, but were outnumbered and defeated by the
                    French. When news of Washington’s failure reached British Prime Minister Thomas
                    Pelham-Holles, Duke of Newcastle, he called for a quick undeclared retaliatory
                    strike. However, his adversaries in the Cabinet outmaneuvered him by making the
                    plans public, thus alerting the French Government and escalating a distant
                    frontier skirmish into a full-scale war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ebraddock.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>General Edward Braddock</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The war did not begin well for the British. The British Government sent General
                    Edward Braddock to the colonies as commander in chief of British North American
                    forces, but he alienated potential Indian allies and colonial leaders failed to
                    cooperate with him. On July 13, 1755, Braddock died after being mortally wounded
                    in an ambush on a failed expedition to capture Fort Duquesne in present-day
                    Pittsburgh. The war in North America settled into a stalemate for the next
                    several years, while in Europe the French scored an important naval victory and
                    captured the British possession of Minorca in the Mediterranean in 1756.
                    However, after 1757 the war began to turn in favor of Great Britain. British
                    forces defeated French forces in India, and in 1759 British armies invaded and
                    conquered Canada.</p>
                <p>Facing defeat in North America and a tenuous position in Europe, the French
                    Government attempted to engage the British in peace negotiations, but British
                    Minister William Pitt (the elder), Secretary for Southern Affairs, sought not
                    only the French cession of Canada but also commercial concessions that the
                    French Government found unacceptable. After these negotiations failed, Spanish
                    King Charles III offered to come to the aid of his cousin, French King Louis XV,
                    and their representatives signed an alliance known as the Family Compact on
                    August 15, 1761. The terms of the agreement stated that Spain would declare war
                    on Great Britain if the war did not end before May 1, 1762. Originally intended
                    to pressure the British into a peace agreement, the Family Compact ultimately
                    reinvigorated the French will to continue the war, and caused the British
                    Government to declare war on Spain on January 4, 1762, after bitter infighting
                    among King George III’s ministers.</p>
                <p>Despite facing such a formidable alliance, British naval strength and Spanish
                    ineffectiveness led to British success. British forces seized French Caribbean
                    islands, Spanish Cuba, and the Philippines. Fighting in Europe ended after a
                    failed Spanish invasion of British ally Portugal. By 1763, French and Spanish
                    diplomats began to seek peace. In the resulting <ref
                        target="/milestones/1750-1775/treaty-of-paris">Treaty of Paris</ref> (1763),
                    Great Britain secured significant territorial gains in North America, including
                    all French territory east of the Mississippi river, as well as Spanish Florida,
                    although the treaty returned Cuba to Spain.</p>
                <p>Unfortunately for the British, the fruits of victory brought seeds of trouble
                    with Great Britain’s American colonies. The war had been enormously expensive,
                    and the British government’s attempts to impose taxes on colonists to help cover
                    these expenses resulted in increasing colonial resentment of British attempts to
                    expand imperial authority in the colonies. British attempts to limit western
                    expansion by colonists and inadvertent provocation of a major Indian war further
                    angered the British subjects living in the American colonies. These disputes
                    ultimately spurred colonial rebellion, which eventually developed into a
                    full-scale war for independence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="albany-plan">
                <head>Albany Plan of Union, <date when="1754">1754</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Albany Plan of Union was a plan to place the British North American colonies
                    under a more centralized government. On July 10, 1754, representatives from
                    seven of the British North American colonies adopted the plan. Although never
                    carried out, the Albany Plan was the first important proposal to conceive of the
                    colonies as a collective whole united under one government.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="albanyplan.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Cartoon originally appearing in Benjamin Franklin’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pennsylvania Gazette</hi> in 1754</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Representatives of the colonial governments adopted the Albany Plan during a
                    larger meeting known as the Albany Congress. The British Government in London
                    had ordered the colonial governments to meet in 1754, initially because of a
                    breakdown in negotiations between the colony of New York and the Mohawk nation,
                    which was part of the Iroquois Confederation. More generally, imperial officials
                    wanted a treaty between the colonies and the Iroquois that would articulate a
                    clear colonial-Indian relations policy. The colonial governments of Maryland,
                    Pennsylvania, New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island, Massachusetts and New
                    Hampshire all sent commissioners to the Congress. Although the treaty with the
                    Iroquois was the main purpose of the Congress, the delegates also met to discuss
                    intercolonial cooperation on other matters. With the French and Indian War
                    looming, the need for cooperation was urgent, especially for colonies likely to
                    come under attack or invasion.</p>
                <p>Prior to the Albany Congress, a number of intellectuals and government officials
                    had formulated and published several tentative plans for centralizing the
                    colonial governments of North America. Imperial officials saw the advantages of
                    bringing the colonies under closer authority and supervision, while colonists
                    saw the need to organize and defend common interests. One figure of emerging
                    prominence among this group of intellectuals was Pennsylvanian Benjamin
                    Franklin. Earlier, Franklin had written to friends and colleagues proposing a
                    plan of voluntary union for the colonies. Upon hearing of the Albany Congress,
                    his newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The Pennsylvania Gazette</hi>, published the
                    political cartoon "Join or Die," which illustrated the importance of union by
                    comparing the colonies to pieces of a snake’s body. The Pennsylvania government
                    appointed Franklin as a commissioner to the Congress, and on his way, Franklin
                    wrote to several New York commissioners outlining ‘short hints towards a scheme
                    for uniting the Northern Colonies’ by means of an act of the British
                    Parliament.</p>
                <p>The Albany Congress began on June 19, 1754, and the commissioners voted
                    unanimously to discuss the possibility of union on June 24. The union committee
                    submitted a draft of the plan on June 28, and commissioners debated aspects of
                    it until they adopted a final version on July 10.</p>
                <p>Although only seven colonies sent commissioners, the plan proposed the union of
                    all the British colonies except for Georgia and Delaware. The colonial
                    governments were to select members of a "Grand Council," while the British
                    Government would appoint a "president General." Together, these two branches of
                    the unified government would regulate colonial-Indian relations and also resolve
                    territorial disputes between the colonies. Acknowledging the tendency of royal
                    colonial governors to override colonial legislatures and pursue unpopular
                    policies, the Albany Plan gave the Grand Council greater relative authority. The
                    plan also allowed the new government to levy taxes for its own support.</p>
                <p>Despite the support of many colonial leaders, the plan, as formulated at Albany,
                    did not become a reality. Colonial governments, sensing that it would curb their
                    own authority and territorial rights, either rejected the plan or chose not to
                    act on it at all. The British Government had already dispatched General Edward
                    Braddock as military commander in chief along with two commissioners to handle
                    Indian relations, and believed that directives from London would suffice in the
                    management of colonial affairs.</p>
                <p>The Albany Plan was not conceived out of a desire to secure independence from
                    Great Britain. Many colonial commissioners actually wished to increase imperial
                    authority in the colonies. Its framers saw it instead as a means to reform
                    colonial-imperial relationsand to recognize that the colonies collectively
                    shared certain common interests. However, the colonial governments’ own fears of
                    losing power, territory, and commerce, both to other colonies and to the British
                    Parliament, ensured the Albany Plan’s failure.</p>
                <p>Despite the failure of the Albany Plan, it served as a model for future attempts
                    at union: it attempted to establish the division between the executive and
                    legislative branches of government, while establishing a common governmental
                    authority to deal with external relations. More importantly, it conceived of the
                    colonies of mainland North America as a collective unit, separate not only from
                    the mother country, but also from the other British colonies in the West Indies
                    and elsewhere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaty-of-paris">
                <head>Treaty of Paris, <date when="1763">1763</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Treaty of Paris of 1763 ended the French and Indian War/Seven Years’ War
                    between Great Britain and France, as well as their respective allies. In the
                    terms of the treaty, France gave up all its territories in mainland North
                    America, effectively ending any foreign military threat to the British colonies
                    there.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="treaty1763.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Treaty of Paris, 1763</head>
                </figure>
                <p>During the war, British forces had scored important overseas victories against
                    France: not only had the British conquered French Canada, they also won
                    victories in India, and captured French island colonies in the Caribbean. In
                    March of 1762, French King Louis XV issued a formal call for peace talks.</p>
                <p>The British Government was also interested in ending the war. The Seven Years’
                    War had been enormously expensive, and the Government had to finance the war
                    with debt. Creditors were beginning to doubt Great Britain’s ability to pay back
                    the loans it had floated on financial markets. In addition, British King George
                    II had died in 1760, and his successor George III was more amenable to ending
                    the war.</p>
                <p>Initial attempts at negotiating a peace settlement failed, and instead French and
                    Spanish diplomats signed the Family Compact, a treaty that brought Spain into
                    the war against Britain. British Prime Minister Lord Bute continued secret and
                    informal talks with French diplomat Étienne-François de Stainville, duc de
                    Choiseul, and they came to an unofficial agreement in June, 1762. Bute promised
                    fairly generous terms, and the two countries agreed to an exchange of
                    ambassadors in September.</p>
                <p>By the time the formal negotiations began, the situation had changed. News had
                    reached Europe of the British capture of Havana, and with it the Spanish colony
                    of Cuba. Spanish King Charles III refused to agree to a treaty that would
                    require Spain to cede Cuba, but the British Parliament would never ratify a
                    treaty that did not reflect British territorial gains made during the war.</p>
                <p>Facing this dilemma, French negotiator Choiseul proposed a solution that
                    redistributed American territory between France, Spain and Great Britain. Under
                    Choiseul’s plan, Britain would gain all French territory east of the
                    Mississippi, while Spain would retain Cuba in exchange for handing Florida over
                    to Great Britain. French territories west of the Mississippi would become
                    Spanish, along with the port of New Orleans. In return for these cessions, along
                    with territory in India, Africa, and the Mediterranean island of Minorca, France
                    would regain the Caribbean islands that British forces had captured during the
                    war. The British Government also promised to allow French Canadians to freely
                    practice Catholicism and provided for French fishing rights off
                    Newfoundland.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="etienne.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>French diplomat Étienne-François de Stainville, duc de Choiseul</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Choiseul preferred to keep the small Caribbean islands of Martinique, Guadeloupe,
                    and St. Lucia rather than hold on to the vast territory stretching from
                    Louisiana to Canada. This decision was motivated by the fact that the islands’
                    sugar industry was enormously profitable. In contrast, Canada had been a drain
                    on the French treasury. The loss of Canada, while lamentable to French
                    officials, made sense from a mercantile perspective.</p>
                <p>The diplomats completed their negotiations and signed the preliminary Treaty of
                    Paris on November 3, 1762. Spanish and French negotiators also signed the Treaty
                    of San Ildefonso at the same time, which confirmed the cession of French
                    Louisiana to Spain.</p>
                <p>Although British King George III and his ministers were in favor of the treaty,
                    it was unpopular with the British public. However, the treaty contained enough
                    concessions to war hawks that the British Parliament ratified the Treaty of
                    Paris by a majority of 319 to 64, and the treaty went into effect on February
                    10, 1763.</p>
                <p>For Anglo-American colonists, the treaty was a theoretical success. By confirming
                    the conquest of Canada and extending British possessions to the Mississippi, the
                    colonists no longer had to worry about the threat of a French invasion. For the
                    American Indians in what had been frontier territory, the treaty proved
                    disastrous. They could no longer pursue what had been a largely effective
                    strategy of playing the French and British against each other to extract the
                    most favorable terms of alliance and preserve their lands against encroachment
                    by Anglo-American colonists.</p>
                <p>Despite what seemed like a success, the Treaty of Paris ultimately encouraged
                    dissension between Anglo-American colonists and the British Government because
                    their interests in North America no longer coincided. The British Government no
                    longer wanted to maintain an expensive military presence, and its attempts to
                    manage a post-treaty frontier policy that would balance colonists’ and Indians’
                    interests would prove ineffective and even counterproductive. Coupled with
                    differences between the imperial government and colonists on how to levy taxes
                    to pay for debts on wartime expenses, the Treaty of Paris ultimately set the
                    colonists on the path towards seeking independence, even as it seemed to make
                    the British Empire stronger than ever. (see Parliamentary Taxation of
                    Colonies)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="parliamentary-taxation">
                <head>Parliamentary taxation of colonies, international trade, and the American
                    Revolution, <date from="1763" to="1775">1763–1775</date>
                </head>
                <p>The American Revolution was precipitated, in part, by a series of laws passed
                    between 1763 and 1775 that regulating trade and taxes. This legislation caused
                    tensions between colonists and imperial officials, who made it clear that the
                    British Parliament would not address American complaints that the new laws were
                    onerous. British unwillingness to respond to American demands for change allowed
                    colonists to argue that they were part of an increasingly corrupt and autocratic
                    empire in which their traditional liberties were threatened. This position
                    eventually served as the basis for the colonial <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">Declaration of
                    Independence</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bostonteaparty.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Boston Tea Party</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1763, the British government emerged from the Seven Years’ War burdened by
                    heavy debts. This led British Prime Minister <persName>George
                        Grenville</persName> to reduce duties on sugar and molasses but also to
                    enforce the law more strictly. Since enforcement of these duties had previously
                    been lax, this ultimately increased revenue for the British Government and
                    served to increase the taxes paid by the colonists. The colonial governments of
                    New York and Massachusetts sent formal letters of protest to Parliament.</p>
                <p>The end of the war had also brought about a postwar recession, and British
                    merchants began to request payment for debts that colonists had incurred buying
                    British imports. Moreover, they wanted payment in British pounds sterling rather
                    than colonial currency of more questionable value. The result was that the
                    British Parliament passed the 1764 Currency Act which forbade the colonies from
                    issuing paper currency. This made it even more difficult for colonists to pay
                    their debts and taxes.</p>
                <p>Soon after Parliament passed the Currency Act, Prime Minister Grenville proposed
                    a Stamp Tax. This law would require colonists to purchase a government-issued
                    stamp for legal documents and other paper goods. Grenville submitted the bill to
                    Parliament for questioning, and only one member raised objections to
                    Parliament’s right to tax the colonies.</p>
                <p>After news of the successful passage of the Stamp Act reached the colonies, the
                    Virginia House of Burgesses passed resolutions denying the British Parliament’s
                    authority to tax the colonies. In Boston, colonists rioted and destroyed the
                    house of the stamp distributor. News of these protests inspired similar
                    activities and protests in other colonies, and thus the Stamp Act served as a
                    common cause to unite the 13 colonies in opposition to the British Parliament.
                    In October of 1765, delegates from 9 colonies met to issue petitions to the
                    British Government denying Parliament’s authority to tax the colonies. An
                    American boycott of British goods, coupled with recession, also led British
                    merchants to lobby for the act’s repeal on pragmatic economic grounds. Under
                    pressure from American colonists and British merchants, the British Government
                    decided it was easier to repeal the Stamp Act than to enforce it.</p>
                <p>The repeal of the Stamp Act temporarily quieted colonial protest, but there was
                    renewed resistance to new taxes instituted in 1767 under the Townshend Acts.
                    However, in 1773, the colonists staged more vocal widespread protests against
                    the British Parliament’s decision to grant the East India Company a monopoly on
                    the tax-free transport of tea. Although Parliament did lower taxes levied on
                    other tea importers, the tax-free status of the British East India Company meant
                    that colonial tea traders could not compete. Enraged colonists responded by
                    encouraging a general boycott of British goods. On December 16, 1773, American
                    colonists disguised as Indians boarded East India Company ships in Boston Harbor
                    and threw crates of tea overboard. This famous protest came to be known as the
                    Boston Tea Party.</p>
                <p>When news of the Tea Party reached England, British officials moved to enforce
                    discipline and order in the colonies. The British Government ordered the closure
                    of the port of Boston until the East India Company was compensated for the
                    destroyed tea. Parliament also passed several pieces of legislation in 1774
                    which attempted to place Massachusetts under direct British control. In the
                    American colonies, these laws were referred to as the Intolerable Acts. British
                    control was further solidified by the appointment of General Thomas Gage as
                    military governor of Massachusetts.</p>
                <p>By 1774, opinion among the colonists was mixed. Some Bostonians felt that the
                    time had come to ease tensions and sent to London a written offer to pay for the
                    destroyed tea. Others put out a colony-wide call for a boycott. However, many
                    colonial merchants were reluctant to participate in a difficult-to-enforce
                    boycott. Despite this disagreement, most colonists agreed that a meeting to
                    discuss an appropriate collective response to British actions was a good idea.
                    Colonial legislatures sent representatives to Philadelphia, and the First
                    Continental Congress convened in September of 1774. The Continental Congress
                    agreed to the Articles of Association on October 20. These Articles listed
                    colonial grievances and called for a locally-enforced boycott in all the
                    colonies to take effect on December 1. The delegates also drafted a petition to
                    King George III laying out their grievances, although by then they doubted that
                    the crisis would be resolved peacefully.</p>
                <p>Realizing that further coercive steps would only enrage the colonists and might
                    lead to war, British military governor Gage wrote to London recommending
                    suspension of the Intolerable Acts. Gage hoped to appease many of the colonists
                    and thereby split colonial moderates from radicals. If London was not amenable
                    to his recommendations, Gage stated that he would need significant
                    reinforcements to crush the growing rebellion.</p>
                <p>British ministers responded to Gage’s suggestions by removing him from his post.
                    They felt that further punitive measures were necessary and pushed Parliament to
                    pass additional trade restrictions on New England. London declared the colonies
                    to be in rebellion, but also offered to stop taxing those colonies that
                    supported the British Government.</p>
                <p>By this time, the most astute leaders from both sides viewed armed conflict as
                    inevitable. Gage’s attempts to secure his position in Boston only brought him
                    into conflict with local militias and a hostile populace, and it was only a
                    matter of time until open war began in 1775. The opportunity for peaceful
                    negotiation came to an end, and the war for American Independence began on April
                    19, 1775 when British troops and American colonists clashed at Lexington and
                    Concord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="proclamation-line-1763">
                <head>Proclamation Line of <date when="1763">1763</date>, Quebec Act of <date
                        when="1774">1774</date> and Westward Expansion</head>
                <p>The British won vast territory in North America after the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1750-1775/french-indian-war">Seven Years’ War</ref>, but
                    with the land came numerous problems of how to govern it. Conflicts arose from
                    the inability of British officials to balance the interests of colonists and
                    Indians, which led to colonial dissatisfaction with imperial rule and,
                    ultimately, to the causes of the American Revolution.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="1763line.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Proclamation Line of 1763—between the red colored colonies and the
                        pink territories</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Treaty of Paris of 1763 that ended the Seven Years’ War provided Great
                    Britain with enormous territorial gains. Under the treaty, Canada and the entire
                    present-day United States east of the Mississippi came under British control.
                    With the official end of the war, Anglo-American colonists began to pour over
                    the Appalachian Mountains in search of land. As the native population had made
                    no land cessions, many of these settlers had no official claim to the land. In
                    many cases, the land was claimed by private land companies, in which the
                    Virginia elite had invested heavily in an attempt to diversify their holdings
                    outside of the volatile tobacco market. Thus, they had an interest in pressing
                    the British Government to address ensuing tensions.</p>
                <p>The settlement of the lands west of the Appalachians brought inevitable tension
                    and conflict between settlers and indigenous peoples. British military officials
                    attempted to halt settlement, but eager settlers and land speculators ignored
                    their directives. With the military unwilling to forcibly remove settlers from
                    the lands, Anglo-American colonists continued to migrate west and lay claim
                    these lands.</p>
                <p>British officials made the situation worse by alienating American Indians who had
                    been allied with France during the Seven Years’ War. The French Government had
                    devoted significant resources to furnishing gifts to their Indian allies. When
                    British forces arrived to take over former French forts, they halted the
                    gift-giving practice, not realizing that doing so undercut the authority of any
                    pro-British leaders within indigenous communities and antagonized the Indian
                    leaders.</p>
                <p>In response to British actions and western settlement, the leader of the Ottawa
                    tribe, Pontiac, sent messages encoded in wampum belts to other communities
                    throughout the present-day Midwest to coordinate an attack on British forts.
                    Unaware of the depth of Indian anger and resentment, British forces were caught
                    largely by surprise and lost all their western forts except for Fort Pitt and
                    Detroit, where British military officials were tipped off and, therefore, able
                    to prevent seizure.</p>
                <p>When news of the rebellion reached London, the government decided to put into
                    action a plan for creating a western Indian reserve, and produced the Royal
                    Proclamation of 1763, which forbid colonial settlement beyond the line of the
                    Appalachian Mountains. The act also created the provinces of Quebec, West
                    Florida, and East Florida. The proclamation was largely ineffective in
                    preventing western settlement, and served only to anger both settlers and the
                    political elite who had invested in western land speculation.</p>
                <p>War with the Indian tribes continued from 1764 into 1766. British officials
                    managed to negotiate peace with the Senecas in the Niagara region and with
                    Indians in the upper Ohio River valley, and, in 1766, Pontiac agreed to a formal
                    treaty signed at Fort Ontario on July 25. Pontiac’s War is diplomatically
                    significant because it was the first war between European settlers and American
                    Indians where Indians had united broadly across tribal lines.</p>
                <p>After the end of Pontiac’s rebellion, regulation of the western frontier was not
                    significantly altered until Parliament passed the Quebec Act of 1774. With this
                    piece of legislation, the British intended to preempt any dissatisfaction among
                    the French Canadian population by restoring French civil law and allowing
                    Catholics to hold office. It also imposed direct crown rule on Quebec and
                    extended Quebec’s borders south to the Ohio River.</p>
                <p>The Quebec Act angered the Virginia elite, since most of the western lands they
                    claimed were now officially part of Quebec or in the Indian reserve. The act,
                    which Parliament passed at the same time as legislation placing Massachusetts
                    under crown control, also fueled resentment among Calvinist New Englanders, who
                    saw in its autocratic, pro-Catholic provisions further evidence of an imperial
                    conspiracy against colonial liberties.</p>
                <p>When the American Revolution began in 1774, tensions between settlers and Indians
                    became a part of the conflict. The Continental Congress’s attempts to secure
                    Indian alliances largely failed, as most Indians saw the British military as the
                    lesser of two evils in their struggle against settlers’ encroachments upon their
                    land. However, the Oneida and Tuscarora Nations of the Iroquois Confederacy did
                    side with the colonists.</p>
                <p>The ultimate effect of British frontier policy was to unite frontiersmen,
                    Virginia land speculators, and New Englanders against unpopular British
                    policies. These groups, angered by British taxation policies, forged
                    revolutionary alliances with other colonists. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
