<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1776–1783</title>
                <title type="short">1776–1783</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1776" to="1783">1776–1783</date>: Diplomacy and the American
                    Revolution</head>
                <p>In the 1770s, the increasingly defiant American colonies began to work toward
                    political independence from the British Government.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="yorktown.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>General George Washington at Yorktown</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Tensions continued to escalate until, in 1775, armed conflict erupted. The
                    colonists, who were economically dependent on Europe, recognized that European
                    nations were unlikely to conclude trade agreements with the Americans unless
                    they declared their independence. The <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/continental-congress">U.S. Continental
                        Congress</ref> endorsed <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName>’s <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">Declaration of Independence</ref>
                    on July 4, 1776, and, with the endorsement of this document, the conflict with
                    Great Britain became a full-fledged War of Independence.</p>
                <p>Unable to defeat the strong British military on their own, the American colonists
                    required foreign assistance. <persName>John Adams</persName> approached the
                    French with the “<ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/model-treaty">Model
                        Treaty</ref>,” which protected neutral trade and shipping rights in the
                    event of a war. The French decision to sign this commercial treaty with the
                    American colonists made France an implicit ally in the war against Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>In 1778, France formally established its position as an ally with a treaty of
                    alliance that committed the French to the war on the condition that the
                    Americans did not seek a separate peace with Great Britain. Following the
                    British surrender at the Battle of Yorktown, the Americans negotiated
                    independently with Great Britain despite their agreement with France. The war
                    was not officially concluded, however, until the agreement to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty of Paris</ref> in 1783, which
                    was signed in concert with treaties between Great Britain, France, and Spain.
                    The final treaty granted full independence and recognized the borders of the new
                        <placeName>United States of America</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="continental-congress">
                <head>Continental Congress, <date from="1774" to="1781">1774–1781</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Continental Congress was the governing body by which the American colonial
                    governments coordinated their resistance to British rule during the first two
                    years of the American Revolution. The Congress balanced the interests of the
                    different colonies and also established itself as the official colonial liaison
                    to <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>. As the war progressed, the Congress
                    became the effective national government of the country, and, as such, conducted
                    diplomacy on behalf of the new United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="continentalcongress.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Continental Congress </head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1774, the British Parliament passed a series of laws collectively known as the
                    Intolerable Acts, with the intent to suppress unrest in colonial Boston by
                    closing the port and placing it under martial law. In response, colonial
                    protestors led by a group called the Sons of Liberty issued a call for a
                    boycott. Merchant communities were reluctant to participate in such a boycott
                    unless there were mutually agreed upon terms and a means to enforce the
                    boycott’s provisions. Spurred by local pressure groups, colonial legislatures
                    empowered delegates to attend a Continental Congress which would set terms for a
                    boycott. The colony of Connecticut was the first to respond.</p>
                <p>The Congress first met in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> on September 5,
                    1774, with delegates from each of the 13 colonies except Georgia. On October 20,
                    the Congress adopted the Articles of Association, which stated that if the
                    Intolerable Acts were not repealed by December 1, 1774, a boycott of British
                    goods would begin in the colonies. The Articles also outlined plans for an
                    embargo on exports if the Intolerable Acts were not repealed before September
                    10, 1775.</p>
                <p>On October 21, the delegates approved separate statements for the people of Great
                    Britain and the North American colonies, explaining the colonial position, and
                    on October 26 a similar address was approved for the people of Quebec.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, on October 26, the delegates drafted a formal petition outlining the
                    colonists' grievances for British King <persName>George III</persName>. Many
                    delegates were skeptical about changing the king’s attitude towards the
                    colonies, but believed that every opportunity should be exhausted to de-escalate
                    the conflict before taking more radical action. They did not draft such a letter
                    to the British Parliament as the colonists viewed the Parliament as the
                    aggressor behind the recent Intolerable Acts. Lastly, not fully expecting the
                    standoff in Massachusetts to explode into full-scale war, the Congress agreed to
                    reconvene in Philadelphia on May 10, 1775.</p>
                <p>By the time Congress met again, war was already underway, and thus the delegates
                    to the Second Continental Congress formed the Continental army and dispatched
                    George Washington to Massachusetts as its commander. Meanwhile, Congress drafted
                    the Olive Branch Petition, which attempted to suggest means of resolving
                    disputes between the colonies and Great Britain. Congress sent the petition to
                    King <persName>George III</persName> on July 8, but he refused to receive
                    it.</p>
                <p>As British authority crumbled in the colonies, the Continental Congress
                    effectively took over as the de facto national government, thereby exceeding the
                    initial authority granted to it by the individual colonial governments. However,
                    the local groups that had formed to enforce the colonial boycott continued to
                    support the Congress. The Second Congress continued to meet until March 1, 1781,
                    when the Articles of Confederation that established a new national government
                    for the United States took effect.</p>
                <p>As the de facto national government, the Continental Congress assumed the role of
                    negotiating diplomatic agreements with foreign nations. The British Parliament
                    the British Parliament banned trade with the colonies and authorized the seizure
                    of colonial vessels on December 23. These actions served to further erode the
                    positions of anti-independence moderates in Congress and bolster those of
                    pro-independence leaders. On April 6, 1776, Congress responded to Parliament's
                    actions by opening American ports to all foreign ships except British vessels.
                    Reports from American agent <persName>Arthur Lee</persName> in London also
                    served to support the revolutionary cause. Lee’s reports suggested that France
                    was interested in assisting the colonies in their fight against Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <p>With a peaceful resolution increasingly unlikely in 1775, Congress began to
                    explore other diplomatic channels and dispatched congressional delegate
                        <persName>Silas Deane</persName> to France in April of 1776.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="deane.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Silas Deane</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Deane succeeded in securing informal French support by May. By then, Congress was
                    increasingly conducting international diplomacy and had drafted the Model Treaty
                    with which it hoped to seek alliances with Spain and France. On July 4, 1776 the
                    Congress took the important step of <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">formally declaring the colonies’
                        independence from Great Britain</ref>. In September, Congress adopted the
                    Model Treaty, and then sent commissioners to France to negotiate a formal
                    alliance. They entered into a a formal alliance with France in 1778. Congress
                    eventually sent diplomats to other European powers to encourage support for the
                    American cause and to secure loans for the money-strapped war effort.</p>
                <p>Congress and the British government made further attempts to reconcile, but
                    negotiations failed when Congress refused to revoke the Declaration of
                    Independence, both in a meeting on September 11, 1776, with British Admiral
                        <persName>Richard Howe</persName>, and when a peace delegation from
                    Parliament arrived in Philadelphia in 1778. Instead, Congress spelled out terms
                    for peace on August 14, 1779, which demanded British withdrawal, American
                    independence, and navigation rights on the Mississippi River. The next month
                    Congress appointed <persName>John Adams</persName> to negotiate such terms with
                    England, but British officials were evasive.</p>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Formal peace negotiations</ref> would
                    have to wait until after the Confederation Congress took over the reins of
                    government on March 1, 1781, following American victories at Yorktown that
                    resulted in British willingness to end the war. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="secret-committee">
                <head>Secret Committee of Correspondence/ Committee for Foreign Affairs, <date
                        from="1775" to="1777">1775–1777</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Continental Congress established the Committee of Secret Correspondence to
                    communicate with sympathetic Britons and other Europeans early in the American
                    Revolution. The committee coordinated diplomatic functions for the Continental
                    Congress and directed transatlantic communication and public relations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bfranklin.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Benjamin Franklin</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Congress initially established the Committee of Correspondence on November 29,
                    1775, to communicate with colonial agents in Britain and “friends in ... other
                    parts of the world.” On the committee were <persName>Benjamin
                        Franklin</persName>, Benjamin Harrison, Thomas Johnson, <persName>John
                        Dickinson</persName>, and <persName>John Jay</persName>. <persName>Robert
                        Morris</persName>, revolutionary financier, soon joined them. Congress
                    granted the committee extensive authority to conduct international diplomacy,
                    including the negotiation of clandestine shipments of arms and other similar
                    activities. Owing to the nature of the correspondence, the members began to add
                    the word “secret” to the committee’s title, and soon it was known as the
                    Committee of Secret Correspondence. The Committee's diplomatic duties grew, and
                    Congress renamed it the Committee for Foreign Affairs on April 17, 1777.</p>
                <p>Of the initial members of the committee, Benjamin Franklin was the most active.
                    Drawing on his extensive European contacts, he began a campaign to rally
                    international support of the American cause. On December 12, 1775, Franklin
                    wrote to Don Gabriel de Bourbon, a prince of the Spanish royal family and one of
                    Franklin's scholarly associates. In his letter, Franklin strongly hinted at the
                    advantages of a Spanish alliance with the American revolutionaries. Franklin
                    dispatched similar letters to American sympathizers in France. He sent these
                    letters through associates whom he trusted to protect the communications from
                    interception by the British.</p>
                <p><persName>Arthur Lee</persName>, a Virginian living in London, also aided the
                    Committee. Congress would later officially appoint Lee as a commissioner for the
                    Committee. Lee had come into contact with the French playwright Beaumarchais,
                    who was then working as a secret French agent investigating British troubles in
                    the colonies. Lee provided Beaumarchais with information about American
                    successes that influenced the French Foreign Minister Charles Gravier, comte de
                    Vergennes, to provide the colonies with clandestine shipments of gunpowder and
                    war materiel.</p>
                <p>The Committee of Correspondence also worked on American soil. In late 1775, a
                    mysterious French traveler named Achard de Bonvouloir appeared in Philadelphia.
                    He had been dispatched by the French Government to contact the Continental
                    Congress, but publicly disavowed any such mission. The committee made contact
                    with him, and Franklin convinced Bonvouloir that the colonies were seeking
                    independence and were unlikely to reconcile with Britain. Franklin encouraged
                    this representative of the French Government to report to his government that
                    France should seek an alliance with the colonies once they declared their
                    independence, and in the meantime provide the colonies with secret
                    assistance.</p>
                <p> Thereafter, the Committee continued to correspond with Lee in London, and, after
                    Congress appointed them in the fall of 1776, also with the commissioners in
                    France. As the British Navy tightened its blockade, however, communication
                    became increasingly difficult, especially after British forces seized
                    Philadelphia in 1777. Once France formally signed an alliance with the United
                    States in 1778, communications improved. With the alliance also came more duties
                    for the Committee and the appointment of French Minister to the United States,
                    Conrad-Alexandre Gérard de Rayneval.</p>
                <p>The Committee also facilitated decisions to solve infighting among the American
                    commissioners in Europe who clashed on financial matters. Lee suspected the
                    early colonial agent in France, Silas Deane, of financial malfeasance and began
                    a campaign to bring about his recall. Thomas Paine, who had become secretary of
                    the Committee, sympathized with Lee. Paine published anonymous pamphlets in
                    which he claimed that Congress possessed documentation of secret French aid that
                    would affirm Lee’s version of events. French Minister Gérard intervened,
                    explaining to the committee that France could not formally admit to providing
                    such aid without risking war with Britain, which it was not ready to do.
                    Congress passed a resolution denying that there had been French aid on January
                    12, 1778.</p>
                <p>The Committee continued to coordinate communication between Congress and
                    diplomats in Europe, and sent more representatives to other European courts to
                    encourage their assistance to the American cause. However, by 1780, an
                    overworked Congress had many more duties, and members of the Committee for
                    Foreign Affairs had begun to neglect their duties. Committee member James Lovell
                    wrote to Arthur Lee and John Jay suggesting that Congress establish a Department
                    of Foreign Affairs to handle the day-to-day business of foreign diplomacy.
                    Congressman James Duane also agreed. The committee members brought the
                    suggestion before Congress, and Congress ultimately decided to create a a
                    committee for the establishment of executive departments. Congress finally
                    agreed to establish departments on February 6, 1781, but it was not until August
                    10 that the new Confederation Congress elected Robert Livingston as Secretary
                    for Foreign Affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="declaration">
                <head>The Declaration of Independence, <date when="1776">1776</date>
                </head>
                <p>By issuing the Declaration of Independence, adopted by the Continental Congress
                    on July 4, 1776, the 13 American colonies severed their political connections to
                    Great Britain. The Declaration summarized the colonists’ motivations for seeking
                    independence. By declaring themselves an independent nation, the American
                    colonists were able to confirm an official alliance with the Government of
                    France and obtain French assistance in the war against Great Britain.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="declaration_independence.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Declaration of Independence</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Throughout the 1760s and early 1770s, the North American colonists found
                    themselves increasingly at odds with British imperial policies regarding <ref
                        target="/milestones/1750-1775/parliamentary-taxation">taxation</ref> and
                        <ref target="/milestones/1750-1775/proclamation-line-1763">frontier
                        policy</ref>. When repeated protests failed to influence British policies,
                    and instead resulted in the closing of the port of Boston and the declaration of
                    martial law in <placeName>Massachusetts</placeName>, the colonial governments
                    sent delegates to a <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/continental-congress"
                        >Continental Congress</ref> to coordinate a colonial boycott of British
                    goods. When fighting broke out between American colonists and British forces in
                    Massachusetts, the Continental Congress worked with local groups, originally
                    intended to enforce the boycott, to coordinate resistance against the British.
                    British officials throughout the colonies increasingly found their authority
                    challenged by informal local governments, although loyalist sentiment remained
                    strong in some areas.</p>
                <p>Despite these changes, colonial leaders hoped to reconcile with the British
                    Government, and all but the most radical members of Congress were unwilling to
                    declare independence. However, in late 1775, Benjamin Franklin, then a member of
                    the Secret Committee of Correspondence, hinted to French agents and other
                    European sympathizers that the colonies were increasingly leaning towards
                    seeking independence. While perhaps true, Franklin also hoped to convince the
                    French to supply the colonists with aid. Independence would be necessary,
                    however, before French officials would consider the possibility of an
                    alliance.</p>
                <p>Throughout the winter of 1775–1776, the members of the Continental Congress came
                    to view reconciliation with Britain as unlikely, and independence the only
                    course of action available to them. When on December 22, 1775, the British
                    Parliament prohibited trade with the colonies, Congress responded in April of
                    1776 by opening colonial ports—this was a major step towards severing ties with
                    Britain. The colonists were aided by the January publication of <persName>Thomas
                        Paine</persName>’s pamphlet <hi rend="italic">Common Sense</hi>, which
                    advocated the colonies’ independence and was widely distributed throughout the
                    colonies. By February of 1776, colonial leaders were discussing the possibility
                    of forming foreign alliances and began to draft the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/model-treaty">Model Treaty</ref> that would
                    serve as a basis for the 1778 alliance with France. Leaders for the cause of
                    independence wanted to make certain that they had sufficient congressional
                    support before they would bring the issue to the vote. On June 7, 1776,
                        <persName>Richard Henry Lee</persName> introduced a motion in Congress to
                    declare independence. Other members of Congress were amenable but thought some
                    colonies not quite ready. However, Congress did form a committee to draft a
                    declaration of independence and assigned this duty to <persName>Thomas
                        Jefferson</persName>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="thomaspaine.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Thomas Paine</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <persName>Benjamin Franklin</persName> and <persName>John Adams</persName>
                    reviewed Jefferson’s draft. They preserved its original form, but struck
                    passages likely to meet with controversy or skepticism, most notably passages
                    blaming King <persName>George III</persName> for the transatlantic slave trade
                    and those blaming the British people rather than their government. The committee
                    presented the final draft before Congress on June 28, 1776, and Congress adopted
                    the final text of the Declaration of Independence on July 4.</p>
                <p>The British Government did its best to dismiss the Declaration as a trivial
                    document issued by disgruntled colonists. British officials commissioned
                    propagandists to highlight the declaration’s flaws and to rebut the colonists’
                    complaints. The Declaration divided British domestic opposition, as some
                    American sympathizers thought the Declaration had gone too far, but in
                    British-ruled Ireland it had many supporters.</p>
                <p>The Declaration’s most important diplomatic effect was to allow for recognition
                    of the United States by friendly foreign governments. The Sultan of Morocco
                    mentioned American ships in a consular document in 1777, but Congress had to
                    wait until the 1778 Treaty of Alliance with France for a formal recognition of
                    U.S. independence. The Netherlands acknowledged U.S. independence in 1782.
                    Although Spain joined the war against Great Britain in 1779, it did not
                    recognize U.S. independence until the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty"
                        >1783 Treaty of Paris</ref>. Under the terms of the treaty, which ended the
                    War of the American Revolution, Great Britain officially acknowledged the United
                    States as a sovereign and independent nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="model-treaty">
                <head>The Model Treaty, <date when="1776">1776</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Model Treaty was a template for commercial treaties that the United States
                    Continental Congress sought to make with <placeName>France</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Spain</placeName> in order to secure assistance in the struggle
                    against the British in the American Revolution. Congress approved the treaty on
                    September 17, 1776. The Model Treaty did not contain provisions for direct
                    military support, but rather for the supply of weapons and other indirect
                    assistance, in addition to favorable commercial terms. The Treaty of Amity and
                    Commerce that the United States and France concluded in 1778 was based on this
                    treaty and was signed concurrently with the Treaty of Alliance that included
                    provisions of a military nature. The Model Treaty also served as a template for
                    further commercial treaties the United States would make in the coming
                    years.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="francespain.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>19th Century Map of France and Spain</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As the delegates to the Continental Congress became more amenable to declaring
                    independence, they considered forging foreign alliances to assist in the
                    struggle. Virginia delegate George Wythe originally advanced the suggestion of
                    seeking a foreign alliance in early 1776, and the idea was referred to
                    committee. This suggestion inspired other leading statesmen, including
                    Massachusetts delegate <persName>John Adams</persName>. Adams noted the
                    advantages of trade with France in his diary in February and March of 1776, and
                    speculated that a separation of the colonies from Great Britain would be
                    advantageous to France. Between March and April, Adams drafted a preliminary
                    version of the Model Treaty in his diary. As an example, he outlined conditions
                    for an alliance between France and the not-yet-independent colonies. In this
                    draft, the United States was to accept no troops from France, nor submit to
                    French authority, but only to present commercial terms.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="johnadams.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>John Adams</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Adams presented a more formal draft of a general model treaty before the
                    Continental Congress on July 18, 1776. The template treaty sought reciprocal
                    trade terms, although not free trade, and made no mention of direct military
                    assistance. Congress adopted a formal version of the Model Treaty on September
                    17. On September 24, Congress drafted instructions to commissioners on how to
                    negotiate a treaty with France based on the template provided in the Model
                    Treaty. The commissioners were also instructed to seek a most-favored-nation
                    trade clause in the absence of the slightly more liberal trade clauses of the
                    Model Treaty, which could be construed as seeking a free trade agreement between
                    the two countries. The commissioners were to seek additional military aid, and
                    also to assure any Spanish diplomats present that the United States had no
                    designs on Spanish territory—Spain was a traditional ally of France and would
                    join the war in the hopes of regaining territories lost in earlier wars and in
                    the interest of maintaining a secure frontier on the northern border of its
                    American Empire. The Congress then appointed commissioners to execute the terms
                    on September 25.</p>
                <p>The United States would have to wait until early 1778 for France to formally
                    agree to a treaty. The formal treaty differed from the Model Treaty in that the
                    two countries granted each other most-favored-nation trading privileges, and
                    also allowed for the presence of consuls in each other’s cities. In addition,
                    the Treaty of Alliance provided additional military stipulations relating to the
                    terms of the alliance, ceding any military gains in North America to the United
                    States, and any gains in the Caribbean to France. More importantly, France
                    agreed not to seek peace with Great Britain without British acknowledgement of
                    American independence, and neither allied country was to seek peace without the
                    other’s consent. The Treaty encouraged other countries to join the alliance, but
                    only if both French and American negotiators were present. The 1778 treaty also
                    included a secret clause allowing for articles to be altered if Spain chose to
                    join the alliance.</p>
                <p>The Model Treaty served as a successful starting point for negotiations. The
                    United States was able to obtain most of the conditions it wanted, and the
                    treaty that resulted proved beneficial to U.S. trade until the disruptions
                    caused by the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/haitian-rev">Haitian</ref> and
                        <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/french-rev">French</ref> revolutions in
                    the 1790s. The treaty also served as a model for future trade compacts,
                    especially the Convention of 1800 between France and the United States that
                    terminated the undeclared <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz"
                        >Quasi-War</ref> with France and restored peace between the two countries.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="french-alliance">
                <head>French Alliance, French Assistance, and European Diplomacy during the American
                    Revolution, <date from="1778" to="1782">1778–1782</date>
                </head>
                <p>During the American Revolution, the American colonies faced the significant
                    challenge of conducting international diplomacy and seeking the international
                    support it needed to fight against the British. The single most important
                    diplomatic success of the colonists during the War for Independence was the
                    critical link they forged with France. Representatives of the French and
                    American governments signed the Treaty of Alliance and the Treaty of Amity and
                    Commerce on February 6, 1778.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="vergennes.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>French Foreign Minister Comte de Vergennes</head>
                </figure>
                <p>American colonists hoped for possible French aid in their struggle against
                    British forces. The Continental Congress established the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/secret-committee">Secret Committee of
                        Correspondence</ref> to publicize the American cause in Europe. Committee
                    member <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/b-franklin"><persName>Benjamin
                            Franklin</persName></ref> wrote to contacts in France with encouraging
                    accounts of colonial resistance. The French had suffered a defeat by the British
                    during the Seven Years’ War and had lost North American territory under the 1763
                    Treaty of Paris. As the French and the British continued to vie for power in the
                    1770s, French officials saw an opportunity in the rebellion of Britain’s North
                    American colonies to take advantage of British troubles. Through secret agents,
                    the French Government began to provide clandestine assistance to the United
                    States, much of which they channeled through American trader Silas Deane.</p>
                <p>As the members of the Continental Congress considered declaring independence,
                    they also discussed the possibility and necessity of foreign alliances, and
                    assigned a committee to draft a <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/model-treaty"
                        >Model Treaty</ref> to serve as guide for this work. After Congress <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/declaration">formally declared
                        independence</ref> from Great Britain in 1776, it dispatched a group of
                    several commissioners led by Benjamin Franklin to negotiate an alliance with
                    France. When news of the Declaration of Independence and the subsequent British
                    evacuation of Boston reached France, French Foreign Minister <persName>Comte de
                        Vergennes</persName> decided in favor of an alliance. However, once news of
                    General <persName>George Washington</persName>’s defeats in New York reached
                    Europe in August of 1776, Vergennes wavered, questioning the wisdom of
                    committing to a full alliance.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Franklin’s popularity in France bolstered French support for the
                    American cause. The French public viewed Franklin as a representative of
                    republican simplicity and honesty, an image Franklin cultivated. A rage for all
                    things Franklin and American swept France, assisting American diplomats and
                    Vergennes in pushing for an alliance. In the meantime, Vergennes agreed to
                    provide the United States with a secret loan.</p>
                <p>Despite the loan and discussions of a full alliance, French assistance to the new
                    United States was limited at the outset. Throughout 1777, Vergennes delayed as
                    he conducted negotiations with the Spanish Government, which was wary of U.S.
                    independence and also wanted assurances that Spain would regain territories if
                    it went to war against the British.</p>
                <p>Vergennes finally decided in favor of an alliance when news of the British
                    surrender at the Battle of Saratoga reached him in December 1777. Vergennes,
                    having heard rumors of secret British peace offers to Franklin, decided not to
                    wait for Spanish support and offered the United States an official French
                    alliance. On February 6, 1778, Benjamin Franklin and the other two
                    commissioners, <persName>Arthur Lee</persName> and <persName>Silas
                        Deane</persName>, signed a Treaty of Alliance and a Treaty of Amity and
                    Commerce with France. The Treaty of Alliance contained the provisions the U.S.
                    commissioners had originally requested, but also included a clause forbidding
                    either country to make a separate peace with Britain, as well as a secret clause
                    allowing for Spain, or other European powers, to enter into the alliance. Spain
                    officially entered the war on June 21, 1779. The Treaty of Amity and Commerce
                    promoted trade between the United States and France and recognized the United
                    States as an independent nation.</p>
                <!--<figure>
                    <graphic url="saratoga.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Washington at the Battle of Saratoga</head>
                </figure>-->
                <p>Between 1778 and 1782 the French provided supplies, arms and ammunition,
                    uniforms, and, most importantly, troops and naval support to the beleaguered
                    Continental Army. The French navy transported reinforcements, fought off a
                    British fleet, and protected Washington’s forces in Virginia. French assistance
                    was crucial in securing the British surrender at Yorktown in 1781.</p>
                <p>With the consent of Vergennes, U.S. commissioners entered negotiations with
                    Britain to end the war, and reached a preliminary agreement in 1782. Franklin
                    informed Vergennes of the agreement and also asked for an additional loan.
                    Vergennes did lodge a complaint on this instance, but also granted the requested
                    loan despite French financial troubles. Vergennes and Franklin successfully
                    presented a united front despite British attempts to drive a wedge between the
                    allies during their separate peace negotiations. The United States, Spain, and
                    France formally ended the war with Britain with the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty of Paris</ref> in 1783.</p>
                <p> Although European powers considered their treaty obligations abrogated by the
                    French Revolution, the United States considered it to be in effect despite
                    President Washington’s policy of neutrality in the war between Britain and
                    France. The Citizen Genêt Affair erupted partially because of clauses contained
                    in the alliance treaty that violated the neutrality policy. The Treaty of Paris
                    also remained technically in effect during the undeclared <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">Quasi-War</ref> with France, and was
                    formally ended by the Convention of 1800 which also terminated the
                    Quasi-War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="b-franklin">
                <head>Benjamin Franklin: First American Diplomat, <date from="1776" to="1785"
                        >1776–1785</date>
                </head>
                <p>Benjamin Franklin, the most distinguished scientific and literary American of the
                    colonial era, was the first American diplomat.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bfranklin2.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Benjamin Franklin</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Franklin served from 1776 to 1778 on a commission to France charged with the
                    critical task of gaining French support for American independence. French
                    aristocrats and intellectuals embraced Franklin as the personification of the
                    New World Enlightenment. His likeness appeared on medallions, rings, watches,
                    and snuffboxes, and fashionable ladies adopted the "coiffure a la Franklin" in
                    imitation of the fur cap he wore instead of a wig. His popularity and diplomatic
                    skill—along with the first American battlefield success at Saratoga—convinced
                    France to recognize American independence and conclude an alliance with the
                    thirteen states in 1778. Franklin presented his credentials to the French court
                    in 1779, becoming the first American Minister (the eighteenth century American
                    equivalent of Ambassador) to be received by a foreign government. Franklin’s
                    home in Passy, just outside Paris, became the center of American diplomacy in
                    Europe. When Thomas Jefferson succeeded Franklin in 1785, French Foreign
                    Minister Vergennes asked: “It is you who replace Dr. Franklin?” Jefferson
                    replied, “No one can replace him, Sir; I am only his successor.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="articles">
                <head>Articles of Confederation, <date from="1777" to="1781">1777–1781</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Articles of Confederation served as the written document that established the
                    functions of the national government of the United States after it declared
                    independence from Great Britain. It established a weak central government that
                    mostly, but not entirely, prevented the individual states from conducting their
                    own foreign diplomacy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="articles.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Articles of Confederation</head>
                </figure>
                <p><ref target="/milestones/1750-1775/albany-plan">The Albany Plan</ref> an earlier,
                    pre-independence attempt at joining the colonies into a larger union, had failed
                    in part because the individual colonies were concerned about losing power to
                    another central insitution. As the American Revolution gained momentum, however,
                    many political leaders saw the advantages of a centralized government that could
                    coordinate the Revolutionary War. In June of 1775, the New York provincial
                    Congress sent a plan of union to the Continental Congress, which, like the
                    Albany Plan, continued to recognize the authority of the British Crown.</p>
                <p>Some Continental Congress delegates had also informally discussed plans for a
                    more permanent union than the Continental Congress, whose status was temporary.
                    Benjamin Franklin had drawn up a plan for “Articles of Confederation and
                    Perpetual Union.” While some delegates, such as Thomas Jefferson, supported
                    Franklin’s proposal, many others were strongly opposed. Franklin introduced his
                    plan before Congress on July 21, but stated that it should be viewed as a draft
                    for when Congress was interested in reaching a more formal proposal. Congress
                    tabled the plan.</p>
                <p>Following the Declaration of Independence, the members of the Continental
                    Congress realized it would be necessary to set up a national government.
                    Congress began to discuss the form this government would take on July 22,
                    disagreeing on a number of issues, including whether representation and voting
                    would be proportional or state-by-state. The disagreements delayed final
                    discussions of confederation until October of 1777. By then, the British capture
                    of Philadelphia had made the issue more urgent. Delegates finally formulated the
                    Articles of Confederation, in which they agreed to state-by-state voting and
                    proportional state tax burdens based on land values, though they left the issue
                    of state claims to western lands unresolved. Congress sent the Articles to the
                    states for ratification at the end of November. Most delegates realized that the
                    Articles were a flawed compromise, but believed that it was better than an
                    absence of formal national government.</p>
                <p>On December 16, 1777, Virginia was the first state to ratify. Other states
                    ratified during the early months of 1778. When Congress reconvened in June of
                    1778, the delegates learned that Maryland, Delaware and New Jersey refused to
                    ratify the Articles. The Articles required unanimous approval from the states.
                    These smaller states wanted other states to relinquish their western land claims
                    before they would ratify the Articles. New Jersey and Delaware eventually agreed
                    to the conditions of the Articles, with New Jersey ratifying on Nov 20, 1778,
                    and Delaware on Feb 1, 1779. This left Maryland as the last remaining
                    holdout.</p>
                <p>Irked by Maryland’s recalcitrance, several other state governments passed
                    resolutions endorsing the formation of a national government without the state
                    of Maryland, but other politicians such as Congressman <persName>Thomas
                        Burke</persName> of North Carolina persuaded their governments to refrain
                    from doing so, arguing that without unanimous approval of the new Confederation,
                    the new country would remain weak, divided, and open to future foreign
                    intervention and manipulation.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, in 1780, British forces began to conduct raids on Maryland communities
                    in the Chesapeake Bay. Alarmed, the state government wrote to the French
                    minister <persName>Anne-César De la Luzerne</persName> asking for French naval
                    assistance. Luzerne wrote back, urging the government of Maryland to ratify the
                    Articles of Confederation. Marylanders were given further incentive to ratify
                    when Virginia agreed to relinquish its western land claims, and so the Maryland
                    legislature ratified the Articles of Confederation on March 1, 1781.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="luzerne.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>French minister Anne-César De la Luzerne</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Continental Congress voted on Jan 10, 1781, to establish a Department of
                    Foreign Affairs; on Aug 10 of that year, it elected Robert R. Livingston as
                    Secretary of Foreign Affairs. The Secretary’s duties involved corresponding with
                    U.S. representatives abroad and with ministers of foreign powers. The Secretary
                    was also charged with transmitting Congress’ instructions to U.S. agents abroad
                    and was authorized to attend sessions of Congress. A further Act of Feb 22,
                    1782, allowed the Secretary to ask and respond to questions during sessions of
                    the Continental Congress.</p>
                <p>The Articles created a sovereign, national government, and, as such, limited the
                    rights of the states to conduct their own diplomacy and foreign policy. However,
                    this proved difficult to enforce, as the national government could not prevent
                    the state of Georgia from pursuing its own independent policy regarding Spanish
                    Florida, attempting to occupy disputed territories and threatening war if
                    Spanish officials did not work to curb Indian attacks or refrain from harboring
                    escaped slaves. Nor could the Confederation government prevent the landing of
                    convicts that the British Government continued to export to its former colonies.
                    In addition, the Articles did not allow Congress sufficient authority to enforce
                    provisions of the 1783 <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty of
                        Paris</ref> that allowed British creditors to sue debtors for
                    pre-Revolutionary debts, an unpopular clause that many state governments chose
                    to ignore. Consequently, British forces continued to occupy forts in the Great
                    Lakes region. These problems, combined with the Confederation government’s
                    ineffectual response to Shays’ Rebellion in Massachusetts, convinced national
                    leaders that a more powerful central government was necessary. This led to the
                    Constitutional Convention that formulated the current Constitution of the United
                    States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="treaty">
                <head>Treaty of Paris, <date when="1783">1783</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1782, Benjamin Franklin rejected informal peace overtures from Great Britain
                    for a settlement that would provide the thirteen states with some measure of
                    autonomy within the British Empire. Franklin insisted on British recognition of
                    American independence and refused to consider a peace separate from France,
                    America’s staunch ally. Franklin did agree, however, to negotiations with the
                    British for an end to the war. Joined by peace commissioners John Adams and John
                    Jay, Franklin engaged the British in formal negotiations beginning on September
                    27, 1782.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="treaty1783.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>American Negotiations of the Peace of Paris</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although Franklin demanded the cessation of Canada to an independent America, he
                    knew that the British Government of <persName>Lord Shelburne</persName>, opposed
                    to American independence, was unprepared to accept that offer. Two months of
                    hard bargaining resulted in a preliminary articles of peace in which the British
                    accepted American independence and boundaries, resolved the difficult issues of
                    fishing rights on the Newfoundland banks and prewar debts owed British
                    creditors, promised restitution of property lost during the war by Americans
                    loyal to the British cause, and provided for the evacuation of British forces
                    from the thirteen states. The preliminary articles signed in Paris on November
                    30, 1782, were only effective when Britain and France signed a similar treaty,
                    which French Foreign Minister <persName>Vergennes</persName> quickly negotiated.
                    France signed preliminary articles of peace with Great Britain on January 20,
                    1783, followed by a formal peace of Paris signed on September 3, 1783.</p>
                <p>The illustration above, a copy of a sketch by the studio of <persName>Benjamin
                        West</persName>, shows the American negotiators of the Peace of Paris. The
                    sketch remains incomplete because British negotiators chose not to sit for their
                    half of the portrait: it serves as a powerful symbol of the division between
                    Great Britain and its former American colonies. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
