<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1784–1800</title>
                <title type="short">1784–1800</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1784" to="1800">1784–1800</date>: The Diplomacy of the Early
                    Republic</head>
                <p>Following the end of the American Revolution, the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> struggled to define its foreign policy, to determine how
                    to implement it, and to maintain necessary commercial ties with Europe without
                    becoming embroiled in European conflicts and politics. Differences over foreign
                    policy became a basis for the founding of political parties in the new nation as
                    the debate pitted the Federalists, led by the Secretary of the Treasury
                        <persName>Alexander Hamilton</persName>, against the Jeffersonians,
                    represented by Secretary of State <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName>. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="alexanderhamilton.jpg" height="280px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Alexander Hamilton</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Federalists supported the development of a strong international commerce and,
                    with it, the creation of a navy capable of protecting U.S. merchant vessels. The
                    Jeffersonians favored expansion across the vast continent that the new republic
                    occupied. </p>
                <p>The Federalists and Jeffersonians also disagreed over U.S. policy toward
                    political events in Europe. After the outbreak of the French Revolution in 1789,
                    the Federalists distrusted France and encouraged closer commercial ties to
                    England, while the Jeffersonians preferred to support the new French
                    Republic.</p>
                <p>Conflict in Europe between France, Britain, and Spain in the late 1790s, resulted
                    in President <persName>George Washington</persName> declaring American
                    neutrality. The Jay Treaty with Britain (1794) and the Pinckney Treaty with
                    Spain (1795) aimed at preserving this neutrality. In his Farewell Address,
                    Washington promoted a vision of American diplomacy that involved no “entangling
                    alliances” with European powers. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="loans">
                <head>U.S. Debt and Foreign Loans, <date from="1775" to="1795">1775–1795</date>
                </head>
                <p>During the American Revolution, a cash-strapped Continental Congress accepted
                    loans from France. Paying off these and other debts incurred during the
                    Revolution proved one of the major challenges of the post-independence period.
                    The new U.S. Government attempted to pay off these debts in a timely manner, but
                    the debts were at times a source of diplomatic tension.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="contcongress.jpg" height="252px" width="350px"/>
                    <head>The Continental Congress</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In order to pay for its significant expenditures during the Revolution, Congress
                    had two options: print more money or obtain loans to meet the budget deficit. In
                    practice it did both, but relied more on the printing of money, which led to
                    hyperinflation. At that time, Congress lacked the authority to levy taxes, and
                    to do so would have risked alienating an American public that had gone to war
                    with the British over the issue of unjust taxation.</p>
                <p>The French Government began to secretly ship war materiel to the American
                    revolutionaries in late 1775. This was accomplished by establishing dummy
                    corporations to receive French funds and military supplies. It was unclear
                    whether this aid was a loan or a gift, and disputes over the status of this
                    early assistance caused strong disagreement between American diplomats in
                    Europe. <persName>Arthur Lee</persName>, one of the American commissioners in
                    France, accused another, <persName>Silas Deane</persName>, of financial
                    misdealings, while the third member of the commission, <persName>Benjamin
                        Franklin</persName>, remained aloof. Lee eventually succeeded in convincing
                    Congress to recall Deane. The early French aid would later resurface as one of
                    the disputes behind the <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">1797 XYZ
                        Affair</ref> that led to the Quasi-War with France.</p>
                <p>During the Revolution, the French Government also provided the Americans with
                    loans, eventually totaling over two million dollars, most of which were
                    negotiated by Benjamin Franklin. <persName>John Adams</persName> also secured a
                    loan from Dutch bankers in 1782. After fighting between the Americans and the
                    British ended in 1783, the new U.S. Government established under the Articles of
                    Confederation needed to pay off its debt, but lacked sufficient tax authority to
                    secure any revenue. The government struggled to pay off the loans, stopping
                    payments of interest to France in 1785 and defaulting on further installments
                    that were due in 1787. The United States also owed money to the Spanish
                    Government and private Dutch investors, but focused on paying off the Dutch
                    because Amsterdam remained the most likely source of future loans, which the
                    United States successfully obtained in 1787 and 1788, despite its precarious
                    financial state.</p>
                <p>Under the U.S. Constitution of <date when="1798">1789,</date> the new federal
                    government enjoyed increased authority to manage U.S. finances and to raise
                    revenues through taxation. Responsibility for managing debts fell to Secretary
                    of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton. Hamilton placed U.S. finances on firmer
                    ground, allowing for the U.S. Government to negotiate new loans at lower
                    interest rates. In addition, the United States began to make regular payments on
                    in its French debts starting in 1790, and also provided an emergency advance to
                    assist the French in addressing the 1791 slave revolt that began the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/haitian-rev">Haitian Revolution</ref>.</p>
                <p>Although the federal government was able to resume debt payments, total federal
                    expenditures exceeded revenues during many years in the 1790s. Hamilton
                    therefore sought additional loans on Dutch capital markets, although the
                    improved U.S. financial situation made these loans easier to obtain. These
                    private loans from Dutch bankers also helped pay off loans owed to the Spanish
                    Government, back pay owed to foreign officers, and U.S. diplomatic expenses in
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>In 1795, the United States was finally able to settle its debts with the French
                    Government with the help of <persName>James Swan</persName>, an American banker
                    who privately assumed French debts at a slightly higher interest rate. Swan then
                    resold these debts at a profit on domestic U.S. markets. The United States no
                    longer owed money to foreign governments, although it continued to owe money to
                    private investors both in the United States and in Europe.</p>
                <p>Although U.S. finances had been shaky under the Articles of Confederation, the
                    United States was able to place itself on a sound financial footing during the
                    1790s. This enabled it to preempt diplomatic embarrassment and dependence on
                    foreign powers during that period, and also improved U.S. credit on European
                    capital markets, which enabled the U.S. Government to obtain low-interest loans
                    for the Louisiana Purchase in 1803.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="convention-and-ratification">
                <head>Constitutional Convention and Ratification, <date from="1787" to="1789"
                        >1787–1789</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Constitutional Convention in <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName> met between
                    May and September of <date when="1798-05">1787</date> to address the problems of
                    the weak central government that existed under the Articles of Confederation.
                    The United States Constitution that emerged from the convention established a
                    federal government with more specific powers, including those related to
                    conducting relations with foreign governments. Under the reformed federal
                    system, many of the responsibilities for foreign affairs fell under the
                    authority of an executive branch, although important powers, such as treaty
                    ratification, remained the responsibility of the legislative branch. After the
                    necessary number of state ratifications, the Constitution came into effect in
                    1789 and has served as the basis of the United States Government ever since.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="constitution.jpg" height="266px" width="220px"/>
                    <head>The U.S. Constitution</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Under the Articles of Confederation, the federal government faced many challenges
                    in conducting foreign policy, largely due to its inability to pass or enforce
                    laws that individual states found counter to their interests. The 1783 Treaty of
                    Paris, which ended the American War of Independence, stipulated that debts owed
                    by Americans to British subjects were to be honored, and also stipulated that
                    former British loyalists could bring forth suits in U.S. courts to recover
                    confiscated property. These provisions were unpopular and many states blocked
                    their enforcement. This led to British refusal to vacate military forts in U.S.
                    territory. Additionally, after the war, British traders flooded U.S. markets
                    with British goods, to the detriment of American importers and manufacturers.
                    The Confederation Congress lacked the authority to regulate this trade, and
                    intrastate trade was further hampered by states’ own attempts to impose import
                    duties on goods from elsewhere in the United States. Lastly, the Spanish
                    Government, which controlled New Orleans, barred American ships from navigating
                    the Mississippi River. Southern delegates to the Confederation Congress wanted
                    to lift this ban, while coastal merchants, especially in the northeast, were
                    willing to make concessions in exchange for a treaty with otherwise favorable
                    commercial terms. The large majorities necessary for ratification of such
                    measures under the Articles of Confederation often resulted in the deadlock
                    along sectional lines between North and South.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="phil-const.jpg" height="231px" width="350px"/>
                    <head>The Constitutional Convention in Philadelphia</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In attempting to resolve such issues, as well as problems arising from the
                    payment of debts from the Revolutionary War and other domestic issues, the
                    delegates to the Constitutional Convention created a model of government that
                    relied upon a series of checks and balances by dividing federal authority
                    between the Legislative, the Judicial, and the Executive branches of government.
                    The framers of the Constitution had originally imagined a weak presidency and a
                    strong legislature divided into a House of Representatives and the Senate. Under
                    the Articles of Confederation, considerable minor paperwork had bogged down
                    important business enough that legislators decided to establish an executive
                    branch to deal with routine paperwork. When writing the Constitution, the
                    framers expected the Senate to handle important issues, particularly the
                    ratification of treaties, while the Executive would attend to matters of lesser
                    consequence. However, as deliberations continued, the Executive branch acquired
                    more power to deal with some of the issues that had been a source of sectional
                    tension under the Articles of Confederation—and so the President acquired the
                    authority to conduct foreign relations. The two-thirds clause for ratification
                    of treaties in the Senate, as opposed to a simple majority, allowed the South a
                    greater voice in these matters and assuaged concerns about the attempts to
                    abandon navigation of the Mississippi.</p>
                <p>The Constitution does not stipulate existence of departments within the executive
                    branch, but the need for such departments was recognized immediately. Congress
                    passed legislation creating the Department of Foreign Affairs in its first
                    session in 1789, and in the same year changed the name to the Department of
                    State after it added several additional domestic duties to the Department.</p>
                <p>After the ratification of the Constitution in 1789, the machinery of state had
                    been designed, but not yet tested and put to use. The provisions for management
                    of foreign affairs would be put to the test in 1794, when the Senate had the
                    opportunity to accept or reject the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/jay-treaty">controversial treaty with Great
                        Britain negotiated by John Jay</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="french-rev">
                <head>The United States and the French Revolution, <date when="1798"
                        >1789–1799</date>
                </head>
                <p>The French Revolution lasted from 1789 until 1799. The Revolution precipitated a
                    series of European wars, forcing the United States to articulate a clear policy
                    of neutrality in order to avoid being embroiled in these European conflicts. The
                    French Revolution also influenced U.S. politics, as pro- and anti- Revolutionary
                    factions sought to influence American domestic and foreign policy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="french-rev.jpg" height="242px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>The French Declaration of Rights</head>
                </figure>
                <p>When the first rumors of political change in France reached American shores in
                    1789, the U.S. public was largely enthusiastic. Americans hoped for democratic
                    reforms that would solidify the existing Franco-American alliance and transform
                    France into a republican ally against aristocratic and monarchical Britain.
                    However, with revolutionary change also came political instability, violence,
                    and calls for radical social change in France that frightened many Americans.
                    American political debate over the nature of the French Revolution exacerbated
                    pre-existing political divisions and resulted in the alignment of the political
                    elite along pro-French and pro-British lines. Secretary of State
                        <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName> became the leader of the pro-French
                    Democratic-Republican Party that celebrated the republican ideals of the French
                    Revolution. Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton led the Federalist
                    Party, which viewed the Revolution with skepticism and sought to preserve
                    existing commercial ties with Great Britain. With the two most powerful members
                    of his cabinet locked in opposition, President <persName>George
                        Washington</persName> tried to strike a balance between the two.</p>
                <p>From 1790 to 1794, the French Revolution became increasingly radical. After
                    French <persName>King Louis XVI</persName> was tried and executed on January 21,
                    1793, war between France and monarchal nations Great Britain and Spain was
                    inevitable. These two powers joined Austria and other European nations in the
                    war against Revolutionary France that had already started in 1791. The United
                    States remained neutral, as both Federalists and Democratic-Republicans saw that
                    war would lead to economic disaster and the possibility of invasion. This policy
                    was made difficult by heavy-handed British and French actions. The British
                    harassed neutral American merchant ships, while the French Government dispatched
                    a controversial Minister to the United States, Edmond-Charles Genêt, whose
                    violations of the American neutrality policy embroiled the two countries in the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/citizen-genet">Citizen Genêt Affair</ref>
                    until his recall in 1794.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bastille.jpg" height="262px" width="350px"/>
                    <head>The Storming of the Bastille</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1794, the French Revolution entered its most violent phase, the Terror. Under
                    foreign invasion, the French Government declared a state of emergency, and many
                    foreigners residing in France were arrested, including American revolutionary
                    pamphleteer Thomas Paine, owing to his British birth. Although U.S. Minister to
                    France Gouverneur Morris was unable to obtain Paine’s release, Morris was able
                    to intercede successfully on behalf of many other Americans imprisoned during
                    the Terror, including the American Consuls at Dunkirk, Rouen, and Le Havre. Once
                    the Terror ended in late July of 1794, the arrests ended, and Paine, who had
                    been scheduled to be executed, was released.</p>
                <p>Although the French Revolution had ended its radical phase, Federalists in the
                    United States remained wary of revolutionary ideology infiltrating the United
                    States. Many French citizens, refugees from the French and Haitian revolutions,
                    had settled in American cities and remained politically active, setting up
                    newspapers and agitating for their political causes. A French spy, Victor
                    Collot, traveled through the United States in 1796, noting the weaknesses in its
                    western border. When a breakdown in diplomatic negotiations resulted in the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1784-1800/xyz">Quasi-War</ref> with France, the
                    Federalist-controlled Congress passed a series of laws known as the Alien and
                    Sedition Acts, intended to curb political dissent and limit the political
                    participation of immigrants by easing deportation and lengthening the time
                    required for citizenship. A number of political radicals were arrested for
                    sedition, including Congressman Matthew Lyon and newspaper editors James
                    Thompson Callendar and William Duane. Many refugees, sensing American hostility,
                    chose to return to France and Haiti since the political situation had
                    temporarily calmed in both places.</p>
                <p>The Alien and Sedition Acts, originally intended to prevent a growth in
                    pro-French sentiment, actually backfired for the Federalists. Taken aback by
                    such extreme measures, swing voters in the presidential election of 1800 instead
                    backed the pro-French Thomas Jefferson and his Democratic-Republican Party,
                    instead of the Federalist John Adams, who was running for re-election as
                    President. Adams had also alienated the anti-Revolutionary wing of his party by
                    seeking peace with France, whose revolution had already been brought to a close
                    by General Napoleon Bonaparte.</p>
                <p>Despite Federalist warnings that electing Jefferson would bring revolution to the
                    United States, Jefferson instead chose to distance himself from political
                    radicals and win over political moderates. The revolution in France was over,
                    and while many Americans voters sympathized with the revolution in the abstract,
                    they did not want the revolution’s most radical changes put into effect in the
                    United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="haitian-rev">
                <head>The United States and the Haitian Revolution, <date when="1791"
                        >1791–1804</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Haitian Revolution created the second independent country in the Americas
                    after the United States became independent in 1783. U.S. political leaders, many
                    of them slaveowners, reacted to the emergence of Haiti as a state borne out of a
                    slave revolt with ambivalence, at times providing aid to put down the revolt,
                    and, later in the revolution, providing support to Toussaint L’Ouverture’s
                    forces. Due to these shifts in policy and domestic concerns, the United States
                    would not officially recognize Haitian independence until 1862.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="haitian-revolution.jpg" height="350px" width="522px"/>
                    <head>Toussaint L'Ouverture holds a printed copy of the Haitian Constitution of
                        1801. (Library of Congress Prints and Photographs Division)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prior to its independence, Haiti was a French colony known as St. Domingue. St.
                    Domingue’s slave-based sugar and coffee industries had been fast-growing and
                    successful, and by the 1760s it had become the most profitable colony in the
                    Americas. With the economic growth, however, came increasing exploitation of the
                    African slaves who made up the overwhelming majority of the population. Prior to
                    and after U.S. independence, American merchants enjoyed a healthy trade with St.
                    Domingue.</p>
                <p>The French Revolution had a great impact on the colony. St. Domingue’s white
                    minority split into Royalist and Revolutionary factions, while the mixed-race
                    population campaigned for civil rights. Sensing an opportunity, the slaves of
                    northern St. Domingue organized and planned a massive rebellion which began on
                    August 22, 1791.</p>
                <p>When news of the slave revolt broke out, American leaders rushed to provide
                    support for the whites of St. Domingue. However, the situation became more
                    complex when civil commissioners sent to St. Domingue by the French
                    revolutionary government convinced one of the slave revolt leaders, Toussaint
                    L’Ouverture, that the new French Government was committed to ending slavery.
                    What followed over the next decade was a complex and multi-sided civil war in
                    which Spanish and British forces also intervened.</p>
                <p>The situation in St. Domingue put the Democratic-Republican party and its leader,
                        <persName>Thomas Jefferson</persName>, in somewhat of a political dilemma.
                    Jefferson believed strongly in the French Revolution and the ideals it promoted,
                    but as a Virginia slaveholder popular among other Virginia slaveholders,
                    Jefferson also feared the specter of slave revolt. When faced with the question
                    of what the United States should do about the French colony of St. Domingue,
                    Jefferson favored offering limited aid to suppress the revolt, but also
                    suggested that the slaveowners should aim for a compromise similar to that
                    Jamaican slaveholders made with communities of escaped slaves in 1739. Despite
                    their numerous differences on other issues, Secretary of the Treasury and leader
                    of the rival Federalist Party Alexander Hamilton largely agreed with Jefferson
                    regarding Haiti policy.</p>
                <p>The Haitian revolution came to North American shores in the form of a refugee
                    crisis. In 1793, competing factions battled for control of the then-capital of
                    St. Domingue, Cap-Français (now Cap-Haïtien.) The fighting and ensuing fire
                    destroyed much of the capital, and refugees piled into ships anchored in the
                    harbor. The French navy deposited the refugees in Norfolk, Virginia. Many
                    refugees also settled in Baltimore, Philadelphia, and New York. These refugees
                    were predominantly white, though many had brought their slaves with them. The
                    refugees became involved in émigré politics, hoping to influence U.S. foreign
                    policy. Anxieties about their actions, along with those of European radicals
                    also residing in the United States, led to the passage of the Alien and Sedition
                    Acts. The growing xenophobia, along with temporarily improved political
                    stability in France and St. Domingue, convinced many of the refugees to return
                    home.</p>
                <p>The beginning of the Federalist administration of President <persName>John
                        Adams</persName> signaled a change in policy. Adams was resolutely
                    anti-slavery and felt no need to aid white forces in St. Domingue. He was also
                    concerned that L’Ouverture would choose to pursue a policy of state-supported
                    piracy like that of the Barbary States. Lastly, St. Domingue’s trade had
                    partially rebounded, and Adams wished to preserve trade links with the colony.
                    Consequently, Adams decided to provide aid to L’Ouverture against his
                    British-supported rivals. This situation was complicated by the Quasi-War with
                    France—L’Ouverture continued to insist that St. Domingue was a French colony
                    even as he pursued an independent foreign policy.</p>
                <p>Under President Thomas Jefferson’s presidency, the United States cut off aid to
                    L’Ouverture and instead pursued a policy to isolate Haiti, fearing that the
                    Haitian revolution would spread to the United States. These concerns were in
                    fact unfounded, as the fledgling Haitian state was more concerned with its own
                    survival than with exporting revolution. Nevertheless, Jefferson grew even more
                    hostile after L’Ouverture’s successor, Jean-Jacques Dessalines, ordered the
                    execution of whites remaining after the Napoleonic attempts to reconquer St.
                    Domingue and reimpose slavery (French defeat led to the Louisiana Purchase.)
                    Jefferson refused to recognize Haitian independence, a policy to which U.S.
                    Federalists also acquiesced. Although France recognized Haitian independence in
                    1825, Haitians would have to wait until 1862 for the United States to recognize
                    Haiti’s status as a sovereign, independent nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="citizen-genet">
                <head>The Citizen Genêt Affair, <date when="1793">1793–1794</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Edmond Charles Genêt</persName> served as French minister to the
                    United States from 1793 to 1794. His activities in that capacity embroiled the
                    United States and France in a diplomatic crisis, as the United States Government
                    attempted to remain neutral in the conflict between Great Britain and
                    Revolutionary France. The controversy was ultimately resolved by Genêt’s recall
                    from his position. As a result of the Citizen Genêt affair, the United States
                    established a set of procedures governing neutrality.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="charles_genet copy.jpg" height="216px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>Edmond Charles Genêt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>American foreign policy in the 1790s was dominated by the events surrounding the
                    French Revolution. Following the overthrow of the monarchy in 1792, the
                    revolutionary French Government clashed with the monarchies of Spain and Great
                    Britain. French policymakers needed the United States to help defend France’s
                    colonies in the Caribbean – either as a neutral supplier or as a military ally,
                    and so they dispatched Edmond Charles Genêt, an experienced diplomat, as
                    minister to the United States. The French assigned Genêt several additional
                    duties: to obtain advance payments on debts that the U.S. owed to France, to
                    negotiate a commercial treaty between the United States and France, and to
                    implement portions of the 1778 Franco-American treaty which allowed attacks on
                    British merchant shipping using ships based in American ports. Genêt’s attempt
                    to carry out his instructions would bring him into direct conflict with the U.S.
                    Government.</p>
                <p>The French Revolution had already reinforced political differences within
                    President George Washington’s Cabinet. The Democratic-Republicans, led by
                    Secretary of State Thomas Jefferson, sympathized with the French
                    revolutionaries. The Federalists, led by Secretary of the Treasury
                        <persName>Alexander Hamilton,</persName> believed that ties with Great
                    Britain were more important. President Washington attempted to steer a neutral
                    course between these two opposing views. He believed that joining Great Britain
                    or France in war could subject the comparatively weak United States to invasion
                    by foreign armies and have disastrous economic consequences. President
                    Washington issued a proclamation of neutrality on April 22, 1793.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tjefferson.jpg" height="316px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Thomas Jefferson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Genêt arrived in Charleston, South Carolina on April 8, 1793—calling himself
                    “Citizen Genêt” to emphasize his pro-revolutionary stance. Genêt immediately
                    began to issue privateering commissions upon his arrival in Charleston, with the
                    consent of South Carolina governor William Moultrie. These commissions
                    authorized the bearers, regardless of their country of origin, to seize British
                    merchant ships and their cargo for personal profit, with the approval and
                    protection of the French Government.</p>
                <p>When Genêt arrived in the U.S. capital of Philadelphia in May to present his
                    credentials, Secretary of State Thomas Jefferson informed him that the United
                    States Cabinet considered the outfitting of French privateers in American ports
                    to be a violation of the U.S. policy of neutrality. Genêt’s mission ran into
                    further difficulties when the U.S. Government expressed no interest in a new
                    commercial treaty, as it already enjoyed favorable trading privileges in French
                    ports. The U.S. Cabinet also refused to make advance payments on U.S. debts to
                    the French government.</p>
                <p>Genêt ignored American warnings and allowed the outfitting of another French
                    privateer, the Little Democrat. Defying numerous warnings from U.S. officials to
                    detain the ship in port, Genêt continued to ready the ship to sail. Genêt also
                    threatened to take his case to the American people, bypassing official
                    government opposition. Genêt failed to realize that Washington and his
                    neutrality policy were politically popular, and that his pro-British enemies
                    would depict such an attempt as foreign meddling in American domestic
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>Washington’s Cabinet met to consider a response to Genêt’s defiant actions. All
                    members agreed to request Genêt’s recall, but were divided as to how to go about
                    doing so. Before the Cabinet reached a decision, Genêt allowed the Little
                    Democrat to sail and begin attacking British shipping. This direct violation of
                    neutrality forced the U.S. Government to take more prompt action and request
                    that the French government recall Genêt. However, Secretary of State Jefferson
                    stopped short of expelling Genet from the United States, as Hamilton had
                    wished.</p>
                <p>By the time Jefferson’s request for recall reached France, power had shifted from
                    the more moderate Girondins, who had originally sent Genêt on his mission, to
                    the radical Jacobins. French policy began to emphasize friendlier relations with
                    neutral countries who could provide crucially needed food supplies. French
                    officials were already dissatisfied with Genêt’s failure to fulfill his
                    diplomatic mission, and the Jacobins suspected him of continued loyalty to the
                    Girondins. The French government recalled Genêt, and demanded that the U.S. hand
                    him over to the commissioners sent to replace him. President Washington and
                    Attorney General Edmund Randolph, aware that Genêt’s return to France would
                    almost certainly result in his execution, allowed Genêt to remain in the United
                    States. U.S. and French diplomatic goals favored friendly neutrality, and the
                    Genêt affair came to an end. Genêt himself continued to reside in the United
                    States until his death in 1834.</p>
                <p>The Genêt affair forced the United States to formulate a consistent policy on the
                    issue of neutrality. Washington’s Cabinet signed a set of rules regarding
                    policies of neutrality on August 3, 1793, and these rules were formalized when
                    Congress passed a neutrality bill on June 4, 1794. This legislation formed the
                    basis for neutrality policy throughout the nineteenth century.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="jay-treaty">
                <head>John Jay’s Treaty, <date when="1794">1794–95</date>
                </head>
                <p>On November 19, 1794 representatives of the United States and Great Britain
                    signed Jay’s Treaty, which sought to settle outstanding issues between the two
                    countries that had been left unresolved since American independence. The treaty
                    proved unpopular with the American public but did accomplish the goal of
                    maintaining peace between the two nations and preserving U.S. neutrality.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="johnjay.jpg" height="320px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>John Jay</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Tensions between the United States and Britain remained high after the
                    Revolutionary War as a result of three key issues. British exports flooded U.S.
                    markets, while American exports were blocked by British trade restrictions and
                    tariffs. The British occupation of northern forts that the British Government
                    had agreed to vacate in the Treaty of Paris (1783) as well as recurrent Native
                    American attacks in these areas also frustrated Americans. Finally, Britain’s
                    impressments of American sailors and seizure of naval and military supplies
                    bound to enemy ports on neutral ships brought the two nations to the brink of
                    war in the late 1700s.</p>
                <p>The French Revolution led to war between Britain and France in 1793. Divisions
                    emerged in the United States between those who supported the French, including
                    Secretary of State <persName>Thomas Jefferson,</persName> and those who
                    supported the British, including Secretary of the Treasury Alexander Hamilton.
                    Fearing the repercussions of a war with Britain, President <persName>George
                        Washington</persName> sided with Hamilton and sent pro-British Chief Justice
                        <persName>John Jay</persName> to negotiate with the British Government. Jay
                    looked to Hamilton for specific instructions for the treaty. Hamilton
                    recommended an approach that would both stabilize relations with Great Britain
                    and guarantee increased trade between the United States and Great Britain.</p>
                <p>Jay’s only significant bargaining chip in the negotiations was the threat that
                    the United States would join the Danish and the Swedish governments in defending
                    their neutral status and resisting British seizure of their goods by force of
                    arms. In an attempt to guarantee good relations with Britain, Hamilton
                    independently informed the British leadership that the United States had no
                    intention of joining in this neutral armament. Hamilton’s actions left Jay with
                    little leverage to force the British to comply with U.S. demands.</p>
                <p>The resulting treaty addressed few U.S. interests, and ultimately granted Britain
                    additional rights. The only concessions Jay obtained was a surrender of the
                    northwestern posts (already agreed to in 1783) and a commercial treaty with
                    Great Britain that granted the United States “most favored nation” status, but
                    seriously restricted U.S. commercial access to the British West Indies. All
                    other outstanding issues, including the Canadian-Maine boundary, compensation
                    for pre-revolutionary debts, and British seizures of American ships, were to be
                    resolved by arbitration. Jay even conceded that the British could seize U.S.
                    goods bound for France if they paid for them and could confiscate without
                    payment French goods on American ships.</p>
                <p>Jay’s Treaty was immensely unpopular with the American public, but it squeaked
                    through the Senate on a 20 to 10 vote on June 24, 1795. President Washington
                    implemented the treaty in the face of popular disapproval, realizing that it was
                    the price of peace with Great Britain and that it gave the United States
                    valuable time to consolidate and rearm in the event of future conflict.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="pickney-treaty">
                <head>Treaty of San Lorenzo/ Pinckney’s Treaty, <date when="1795">1795</date>
                </head>
                <p>Spanish and U.S. negotiators concluded the Treaty of San Lorenzo, also known as
                    Pinckney’s Treaty, on October 27, 1795. The treaty was an important diplomatic
                    success for the United States. It resolved territorial disputes between the two
                    countries and granted American ships the right to free navigation of the
                    Mississippi River as well as duty-free transport through the port of New
                    Orleans, then under Spanish control.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tpinckney.jpg" height="270px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Thomas Pinckney</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prior to the treaty, the western and southern borders of the United States had
                    been a source of tension between Spain and the United States. The U.S. border
                    extended to the Mississippi River, but its southern stretch remained in Spanish
                    territory, and Spanish officials, reluctant to encourage U.S. trade and
                    settlement in a strategic frontier area, kept the Mississippi River closed to
                    American shipping. Moreover, both Spain and the United States claimed portions
                    of the present-day states of Alabama and Mississippi, and earlier negotiations
                    to resolve the territorial disputes had broken off inconclusively. The Spanish
                    government maintained several forts in the disputed territories, and could also
                    count on indigenous resistance to U.S. attempts to survey or encroach upon
                    Native American lands. U.S. citizens from the southern states and frontier areas
                    found Spanish policies restrictive, and wanted the U.S. Government to
                    renegotiate its positions.</p>
                <p>Prior to 1789, Spanish policy had focused on keeping American trade and
                    settlement in frontier areas to a minimum, and so neither Spanish colonial
                    officials nor policymakers in Madrid were interested in granting the concessions
                    that U.S. negotiators had attempted to obtain earlier. However, Spanish
                    interests changed during the wars of the French Revolution. Spain joined the
                    other European monarchies in war against France in 1793, but by 1794 Spanish
                    forces experienced defeats in the Caribbean and Europe. Spanish King Charles IV,
                    uninterested in managing political affairs, had earlier handed political and
                    diplomatic responsibilities to his prime minister, Manuel de Godoy. Godoy sought
                    to extract Spain from its alliance with its traditional enemy Great Britain, and
                    to restore peace with France. Godoy’s policy was not without risks, as
                    antagonizing the British would put Spanish colonies in the Americas at risk.</p>
                <p>While Spanish diplomats sought to shift Spanish alliances, U.S. diplomat John Jay
                    arrived in London to negotiate a treaty with Great Britain. Spanish officials
                    feared that Jay’s negotiations would result in an Anglo-American alliance and an
                    invasion of Spanish possessions in North America. Sensing the need for
                    rapprochement, Godoy sent a request to the U.S. Government for a representative
                    empowered to negotiate a new treaty. President <persName>George
                        Washington</persName> selected South Carolinian <persName>Thomas
                        Pinckney,</persName> who had been serving as United States minister to Great
                    Britain.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="charlesiv.jpg" height="354px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>Charles IV of Spain</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Pinckney arrived in Spain in June of 1795, and negotiations proceeded swiftly.
                    Spain’s political and military position had weakened under its defeats and war
                    expenses, while population growth in Kentucky and Tennessee, combined with a
                    shortage of European ships to sustain trade with Louisiana, made Spanish
                    officials amenable to a change in restrictive Spanish trade policies. Godoy
                    offered to accept the 31st parallel as the U.S.-Florida border as well as the
                    right to free navigation of the Mississippi, which Americans west of the
                    Appalachians supported enthusiastically. In return, Godoy requested that the
                    United States commit to an alliance with Spain.</p>
                <p>Pinckney rejected the alliance, and after further consultation Godoy provided the
                    same offer without the necessity of the alliance. Nevertheless, negotiations
                    came to an impasse as the Spanish continued to insist on their right to require
                    duties for goods passing through Spanish-held New Orleans. Pinckney threatened
                    to leave without signing a treaty unless the Spanish dropped duties on American
                    trade passing through New Orleans. The next day, Godoy agreed to Pinckney’s
                    demands, and the two negotiators signed the treaty on October 27, 1795. The
                    final treaty also voided Spanish guarantees of military support that colonial
                    officials had made to Native Americans in the disputed regions, greatly
                    weakening those communities’ ability to resist encroachment upon their
                    lands.</p>
                <p>The Treaty of San Lorenzo enabled and encouraged American settlers to continue
                    westward expansion, and made frontier areas more attractive and lucrative.
                    Consequently, it was popular with the American public, especially in the West
                    and South. Since Thomas Pinckney was associated with the Federalist Party, the
                    treaty served to bolster the Federalists outside of their New England stronghold
                    and give the party a stronger base in areas where it had traditionally been
                    weak. Diplomatically, the treaty marked a reverse in Spanish policies that
                    attempted to maintain a strong buffer region in North America, while placing the
                    United States in a stronger position in relation to European powers compared to
                    the U.S. concessions made in Jay’s Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="washington-farewell">
                <head>Washington’s Farewell Address, <date when="1796">1796</date>
                </head>
                <p>To announce his decision not to seek a third term as President, <persName>George
                        Washington</persName> presented his Farewell Address in a newspaper article
                    September 17, 1796.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="gwashington.jpg" height="211px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>George Washington</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Frustrated by French meddling in U.S. politics, Washington warned the nation to
                    avoid permanent alliances with foreign nations and to rely instead on temporary
                    alliances for emergencies. Washington’s efforts to protect the fragile young
                    republic by steering a neutral course between England and France during the
                    French Revolutionary Wars was made extremely difficult by the intense rhetoric
                    flowing from the pro-English Federalists, led by Alexander Hamilton, and the
                    pro-French, personified by Thomas Jefferson. In his farewell address, Washington
                    exhorted Americans to set aside their violent likes and dislikes of foreign
                    nations, lest they be controlled by their passions: “The nation which indulges
                    toward another an habitual hatred or an habitual fondness is in some degree a
                    slave.” Washington’s remarks have served as an inspiration for American
                    isolationism, and his advice against joining a permanent alliance was heeded for
                    more than a century and a half. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="xyz">
                <head>The XYZ Affair and the Quasi-War with France, <date when="1798"
                        >1798–1800</date>
                </head>
                <p>The XYZ Affair was a diplomatic incident between French and United States
                    diplomats that resulted in a limited, undeclared war known as the Quasi-War.
                    U.S. and French negotiators restored peace with the Convention of 1800, also
                    known as the Treaty of Mortefontaine.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="egerry.jpg" height="266px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Elbridge Gerry</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the late 1700s, the final French Revolutionary government, the Directory, was
                    experiencing problems financing its European wars. Many leaders were also angry
                    that the United States had concluded the Jay Treaty with Great Britain in 1794.
                    Consequently, in 1796 French leaders decided to issue an order allowing for the
                    seizure of American merchant ships, carefully timed to catch as many as possible
                    by surprise. President John Adams dispatched three U.S. envoys to restore
                    harmony between the United States and <persName>France—Elbridge
                    Gerry</persName>, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/pinckney-charles-cotesworth">Charles
                        Cotesworth Pinckney</ref>, and <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-john">John Marshall.</ref>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="jmarshall.jpg" height="303px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>John Marshall</head>
                </figure>
                <p>These commissioners, like others of the Adams administration, viewed France as a
                    center of decadence and intrigue and the rampant intrigue and factions of the
                    Directory made it difficult for the Americans to accomplish their mission. Upon
                    arriving in France, Gerry, Pinckney and Marshall found that they were unable to
                    formally meet with the Foreign Minister, the <persName>Marquis de
                        Talleyrand</persName>. The U.S. envoys were instead approached by several
                    intermediaries, Nicholas Hubbard (later W,) Jean Hottinguer (X), Pierre Bellamy
                    (Y), and Lucien Hauteval (Z.) Also involved with these negotiations was the
                    playwright Pierre Beaumarchais, who had been involved in funneling French aid to
                    the United States during the American Revolution. These French intermediaries
                    stated that Talleyrand would be willing to meet with the Americans and come to
                    an agreement if several conditions were to be satisfied. The French demanded
                    that the United States provide France with a low-interest loan, assume and pay
                    American merchant claims against the French, and lastly pay a substantial bribe
                    to Talleyrand. The U.S. envoys were shocked, and also skeptical that any
                    concessions would bring about substantial changes in French policy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="talleyrand.jpg" height="264px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Marquis de Talleyrand</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Talleyrand’s strategy was mainly one of delay. He intended to end attacks on U.S.
                    merchant shipping, but wanted first to increase his personal wealth, strengthen
                    his political position within the Directory government, and ensure that he would
                    deal only with Elbridge Gerry, the American commissioner who seemed most
                    friendly to French interests. Talleyrand’s intermediaries were also interested
                    in preserving peace with the United States as many of them had investments in
                    U.S. businesses. However, as French military victories in Europe increased
                    French power, the French changed the loan terms and threatened an invasion of
                    the United States if the U.S. envoys did not capitulate. When the U.S. envoys
                    proved unwilling to accede to French demands, Talleyrand eventually met with
                    them formally, and dropped most of his requirements, but did not agree to end
                    the seizures of American ships. Pinckney and Marshall made preparations to leave
                    France, while Gerry intended to stay in the hopes of averting a war.</p>
                <p>In the meantime, the envoys’ dispatches reached the United States. President
                    Adams prepared for war, and pro-war Federalists pushed Congress to support him.
                    Leaders of the Democratic-Republican party were suspicious of Adams’ motives and
                    demanded that he publicly release the diplomatic correspondence describing the
                    negotiations in France. Adams, knowing its contents, obliged them and released
                    the correspondence, but replaced the names of the French intermediaries with the
                    letters W, X, Y, and Z.</p>
                <p>Thereafter Adams continued preparations for war, but did not venture to openly
                    declare war. Talleyrand, realizing his blunder, attempted to restore relations,
                    and Congress approved a commission to negotiate an agreement with the French
                    government. In the meantime, the U.S. Navy began to fight the French in the
                    Caribbean, while offering support to Toussaint L’Ouverture in Haiti. In 1799,
                    Congress also passed the Logan Act in response to the visit of a pacifist
                    Quaker, George Logan, who conducted negotiations with Talleyrand as a private
                    citizen and returned to the United States announcing Talleyrand’s peaceful
                    intentions. The Logan Act criminalized unauthorized diplomatic negotiations.</p>
                <p>In the meantime peace negotiations proceeded in France. Napoleon had come to
                    power, and was seeking to re-obtain Louisiana from Spain. Consequently,
                    Talleyrand, who remained as Foreign Minister, wanted to prevent further
                    hostility with the United States. For their part, the British had delighted in
                    the anti-French uproar in the United States and moved to assist the Americans
                    against a common foe, revolutionary France. However, President Adams ultimately
                    wanted to avoid a major war, confident that had France wanted war it would have
                    responded to American attacks on French ships. Talleyrand feared that limited
                    hostilities with the United States might escalate into a full-scale war and let
                    it be known that he would accept a new American diplomatic representative. Adams
                    nominated a new representative to France despite public and Federalist
                    disappointment that there would be no war, but conceded to Federalist demands
                    and expanded the single nomination into a commission of three.</p>
                <p>The negotiators chose to annul the 1778 Treaty of Alliance, and instead
                    negotiated a new agreement based on the 1776 Model Treaty—this resulted in the
                    Convention of 1800. Since the new agreement made no provisions for compensation
                    for the seizure of U.S. merchant ships, the Senate did not ratify a finalized
                    version of the treaty until December 18, 1801. The Convention of 1800 terminated
                    the only formal treaty of alliance of the United States. It would be nearly a
                    century and a half before the United States entered into another formal
                    alliance.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
