<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1801–1829</title>
                <title type="short">1801–1829</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1801" to="1829">1801–1829</date>: Securing the Republic</head>
                <p>In the early part of the 1800s, the <placeName>United States</placeName>
                    developed more confidence as an independent nation.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="1800.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The United States in 1800</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Opportunities to expand westward strengthened the notion that the United States
                    should continue its quest to occupy more territory of the vast North American
                    continent. The European powers did little to stop the young nation from
                    extending its borders as they were embroiled in the ongoing <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/napoleonic-wars">Napoleonic Wars</ref> in
                    Europe. Indeed, the economic pressure of these European conflicts compelled the
                    French and the Spanish to sell the Louisiana and Florida territories to the U.S.
                    Government, more than doubling the size of the United States. During this
                    period, the U.S. also built an economy based on trade and commerce, and premised
                    on the same neutrality as outlined by the founders in the Early Republic. The
                    United States even went to war with Britain in 1812, when British actions
                    threatened American neutrality and trading rights. Finally, the United States
                    used the newfound independence of the Latin American states from their former
                    colonial ruler of Spain to establish the idea of an American sphere of influence
                    in the Western Hemisphere and to announce to the European powers the end of the
                    era of colonization in the Americas. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="barbary-wars">
                <head>Barbary Wars, <date from="1801" to="1805">1801–1805</date> and <date
                        from="1815" to="1816">1815–1816</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Barbary States were a collection of North African states, many of which
                    practiced state-supported piracy in order to exact tribute from weaker Atlantic
                    powers. Morocco was an independent kingdom, Algiers, Tunis, and Tripoli owed a
                    loose allegiance to the Ottoman Empire. The United States fought two separate
                    wars with <placeName>Tripoli</placeName> (1801–1805) and
                        <placeName>Algiers</placeName> (1815–1816), although at other times it
                    preferred to pay tribute to obtain the release of captives held in the Barbary
                    States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="barbarywars.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Barbary Wars</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The practice of state-supported piracy and ransoming of captives was not wholly
                    unusual for its time. Many European states commissioned privateers to attack
                    each others’ shipping and also participated in the transatlantic slave trade.
                    The two major European powers, Great Britain and France, found it expedient to
                    encourage the Barbary States’ policy and pay tribute to them, as it allowed
                    their merchant shipping an increased share of the Mediterranean trade, and
                    Barbary leaders chose not to challenge the superior British or French
                    navies.</p>
                <p>Prior to independence, American colonists had enjoyed the protection of the
                    British Navy. However, once the United States declared independence, British
                    diplomats were quick to inform the Barbary States that U.S. ships were open to
                    attack. In 1785, <persName>Dey Muhammad</persName> of
                        <placeName>Algiers</placeName> declared war on the United States and
                    captured several American ships. The financially troubled Confederation
                    Government of the United States was unable to raise a navy or the tribute that
                    would protect U.S. ships.</p>
                <p>In contrast to the dispute with <placeName>Algiers, U.S. negotiations with
                    </placeName>Morocco went well. Moroccan Sultan <persName>Sidi
                        Muhammad</persName> had seized a U.S. merchant ship in 1784 after the United
                    States had ignored diplomatic overtures. However, Muhammad ultimately followed a
                    policy of peaceful trade, and the United States successfully concluded a treaty
                    with Morocco in 1786. However, Congress was still unable to raise enough funds
                    to satisfy the Dey of Algiers.</p>
                <p>In an attempt to address the challenge posed by the Dey of Algiers, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson,</ref>
                    then U.S. Minister to France, attempted to build a coalition of weaker naval
                    powers to defeat Algiers, but was unsuccessful. However, the Kingdom of Portugal
                    was also at war with Algiers, and blocked Algerian ships from sailing past the
                    Straits of Gibraltar. As a result, U.S. merchant ships in the Atlantic Ocean
                    remained safe for a time and temporarily relieved the U.S. Government from the
                    challenges posed by the Barbary States.</p>
                <p>In 1793 a brief Portuguese-Algerian truce exposed American merchant ships to
                    capture, forcing the United States, which had thus far only managed to conclude
                    a treaty with Morocco, to engage in negotiations with the other Barbary States.
                    In 1795, The U.S. Government dispatched diplomats <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/barlow-joel">Joel Barlow</ref>, Joseph
                    Donaldson, and Richard O’Brien to North Africa and successfully concluded
                    treaties with the states of Algiers, Tunis, and Tripoli. Under the terms of
                    these treaties, the United States agreed to pay tribute to these states. The
                    treaty with Algiers freed 83 American sailors.</p>
                <p>The adoption of the Constitution in 1789 gave the U.S. Government the power to
                    levy taxes and to raise and maintain armed forces, powers which had been lacking
                    under the Articles of Confederation. In 1794, in response to Algerian seizures
                    of American ships, Congress authorized construction of the first 6 ships of the
                    U.S. Navy. In 1801, the Pasha of Tripoli, Yusuf Qaramanli, citing late payments
                    of tribute, demanded additional tribute and declared war on the United States.
                    The United States successfully defeated Qaramanli’s forces with a combined naval
                    and land assault by the United States Marine Corps. The U.S. treaty with Tripoli
                    concluded in 1805 included a ransom for American prisoners in Tripoli, but no
                    provisions for tribute.</p>
                <p>In 1812, the new Dey of Algiers, <persName>Hajji Ali,</persName> rejected the
                    American tribute negotiated in the 1795 treaty as insufficient and declared war
                    on the United States. Algerian corsairs captured an American ship several weeks
                    later. In accordance with an agreement between the Dey and British diplomats,
                    the Algerian declaration was timed to coincide with the start of the War of 1812
                    between Britain and the United States. The war with Britain prevented the U.S.
                    Government from either confronting Algerian forces or ransoming U.S. captives in
                    Algiers. Once the Treaty of Ghent ended war with Britain, President James
                    Madison requested that Congress declare war on
                    Algiers, with Congress authorizing the use of force on March 3, 1815. The U.S. Navy, greatly increased in size
                    after the War of 1812, was able send an entire squadron, led by Commodore
                    Stephen Decatur, to the Mediterranean.</p>
                <p>When the U.S. naval expedition arrived in <placeName>Algiers</placeName>, a new
                    ruler, <persName>Dey Omar,</persName> was in power. Omar wished to restore order
                    after several years of political instability and was acutely aware that he could
                    no longer count on British support against the Americans. Decatur had already
                    defeated two Algerian warships and captured hundreds of prisoners of war, and
                    was in a favorable position for negotiation. Dey Omar reluctantly accepted the
                    treaty proposed by Decatur that called for an exchange of U.S. and Algerian
                    prisoners and an end to the practices of tribute and ransom. Having defeated the
                    most powerful of the Barbary States, Decatur sailed to Tunis and Tripoli and
                    obtained similar treaties. In Tripoli, Decatur also secured from Pasha Qaramanli
                    the release of all European captives. The U.S. Senate ratified Decatur’s
                    Algerian treaty on December 5, 1815. Dey Omar repudiated the treaty, but another
                    U.S. squadron arrived after a combined Anglo-Dutch bombardment of Algiers, and
                    U.S. commissioner William Shaler dictated terms of a new treaty which contained
                    essentially the same provisions as the old one. Shaler concluded his
                    negotiations on December 23, 1815, but the Senate, owing to an accidental
                    oversight, did not ratify the treaty until February 11, 1822.</p>
                <p>The Barbary States, although they did not capture any more U.S. ships, began to
                    resume raids in the Mediterranean, and despite punitive British bombardments did
                    not end their practices until the French conquest of Algeria in 1830.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="napoleonic-wars">
                <head>Napoleonic Wars and the United States, <date from="1803" to="1815"
                        >1803–1815</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Napoleonic Wars continued the Wars of the French Revolution. Great Britain
                    and France fought for European supremacy, and treated weaker powers
                    heavy-handedly. The United States attempted to remain neutral during the
                    Napoleonic period, but eventually became embroiled in the European conflicts,
                    leading to the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>
                    against Great Britain.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="napoleanicwars.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Napoleonic Wars</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <persName>Napoleon Bonaparte</persName> seized power in 1799 after overthrowing
                    the French revolutionary government. During this time, U.S. and French
                    negotiators were concluding negotiations to end the Quasi-War with France. In
                    1802, Napoleon ended ten years of warfare with Great Britain under the Peace of
                    Amiens. He used this opportunity to attempt to crush the Haitian Revolution, but
                    the army he sent met with defeat. Napoleon had also re-obtained the North
                    American province of Louisiana from Spain in 1800. However, the loss of Haiti
                    made Louisiana strategically undesirable, and with war again on the horizon with
                    Great Britain, Napoleon was willing to agree to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">Louisiana Purchase</ref>
                    in 1803.</p>
                <p>As expected, Britain declared war on France in 1803, and would remain at war for
                    over a decade. During this period of war, Napoleon and British leaders
                    concentrated on European affairs, but the conflict spilled over into the
                    Atlantic. From 1803 to 1806, the United States succeeded in remaining neutral,
                    but suffered from impressment, British seizure of British-born naturalized U.S.
                    citizens into the British navy. President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    sent <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/pinkney-william">William
                        Pinkney</ref> and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James
                        Monroe</ref> to negotiate a treaty that would halt the impressment of
                    American sailors, but when the signed treaty came back without any British
                    concessions on the impressment issue, Jefferson did not pass it on to the Senate
                    for ratification.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="napoleon.jpg" height="412px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>Napoleon Bonarparte</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1806, Napoleon issued the Berlin Decree, which forbade trade with Britain, and
                    the British Government responded the next year with Orders in Council, which
                    instituted a blockade of French-controlled Europe, and authorized the British
                    navy to seize ships violating the blockade. Napoleon responded with further
                    trade restrictions in the Milan Decree of 1807.</p>
                <p>U.S. relations with Great Britain became increasingly rocky during this period.
                    On June 22, 1807, the H.M.S. <hi rend="italic">Leopard</hi> bombarded and
                    forcibly boarded the U.S.S. <hi rend="italic"/>Chesapeake off Norfolk, Virginia
                    in search of British navy deserters. President Jefferson responded with an
                    embargo on all foreign trade in an effort to weaken the British economy. The
                    embargo was extremely unpopular in New England, where the economy was heavily
                    dependent on trade with Britain. Moreover, the British economy was not strongly
                    affected by the embargo, which proved difficult to enforce. In early 1809, in
                    one of his final acts as president, Jefferson replaced the embargo with the
                    Non-Intercourse Act, which allowed trade with other nations except Britain and
                    France. This act also proved virtually impossible to enforce.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="jamesmadison.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>James Madison</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Jefferson’s successor, President <persName>James Madison</persName>, confronted a
                    dilemma—to continue with the ineffective Non-Intercourse Act was effectively to
                    submit to British terms of trade since the British navy controlled the Atlantic.
                    Madison was assisted by the passage in 1810 of Nathaniel Macon’s Bill No. 2,
                    which offered Britain and France the option of ceasing their seizure of U.S.
                    merchant ships in return for U.S. participation in their trade bloc. Napoleon
                    was the first to offer concessions, which Madison publicly accepted at face
                    value despite his private skepticism. In doing so, Madison pushed the United
                    States closer to war with Britain.</p>
                <p>During this period, Madison also had to address a problem created by Secretary of
                    State, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/smith-robert">Robert Smith</ref>,
                    who had personally stated to the British minister his pro-British sympathies.
                    When Madison confronted Smith and offered him a graceful departure as U.S.
                    Minister to Russia, Smith appeared to accept his offer, and then leaked cabinet
                    papers as part of a smear campaign against President Madison. U.S. diplomat Joel
                    Barlow published a reply and swung public opinion against Smith, who resigned on
                    April 1, 1811.</p>
                <p>Relations with Great Britain continued to deteriorate. A U.S. Navy ship mistook a
                    much smaller British ship, the HMS <hi rend="italic">Little Belt</hi>, for a
                    British Navy ship that had impressed American sailors and fired upon it.
                    Consequently, Thomas Foster, British Minister to the United States, stated that
                    Britain would not offer any compensation for the 1807 <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chesapeake</hi> incident. Foster also informed Madison that the British
                    Government would not revoke the Orders in Council. By the spring of 1812,
                    Madison had decided upon war with Great Britain—although he also considered
                    declaring war on France as well. Congress passed a declaration of war on June
                    17, which Madison signed the next day. The war continued into 1815, although
                    diplomats signed the Treaty of Ghent on December 23, 1814.</p>
                <p>The Napoleonic Wars marked a period of U.S. weakness in the face of British
                    power. However, in the postwar period, British policies began to soften, leading
                    to the Rush-Bagot agreement and the Convention of 1818.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="louisiana-purchase">
                <head>Louisiana Purchase, <date when="1803">1803</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Louisiana Purchase encompassed 530,000,000 acres of territory in North
                    America that the <placeName>United States</placeName> purchased from
                        <placeName>France</placeName> in 1803 for $15 million.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="purchase.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Louisiana Purchase</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As the United States spread across the Appalachians, the Mississippi River became
                    an increasingly important conduit for the produce of America’s West (which at
                    that time referred to the land between the Appalachians and the Mississippi).
                    Since 1762, <placeName>Spain</placeName> had owned the territory of Louisiana,
                    which included 828,000 square miles. The territory made up all or part of
                    fifteen modern U.S. states between the Mississippi River and the Rocky
                    Mountains. The <ref target="/milestones/1784-1800/pickney-treaty">Pinckney
                        treaty of 1795</ref> had resolved friction between Spain and the United States over the
                    right to navigate the Mississippi and the right for Americans to transfer their
                    goods to ocean-going vessels at New Orleans. With the
                    Pinckney treaty in place and the weak Spanish empire in control of Louisiana,
                    American statesmen felt comfortable that the United States’ westward expansion
                    would not be restricted in the future.</p>
                <p>This situation was threatened by <persName>Napoleon Bonaparte</persName>’s plans
                    to revive the French empire in the New World. He planned to recapture the
                    valuable sugar colony of St. Domingue from a slave rebellion, and then use
                    Louisiana as the granary for his empire. France acquired Louisiana from Spain in
                    1800 and took possession in 1802, sending a large French army to St. Domingue
                    and preparing to send another to New Orleans. Westerners became very
                    apprehensive about having the more-powerful French in control of New Orleans:
                    President <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas
                        Jefferson noted</ref>, <quote>“There is on the globe one single spot, the
                        possessor of which is our natural and habitual enemy. It is New
                        Orleans.”</quote>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="monroe.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>James Monroe</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In addition to making military preparations for a conflict in the Mississippi
                    Valley, Jefferson sent <persName>James Monroe</persName> to join
                        <persName>Robert Livingston</persName> in France to try to purchase New
                    Orleans and West Florida for as much as $10 million. Failing that, they were to
                    attempt to create a military alliance with England. Meanwhile, the French army
                    in St. Domingue was being decimated by yellow fever, and war between France and
                    England still threatened. Napoleon decided to give up his plans for Louisiana,
                    and offered a surprised Monroe and Livingston the entire territory of Louisiana
                    for $15 million. Although this far exceeded their instructions from President Jefferson, they agreed. </p>
                <p>When news of the sale reached the United States, the West was elated. President
                        <persName>Jefferson,</persName> however, was in a quandary. He had always
                    advocated strict adherence to the letter of the Constitution, yet there was no
                    provision empowering him to purchase territory. Given the public support for the
                    purchase and the obvious value of Louisiana to the future growth of the United
                    States, however, Jefferson decided to ignore the legalistic interpretation of
                    the Constitution and forgo the passage of a Constitutional amendment to validate
                    the purchase. This decision contributed to the principle of implied powers of
                    the federal government.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="war-of-1812">
                <head>War of <date from="1812" to="1815">1812–1815</date>
                </head>
                <p>As an important neutral trading nation, the United States became ensnarled in the
                    European conflict that pitted Napoleonic France against Great Britain and her
                    continental allies.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="warof1812.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>War of 1812</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1806 France prohibited all neutral trade with Great Britain and in 1807 Great
                    Britain banned trade between France, her allies, and the Americas. Congress
                    passed an embargo act in 1807 in retaliation, prohibiting U.S. vessels from
                    trading with European nations, and later the Non-Intercourse Acts, aimed solely
                    at France and Britain. The embargo and non-intercourse act proved ineffective
                    and in 1810 the United States reopened trade with France and Great Britain
                    provided they ceased their blockades against neutral trading. Great Britain
                    continued to stop American merchant ships to search for Royal Navy deserters, to
                    impress American seamen on the high seas into the Royal Navy, and to enforce its
                    blockade of neutral commerce. Madison made the issue of impressment from ships
                    under the American flag a matter of national sovereignty—even after the British
                    agreed to end the practice—and asked Congress for a declaration of War on Great
                    Britain on <date when="1812-06-01">June 1, 1812.</date> Many who supported the
                    call to arms saw British and Spanish territory in North America as potential
                    prizes to be won by battle or negotiations after a successful war.</p>
                <p>Pro-British Federalists in Washington were outraged by what they considered
                    Republican favoritism toward France. The leading Republican, <persName>Thomas
                        Jefferson</persName> responded, that <quote>“the English being equally
                        tyrannical at sea as he [Napoleon] is on land, and that tyranny bearing on
                        us in every point of either honor or interest, I say ‘down with
                        England.’”</quote> The United States declared the war on Britain. After
                    Napoleon’s disastrous Russian campaign of 1812, the British concentrated on the
                    American continent, enacting a crippling blockading of the east coast, attacking
                    Washington and burning the White House and other Government buildings, and
                    acquiring territory in Maine and the Great Lakes region. American forces,
                    however, won important naval and military victories at sea, on Lake Champlain,
                    and at Baltimore and Detroit. Canadians defeated an American invasion of Lower
                    Canada. By 1814 neither side could claim a clear victory and both war weary
                    combatants looked to a peaceful settlement.</p>
                <p>Under the mediation of the Czar of Russia, Great Britain and the United States
                    came together in the summer of 1814 to negotiate the terms of peace. On
                    Christmas Eve British and American negotiators signed the Treaty of Ghent,
                    restoring the political boundaries on the North American continent to the status
                    quo ante bellum, establishing a boundary commission to resolve further
                    territorial disputes, and creating peace with Indian nations on the frontier. As
                    the Ghent negotiations suggested, the real causes of the war of 1812, were not
                    merely commerce and neutral rights, but also western expansion, relations with
                    American Indians, and territorial control of North America.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rush-bagot">
                <head>Rush-Bagot Pact, <date when="1817">1817</date> and Convention of <date
                        when="1818">1818</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Rush-Bagot Pact was an agreement between the United States and Great Britain
                    to eliminate their fleets from the Great Lakes, excepting small patrol vessels.
                    The Convention of 1818 set the boundary between the Missouri Territory in the
                    United States and British North America (later Canada) at the forty-ninth
                    parallel. Both agreements reflected the easing of diplomatic tensions that had
                    led to the War of 1812 and marked the beginning of Anglo-American
                    cooperation.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="greatlakes.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Map of the Great Lakes</head>
                </figure>
                <p>U.S. political leaders had long expressed interest in disarming the Great Lakes
                    and had proposed such a measure during negotiations that led to the 1794 Jay
                    Treaty, but British officials had rejected this proposal. During the War of
                    1812, both Great Britain and the United States had built fleets of ships on
                    lakes Erie and Ontario, and fought many battles in the region. Near the end of
                    the war, U.S. forces had achieved dominance over the Lakes. After the war, both
                    powers were wary of one another’s military strength and a postwar shipbuilding
                    race ensued. However, both countries also wished to reduce their military
                    expenditures. Unfortunately, the Treaty of Ghent, which ended the war, contained
                    no disarmament provisions. However, it did establish commissions to resolve
                    contested areas along the border (as determined by the 1783 Treaty of Paris)
                    between the United States and British North America.</p>
                <p>Although tensions between Great Britain and the United States remained high along
                    the Great Lakes, overall relations improved. Postwar trade rebounded, and
                    British political leaders increasingly viewed the United States as a valuable
                    trading partner, while also realizing that British North America would be
                    expensive and difficult to defend should another war break out. When U.S.
                    Minister to Great Britain, <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName>, proposed
                    disarmament on January 25, 1816, British Foreign Secretary Viscount Castlereagh
                    responded favorably. The British Government had already dispatched
                        <persName>Charles Bagot</persName> as Minister to the United States with the
                    intention of improving relations between the two countries.</p>
                <p>Bagot met with Secretary of State <persName>James Monroe</persName> informally,
                    and finally reached an agreement with his successor, Acting Secretary
                        <persName>Richard Rush.</persName> The agreement limited military navigation
                    on the Great Lakes to one to two vessels per country on each lake. The U.S.
                    Senate ratified the agreement on April 28, 1818. The British Government
                    considered a diplomatic exchange of letters between Rush and Bagot sufficient to
                    make the agreement effective.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="richardrush.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Richard Rush</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In addition to the issue of military navigation of the Great Lakes, the British
                    Government was also open to negotiations regarding a number of other points of
                    contention that had not been resolved by the Treaty of Ghent. Several
                    commissions met to settle border disputes along the U.S. border with British
                    North America. One of these commissions awarded several islands off the coasts
                    of Maine to New Brunswick. However, negotiators deadlocked over other parts of
                    the northern borders of Maine and New Hampshire. That issue would not be
                    resolved until the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/webster-treaty">1842
                        Webster-Ashburton Treaty</ref>, which also resolved the border between
                    Canada and northeastern Minnesota.</p>
                <p>Several other separate committees determined other stretches of border that
                    negotiators at the <ref target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">1783 Treaty of
                        Paris</ref> had drawn with faulty maps. The commissions divided the St.
                    Lawrence and other rivers connecting the Great Lakes to allow both countries
                    navigable channels, and handed Wolfe Island near Kingston, Ontario to the
                    British and Grosse Île near Detroit to the United States. British and U.S.
                    negotiators also agreed to make present-day Angle Inlet, Minnesota the end point
                    of the 1783 border and to allow the Convention of 1818, concluded by Rush and
                    Albert Gallatin, to determine the border to the west of that point.</p>
                <p>While these commissions debated border issues, Rush and Gallatin concluded the
                    Anglo-American Convention of 1818 that, among other things, confirmed permanent
                    U.S. rights to fish off Newfoundland and Labrador. The Convention also made
                    provisions for Russian mediation over the issue of escaped slaves in British
                    hands (U.S. slaveowners were eventually provided monetary compensation) and also
                    determined that the border from Angle Inlet would run south to the forty-ninth
                    parallel, and then due west to the Rocky Mountains. The Oregon Country would
                    remain open to both countries for ten years.</p>
                <p>Although the agreements did not completely settle border disputes and trade
                    arrangements, the Rush-Bagot agreement and the Convention of 1818 marked an
                    important turning point in Anglo-American and American-Canadian relations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="florida">
                <head>Acquisition of Florida: Treaty of Adams-Onis <date when="1819">(1819)</date>
                    and Transcontinental Treaty <date when="1821">(1821)</date>
                </head>
                <p>The colonies of East Florida and West Florida remained loyal to the British
                    during the war for American independence, but by the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">Treaty of Paris</ref> in 1783 they
                    returned to Spanish control. After 1783, Americans immigrants moved into West
                    Florida.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="eastwestflorida.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>East and West Florida</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1810, these American settlers in West Florida rebelled, declaring independence
                    from Spain. President <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james"
                        >James Madison</ref> and Congress used the incident to claim the region,
                    knowing full well that the Spanish government was seriously weakened by
                    Napoleon’s invasion of Spain. The United States asserted that the portion of
                    West Florida from the Mississippi to the Perdido rivers was part of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/louisiana-purchase">Louisiana Purchase of
                        1803</ref>. Negotiations over Florida began in earnest with the mission of
                    Don Luis de Onís to Washington in 1815 to meet Secretary of State
                        <persName>James Monroe.</persName> The issue was not resolved until Monroe
                    was president and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John
                        Quincy Adams</ref> his Secretary of State. Although U.S. Spanish relations
                    were strained over suspicions of American support for the independence struggles
                    of Spanish-American colonies, the situation became critical when General Andrew
                    Jackson seized the Spanish forts at Pensacola and St. Marks in his 1818
                    authorized raid against Seminoles and escaped slaves who were viewed as a
                    threat to Georgia. Jackson executed two British citizens on charges of inciting
                    the Indians and runaways. Monroe’s government seriously considered denouncing
                    Jackson’s actions, but Adams defended the Jackson citing the necessity to
                    restrain the Indians and escaped slaves since the Spanish failed to do so. Adams
                    also sensed that Jackson’s Seminole campaign was popular with Americans and it
                    strengthened his diplomatic hand with Spain.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="johnquincyadams.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>John Quincy Adams</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Adams used the Jackson’s military action to present Spain with a demand to either
                    control the inhabitants of East Florida or cede it to the United States.
                    Minister Onís and Secretary Adams reached an agreement whereby Spain ceded East
                    Florida to the United States and renounced all claim to West Florida. Spain
                    received no compensation, but the United States agreed to assume liability for
                    $5 million in damage done by American citizens who rebelled against Spain. Under
                    the Onís-Adams Treaty of 1819 (also called the Transcontinental Treaty and
                    ratified in 1821) the United States and Spain defined the western limits of the
                    Louisiana Purchase and Spain surrendered its claims to the Pacific Northwest. In
                    return, the United States recognized Spanish sovereignty over Texas. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="monroe">
                <head>Monroe Doctrine, <date when="1823">1823</date>
                </head>
                <p>In his December 2, 1823, address to Congress, President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref>
                    articulated United States’ policy on the new political order developing in the
                    rest of the Americas and the role of Europe in the Western Hemisphere.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="jmonroe.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President James Monroe</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The statement, known as the Monroe Doctrine, was little noted by the Great Powers
                    of Europe, but eventually became a longstanding tenet of U.S. foreign policy.
                    Monroe and his Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy Adams</ref>
                    drew upon a foundation of American diplomatic ideals such as disentanglement
                    from European affairs and defense of neutral rights as expressed in Washington’s
                    Farewell Address and Madison’s stated rationale for waging the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>. The three main
                    concepts of the doctrine—separate spheres of influence for the Americas and
                    Europe, non-colonization, and non-intervention—were designed to signify a clear
                    break between the New World and the autocratic realm of Europe. Monroe’s
                    administration forewarned the imperial European powers against interfering in
                    the affairs of the newly independent Latin American states or potential United
                    States territories. While Americans generally objected to European colonies in
                    the New World, they also desired to increase United States influence and trading
                    ties throughout the region to their south. European mercantilism posed the
                    greatest obstacle to economic expansion. In particular, Americans feared that
                    Spain and France might reassert colonialism over the Latin American peoples who
                    had just overthrown European rule. Signs that Russia was expanding its presence
                    southward from Alaska toward the Oregon Territory were also disconcerting.</p>
                <p>For their part, the British also had a strong interest in ensuring the demise of
                    Spanish colonialism, with all the trade restrictions mercantilism imposed.
                    Earlier in 1823 British Foreign Minister George Canning suggested to Americans
                    that two nations issue a joint declaration to deter any other power from
                    intervening in Central and South America. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy
                    Adams</ref>, however, vigorously opposed cooperation with Great Britain,
                    contending that a statement of bilateral nature could limit United States
                    expansion in the future. He also argued that the British were not committed to
                    recognizing the Latin American republics and must have had imperial motivations
                    themselves.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="canning.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>British Foreign Minister George Canning</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The bilateral statement proposed by the British thereby became a unilateral
                    declaration by the United States. As Monroe stated: <quote>“The American
                        continents … are henceforth not to be considered as subjects for future
                        colonization by any European powers.”</quote> Monroe outlined two separate
                    spheres of influence: the Americas and Europe. The independent lands of the
                    Western Hemisphere would be solely the United States’ domain. In exchange, the
                    United States pledged to avoid involvement in the political affairs of Europe,
                    such as the ongoing Greek struggle for independence from the Ottoman Empire, and
                    not to interfere in the existing European colonies already in the Americas.</p>
                <p>By the mid-1800s, Monroe’s declaration, combined with ideas of Manifest Destiny,
                    provided precedent and support for U.S. expansion on the American continent. In
                    the late 1800s, U.S. economic and military power enabled it to enforce the
                    Monroe Doctrine. The doctrine’s greatest extension came with <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/roosevelt-and-monroe-doctrine">Theodore
                        Roosevelt’s Corollary</ref>, which inverted the original meaning of the
                    doctrine and came to justify unilateral U.S. intervention in Latin America.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
