<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1830–1860</title>
                <title type="short">1830–1860</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1830" to="1860">1830–1860</date>: Diplomacy and Westward
                    Expansion</head>
                <p>During this crucial period, the United States pursued a policy of expansion based
                    on “manifest destiny,” the ideology that Americans were in fact destined to
                    extend their nation across the continent.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="westward.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Illustration of “Manifest Destiny” ( John Gast, 1872)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States even proved to be willing to go to war to secure new
                    territories. While it managed to negotiate an agreement with <placeName>Great
                        Britain</placeName> to secure the Oregon territory, acquiring the valuable
                    territory south of it—including <placeName>California</placeName> and its
                    important Pacific harbors—required the use of force, and, in 1845, the United
                    States embarked on its first offensive war by invading
                        <placeName>Mexico</placeName>.</p>
                <p>In addition to advancing westward, the United States also continued to expand
                    economically through investment in foreign markets and international trade. With
                    these growing commercial interests, came a larger navy and increased
                    international presence. The United States began to turn to the Pacific for new
                    economic opportunities, establishing a presence in <placeName>China</placeName>,
                    and opening <placeName>Japan</placeName> and <placeName>Korea</placeName> to
                    western commercial interests.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="indian-treaties">
                <head>Indian Treaties and the Removal Act of <date when="1830">1830</date>
                </head>
                <p>The U.S. Government used treaties as one means to displace Indians from their
                    tribal lands, a mechanism that was strengthened with the Removal Act of 1830. In
                    cases where this failed, the government sometimes violated both treaties and
                    Supreme Court rulings to facilitate the spread of European Americans westward
                    across the continent.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="andrewjackson.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Andrew Jackson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As the 19th century began, land-hungry Americans poured into the backcountry of
                    the coastal South and began moving toward and into what would later become the
                    states of Alabama and Mississippi. Since Indian tribes living there appeared to
                    be the main obstacle to westward expansion, white settlers petitioned the
                    federal government to remove them. Although Presidents <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref>
                    argued that the Indian tribes in the Southeast should exchange their land for
                    lands west of the Mississippi River, they did not take steps to make this
                    happen. Indeed, the first major transfer of land occurred only as the result of
                    war.</p>
                <p>In 1814, Major General <persName>Andrew Jackson</persName> led an expedition
                    against the Creek Indians climaxing in the Battle of Horse Shoe Bend (in present
                    day Alabama near the Georgia border), where Jackson’s force soundly defeated the
                    Creeks and destroyed their military power. He then forced upon the Indians a
                    treaty whereby they surrendered to the United States over twenty-million acres
                    of their traditional land—about one-half of present day Alabama and one-fifth of
                    Georgia. Over the next decade, Jackson led the way in the Indian removal
                    campaign, helping to negotiate nine of the eleven major treaties to remove
                    Indians.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="horshoebend.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Depiction of William Weatherford surrendering to Andrew Jackson after the
                        Battle of Horseshoe Bend </head>
                </figure>
                <p>Under this kind of pressure, Native American tribes—specifically the Creek,
                    Cherokee, Chickasaw, and Choctaw—realized that they could not defeat the
                    Americans in war. The appetite of the settlers for land would not abate, so the
                    Indians adopted a strategy of appeasement. They hoped that if they gave up a
                    good deal of their land, they could keep at least some a part of it. The
                    Seminole tribe in Florida resisted, in the Second Seminole War (1835–1842) and
                    the Third Seminole War (1855–1858), however, neither appeasement nor resistance
                    worked.</p>
                <p>From a legal standpoint, the United States Constitution empowered Congress to
                        <quote>“regulate commerce with foreign nations, and among the several
                        States, and with the Indian tribes.”</quote> In early treaties negotiated
                    between the federal government and the Indian tribes, the latter typically
                    acknowledged themselves <quote>“to be under the protection of the United States
                        of America, and of no other sovereign whosoever.”</quote> When Andrew
                    Jackson became president (1829–1837), he decided to build a systematic approach
                    to Indian removal on the basis of these legal precedents.</p>
                <p>To achieve his purpose, Jackson encouraged Congress to adopt the Removal Act of
                    1830. The Act established a process whereby the President could grant land west
                    of the Mississippi River to Indian tribes that agreed to give up their
                    homelands. As incentives, the law allowed the Indians financial and material
                    assistance to travel to their new locations and start new lives and guaranteed
                    that the Indians would live on their new property under the protection of the
                    United States Government forever. With the Act in place, Jackson and his
                    followers were free to persuade, bribe, and threaten tribes into signing removal
                    treaties and leaving the Southeast.</p>
                <p>In general terms, Jackson’s government succeeded. By the end of his presidency,
                    he had signed into law almost seventy removal treaties, the result of which was
                    to move nearly 50,000 eastern Indians to Indian Territory—defined as the region
                    belonging to the United States west of the Mississippi River but excluding the
                    states of Missouri and Iowa as well as the Territory of Arkansas—and open
                    millions of acres of rich land east of the Mississippi to white settlers.
                    Despite the vastness of the Indian Territory, the government intended that the
                    Indians’ destination would be a more confined area—what later became eastern
                    Oklahoma.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="removal.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Trail of Tears (Robert Lindneux, 1942)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Cherokee Nation resisted, however, challenging in court the Georgia laws that
                    restricted their freedoms on tribal lands. In his 1831 ruling on Cherokee Nation
                    v. the State of Georgia, Chief Justice <persName>John Marshall</persName>
                    declared that <quote>“the Indian territory is admitted to compose a part of the
                        United States,”</quote> and affirmed that the tribes were <quote>“domestic
                        dependent nations” and “their relation to the United States resembles that
                        of a ward to his guardian.”</quote> However, the following year the Supreme
                    Court reversed itself and ruled that Indian tribes were indeed sovereign and
                    immune from Georgia laws. President Jackson nonetheless refused to heed the
                    Court’s decision. He obtained the signature of a Cherokee chief agreeing to
                    relocation in the Treaty of New Echota, which Congress ratified against the
                    protests of <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel
                        Webster</ref> and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clay-henry">Henry
                        Clay</ref> in 1835. The Cherokee signing party represented only a faction of
                    the Cherokee, and the majority followed Principal Chief <persName>John
                        Ross</persName> in a desperate attempt to hold onto their land. This attempt
                    faltered in 1838, when, under the guns of federal troops and Georgia state
                    militia, the Cherokee tribe were forced to the dry plains across the
                    Mississippi. The best evidence indicates that between three and four thousand
                    out of the fifteen to sixteen thousand Cherokees died en route from the brutal
                    conditions of the “Trail of Tears.”</p>
                <p>With the exception of a small number of Seminoles still resisting removal in
                        <placeName>Florida</placeName>, by the 1840s, from the Atlantic to the
                    Mississippi, no Indian tribes resided in the American South. Through a
                    combination of coerced treaties and the contravention of treaties and judicial
                    determination, the United States Government succeeded in paving the way for the
                    westward expansion and the incorporation of new territories as part of the
                    United States. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="amistad">
                <head>The Amistad Case, <date when="1839">1839</date>
                </head>
                <p>When the Spanish cargo schooner La Amistad came aground off the coast of
                        <placeName>Long Island, New York</placeName> in August 1839, the United
                    States found itself with an explosive legal and diplomatic case that would pit
                    the American system’s ability to provide justice for all on its shores against
                    the federal government’s ability to enforce its treaty obligations where the
                    jurisdiction of states is involved. Officers of the United States survey ship
                    Washington found the Amistad in a state of distress, bearing 53 Africans and the
                    two Spaniards who purchased them in Cuba with the intention of trading them into
                    slavery there. The Africans had mutinied, however, and attempted to have the
                    Spanish owners sail them back to Africa. After the American naval officers
                    helped the owners recover control of the ship and arranged for the guarded
                    detention of the Africans in <placeName>Connecticut</placeName>, procuring the
                    Africans’ freedom became the cause celebre of the burgeoning abolitionist and
                    missionary movement.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cinque.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Joseph Cinqué of the Amistad (Nathaniel Jocelyn, 1840)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Two lawsuits ensued. The Washington officers brought the first case to federal
                    district court over salvage claims while the second case began in a Connecticut
                    court after the state arrested the Spanish traders on charges of enslaving free
                    Africans. The Spanish foreign minister, however, demanded that the Amistad and
                    its cargo be released from custody and the “slaves” sent to Cuba for punishment
                    by Spanish authorities. While the <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/van-buren-martin">Van Buren</ref>
                    administration accepted the Spanish crown’s argument, Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/forsyth-john">John Forsyth</ref>
                    explained, the president could not order the release of the Amistad and its
                    cargo because the executive could not interfere with the judiciary under
                    American law. He could also not release the Spanish traders from imprisonment in
                    Connecticut because that would constitute federal intervention in a matter of
                    state jurisdiction. Less interested in the separation of powers or the division
                    of sovereignty in a federal state than in procuring immediate satisfaction for
                    the Queen’s honor, the Spanish minister retorted that the arrest of Spaniards
                    and the holding of their “Negro property” were violations of the treaty of 1795
                    between Spain and the United States. Thus, at Forsyth’s direction, an attorney
                    for the United States government appeared before the U. S. District Court and
                    presented Spain’s argument that since a federally owned ship rescued the
                    Amistad, the United States was obligated by international treaty to return the
                    ship and its cargo to the Spanish owners.</p>
                <p>The district court judge ruled that the Africans were not Spanish slaves, being
                    captured as free men in Africa, and he ordered the U.S. to release them from
                    prison and transport them back to Africa. Rejecting the argument that the
                    Africans were the Spanish traders’ private property and their sale subject to
                    salvage claims, the judge ruled that the Washington officers’ salvage payments
                    be taken from the remaining cargo of the Amistad. The U.S. Government, feeling
                    pressure from Spain and fearing Southern outcry against the court’s advocacy of
                    African freedom, appealed the decision to the Supreme Court. To argue against
                    the U.S. Government for the Africans’ freedom, the Christian Missionary
                    Association convinced former President and Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-john-quincy">John Quincy Adams</ref>
                    to come out of retirement and face the predominantly southern Supreme Court
                    bench. In a masterpiece of American law, Adams presented the case of the
                    Africans’ freedom as a test of the American republic’s sincerity in the ideals
                    it espoused abroad. The Supreme Court ruled for the Africans, accepting the
                    argument that they were never citizens of Spain and were illegally taken from
                    Africa where they lived in a state of freedom. The court acknowledged that the
                    United States’ argument that it had obligations to Spain under the treaty, but
                    said that the treaty “never could have been intended to take away the equal
                    rights of [the Africans].” The 53 Africans returned to their homeland and the
                    job of resisting Spain’s continued demand for damages passed onto incoming
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel
                        Webster.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="china-1">
                <head>The Opening to China Part I: the First Opium War, the United States, and the
                    Treaty of Wangxia, <date from="1839" to="1844">1839–1844</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Treaty of Wangxia (Wang-hsia) was the first formal treaty signed between the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> and <placeName>China</placeName> in
                    1844. It served as an American counterpart to the Anglo-Chinese Treaty of
                    Nanjing that ended the First Opium War in 1842.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chinatreaty.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Signing of the Treaty of Nanjing in 1842</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Opium War and these treaties were emblematic of an era in which Western
                    powers tried to gain unfettered access to Chinese products and markets for
                    European and U.S. trade.</p>
                <p>Western traders, including those from the United States, had long sought a
                    variety of Chinese products (including furniture, silk and tea), but found there
                    were few products that China wanted from the West. American trade with China
                    began as early as 1784, relying on North American exports such as furs,
                    sandalwood, and ginseng, but American interest in Chinese products soon
                    outstripped the Chinese appetite for these American exports. The British had
                    already discovered a great market in southern China for smuggled opium, and
                    American traders soon also turned to opium to supplement their exports to China.
                    Beyond the health problems related to opium addiction, the increasing opium
                    trade with the Western powers meant that for the first time, China imported more
                    goods than it exported. Settling this financial problem eventually led to the
                    First Opium War between Great Britain and China, from 1839 to 1842. After
                    defeating the Chinese in a series of naval conflicts, the British were in a
                    position to make a large number of demands from the weaker Qing Government of
                    China, in the Anglo-Chinese Treaty of <placeName>Nanjing</placeName>. Not to be
                    outdone, U.S. negotiators sought to conclude a similar treaty with the Chinese,
                    to guarantee the United States many of the favorable terms awarded the British.
                    The Chinese readily agreed in an effort to keep all foreigners on the same
                    footing.</p>
                <p>U.S. President <persName>John Tyler</persName> chose Massachusetts Congressman
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/cushing-caleb">Caleb Cushing</ref> as
                    his representative in treaty negotiations with the Chinese. Cushing and his
                    counterparts reached the terms of the treaty quickly and signed it at Wangxia, a
                    suburb of the Portuguese port city of Macau, in 1844. The Treaty of Wangxia
                    replicated many of the key terms of the Treaty of Nanjing. Most importantly, it
                    established five treaty ports as open for Chinese-Western trade (Guangzhou,
                    Xiamen, Fuzhou, Ningbo, and Shanghai). These treaty ports became key crossroads
                    for Western and Chinese culture, as they were the first locations where
                    foreigners and foreign trading operations could own land in China.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cushing.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Massachusetts Congressman Caleb Cushing</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The U.S. treaty was somewhat longer than the British version, as it included
                    major points from the Treaty of Nanjing, but also added some issues of
                    particular interest to the United States. Article 17 protected the interests of
                    American missionaries in China (several had acted as translators during the
                    negotiation process). Article 18 allowed Americans living or working in China to
                    employ tutors to help them learn Chinese, a practice formerly forbidden by the
                    Chinese Government. Unlike Great Britain, the United States agreed that anyone
                    involved in the opium trade or the smuggling of contraband would be prosecuted
                    under Chinese law, but, with that exception, the treaty allowed for other
                    Americans in China to be afforded the benefits of extraterritoriality. This
                    meant that any American accused of committing a crime in China would not be
                    subject to the jurisdiction of the local law, but would instead be tried and, if
                    necessary, punished by American officials in China. Due to the
                    most-favored-nation clause in all of the western powers’ treaties with the
                    Chinese Government, any special consideration given one power could ultimately
                    be claimed by them all.</p>
                <p>In the 1850s, the United States and the European powers grew increasingly
                    dissatisfied with both the terms of their treaties with China, and the Qing
                    Government’s failure to adhere to them. The British forced the issue by
                    attacking the Chinese port cities of <placeName>Guangzhou</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Tianjin</placeName> in the Second Opium War (1857–1858). Under
                    the most-favored-nation clause, all of the foreign powers operating in China
                    were permitted to seek the same concessions of China that Great Britain achieved
                    by force. As a result, France, Russia, and the United States all signed treaties
                    with China at Tianjin in quick succession in 1858.</p>
                <p>The agreements reached between the Western powers and China following the Opium
                    Wars came to be known as the “unequal treaties” because in practice they gave
                    foreigners privileged status and extracted concessions from the Chinese.
                    Ironically, the Qing Government had fully supported the clauses on
                    extraterritoriality and most-favored nation status in the first treaties in
                    order to keep the foreigners in line. This treaty system also marked a new
                    direction for Chinese contact with the outside world. For years, the Chinese had
                    conducted their foreign policy through the tribute system, in which foreign
                    powers wishing to trade with China were required first to bring a tribute to the
                    emperor, acknowledging the superiority of Chinese culture and the ultimate
                    authority of the Chinese ruler. Unlike China’s neighbors, the European powers
                    ultimately refused to make these acknowledgements in order to trade, and they
                    demanded instead that China adhere to Western diplomatic practices, such as the
                    creation of treaties. Although the unequal treaties and the use of the
                    most-favored-nation clause were effective in creating and maintaining open trade
                    with China, both were also important factors in building animosity and
                    resentment toward Western imperialism.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="webster-treaty">
                <head>Webster-Ashburton Treaty, <date when="1842">1842</date>
                </head>
                <p>During <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel
                        Webster</ref>’s first term as Secretary of State (1841–1843), the primary
                    foreign policy issues involved Great Britain. These included the northeast
                    borders of the United States, the involvement of American citizens in the
                    Canadian rebellion of 1837, and the suppression of the international slave
                    trade. The Webster-Ashburton Treaty, signed August 9, 1842, resolved these
                    frictions in Anglo-American relations. On April 4, 1842, British diplomat Lord
                    Ashburton arrived in Washington at the head of a special mission to the United
                    States. The first order of business was settling the border between the United
                    States and Canada.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="webster-ashburton.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Webster-Ashburton Treaty</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Several disputes had arisen from differing interpretations of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1776-1783/treaty">1783 Treaty of Paris</ref> that ended
                    the Revolutionary War. When these differences led New Brunswick officials to
                    arrest some Americans in disputed areas, Maine called out the militia and seized
                    the territory in question, the so-called Aroostock War. The incident dramatized
                    the need for a border settlement. Webster and Ashburton agreed on a division of
                    disputed territory, giving 7,015 square miles to the United States and 5,012 to
                    Great Britain; agreed on the boundary line through the Great Lakes to the Lake
                    of the Woods; and agreed on provisions for open navigation in several bodies of
                    water. The issue of the Oregon border was left to a later date. After the
                    suppression of the Canadian Rebellion of 1837, several participants fled to the
                    United States where some American adventurers joined them. This band occupied a
                    Canadian island in the Niagara River and engaged a U.S. ship, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Caroline</hi>, to re-supply them. Canadian troops seized the
                        <hi rend="italic">Caroline</hi> in a New York port, killing one crewman in
                    the process, and set the ship free to drift over Niagara Falls. Later,
                        <persName>Alexander McLeod</persName> crossed into New York, bragging that
                    he had participated in the seizure of the <hi rend="italic">Caroline</hi>, and
                    had killed the crewman. McLeod was arrested. Great Britain maintained that
                    McLeod had acted as a member the British forces and that it would take
                    responsibility for his actions. Should he be executed, it would mean war.</p>
                <p>The U.S. Government agreed that McLeod could not be tried for actions committed
                    under orders of the British Government, but it was legally incapable of
                    compelling the State of New York to release him. New York would not back down
                    and tried McLeod. He was acquitted, but hard feelings remained. Webster and
                    Ashburton agreed on the principles of international law involved and exchanged
                    conciliatory statements. The United States enacted a law allowing Federal judges
                    to discharge any person proved to have acted under instruction of a foreign
                    power. The United States and Canada later concluded an extradition treaty.
                    Secretary Webster would not agree to British inspection of U.S. ships suspected
                    of carrying slaves, but did agree that U.S. warships would be maintained off the
                    coast of Africa to search suspected slavers flying the American flag.
                    Unfortunately, the United States did not implement this agreement very
                    vigorously until the Civil War began. Webster and Ashburton also settled the
                    case of the <hi rend="italic">Creole</hi>, although it was not mentioned in the
                    treaty. The <hi rend="italic">Creole</hi> was sailing to New Orleans with 135
                    slaves, when a mutiny resulted in the death of one of the white passengers. The
                    ship sailed to the <placeName>Bahamas</placeName> where the slaves were freed.
                        <placeName>Great Britain</placeName> eventually paid $110,330 to the United
                    States on the grounds that under international law officials in the Bahamas
                    should not have allowed the slaves to be freed. Also, outside of the treaty,
                    Great Britain agreed to end the impressment of American sailors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="oregon-territory">
                <head>The Oregon Territory, <date when="1846">1846</date></head>
                <p>Along with territorial disputes with Spain and Mexico over the Southwest, the
                    fate of the Oregon Territory was one of the major diplomatic issues of the first
                    half of the 19th century.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="oregon.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Landscape in Oregon Country (Charles Marion Russell)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The territory became a focus of those who believed that it was the United States’
                    obligation and right to extend its rule and liberties across the North American
                    continent. The Oregon Territory stretched from the Pacific coast to the Rocky
                    Mountains, encompassing the area including present-day Oregon, Washington, and
                    most of British Columbia.</p>
                <p>Originally Spain, Great Britain, Russia, and the United States claimed the
                    territory. In 1819, under terms of the Transcontinental Treaty, <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/florida">Spain ceded its claims to the
                        territory to the United States</ref>. Shortly thereafter the United States
                    contested a unilateral Russian move to grant its citizens a fishing, whaling,
                    and commercial monopoly from the Bering Straits to the 51st parallel. In 1823
                    President Monroe promulgated his <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe"
                        >doctrine</ref>, which put Russia on notice that the United States did not
                    accept Russian attempts at monopoly. The U.S. claim was based on the
                    explorations of Lewis and Clark and on the establishment of trading posts set up
                    by <persName>John Jacob Astor</persName>’s Pacific Fur Company, such as Astoria
                    at the mouth of the Columbia River. Great Britain based its claim, in part, on
                    James Cook’s exploration of the Columbia River.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="astor.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>John Jacob Astor</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As early as 1818 British and American Commissioners had fixed the border between
                    the United States and Canada at the 49th parallel from the Lake of the Woods
                    (Minnesota Territory) west to the Rocky Mountains. The United States had
                    proposed to extend the border along the same parallel to the Pacific Ocean, but
                    Great Britain insisted that the northern border be drawn west to the Columbia
                    River and then follow that river to the ocean. Neither side then budged, but
                    they did agree to postpone the decision for 10 years. In 1827 Washington and
                    London agreed to postpone the issue indefinitely subject to one year’s notice by
                    either party. There the matter remained until the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/webster-treaty">Webster-Ashburton Treaty of
                        1842</ref> partially delineated the northeastern U.S.-Canada border, but
                    left the border of the Oregon Territory unsettled.</p>
                <p>By 1843, increased American immigration on the Oregon Trail to the Territory made
                    the border issue a burning one in Congress, where jingoists raised the slogan of
                    “54 degrees 40 minutes or fight.” President James Polk, a supporter of Manifest
                    Destiny with an eye also on the Mexican Southwest and California, was eager to
                    settle the boundary of the Oregon Territory and proposed a settlement on the 49
                    degree line to Great Britain. British Minister to Washington, Richard Pakenham,
                    and Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/buchanan-james"
                        >James Buchanan,</ref> supported and encouraged by British Foreign Secretary
                        <persName>Lord Aberdeen</persName> and Senator <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/calhoun-john-caldwell">John C.
                        Calhoun</ref> of South Carolina, worked out a compromise. With some minor
                    modifications, which reserved the whole of Vancouver Island to Canada, Great
                    Britain agreed to Polk’s suggestion. The Senate ratified the treaty by a vote of
                    41-14 on June 18, 1846. A later controversy over the precise boundaries in the
                    Juan de Fuca Strait was resolved by international arbitration in favor of the
                    United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="texas-annexation">
                <head>The Annexation of Texas, the Mexican-American War, and the Treaty of
                    Guadalupe-Hidalgo, <date from="1845" to="1848">1845–1848</date>
                </head>
                <p>During his tenure, U.S. President <persName>James K. Polk</persName> oversaw the
                    greatest territorial expansion of the United States to date. Polk accomplished
                    this through the annexation of Texas in 1845, the negotiation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/oregon-territory">Oregon Treaty</ref> with
                    Great Britain in 1846, and the conclusion of the Mexican-American War in 1848,
                    which ended with the signing and ratification of the Treaty of Guadalupe-Hidalgo
                    in 1848. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="mexicanwar.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Battle of Veracruz</head>
                </figure>
                <p>These events brought within the control of the United States the future states of
                    Texas, California, Nevada, New Mexico, Arizona, Utah, Washington, and Oregon, as
                    well as portions of what would later become Oklahoma, Colorado, Kansas, Wyoming,
                    and Montana.</p>
                <p>Following Texas’ successful war of independence against Mexico in 1836, President
                        <persName>Martin van Buren</persName> refrained from annexing
                        <placeName>Texas</placeName> after the Mexicans threatened war. Accordingly,
                    while the United States extended diplomatic recognition to Texas, it took no
                    further action concerning annexation until 1844, when President <persName>John
                        Tyler</persName> restarted negotiations with the Republic of Texas. His
                    efforts culminated on April 12 in a Treaty of Annexation, an event that caused
                    Mexico to sever diplomatic relations with United States. Tyler, however, lacked
                    the votes in the Senate to ratify the treaty, and it was defeated by a wide
                    margin in June. Shortly before he left office, Tyler tried again, this time
                    through a joint resolution of both houses of Congress. With the support of
                    President-elect Polk, Tyler managed to get the joint resolution passed on March
                    1, 1845, and Texas was admitted into the United States on December 29.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="presidentyler.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President John Tyler</head>
                </figure>
                <p>While Mexico did not follow through with its threat to declare war if the United
                    States annexed Texas, relations between the two nations remained tense due to
                    Mexico’s disputed border with Texas. According to the Texans, their state
                    included significant portions of what is today New Mexico and Colorado, and the
                    western and southern portions of Texas itself, which they claimed extended to
                    the Rio Grande River. The Mexicans, however, argued that the border only
                    extended to the Nueces River, north of the Rio Grande.</p>
                <p>In July, 1845, Polk, who had been elected on a platform of expansionism, ordered
                    the commander of the U.S. Army in Texas, <persName>Zachary Taylor,</persName> to
                    move his forces into the disputed lands that lay between the Nueces and Rio
                    Grande rivers. In November, Polk dispatched Congressman <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/slidell-john">John Slidell</ref> to Mexico
                    with instructions to negotiate the purchase of the disputed areas along the
                    Texas-Mexican border, and the territory comprising the present-day states of New
                    Mexico and California.</p>
                <p>Following the failure of Slidell’s mission in May 1846, Polk used news of
                    skirmishes inside disputed territory between Mexican troops and Taylor’s army to
                    gain Congressional support for a declaration of war against Mexico. On May 13,
                    1846, the United States declared war on Mexico.</p>
                <p>Following the capture of <placeName>Mexico City</placeName> in September 1847,
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/trist-nicholas-philip">Nicholas
                        Trist</ref>, chief clerk of the Department of State and Polk’s peace
                    emissary, began negotiations for a peace treaty with the Mexican Government
                    under terms similar to those pursued by Slidell the previous year. Polk soon
                    grew concerned by Trist’s conduct, however, believing that he would not press
                    for strong enough terms from the Mexicans, and because Trist became a close
                    friend of General <persName>Winfield Scott,</persName> a Whig who was thought to
                    be a strong contender for his party’s presidential nomination for the 1848
                    election. Furthermore, the war had encouraged expansionist Democrats to call for
                    a complete annexation of Mexico. Polk recalled Trist in October.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="trist.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Chief Clerk of the Department of State, Nicholas Trist</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Believing that he was on the cusp of an agreement with the Mexicans, Trist
                    ignored the recall order and presented Polk with the Treaty of
                    Guadalupe-Hidalgo, which was signed in <placeName>Mexico City</placeName> on
                    February 2, 1848. Under the terms of the treaty, Mexico ceded to the United
                    States approximately 525,000 square miles (55% of its prewar territory) in
                    exchange for a $15 million lump sum payment, and the assumption by the U.S.
                    Government of up to $3.25 million worth of debts owed by Mexico to U.S.
                    citizens.</p>
                <p>While Polk would have preferred a more extensive annexation of Mexican territory,
                    he realized that prolonging the war would have disastrous political consequences
                    and decided to submit the treaty to the Senate for ratification. Although there
                    was substantial opposition to the treaty within the Senate, on March 10, 1848,
                    it passed by a razor-thin margin of 38 to 14.</p>
                <p>The war had another significant outcome. On August 8, 1846, Congressman
                        <persName>David Wilmot</persName> introduced a rider to an appropriations
                    bill that stipulated that “neither slavery nor involuntary servitude shall ever
                    exist” in any territory acquired by the United States in the war against Mexico.
                    While Southern senators managed to block adoption of the so-called “Wilmot
                    Proviso,” it nonetheless provoked a political firestorm. The question of whether
                    slavery could expand throughout the United States continue to fester until the
                    defeat of the Confederacy in 1865. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="liberia">
                <head>Founding of Liberia, <date when="1847">1847</date>
                </head>
                <p>The founding of <ref target="/countries/liberia">Liberia</ref> in the early 1800s
                    was motivated by the domestic politics of slavery and race in the United States
                    as well as by U.S. foreign policy interests. In 1816, a group of white Americans
                    founded the American Colonization Society (ACS) to deal with the “problem” of
                    the growing number of free blacks in the United States by resettling them in
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName>. The resulting state of Liberia would become
                    the second (after Haiti) black republic in the world at that time.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="roberts.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Joseph Jenkins Roberts, First President of Liberia</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prominent Americans such as <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/clay-henry"
                        >Henry Clay, </ref>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/webster-daniel">Daniel Webster,</ref> and
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/randolph-john">John Randolph</ref>
                    were among the best known members of ACS. Former President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/jefferson-thomas">Thomas Jefferson</ref>
                    publicly supported the organization’s goals, and President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/madison-james">James Madison</ref>
                    arranged public funding for the Society. The motives for joining the society
                    were vast as a range of people from abolitionists to slaveholders counted
                    themselves members. On the other hand, many abolitionists, both black and white,
                    ultimately rejected the notion that it was impossible for the races to integrate
                    and therefore did not support the idea of an African-American colony in Africa.
                    Still, the ACS had powerful support and its colonization project gained
                    momentum.</p>
                <p>In 1818 the Society sent two representatives to <placeName>West
                        Africa</placeName> to find a suitable location for the colony, but they were
                    unable to persuade local tribal leaders to sell any territory. In 1820, 88 free
                    black settlers and 3 society members sailed for Sierra Leone. Before departing
                    they had signed a constitution requiring that an agent of the Society administer
                    the settlement under U.S. laws. They found shelter on Scherbo Island off the
                    west coast of Africa, but many died from malaria. In 1821, a U.S. Navy vessel
                    resumed the search for a place of permanent settlement in what is now Liberia.
                    Once again the local leaders resisted American attempts to purchase land. This
                    time, the Navy officer in charge, Lieutenant Robert Stockton, coerced a local
                    ruler to sell a strip of land to the Society. The Scherbo Island group moved to
                    this new location and other blacks from the United States joined them. The local
                    tribes continually attacked the new colony and in 1824, the settlers built
                    fortifications for protection. In that same year, the settlement was named
                    Liberia and its capital Monrovia, in honor of President <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/monroe-james">James Monroe</ref> who had
                    procured more U.S. Government money for the project.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="stockton.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Lieutenant Robert Stockton</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Other colonization societies sponsored by individual states purchased land and
                    sent settlers to areas near<placeName>Monrovia</placeName>. Africans removed
                    from slave ships by the U.S. Navy after the abolition of the trans-Atlantic
                    slave trade were also put ashore in Liberia. In 1838 most of these settlements,
                    with up to 20,000 people, combined into one organization. The settlers attempted
                    to retain the culture they had brought from the United States and for the most
                    part did not integrate with the native societies. Today, about 5 percent of the
                    population of Liberia is descended from these settlers.</p>
                <p>The U.S. Government had provided Liberia some financial support, but Washington
                    expected Monrovia to move toward self-sufficiency. Commerce was the first
                    economic sector to grow in the colony. However, French and British traders
                    continually encroached upon Liberian territory. As it was not a sovereign state,
                    it was hard-pressed to defend its economic interests. The U.S. Government lent
                    some diplomatic support, but Britain and France had territories in West Africa
                    and were better poised to act. As a result, in 1847, Liberia declared
                    independence from the American Colonization Society in order to establish a
                    sovereign state and create its own laws governing commerce.</p>
                <p>Despite protests by the affected British companies, London was the first to
                    extend recognition to the new republic, signing a treaty of commerce and
                    friendship with <placeName>Monrovia</placeName> in 1848. Because of fears of the
                    impact this might have on the issue of slavery in the United States, Washington
                    did not recognize the nation it had played a role in creating. In the meantime,
                    a mass exodus of African-Americans to Liberia never materialized. Though
                    President <persName>Abraham Lincoln</persName> was open to promoting the idea,
                    several abolitionists in his cabinet opposed it, some for moral considerations
                    and others for the more practical reason of retaining sufficient labor and
                    military forces for the future. The United States finally established diplomatic
                    relations with Liberia in <date when="1862">1862,</date> and continued to
                    maintain strong ties until the 1990s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="pacific-expansion">
                <head> United States Maritime Expansion across the Pacific during the 19th
                    Century</head>
                <p>The westward expansion of the United States during the 19th century was not
                    limited to North America, but rather included an ongoing push to establish a
                    stronger U.S. presence in and across the Pacific Ocean. This maritime expansion,
                    driven mostly by commerce, had important implications for U.S. foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="maritimeexpansion.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>“Flying Cloud” (James E. Buttersworth, 1859–60)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The appeal of profits to be earned from the China trade served as the initial
                    impetus to motivate U.S. citizens and officials to enter into the Pacific
                    region. <placeName>China</placeName> was the source of some of the world’s most
                    sought after commodities—tea, porcelain, and silk—and Western merchants had
                    sought access to this highly lucrative trade since at least the 17th century.
                    Following U.S. independence, U.S.-based merchants continued to seek opportunity
                    in China. In February 1784 the Empress of China became the first ship to sail
                    from the United States to China, and in its wake came a steady flow of merchants
                    in search of wealth. During the first decades of the 19th century, U.S.
                    merchants amassed sizable fortunes that they subsequently invested in the
                    development of their homeland. As this trade grew, U.S. traders built a small
                    outpost in China and their interactions with Chinese subjects became more
                    complex and occasionally contentious. The U.S. Government realized that it had
                    to establish formal diplomatic ties in order to protect the interests of its
                    citizens. In the wake of war between Britain and China, and the subsequent
                    opening of diplomatic relations between those two countries, the United States
                    moved to negotiate its own treaty with the Chinese Government. The resulting
                    agreement, <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-1">the Treaty of
                        Wangxia</ref>, was ratified in 1844, and soon thereafter U.S. ministers and
                    consuls took up residence in China’s capital and port cities.</p>
                <p>Making the journey to <placeName>China</placeName> and maintaining the U.S.
                    presence there also required a network of ports extending across the Pacific
                    Ocean, and as such, the <placeName>China</placeName> trade soon drove the United
                    States to expand its presence throughout the Pacific region. Perhaps most
                    significantly, when Commodore Matthew Perry sailed his ships to Japan in 1853,
                    his primary motivation was to establish a foothold that would strengthen the
                    U.S. position for trade and diplomacy in the region. In other words, the United
                    States opened relations with <placeName>Japan</placeName> in large part to
                    enhance its status in China. On a smaller scale, as U.S. merchants began to stop
                    at many of the Pacific Islands to replenish supplies and acquire goods to trade
                    with Chinese merchants, the U.S. Government appointed consuls to several of
                    these places. For example, consulates were established in Fiji in 1844, Samoa in
                    1856, and the Marshall Islands in 1881. The U.S. presence in Hawai’i grew out of
                    the need for a substantial base of operations in the Pacific to support U.S.
                    interests in <placeName>China</placeName>. Ultimately this need became so great,
                    and the U.S. presence so large, that the <placeName>United States</placeName>
                    annexed the islands in <date when="1898">1898</date>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="perry.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Commodore Matthew Perry</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The process of U.S. maritime expansion in the Pacific eventually became a goal in
                    and of itself, culminating in the acquisition of the Philippines from Spain in
                    1898. <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">The
                        Spanish-American War</ref> began with a dispute over Cuba, but a rising tide
                    of interest in overseas empire among U.S. leaders, such as President
                        <persName>William McKinley</persName> and future President
                        <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName>, helped expand the conflict to
                    Spanish possessions in Asia. After a swift victory over Spain, the United States
                    set up a temporary military administration to govern the islands and promote
                    their political, economic, and social development. The <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> established full colonial rule over the
                        <placeName>Philippines</placeName> in <date when="1900">1900</date> during
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/war"> Philippine-American War</ref>.</p>
                <p>U.S. expansion across the Pacific fundamentally changed the global position of
                    the United States. In 1800, the United States held closely to <persName>George
                        Washington</persName>’s advice to avoid “entangling alliances” while
                    pursuing foreign relations based upon trade. By 1900, the United States was a
                    recognized world power with substantial commercial, political, and military
                    interests and territorial holdings throughout the Pacific region. Maritime
                    expansion led to the proclamation of an <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/hay-and-china">Open Door policy for
                            <placeName>China</placeName>
                    </ref> in 1899­–1900, and set the stage for much greater involvement in local
                    and regional politics and trade during the early 20th century.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="gadsden-purchase">
                <head>Gadsden Purchase, <date from="1853" to="1854">1853–1854</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Gadsden Purchase, or Treaty, was an agreement between the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName> and <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, finalized in 1854, in
                    which the United States agreed to pay Mexico $10 million for a 29,670 square
                    mile portion of Mexico that later became part of <placeName>Arizona</placeName>
                    and <placeName>New Mexico</placeName>. Gadsden’s Purchase provided the land
                    necessary for a southern transcontinental railroad and attempted to resolve
                    conflicts that lingered after the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation">Mexican-American
                    War</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="gadsdenpurchase.jpg" height="258px" width="450px"/>
                    <head>Map Depicting the Gadsden Purchase</head>
                </figure>
                <p>While the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo formally ended the Mexican-American War in
                        <date when="1848-02">February 1848</date>, tensions between the Governments
                    of Mexico and the United States continued to simmer over the next six years. The
                    two countries each claimed the Mesilla Valley as part of their own country. The
                    Mexican Government demanded monetary compensation for Native American attacks in
                    the region because, under the Treaty, the United States had agreed to protect
                    Mexico from such attacks; however, the United States refused to comply,
                    insisting that while they had agreed to protect Mexico from Native American
                    attacks, they had not agreed to financially compensate for attacks that did
                    occur. The persistent efforts of private American citizens to enter Mexico
                    illegally and incite rebellions in an effort to gain territory exacerbated
                    tensions between the governments.</p>
                <p>These continuing tensions between Mexico and the United States complicated U.S.
                    efforts to find a southern route for a transcontinental railroad as the only
                    viable routes passed through Mexican territory. In 1847, the United States
                    attempted to buy the Isthmus of Tehuantepec, an isthmus on the southern edge of
                    North America, as an alternative means of providing a southern connection
                    between the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. Mexico, however, had already granted
                    Mexican Don <persName>José de Garay</persName> the right to build colonies for
                    Americans on the isthmus with capital from the New Orleans Company. Fearing the
                    colonists would rebel as those in Texas had, Mexican President Juan Ceballos
                    revoked the grant, angering U.S. investors.</p>
                <p>In 1853, Mexican officials evicted Americans from their property in the disputed
                    Mesilla Valley. When the U.S. Government did not act, Governor William Lane of
                    New Mexico declared the Mesilla Valley part of the U.S. territory of New Mexico.
                    Mexican President <persName>Antonio de Santa Anna</persName> responded by
                    sending troops into the valley. Attempting to defuse the situation, U.S.
                    President Franklin Pierce sent <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/gadsden-james">James Gadsden</ref>, the
                    new U.S. Minister to Mexico, to negotiate with Santa Anna. Secretary of State
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marcy-william-learned">William
                        Marcy</ref> instructed Gadsden to renegotiate a border that provided a route
                    for a southern railroad, arrange for a release of U.S. financial obligations for
                    Native American attacks, and settle the monetary claims between the countries
                    related to the Garay project.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="santanna.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Mexican President Antonio de Santa Anna</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Gadsden met with Santa Anna on September 25, 1853. President
                        <persName>Pierce</persName> sent verbal instructions for Gadsden through
                    Christopher Ward, an agent for U.S. investors in the Garay project, giving
                    Gadsden negotiating options ranging from $50 million for lower California and a
                    large portion of northern Mexico to $15 million for a smaller land deal that
                    would still provide for a southern railroad. Ward also lied to Gadsden, stating
                    the President wanted the claims of the Garay party addressed in any treaty
                    concluded with the Mexican Government; however, President Pierce never gave Ward
                    these instructions because he did not believe in government involvement in
                    affairs between private companies and foreign governments. Santa Anna refused to
                    sell a large portion of Mexico, but he needed money to fund an army to put down
                    ongoing rebellions, so on December 30, 1853 he and Gadsden signed a treaty
                    stipulating that the United States would pay $15 million for 45,000 square miles
                    south of the New Mexico territory and assume private American claims, including
                    those related to the Garay deal. The United States Government agreed to work
                    toward preventing American raids along Mexico’s border and
                        <placeName>Mexico</placeName> voided U.S. responsibility for Native American
                    attacks.</p>
                <p>With a great deal of difficulty resulting from the increasing strife between the
                    northern and southern states, the U.S. Senate ratified a revised treaty on April
                    25, 1854. The new treaty reduced the amount paid to Mexico to $10 million and
                    the land purchased to 29,670 square miles, and removed any mention of Native
                    American attacks and private claims. President Pierce signed the treaty and
                    Gadsden presented the new treaty to Santa Anna, who signed it on June 8,
                    1854.</p>
                <p>After Gadsden’s Purchase a new border dispute caused tension over the United
                    States’ payment, and the treaty failed to resolve the issues surrounding
                    financial claims and border attacks. However, it did create the southern border
                    of the present-day United States, despite the beliefs of the vast majority of
                    policymakers at the time who thought the United States would eventually expand
                    further into Mexico.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="opening-to-japan">
                <head>The United States and the Opening to Japan, <date when="1853">1853</date>
                </head>
                <p>On July 8, 1853, American Commodore <persName>Matthew Perry</persName> led his
                    four ships into the harbor at <placeName>Tokyo Bay</placeName>, seeking to
                    re-establish for the first time in over 200 years regular trade and discourse
                    between Japan and the western world.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="perry.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Commodore Matthew Perry</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although he is often credited with opening <placeName>Japan</placeName> to the
                    western world, Perry was not the first westerner to visit the islands.
                    Portuguese, Spanish, and Dutch traders engaged in regular trade with Japan in
                    the 16th and 17th centuries. Persistent attempts by the Europeans to convert the
                    Japanese to Catholicism and their tendency to engage in unfair trading practices
                    led Japan to expel most foreigners in 1639. For the two centuries that followed,
                        <placeName>Japan</placeName> limited trade access to Dutch and Chinese ships
                    with special charters.</p>
                <p>There were several reasons why the United States became interested in
                    revitalizing contact between <placeName>Japan</placeName> and the West in the
                    mid-19th century. First, the combination of the opening of Chinese ports to
                    regular trade and the annexation of California, creating an American port on the
                    Pacific, ensured that there would be a steady stream of maritime traffic between
                    North America and Asia. Then, as American traders in the Pacific replaced
                    sailing ships with steam ships, they needed to secure coaling stations, where
                    they could stop to take on provisions and fuel while making the long trip from
                    the United States to China. The combination of its advantageous geographic
                    position and rumors that Japan held vast deposits of coal increased the appeal
                    of establishing commercial and diplomatic contacts with the Japanese.
                    Additionally, the American whaling industry had pushed into the North Pacific by
                    the mid-18th century, and sought safe harbors, assistance in case of shipwrecks,
                    and reliable supply stations. In the years leading up to the Perry mission, a
                    number of American sailors found themselves shipwrecked and stranded on Japanese
                    shores, and tales of their mistreatment at the hands of the unwelcoming Japanese
                    spread through the merchant community and across the United States.</p>
                <p>The same combination of economic considerations and belief in Manifest Destiny
                    that motivated U.S. expansion across the North American continent also drove
                    American merchants and missionaries to journey across the Pacific. At the time,
                    many Americans believed that they had a special responsibility to modernize and
                    civilize the Chinese and Japanese. In the case of Japan, missionaries felt that
                    Protestant Christianity would be accepted where Catholicism had generally been
                    rejected. Other Americans argued that, even if the Japanese were unreceptive to
                    Western ideals, forcing them to interact and trade with the world was a
                    necessity that would ultimately benefit both nations.</p>
                <p>Commodore Perry’s mission was not the first American overture to the Japanese. In
                    the 1830s, the Far Eastern squadron of the U.S. Navy sent several missions from
                    its regional base in Guangzhou (Canton), China, but in each case, the Japanese
                    did not permit them to land, and they lacked the authority from the U.S.
                    Government to force the issue. In 1851, President <persName>Millard
                        Fillmore</persName> authorized a formal naval expedition to Japan to return
                    shipwrecked Japanese sailors and request that Americans stranded in Japan be
                    returned to the United States. He sent Commodore John Aulick to accomplish these
                    tasks, but before Aulick left Guangzhou for Japan, he was relieved of his post
                    and replaced by Commodore Matthew Perry. A lifetime naval officer, Perry had
                    distinguished himself in the Mexican-American War and was instrumental in
                    promoting the United States Navy’s conversion to steam power.</p>
                <p>Perry first sailed to the Ryukyus and the Bonin Islands southwest and southeast
                    of the main Japanese islands, claiming territory for the United States, and
                    demanding that the people in both places assist him. He then sailed north to Edo
                    (Tokyo) Bay, carrying a letter from the U.S. President addressed to the Emperor
                    of Japan. By addressing the letter to the Emperor, the United States
                    demonstrated its lack of knowledge about the Japanese government and society. At
                    that time, the Japanese emperor was little more than a figurehead, and the true
                    leadership of Japan was in the hands of the Tokugawa Shogunate.</p>
                <p>Perry arrived in Japanese waters with a small squadron of U.S. Navy ships,
                    because he and others believed the only way to convince the Japanese to accept
                    western trade was to display a willingness to use its advanced firepower. At the
                    same time, Perry brought along a variety of gifts for the Japanese Emperor,
                    including a working model of a steam locomotive, a telescope, a telegraph, and a
                    variety of wines and liquors from the West, all intended to impress upon the
                    Japanese the superiority of Western culture. His mission was to complete an
                    agreement with the Japanese Government for the protection of shipwrecked or
                    stranded Americans and to open one or more ports for supplies and refueling.
                    Displaying his audacity and readiness to use force, Perry’s approach into the
                    forbidden waters around Tokyo convinced the Japanese authorities to accept the
                    letter.</p>
                <p>The following spring, Perry returned with an even larger squadron to receive
                    Japan’s answer. The Japanese grudgingly agreed to Perry’s demands, and the two
                    sides signed the Treaty of Kanagawa on March 31, 1854. According to the terms of
                    the treaty, <placeName>Japan</placeName> would protect stranded seamen and open
                    two ports for refueling and provisioning American ships: Shimoda and Hakodate.
                    Japan also gave the United States the right to appoint consuls to live in these
                    port cities, a privilege not previously granted to foreign nations. This treaty
                    was not a commercial treaty, and it did not guarantee the right to trade with
                    Japan. Still, in addition to providing for distressed American ships in Japanese
                    waters, it contained a most-favored-nation clause, so that all future
                    concessions Japan granted to other foreign powers would also be granted to the
                    United States. As a result, Perry’s treaty provided an opening that would allow
                    future American contact and trade with <placeName>Japan</placeName>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="harris.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Townsend Harris</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The first U.S. consul assigned to a Japanese port was <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/harris-townsend">Townsend Harris</ref>.
                    Like many of the early consuls in Asia, Harris was a New York merchant dealing
                    with Chinese imports. He arrived in Shimoda in 1856, but, lacking the navy
                    squadron that strengthened Perry’s bargaining position, it took Harris far
                    longer to convince the Japanese to sign a more extended treaty. Ultimately,
                    Japanese officials learned of how the British used military action to compel the
                    opening to China, and decided that it was better to open its doors willingly
                    than to be forced to do so. The United States and Japan signed their first true
                    commercial treaty, sometimes called the Harris Treaty, in 1858. The European
                    powers soon followed the U.S. example and drew up their own treaties with Japan.
                        <placeName>Japan</placeName> sent its first mission to the West in 1860,
                    when Japanese delegates journeyed to the United States to exchange the ratified
                    Harris Treaty.</p>
                <p>Although <placeName>Japan</placeName> opened its ports to modern trade only
                    reluctantly, once it did, it took advantage of the new access to modern
                    technological developments. <placeName>Japan</placeName>’s opening to the West
                    enabled it to modernize its military, and to rise quickly to the position of the
                    most formidable Asian power in the Pacific. At the same time, the process by
                    which the United States and the Western powers forced Japan into modern
                    commercial intercourse, along with other internal factors, weakened the position
                    of the Tokugawa Shogunate to the point that the shogun fell from power. The
                    Emperor gained formal control of the country in the Meiji Restoration of 1868,
                    with long-term effects for the rule and modernization of
                        <placeName>Japan</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="china-2">
                <head>The Opening to China Part II: the Second Opium War, the United States, and the
                    Treaty of Tianjin, <date from="1857" to="1859">1857–1859</date>
                </head>
                <p>Following the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-1">First Opium War in the
                        1840s</ref>, the Western powers concluded a series of treaties with
                        <placeName>China</placeName> in an effort to open its lucrative markets to
                    Western trade. In the 1850s, the United States and the European powers grew
                    increasingly dissatisfied with both the terms of their treaties with China and
                    the Qing Government’s failure to adhere to them. The British forced the issue by
                    attacking the Chinese port cities of <placeName>Guangzhou</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Tianjin</placeName> in the Second Opium War. Under the
                    most-favored-nation clause contained in the existing treaties, all of the
                    foreign powers operating in China were permitted to seek the same concessions of
                    China that Great Britain achieved by force. As a result, France, Russia, and the
                    United States all signed treaties with China at Tianjin in quick succession in
                    1858.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="princegong.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Prince Gong, 1860 (Felice Beato, photographer)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>These treaties granted the Western powers a number of rights and privileges. The
                    number of treaty ports increased, with new ports opened to Western trade along
                    the Chinese coast, on the islands of <placeName>Taiwan</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Hainan</placeName>, and along the <placeName>Yangtze
                        River</placeName> in the interior. With the opening of the Yangtze River,
                    foreigners also gained full access to the interior, and were free to travel and
                    conduct business or missions anywhere in China. The British demanded the right
                    of Chinese citizens to emigrate on British ships. British (and therefore,
                    French, American and Russian) diplomats were permitted to establish legations
                    and live in Beijing. The agreements reached at Tianjin also set a new, low
                    tariff for imported goods, giving foreign traders an important advantage.
                    Frustrated by irregularities in Chinese customs services, British and U.S.
                    merchants finally established the Imperial Maritime Customs Service, which
                    regulated trade for the benefit of foreign merchants and provided a steady
                    source of revenue to the Chinese Government.</p>
                <p>Although the Chinese signed the treaties in 1858, it took two more years of
                    fighting before the Chinese Government was disposed to ratify them and accept
                    the terms. Noticing Chinese resistance to some of the principle clauses, in
                    particular to the residence of foreign ambassadors in Beijing, the British
                    continued their attacks on Chinese forts. Although the Chinese repulsed an
                    attack on the Dagu forts in 1859, that one victory was not enough to stop the
                    British forces from making their way north to Beijing. Joined by French forces,
                    the British entered the city and burned the Summer Palace in the northwestern
                    periphery, but spared the Forbidden City, home of the Chinese emperor.</p>
                <p>While the British and French used military power to convince China to accept the
                    new treaty agreements, U.S. diplomat John Ward sought, and finally achieved
                    through diplomatic negotiations, an exchange of treaty ratifications in 1859.
                    Under the most-favored-nation clause, the U.S. ratification allowed the other
                    powers to take advantage of the treaty provisions of the Treaty of Tianjin
                    secured by American diplomacy.</p>
                <p>The agreements reached between the Western powers and China following the Opium
                    Wars came to be known as the “unequal treaties” because in practice they gave
                    foreigners privileged status and extracted concessions from the Chinese.
                    Ironically, the Qing Government had fully supported the clauses on
                    extraterritoriality and most-favored nation status in the first treaties in
                    order to keep the foreigners in line. This treaty system also marked a new
                    direction for Chinese contact with the outside world. For years, the Chinese had
                    conducted their foreign policy through the tribute system, in which foreign
                    powers wishing to trade with China were required first to bring a tribute to the
                    emperor, acknowledging the superiority of Chinese culture and the ultimate
                    authority of the Chinese ruler. Unlike China’s neighbors, the European powers
                    ultimately refused to make these acknowledgements in order to trade, and they
                    demanded instead that China adhere to Western diplomatic practices, such as the
                    creation of treaties. Although the unequal treaties and the use of the
                    most-favored-nation clause were effective in creating and maintaining open trade
                    with China, both were also important factors in building animosity and
                    resentment toward Western imperialism.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="territorial-expansion">
                <head>Territorial Expansion, Filibustering, and U.S. Interest in Central America and
                    Cuba, <date from="1849" to="1861">1849–1861</date>
                </head>
                <p>During the years between the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/texas-annexation"
                        >Mexican-American War</ref> and the Civil War, the United States became
                    increasingly involved in <placeName>Central America</placeName> and the
                    Caribbean. While U.S. Government officials attempted to acquire territorial
                    possessions in that region, private citizens (known as “filibusterers”) also
                    organized armed expeditions to various places in Mexico, Central America, and
                    Cuba. Filibustering and official U.S. diplomacy were equally unsuccessful in
                    acquiring permanent and significant territorial gains, and also tended to incite
                    local antagonism against U.S. actions in the region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="presidentfillmore.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Millard Fillmore</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After the territorial acquisitions of the 1840s, the idea of additional
                    territorial expansion remained popular with the U.S. public, as did the idea of
                    spreading republican government. Many pro-slavery Southerners sought to expand
                    southwards, allowing for more territory where slavery could continue to grow and
                    expand. Some even imagined the United States as a great slave-owning republic
                    that would stretch across the Caribbean to Brazil.</p>
                <p>These expansionist dreams were aided at first by a Venezuelan-born resident of
                    Cuba, <persName>Narciso López</persName>, who, like some wealthy Cuban
                    slave-owners, was wary of shaky Spanish rule over the island, and thus sought to
                    have it annexed by the United States in order to ensure slavery’s preservation
                    in Cuba. Cuban property owners were concerned that Spain would give in to
                    British pressure to abolish slavery in Cuba. López organized several failed
                    expeditions to liberate Cuba from Spanish rule, the last resulting in his
                    capture and execution in <placeName>Havana</placeName> in 1851. The American
                    public condemned Spanish actions, especially López’s execution without trial,
                    but U.S. President Millard Fillmore did not issue a denunciation. Public anger
                    against Fillmore’s seemingly lukewarm support for expansion contributed to a
                    Whig defeat in 1852.</p>
                <p>In an attempt to mollify the Democratic Party’s staunch proslavery wing, the new
                    President, <persName>Franklin Pierce</persName>, appointed the proslavery
                    politician Pierre Soulé as Minister to Spain in 1853. However, Soulé did not
                    possess a personality well-suited to tactful diplomacy. During his appointment,
                    Soulé disregarded his instructions to preserve Spanish sovereignty and delivered
                    an unauthorized ultimatum to the Spanish Government regarding a seized U.S.
                    merchant ship. Soulé also wounded the French Ambassador in a duel and began to
                    associate with Spanish revolutionaries planning to overthrow the government. In
                    1854, Soulé met with other U.S. Ministers to draft a document known as the
                    Ostend Manifesto, which outlined U.S. reasons for attempting to purchase Cuba
                    from Spain. Once the documents were publicly released, they proved embarrassing
                    for the Pierce Administration, and U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/marcy-william-learned">William Marcy</ref>
                    implied that Soulé had instigated the meeting. In the meantime, the Spanish
                    Government began to take countermeasures against U.S. interest in Cuba. The
                    Spanish Minister to the United States, Angel Calderón de la Barca, gathered
                    intelligence on planned filibustering expeditions to Cuba. In Cuba, officials
                    took steps to free slaves who had arrived on the island after 1835 and planned
                    to organize a free black militia that would oppose any proslavery invaders.
                    Growing antislavery sentiment in the northern United States and Spanish
                    determination to hold on to Cuba eventually forced U.S. leaders to end attempts
                    to acquire the island.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="pierce-franklin.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Franklin Pierce</head>
                </figure>
                <p>However, as <placeName>Cuba</placeName> receded from controversy, filibustering
                    again gained attention in Nicaragua. American William Walker, who had led a
                    failed filibustering expedition to Baja California in 1853, launched an
                    expedition to <placeName>Nicaragua</placeName> in 1855. Allying himself at first
                    with the Liberal faction in Nicaraguan politics, he eliminated his local rivals
                    and became president in 1856. However, Walker’s policies hurt British business
                    interests, as well as those of American tycoon <persName>Cornelius
                        Vanderbilt</persName>. Walker also alienated his Nicaraguan Liberal allies,
                    and his regime caused growing anti-American sentiment elsewhere in Central
                    America. These factors eventually led to Walker’s downfall in 1857, despite his
                    attempts to secure proslavery support by re-legalizing slavery in the Central
                    American country. Walker attempted a re-conquest of Nicaragua in 1860, but was
                    captured and executed.</p>
                <p>Overall, official U.S. policy toward filibusterers was one of initial lenience
                    driven by popular support. However, U.S. officials ultimately did take steps to
                    curb filibusterers’ actions once they proved embarrassing to U.S. diplomatic
                    relations. Despite this official ambivalence toward these filibusterers, U.S.
                    leaders often protested the lack of due process by which foreign governments
                    imprisoned and executed U.S. citizens involved in filibustering. Overall,
                    filibustering and U.S. policies seem to have hindered more than helped U.S.
                    attempts at territorial expansion in this time period. The Gadsden Purchase was
                    the only official territorial acquisition during the 1850s. Filibustering tended
                    to encourage local hostility to U.S. expansion and spread international
                    resistance to growing U.S. power. U.S. expansion in the later 1850s was also
                    hindered by domestic sectional tensions over slavery.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
