<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1861–1865</title>
                <title type="short">1861–1865</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1861" to="1865">1861–1865</date>: The Civil War and International
                    Diplomacy</head>
                <p>In 1861, eleven states seceded from the United States to form the Confederate
                    States of America and, over the course of the next four years, the U.S. fought
                    to bring the Confederate States back under control.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="civilwar.jpg" height="190px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>The Battle of Gettysburg, by Currier and Ives. (1863)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>During the Civil War the Confederacy repeatedly sought international support for
                    its cause, often calling upon foreign reliance on its cotton exports to obtain
                    it. The Union, on the other hand, strove to prevent other nations from
                    recognizing the Confederacy as a legitimate nation and from getting involved in
                    the Civil War.</p>
                <p>In an attempt to starve the Confederate economy and to cut it off from its
                    international supporters, the Union engaged in a <ref
                        target="/milestones/1861-1865/blockade">blockade of Confederate
                    ports</ref>—a move that was of questionable legality in international law.
                    Despite the Confederacy’s significant international commercial ties, the lack of
                    definitive military victories for the South and the success of Union efforts to
                    link the Confederacy with the institution of slavery ultimately prevented any of
                    the European powers from officially recognizing or supporting the South.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="confederacy">
                <head>Preventing Diplomatic Recognition of the Confederacy, <date when="1861"
                        >1861–1865</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>One of the most important victories won by the United States during the Civil War
                    was not ever fought on a battlefield. Rather, it was a series of diplomatic
                    victories that ensured that the Confederacy would fail to achieve diplomatic
                    recognition by even a single foreign government. Although this success can be
                    attributed to the skill of Northern diplomats, the anti-slavery sentiments of
                    the European populace, and European diversion to crises in Poland and Denmark,
                    the most important factor stills rises from the battlefields on American soil.
                    The Confederate states were incapable of winning enough consecutive victories to
                    convince European governments that they could sustain independence.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cottongin.jpg" height="152px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Artistic rendering of the Cotton Gin, central to the Southern Cotton
                        Plantation Economy</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Impact of Northern Blockade</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Southerners began the war effort confident that the cotton their plantations
                    provided European textile manufacturers would naturally ally their governments
                    to the Confederacy, especially Great Britain. After declaring secession, the
                    North would declare a <ref target="/milestones/1861-1865/blockade">blockade on
                        Southern ports</ref>. Any interruption of cotton supply would disrupt the
                    British economy and reduce the workers to starvation, they thought. Britain
                    would have to break the blockade and provoke a war with the North that would
                    allow Confederates to solidify independence and gain international
                    recognition.</p>
                <p>When the Union did declare a blockade upon the rebel states in April 1861,
                    however, it did not prompt the response expected from the Europeans. The
                    blockade’s legal and political implications took on greater significance than
                    its economic effects because it undermined Lincoln’s insistence that the war was
                    merely an internal insurrection. A blockade was a weapon of war between
                    sovereign states. In May, Britain responded to the blockade with a proclamation
                    of neutrality, which the other European powers followed. This tacitly granted
                    the Confederacy belligerent status, the right to contract loans and purchase
                    supplies in neutral nations and to exercise belligerent rights on the high seas.
                    The Union was greatly angered by European recognition of Southern belligerency,
                    fearing that is was a first step toward diplomatic recognition, but as British
                    Foreign Secretary Lord <persName>John Russell</persName> said, “The question of
                    belligerent rights is one, not of principle, but of fact.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="russell-john.jpg" height="255px" width="191px"/>
                    <head>British Foreign Secretary Lord John Russell.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Sensitive to any further international recognition of the Confederates as
                    statesmen rather than rebels, Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William H.
                        Seward</ref> instructed <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles Francis
                        Adams</ref>, Minister to England and the son of former Secretary of State
                    and President <persName>John Quincy Adams</persName>, to warn the British not to
                    “fraternize with our domestic enemy,” whether officially or unofficially, or
                    risk an Anglo-American war. But the Union realized that Europe’s declarations of
                    neutrality also constituted official acceptance of the blockade, a position with
                    many long-standing implications. Although international law stated that a
                    blockade must be “physically effective” to be legally binding on neutral powers,
                    the definition was ambiguous. From before the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1801-1829/war-of-1812">War of 1812</ref>, the United
                    States had insisted upon a strict definition in order to maintain trading rights
                    as a neutral. Now, however, the United States was the belligerent and Britain
                    the predominant neutral power. By officially respecting the Union blockade, even
                    if it was not fully “physically effective,” Britain maintained a consistent
                    position on belligerent rights. The U.S. reversal of its traditional position
                    stressing neutral rights set the precedent that it would be obligated to respect
                    the British argument in future naval issues. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="blockade">
                <head>The Blockade of Confederate Ports, <date from="1861" to="1865"
                        >1861–1865</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>During the Civil War, Union forces established a blockade of Confederate ports
                    designed to prevent the export of cotton and the smuggling of war materiel into
                    the Confederacy. The blockade, although somewhat porous, was an important
                    economic policy that successfully prevented Confederate access to weapons that
                    the industrialized North could produce for itself. The U.S. Government
                    successfully convinced foreign governments to view the blockade as a legitimate
                    tool of war. It was less successful at preventing the smuggling of cotton,
                    weapons, and other materiel from Confederate ports to transfer points in Mexico,
                    the Bahamas, and Cuba, as this trade remained profitable for foreign merchants
                    in those regions and elsewhere.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="blockade.jpg" height="240px" width="310px"/>
                    <head>1861 Cartoon of the Union Blockade of the South during the Civil
                        War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William Henry
                        Seward</ref> recommended adopting the blockade shortly after the Battle of
                    Fort Sumter in April, 1861 that marked the beginning of Civil War hostilities.
                        <persName>Gideon Welles</persName>, the Secretary of the Navy, argued for a
                    de facto but undeclared blockade, which would prevent foreign governments from
                    granting the Confederacy belligerent status. President Abraham Lincoln sided
                    with Seward and proclaimed the blockade on April 19. Lincoln extended the
                    blockade to include North Carolina and Virginia on April 27. By July of 1861,
                    the Union Navy had established blockades of all the major southern ports.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">South Recognized as a Belligerent</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Following the U.S. announcement of its intention to establish an official
                    blockade of Confederate ports, foreign governments began to recognize the
                    Confederacy as a belligerent in the Civil War. Great Britain granted belligerent
                    status on May 13, 1861, Spain on June 17, and Brazil on August 1. Other foreign
                    governments issued statements of neutrality.</p>
                <p>As the Union Navy took steps to enforce the blockade, controversies arose with
                    foreign governments over the legality of Union seizures of neutral shipping, as
                    well as other related practices. The most important of these was the arrest of
                    Confederate commissioners that precipitated the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1861-1865/trent-affair">Trent Affair</ref> in November
                    of 1861, an incident that was resolved by the release of the commissioners one
                    month later. Foreign governments acknowledged the right to stop and search
                    neutral ships in international waters, but were displeased by what they saw as
                    violations of the spirit rather than the letter of the law; Union ships
                    typically determined which ships in Caribbean ports were preparing to run the
                    blockade into the Confederacy, and would wait outside the territorial limits for
                    those ships to clear port. British officials were also concerned about the
                    treatment of crews of seized ships, as well as the seizure of British mail.
                    British Minister to the United States, Baron Richard Lyons, repeatedly voiced
                    his government’s objections to U.S. Secretary of State William Henry Seward,
                    prompting Seward to invite Lyons to a meeting with President Lincoln. During
                    this meeting Lyons persuaded Lincoln to adopt British neutrality policies by
                    promising that the British Government would continue to view the blockade as a
                    legitimate tool of war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="seward-william.jpg" height="322px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State William Seward</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Effects on International Trade</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The blockade had a negative impact on the economies of other countries. Textile
                    manufacturing areas in Britain and France that depended on Southern cotton
                    entered periods of high unemployment, while French producers of wine, brandy and
                    silk also suffered when their markets in the Confederacy were cut off. Although
                    Confederate leaders were confident that Southern economic power would compel
                    European powers to intervene in the Civil War on behalf of the Confederacy,
                    Britain and France remained neutral despite their economic problems, and later
                    in the war developed new sources of cotton in Egypt and India. Although British
                    Prime Minister <persName>Henry John Temple</persName>, Viscount Palmerston, was
                    personally sympathetic to the Confederacy, and many other elite Britons felt
                    similarly, strong domestic abolitionist sentiment in Britain and in his cabinet
                    prevented Palmerston from taking stronger steps toward assisting the
                    Confederacy. Napoleon III of France was also sympathetic to the Confederacy, but
                    wanted to pursue a joint policy with Britain regarding the U.S. Civil War, and
                    so remained neutral. Moreover, Napoleon III’s chief concern during the Civil War
                    years was France’s intervention in Mexico.</p>
                <p>As the war progressed and more territory came under Union control, the blockade
                    became more effective, but less of an international issue. However, until the
                    capture of Fort Fisher in 1865, the Confederate Army was still able to obtain
                    some supplies via blockade running ships. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="trent-affair">
                <head>The <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> Affair, <date when="1861">1861</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On November 8, 1861, Charles Wilkes, a U.S. Navy Officer, captured two
                    Confederate envoys aboard the British mail ship, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Trent</hi>. Great Britain accused the United States of violating British
                    neutrality, and the incident created a diplomatic crisis between the United
                    States and Great Britain during the Civil War.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilkes-charles.jpg" height="381px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Naval Officer Charles Wilkes</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Confederate Envoys</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jefferson Davis</persName>, President of the Confederate States of
                    America, had dispatched these envoys—James Mason, former Chairman of the U.S.
                    Senate Foreign Relations Committee and John Slidell, a prominent New Orleans
                    lawyer—to secure British and French recognition of the Confederate States as a
                    sovereign nation. Great Britain and France had maintained their diplomatic
                    relations with the United States following the outbreak of the Civil War and had
                    recognized the Confederacy as a belligerent power, but not a sovereign
                    government, in early 1861. Davis sought to change this by negotiating with these
                    nations for <ref target="/milestones/1861-1865/confederacy">full diplomatic
                        recognition</ref>. Official diplomatic recognition by Britain and France
                    would not only lend credibility to the Confederacy’s bid for independence but
                    would also pave the way for lucrative trade deals between the Confederate States
                    and the European powers. Davis hoped that recent Confederate victories against
                    Union troops would favorably dispose British and French officials to receive his
                    envoys.</p>
                <p>In October 1861, Mason and Slidell slipped through the U.S. naval blockade and
                    left Charleston, South Carolina for Cuba, where they took passage for England on
                    the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi>. U.S. Captain Wilkes intercepted the <hi
                        rend="italic">Trent</hi> on November 8, 1861 and, without permission from
                    Washington, ordered his lieutenant to board and search the ship. The U.S.
                    boarding party took Mason, Slidell, and their secretaries as prisoners, but
                    allowed the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> to depart for England.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">British Reaction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Initial reaction on both sides of the Atlantic was strong. The United States,
                    still smarting from the defeat at Bull Run during the summer, publicly
                    celebrated this turn of events as a victory against the Confederacy and a blow
                    to Confederate diplomacy. The British, on the other hand, strongly protested
                    Wilkes’s action as illegal and a violation of their neutrality and demanded the
                    release of the captive Confederate envoys as well as a formal apology. Although
                    British officials continued to advocate a policy of neutrality, they did order
                    troops to Canada and additional ships to the Western Atlantic. Neither the
                    United States nor Great Britain wanted war, but it was clear that, at best, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> incident had sparked a major diplomatic
                    disagreement and, at worst, appeared to have pushed Great Britain and the United
                    States toward the potential for armed conflict.</p>
                <p>Thanks to a communication malfunction, the cable containing the severe early
                    reaction and demands of British officials took almost a month to arrive in
                    Washington. By then, emotions had cooled on both sides and a more balanced view
                    of the situation prevailed. Nevertheless, the British still expected a response
                    from President Abraham Lincoln and continued to emphasize that Captain Wilkes
                    had acted without official authorization.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong"/>Diffusing the Crisis</p>
                <p>The Lincoln administration understood that it would be unwise to risk a possible
                    armed conflict and perpetuate bad relations with a foreign power while it was
                    prosecuting a war against the Confederacy and moved to smooth things over
                    through diplomatic negotiations. <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/adams-charles-francis">Charles Francis
                        Adams</ref>, the U.S. Minister to Great Britain assured the British that the
                    United States did not want a war and advised President Lincoln and Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                        Seward</ref> that they should conform to some of the British demands.</p>
                <p>On December 26, 1861, Seward presented an official note summarizing the Lincoln
                    administration’s position to Lord Lyons, the British Minister to the United
                    States. Seward defended Wilkes’ action, although he conceded that Wilkes had
                    erred by not seizing the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> and letting a court affirm
                    the legality of taking contraband prisoners. Nevertheless, Seward agreed to
                    release the prisoners. Lyons, under orders from London, accepted this
                    explanation thereby diffusing the diplomatic crisis.</p>
                <p>Ultimately, President Lincoln and Secretary Seward were satisfied with this
                    outcome. However, the <hi rend="italic">Trent</hi> affair confirmed that the
                    British were willing to defend their position of neutrality in the American
                    Civil War, a position that both the Union and the Confederacy had hoped to
                    change. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="french-intervention">
                <head>French Intervention in Mexico and the American Civil War, <date from="1862"
                        to="1867">1862–1867</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In 1862, French Emperor <persName>Napoleon III</persName> maneuvered to establish
                    a French client state in <placeName>Mexico</placeName>, and eventually installed
                        <persName>Maximilian of Habsburg</persName>, Archduke of Austria, as Emperor
                    of Mexico. Stiff Mexican resistance caused Napoleon III to order French
                    withdrawal in 1867, a decision strongly encouraged by a United States recovered
                    from its Civil War weakness in foreign affairs. Earlier, during the Civil War,
                    U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William Henry
                        Seward</ref> followed a more cautious policy that attempted to keep
                    relations with France harmonious and prevent French willingness to assist the
                    Confederacy. Consequently, Maximilian’s government <ref
                        target="/milestones/1861-1865/confederacy">rebuffed Confederate diplomatic
                        overtures</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="maximilianofmexico.jpg" height="332px" width="230px"/>
                    <head>Maximilian of Habsburg, Archduke of Austria, Emperor of Mexico</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1857, Mexico became embroiled in a civil war that pitted the forces of Liberal
                    reformist Benito Juárez against Conservatives led by Félix Zuloaga.
                    Conservatives exerted control from Mexico City, and the Liberals from Veracruz.
                    The United States recognized the Juárez government in 1859, and in January of
                    1861, Liberal forces captured Mexico City, greatly strengthening Juárez’s
                    position and legitimacy. However, continued instability had coincided with
                    growing foreign debt that was increasingly difficult for the Mexican government
                    to pay. Secretary of State Seward offered a plan that would provide mining
                    concessions in exchange for American loans. In the event that the debts were not
                    repaid, Mexico would agree to the cession of Baja California and other Mexican
                    states. The terms of the loan were onerous to the Mexican government, but U.S.
                    diplomat <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/corwin-thomas">Thomas
                        Corwin</ref> successfully negotiated a treaty with Mexican representative
                        <persName>Manuel Maria Zamacona</persName>. Ultimately, though, the U.S.
                    Congress rejected the treaty on grounds that it would drain money from Civil War
                    expenditures.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="juarez-benito.jpg" height="283px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Benito Juárez</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Europeans Enter Mexico</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With no other options, Juárez suspended payments on Mexican debt for two years.
                    In response, representatives from the Spanish, French, and British governments
                    met in London, and on October 31, 1861, signed a tripartite agreement to
                    intervene in Mexico to recover the unpaid debts. European forces landed at
                    Veracruz on December 8. Juárez urged resistance, while Conservatives saw the
                    intervening forces as valuable allies in their struggle against the Liberals.
                    Although the British and Spanish governments had more limited plans for
                    intervention, Napoleon III was interested in reviving French global ambitions,
                    and French forces captured Mexico City, while Spanish and British forces
                    withdrew after French plans became clear. In 1863, Napoleon III invited
                    Maximilian, Archduke of Austria, to become Emperor of Mexico. Maximilian
                    accepted the offer and arrived in Mexico in 1864. Although Maximilian’s
                    Conservative government controlled much of the country, Liberals held on to
                    power in northwestern Mexico and parts of the Pacific coast.</p>
                <p>In response to these actions, Secretary of State Seward issued statements of
                    disapproval, but the U.S. Government was unable to intervene directly because of
                    the American Civil War. Moreover, both Seward and U.S. President Abraham Lincoln
                    did not want to further antagonize Napoleon III, and risk his intervention on
                    the side of the Confederacy. The U.S. Government also rejected overtures from
                    other Latin American countries for a pan-American solution to the conflict.
                    However, the Mexican Minister to the United States, <persName>Matías
                        Romero</persName>, worked carefully to build American support for Mexico.
                    Seward soon began to show increased support for Juárez’s government.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Napoleon’s Withdrawal from Mexico</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The end of the American Civil War in 1865 coincided with the beginnings of
                    success for Juárez’s forces against Maximilian’s. Maximilian, ill-informed on
                    Mexican affairs prior to his arrival, alienated his Conservative allies by
                    attempting to adopt more Liberal policies, while he failed to win over Liberals,
                    who saw him as a tool of French interests and Mexican Conservatives. In 1865,
                    Liberal military victories made Maximilian’s position increasingly difficult.
                    Meanwhile, U.S. Generals <persName>Ulysses S. Grant</persName> and
                        <persName>Philip Henry Sheridan</persName> bypassed Seward and began covert
                    support of Juárez along the Texas-Mexico border. By then, the intervention in
                    Mexico had grown unpopular with the French public, and was an increasing drain
                    on the French treasury. On January 31, 1866, Napoleon III ordered the withdrawal
                    of French troops, to be conducted in three stages from November 1866 to November
                    1867. Seward, who had earlier been more cautious, warned the Austrian Government
                    against replacing French troops with its own forces, and the threat of war
                    convinced the Austrian government to refrain from sending Maximilian
                    reinforcements. Without European support, Maximilian was unable to retain power.
                    His capture by Mexican forces, court-martial, and sentence to be executed,
                    marked the end of direct European intervention in Mexico. Seward hoped that U.S.
                    support for Juárez would improve relations with Mexico, but as part of Seward’s
                    broader strategy of U.S. expansion, he hoped that the improved relations would
                    eventually convince Mexico to join the United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S. Neutrality</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Throughout the period of French intervention, the overall U.S. policy was to
                    avoid direct conflict with France, and voice displeasure at French interference
                    in Mexican affairs, but ultimately to remain neutral in the conflict. After
                    1866, Seward provided more direct support for Juárez, while French willingness
                    to withdraw de-escalated Franco-American tensions. Although U.S. support for
                    Juárez improved U.S.-Mexican relations temporarily, disputes over policing of
                    the border under Secretary of State <persName>William Evarts</persName> would
                    erode the good will built during Seward’s tenure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="alabama">
                <head>The Alabama Claims, <date from="1862" to="1872">1862–1872</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The <placeName>Alabama</placeName> claims were a diplomatic dispute between the
                    United States and Great Britain that arose out of the U.S. Civil War. The
                    peaceful resolution of these claims seven years after the war ended set an
                    important precedent for solving serious international disputes through
                    arbitration, and laid the foundation for greatly improved relations between
                    Britain and the United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bulloch-brothers.jpg" height="388px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>The Bulloch Brothers, Naval Officers for the Confederacy</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">British-Built, Confederate-Operated</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The controversy began when Confederate agents contracted for warships from
                    British boatyards. Disguised as merchant vessels during their construction in
                    order to circumvent British neutrality laws, the craft were actually intended as
                    commerce raiders. The most successful of these cruisers was the Alabama, which
                    was launched on July 29, 1862. It captured 58 Northern merchant ships before it
                    was sunk in June 1864 by a U.S. warship off the coast of France. In addition to
                    the <hi rend="italic"/>Alabama, other British-built ships in the Confederate
                    Navy included the <hi rend="italic">Florida</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Georgia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Rappahannock</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Shenandoah</hi>. Together, they sank more than 150 Northern ships and
                    impelled much of the U.S. merchant marine to adopt foreign registry. The damage
                    to Northern shipping would have been even worse had not fervent protests from
                    the U.S. Government persuaded British and French officials to seize additional
                    ships intended for the Confederacy. Most famously, on September 3, 1863, the
                    British Government impounded two ironclad, steam-driven “Laird rams” that
                    Confederate agent <persName>James D. Bulloch</persName> had surreptitiously
                    arranged to be built at a shipyard in Liverpool.</p>
                <p>The United States demanded compensation from Britain for the damage wrought by
                    the British-built, Southern-operated commerce raiders, based upon the argument
                    that the British Government, by aiding the creation of a Confederate Navy, had
                    inadequately followed its neutrality laws. The damages discussed were enormous.
                        <persName>Charles Sumner</persName>, Chairman of the Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee, argued that British aid to the Confederacy had prolonged
                    the Civil War by 2 years, and indirectly cost the United States hundreds of
                    millions, or even billions of dollars (the figure Sumner suggested was $2.125
                    billion). Some Americans adopted this argument and suggested that Britain should
                    offer Canada to the United States in compensation. Such proposals were not taken
                    seriously by British statesmen, but they convey the passion with which some
                    Americans viewed the issue.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Treaty of Washington</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After years of unsuccessful U.S. diplomatic initiatives, a Joint High Commission
                    meeting in Washington, D.C. during the early part of 1871 arrived at the basis
                    for a settlement. The British Government expressed regret for its contribution
                    to the success of Confederate commerce raiders. This agreement, dated May 8,
                    1871, and known as the Treaty of Washington, also established an arbitration
                    commission to evaluate the merit of U.S. financial claims on Britain. In
                    addition, the treaty addressed Anglo-American disputes over boundaries and
                    fishing rights. The arbitration commission, which issued its decision in
                    September 1872, rejected American claims for indirect damages, but did order
                    Britain to pay the United States $15.5 million as compensation for the Alabama
                    claims. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="victory">
                <head>The Consequences of Union Victory, <date when="1865">1865</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The outcome of the Civil War resulted in a strengthening of U.S. foreign power
                    and influence, as the definitive Union defeat of the Confederacy firmly
                    demonstrated the strength of the United States Government and restored its
                    legitimacy to handle the sectional tensions that had complicated U.S. external
                    relations in the years before the Civil War. The renewed strength of the U.S.
                    Government led to the defeat of <ref
                        target="/milestones/1861-1865/french-intervention">French intervention in
                        Mexico</ref>, and hastened the confederation of
                        <placeName>Canada</placeName> in 1867.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="courthouse.jpg" height="200px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>Appomattox Court House, Virginia</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Union victory also ensured continuing support for the international abolishment
                    of racial slavery.</p>
                <p>As the Confederacy collapsed, U.S. leaders were able to shift resources to
                    resisting French intervention in Mexico and to deploy troops along the
                    Texas-Mexico border. U.S. pressure, combined with Mexican resentment and
                    military success against Emperor <persName>Maximilian</persName> ultimately
                    compelled French Emperor <persName>Napoleon III</persName> to end his imperial
                    venture in Mexico.</p>
                <p>In the north, fears of a resurgent United States and calls by some U.S.
                    politicians for the annexation of British North American territory allowed
                    Canadian politicians to overcome their own sectional differences, while also
                    spurring British parliamentary leaders to urge a stronger central government in
                    British North America, especially after Irish-born civil war veterans launched
                    several unsuccessful raids into Canada. This resulted in the British North
                    America Act of 1867, which united Ontario, Quebec, Nova Scotia and New
                    Brunswick. Subsequently, in 1870, Canadian Prime Minister <persName>John
                        MacDonald</persName> successfully convinced the British Government to cede
                    the lands of the Hudson’s Bay Company to Canada, crushing the hopes of U.S.
                    expansionists who hoped to acquire those lands for the United States. Although
                    it took considerable negotiation, the U.S. Government was also able to obtain
                    restitution for claims stemming from the attacks on merchant shipping by
                    British-built Confederate warships such as the Alabama.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="macdonald-john.jpg" height="317px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Canadian Prime Minister John MacDonald</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The renewed international image of the United States also helped Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                        Seward</ref> in his attempts to acquire additional territory in the postwar
                    period. In 1867, Seward succeeded in <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">purchasing Alaska from the
                        Russian Government</ref>. Seward also sought to acquire territories in the
                    Caribbean, and to negotiate permission to build the Panama Canal. The postwar
                    period also saw attempts by U.S. political leaders, including Seward, to
                    resettle freed slaves abroad in either Mexico or Brazil, but the governments of
                    those countries dissuaded Seward from these efforts. However, Brazil, where
                    slavery remained legal until 1888, did become a magnet for disaffected
                    Confederates angered by the end of slavery in the United States. Between 3,000
                    and 20,000 former Confederates resettled in Brazil, although a considerable
                    number returned to the United States. However, William Lidgerwood, the U.S.
                    Chargé d’Affaires in Brazil, recommended that passports be denied for those who
                    had renounced U.S. citizenship. By doing so, Lidgerwood created a class of
                    stateless people, because some former Confederates had renounced their Brazilian
                    citizenship in order to return to the United States. Although many former
                    Confederates were eventually able to return, some remained in Brazil and
                    continued to advocate the proslavery cause.</p>
                <p>The end of the Confederacy generally signaled a defeat for pro-slavery advocates
                    as the international abolitionist movement gained strength in the 1860s and
                    1870s. Increasingly, abolitionists pressured European and American governments
                    to end slavery and other forms of bondage in their territories. The Russian
                    empire had already announced the end of serfdom in 1861, and the Dutch
                    government abolished slavery in its colonies in 1863. The Spanish Government
                    abolished slavery in <placeName>Puerto Rico</placeName> in 1873, although
                    slavery would remain legal in Cuba until 1886. Brazil also took measures toward
                    gradual abolition in 1871, although slavery would not be fully abolished there
                    until 1888.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
