<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1866–1898</title>
                <title type="short">1866–1898</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1866" to="1898">1866–1898</date>: The Continued Expansion of United
                    States Interests</head>
                <p>In the wake of the Civil War, the United States continued to expand into new
                    territory and new markets.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="alaskaratification.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Russian ratification of the Alaska purchase, June 1867 </head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1867, the U.S. nearly doubled its holdings with the purchase of the territory
                    of <placeName>Alaska</placeName> from the Russians. During this period, U.S.
                    economic power grew, driven by new inventions in communication and
                    transportation that closed the distance from coast to coast, and by a massive
                    influx of immigration that sparked an explosion of industrialization and
                    urbanization throughout the country. The combination of high productivity and
                    the industrial revolution resulted in a production rate that vastly outstripped
                    that which people in the United States could consume. Following two devastating
                    economic recessions, U.S. foreign policy leaders focused on finding foreign
                    markets to absorb excess goods. This renewed emphasis on exploring international
                    business opportunities resulted in a buildup of U.S. naval forces to protect
                    commercial shipping and overseas interests. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="telegraph">
                <head>U.S. Diplomacy and the Telegraph, <date when="1866">1866</date>
                </head>
                <p>The development of the electric telegraph greatly changed the way diplomacy was
                    conducted in the 19th century. Until that time information was exchanged at the
                    speed of a sailing ship or a galloping horse. During the 1830s and 1840s,
                    inventors working independently in several countries developed workable electric
                    telegraphs, and these devices quickly superceded other technologies with the
                    same name. By the mid-nineteenth century, telegraphy had acquired its present
                    definition as a device for converting messages into electric impulses that
                    traveled instantaneously by wire to distant receivers, where they were converted
                    back into readable text. European foreign ministries first used telegraphy
                    during the early 1850s, but it did not become an important tool in the diplomacy
                    of the United States until the completion of a successful transatlantic cable in
                    1866.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="telegram.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The first telegram sent across the Atlantic, reading “What hath God
                        wrought.”</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The most significant characteristic of the telegraph was its speed. Telegrams
                    traveled like lightning across continents and oceans. Even with the additional
                    time required for coding and handling, telegrams were typically available within
                    a few hours of being sent. This speed brought many advantages to policymakers
                    who found that they could respond rapidly to far off crises of whose very
                    existence they would previously have remained ignorant for weeks. But the
                    telegraph also brought disadvantages. The ability to act quickly placed new time
                    pressures upon political leaders, especially since telegraphy could inform
                    newspapers and an expectant public just as swiftly. The acceleration of
                    international disputes posed challenges to foreign ministries, which frequently
                    used delay as a tool in resolving international crises. The long pauses caused
                    by relatively slow communication had previously allowed tempers to cool,
                    provided time for careful, methodical diplomacy, and offered harried political
                    leaders an opportunity to conceive creative solutions to complex problems.</p>
                <p>Telegraphy increased the centralization of foreign ministries. When ambassadors
                    were months away from their political superiors, they were often forced to take
                    pressing and important decisions before they could receive their instructions.
                    In such circumstances, they exercised enormous power, sometimes even acting as
                    policymakers in their own right. In contrast, telegraphy circumscribed the
                    independence of diplomats. It reduced the pressure of difficult decisions, which
                    diplomats had previously faced without ready access to advice from their
                    superiors. Yet, it also diminished the prestige and the power of diplomatic
                    representatives. Their function changed. Whereas diplomats had once received
                    autonomy because the sending of instructions to respond to every eventuality was
                    slow and cumbersome, they now, in the age of the telegraph, were prized in part
                    for their inefficiency. They provided an extra layer of expertise and slowed the
                    policymaking process, thereby reducing the chances of a catastrophic error.</p>
                <p>The formation and implementation of foreign policy can be a high-risk endeavor.
                    In an environment in which miscalculation can lead to a disastrous war or
                    diplomatic defeat, foreign ministries tend to be skeptical of radical changes
                    and untried methods. Yet, foreign ministries did cautiously adapt to the
                    telegraph. In 1859, Britain’s Foreign Office hired resident clerks to handle
                    telegrams received after the close of business. The U.S. Department of State
                    established a telegraph office in 1866, a few months after the permanent
                    establishment of transatlantic telegraphy. Diplomats learned to write more
                    concisely in order to reduce telegraph expenses, which typically increased with
                    the length of messages. Foreign ministries made more frequent use of codes in an
                    (often fruitless) effort to keep the contents of their telegrams secret from
                    spies.</p>
                <p>In the late 20th and early 21st centuries, new technologies of
                    communication—especially networked computers and fiber optic cables (which
                    carried light rather than electricity)—marked the end of diplomacy by telegraph.
                    Yet, the telegraph deserves to be remembered as the technology that brought
                    diplomacy into the high-speed age of electricity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="alaska-purchase">
                <head>Purchase of Alaska, <date when="1867">1867</date>
                </head>
                <p>The purchase of <placeName>Alaska</placeName> in 1867 marked the end of Russian
                    efforts to expand trade and settlements to the Pacific coast of North America,
                    and became an important step in the United States rise as a great power in the
                    Asia-Pacific region. Beginning in 1725, when Russian Czar <persName>Peter the
                        Great</persName> dispatched Vitus Bering to explore the Alaskan coast,
                    Russia had a keen interest in this region, which was rich in natural resources
                    and lightly inhabited. As the United States expanded westward in the early
                    1800s, Americans soon found themselves in competition with Russian explorers and
                    traders. St. Petersburg, however, lacked the financial resources to support
                    major settlements or a military presence along the Pacific coast of North
                    America and permanent Russian settlers in Alaska never numbered more than four
                    hundred. Defeat in the Crimean War further reduced Russian interest in this
                    region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="alaskatreaty.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Signing of the Alaska Treaty, 1867</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Russia offered to sell Alaska to the United States in 1859, believing the United
                    States would off-set the designs of Russia’s greatest rival in the Pacific,
                    Great Britain. The looming U.S. Civil War delayed the sale, but after the war,
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry"
                        >William Seward</ref> quickly took up a renewed Russian offer and on March
                    30, 1867, agreed to a proposal from Russian Minister in Washington, Edouard de
                    Stoeckl, to purchase Alaska for $7.2 million. The Senate approved the treaty of
                    purchase on April 9; President Andrew Johnson signed the treaty on May 28, and
                    Alaska was formally transferred to the United States on October 18, 1867. This
                    purchase ended Russia’s presence in North America and ensured U.S. access to the
                    Pacific northern rim.</p>
                <p>For three decades after its purchase the United States paid little attention to
                    Alaska, which was governed under military, naval, or Treasury rule or, at times,
                    no visible rule at all. Seeking a way to impose U.S. mining laws, the United
                    States constituted a civil government in 1884. Skeptics had dubbed the purchase
                    of Alaska “Seward’s Folly,” but the former Secretary of State was vindicated
                    when a major gold deposit was discovered in the Yukon in 1896, and Alaska became
                    the gateway to the Klondike gold fields. The strategic importance of Alaska was
                    finally recognized in World War II. Alaska became a state on January 3, 1959.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="burlingame-seward-treaty">
                <head>The Burlingame-Seward Treaty, <date when="1868">1868</date>
                </head>
                <p>China and the United States concluded the Burlingame-Seward Treaty in 1868 to
                    expand upon the Treaty of Tianjin of 1858. The new treaty established some basic
                    principles that aimed to ease immigration restrictions, and represented a
                    Chinese effort to limit American interference in internal Chinese affairs.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="burlingame-anson.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Republican Laywer and former U.S. Representative from Massachusetts, Anson
                        Burlingame</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/burlingame-anson">Anson Burlingame</ref>,
                    a lawyer and former Republican representative to Congress from Massachusetts,
                    became the U.S. Minister to <placeName>China</placeName> in 1861 and, under the
                    orders of Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/seward-william-henry">William
                    Seward</ref>, worked to establish the United States as a power in the East. The
                    United States wanted to gain access to profitable trading opportunities and
                    foster the spread of Christianity in Asia, alongside the leading European
                    nations, who also sought to gain inroads in China and Japan. As a part of the
                    general effort to convince the Chinese to adopt a more Western approach to
                    diplomacy and governance, the Western powers also encouraged the Chinese
                    Government to send diplomatic missions abroad. Finally persuaded to do so, the
                    Chinese requested that Burlingame accompany their representatives on a tour that
                    included stops in the major capitals of Washington, London, Paris, and Berlin.
                    Burlingame, originally a representative of the U.S. Government, gave up his post
                    to assist the Chinese in their treaty negotiations with Seward.</p>
                <p>While in Washington, Burlingame negotiated a treaty with Seward to revise and
                    expand upon the points established in the Treaty of Tianjin of 1858. The first
                    few articles of the new treaty protected commerce conducted in Chinese ports and
                    cities, and established the right of China to appoint consuls to American port
                    cities. The more groundbreaking articles included measures that promised the
                    Chinese the right to free immigration and travel within the United States, and
                    allowed for the protection of Chinese citizens in the United States in
                    accordance with the most-favored-nation principle. Another article gave the
                    citizens of the two nations reciprocal access to education and schooling when
                    living in the other country. All of these articles served to reinforce the
                    principle of equality between the two nations.</p>
                <p>The final article of the Burlingame-Seward Treaty offered China some protection
                    from external influence in internal matters. In this article the U.S. recognized
                    that the decision to begin new construction projects or similar improvements
                    belonged in the hands of the local government, not foreign powers or their
                    representatives. This point was intended to safeguard against undue U.S.
                    involvement in Chinese domestic affairs.</p>
                <p>Despite the reciprocal protections that the Treaty afforded Chinese in the United
                    States and Americans in China, the Treaty ultimately reinforced U.S. trade
                    interests with China under the principle of the most-favored-nation concept, and
                    it ensured a steady flow of low-cost Chinese immigrant labor for U.S. firms. For
                    these reasons, American industrial leaders initially celebrated the Treaty as a
                    major advancement for American commercial interests.</p>
                <p>However, the success of the treaty was short-lived. By the late 1870s, U.S.
                    industrial leaders and politicians could no longer ignore the increasing
                    anti-Chinese sentiment in the United States, particularly in the western states;
                    in fact, industrialists and politicians often promoted anti-Chinese activities.
                    A new treaty signed in 1880 revised the Burlingame-Seward agreement, and the
                    Chinese Exclusion Act of 1882 abrogated its free immigration clauses
                    altogether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="commodore-shufeldt">
                <head>Commodore Robert W. Shufeldt’s Voyage to Africa, the Middle East, and Asia,
                        <date from="1878" to="1880">1878–1880</date>
                </head>
                <p>Between 1878 and 1880, Commodore <persName>Robert Shufeldt</persName> commanded
                    the U.S.S. <hi rend="italic">Ticonderoga</hi> on a mission to
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName>, the <placeName>Middle East</placeName>, and
                        <placeName>Asia</placeName> in an attempt to further open those regions to
                    U.S. trade. The voyage was moderately successful at raising awareness of U.S.
                    manufactures, but concrete results in the form of trade agreements were mostly
                    lacking, except for an unratified 1880 treaty with Anjouan. However, Shufeldt
                    was able to lay the groundwork for an 1883 commercial treaty with Korea.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ticonderoga.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Recommisioned USS <hi rend="italic">Ticonderoga</hi>, led by Commodore
                        Robert Shufeldt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Planning the Voyage</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Shufeldt’s trip was conceived in 1878 by Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/evarts-william-maxwell">William
                        Evarts</ref> and Secretary of the Navy <persName>Richard W.
                        Thompson</persName>. The U.S. economy had suffered greatly after the Panic
                    of 1873 and entered into a depression worsened by weak consumer demand. Evarts
                    and Thompson hoped that a successful trade mission would open new markets for
                    U.S. manufactures. The mission as described by Evarts and Thompson was to visit
                    the “unfrequented ports of Africa, Asia, the islands of the Persian Ocean, and
                    the adjacent seas, particularly where there are at present no American
                    Commercial representatives with a view to the encouragement and extension of
                    American Commerce.” For this task, they chose Commodore Robert Wilson Shufeldt
                    (1822–1895), who had enjoyed a long and distinguished naval career.</p>
                <p>Evarts instructed Shufeldt to renegotiate existing treaties and arrange new ones
                    in the places he was scheduled to visit. Senator Aaron Sargent of California
                    also hoped that Shufeldt would be able to improve relations with Korea, where
                    U.S. Marines had invaded in 1871. Shufeldt was also instructed to arbitrate a
                    boundary dispute between the West African nation of Liberia and the British
                    colony of Sierra Leone.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Ticonderoga</hi> left the United States on December 7,
                    1878, and arrived in Liberia on January 15, 1879. Shufeldt successfully
                    arbitrated the boundary dispute with Sierra Leone, and the lands east of the
                    Sugaree River were awarded to Liberia. From Liberia, Shufeldt sailed south along
                    the coast of Africa toward Cape Town, making numerous stops, and recommending
                    the establishment of consulates in key ports along the African coast. Shufeldt
                    also recommended that the United States acquire the Spanish-controlled island of
                    Fernando Po (present-day Bioko in Equatorial Guinea) in order to secure access
                    to palm oil. Noting the hostility of European colonial officials to his mission,
                    Shufeldt expressed a general concern about what seemed to be the joint
                    Anglo-French division of Africa that might interfere with future U.S. trade in
                    the African continent.</p>
                <p>Rounding the Cape of Good Hope, Shufeldt then sailed up the eastern coast of
                    Africa, stopping at Madagascar, and then heading to the island of Anjouan (also
                    known as Johanna or Nzwane) in the present-day Comoros, where he successfully
                    negotiated a commercial treaty with its ruler, Sultan Abdallah, on October 4,
                    1879. Abdallah was concerned about British and French encroachments upon his
                    rule, and hoped to cultivate the United States as a possible ally. However, the
                    treaty was not ratified by the U.S. Senate.</p>
                <p>Following his visit to Anjouan, Shufeldt sailed northwards and visited the
                    Persian Gulf, where he also noted increasing British influence. Shufeldt
                    recommended the establishment of U.S. relations with Persia (present-day Iran),
                    and a U.S. legation was established there in 1883.</p>
                <p>From the Persian Gulf, Shufeldt sailed to India, Singapore, Borneo, the
                    Philippines, and Hong Kong before heading to Japan, where he aimed to secure
                    Japanese mediation for his negotiations with the Korean government. The Korean
                    government had been hostile to U.S. entreaties since an unsuccessful U.S.
                    attempt to forcibly establish a commercial footing in 1871. However, Japanese
                    mediation ultimately was not successful during Shufeldt’s voyage. Shufeldt left
                    Japan for China, where he hoped to negotiate with Chinese Viceroy Li Hongzhang
                    (also transliterated Hung-Chang) to obtain a commercial treaty with Korea. Li
                    had followed a policy of reasserting Chinese claims over Korea and curbing
                    Korean autonomy, and so was not amenable to arranging an agreement at that time.
                    Shufeldt also hoped that Li Hongzhang would be interested in American assistance
                    in the reorganization of the Chinese Navy, but the Chinese government had
                    already secured French assistance. Shufeldt ultimately had to leave East Asia
                    without any diplomatic agreements.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="li.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Chinese Viceroy Li Hongzhang</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Overall, Shufeldt’s voyage succeeded in raising the U.S.’s international profile
                    and prestige, but came short of producing significant concrete results. However,
                    the voyage did lay the necessary groundwork for the 1883 Korean treaty which was
                    signed on May 22, 1883 after Shufeldt had been promoted to Rear Admiral and had
                    secured a diplomatic post in China.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="chinese-immigration">
                <head>Chinese Immigration and the Chinese Exclusion Acts</head>
                <p>In the <date when="1850">1850</date>s, Chinese workers migrated to the United
                    States, first to work in the gold mines, but also to take agricultural jobs, and
                    factory work, especially in the garment industry. Chinese immigrants were
                    particularly instrumental in building railroads in the American west, and as
                    Chinese laborers grew successful in the United States, a number of them became
                    entrepreneurs in their own right. As the numbers of Chinese laborers increased,
                    so did the strength of anti-Chinese sentiment among other workers in the
                    American economy. This finally resulted in legislation that aimed to limit
                    future immigration of Chinese workers to the United States, and threatened to
                    sour diplomatic relations between the United States and China.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chineseexclusionact.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Chinese Exclusion Act</head>
                </figure>
                <p>American objections to Chinese immigration took many forms, and generally stemmed
                    from economic and cultural tensions, as well as ethnic discrimination. Most
                    Chinese laborers who came to the United States did so in order to send money
                    back to China to support their families there. At the same time, they also had
                    to repay loans to the Chinese merchants who paid their passage to America. These
                    financial pressures left them little choice but to work for whatever wages they
                    could. Non-Chinese laborers often required much higher wages to support their
                    wives and children in the United States, and also generally had a stronger
                    political standing to bargain for higher wages. Therefore many of the
                    non-Chinese workers in the United States came to resent the Chinese laborers,
                    who might squeeze them out of their jobs. Furthermore, as with most immigrant
                    communities, many Chinese settled in their own neighborhoods, and tales spread
                    of Chinatowns as places where large numbers of Chinese men congregated to visit
                    prostitutes, smoke opium, or gamble. Some advocates of anti-Chinese legislation
                    therefore argued that admitting Chinese into the United States lowered the
                    cultural and moral standards of American society. Others used a more overtly
                    racist argument for limiting immigration from East Asia, and expressed concern
                    about the integrity of American racial composition.</p>
                <p>To address these rising social tensions, from the 1850s through the 1870s the
                    California state government passed a series of measures aimed at Chinese
                    residents, ranging from requiring special licenses for Chinese businesses or
                    workers to preventing naturalization. Because anti-Chinese discrimination and
                    efforts to stop Chinese immigration violated the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/burlingame-seward-treaty">1868
                        Burlingame-Seward Treaty</ref> with China, the federal government was able
                    to negate much of this legislation.</p>
                <p>In 1879, advocates of immigration restriction succeeded in introducing and
                    passing legislation in Congress to limit the number of Chinese arriving to
                    fifteen per ship or vessel. Republican President <persName>Rutherford B.
                        Hayes</persName> vetoed the bill because it violated U.S. treaty agreements
                    with <placeName>China</placeName>. Nevertheless, it was still an important
                    victory for advocates of exclusion. Democrats, led by supporters in the West,
                    advocated for all-out exclusion of Chinese immigrants. Although Republicans were
                    largely sympathetic to western concerns, they were committed to a platform of
                    free immigration. In order to placate the western states without offending
                    China, President Hayes sought a revision of the Burlingame-Seward Treaty in
                    which China agreed to limit immigration to the United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hayes-rutherford.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Rutherford B. Hayes</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1880, the Hayes Administration appointed U.S. diplomat <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/angell-james-burrill">James B.
                        Angell</ref> to negotiate a new treaty with China. The resulting Angell
                    Treaty permitted the United States to restrict, but not completely prohibit,
                    Chinese immigration. In 1882, Congress passed the Chinese Exclusion Act, which,
                    per the terms of the Angell Treaty, suspended the immigration of Chinese
                    laborers (skilled or unskilled) for a period of 10 years. The Act also required
                    every Chinese person traveling in or out of the country to carry a certificate
                    identifying his or her status as a laborer, scholar, diplomat, or merchant. The
                    1882 Act was the first in American history to place broad restrictions on
                    immigration.</p>
                <p>For American presidents and Congressmen addressing the question of Chinese
                    exclusion, the challenge was to balance domestic attitudes and politics, which
                    dictated an anti-Chinese policy, while maintaining good diplomatic relations
                    with China, where exclusion would be seen as an affront and a violation of
                    treaty promises. The domestic factors ultimately trumped international concerns.
                    In 1888, Congress took exclusion even further and passed the Scott Act, which
                    made reentry to the United States after a visit to China impossible, even for
                    long-term legal residents. The Chinese Government considered this act a direct
                    insult, but was unable to prevent its passage. In 1892, Congress voted to renew
                    exclusion for ten years in the Geary Act, and in 1902, the prohibition was
                    expanded to cover Hawaii and the Philippines, all over strong objections from
                    the Chinese Government and people. Congress later extended the Exclusion Act
                    indefinitely.</p>
                <p>In China, merchants responded to the humiliation of the exclusion acts by
                    organizing an anti-American boycott in 1905. Though the movement was not
                    sanctioned by the Chinese government, it received unofficial support in the
                    early months. President Theodore Roosevelt recognized the boycott as a direct
                    response to unfair American treatment of Chinese immigrants, but with American
                    prestige at stake, he called for the Chinese government to suppress it. After
                    five difficult months, Chinese merchants lost the impetus for the movement, and
                    the boycott ended quietly.</p>
                <p>The Chinese Exclusion Acts were not repealed until 1943, and then only in the
                    interests of aiding the morale of a wartime ally during World War II. With
                    relations already complicated by the Opium Wars and the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-1">Treaties of Wangxia</ref> and <ref
                        target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-2">Tianjian</ref>&gt;, the increasingly
                    harsh restrictions on Chinese immigration, combined with the rising
                    discrimination against Chinese living in the United States in the 1870s-early
                    1900s, placed additional strain on the diplomatic relationship between the
                    United States and China.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="mahan">
                <head>Mahan’s The Influence of Sea Power upon History: Securing International
                    Markets in the <date when="1890">1890s</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1890, Captain <persName>Alfred Thayer Mahan</persName>, a lecturer in naval
                    history and the president of the United States Naval War College, published <hi
                        rend="italic">The Influence of Sea Power upon History, 1660–1783,</hi> a
                    revolutionary analysis of the importance of naval power as a factor in the rise
                    of the British Empire. Two years later, he completed a supplementary volume, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Influence of Sea Power upon the French Revolution and
                        Empire, 1793–1812</hi>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bookcover.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Book Cover of the 12th Edition of Thayer Mahan’s The Influence of Sea
                        Power upon History, 1660–1783</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Mahan argued that British control of the seas, combined with a corresponding
                    decline in the naval strength of its major European rivals, paved the way for
                    Great Britain’s emergence as the world’s dominant military, political, and
                    economic power. Mahan and some leading American politicians believed that these
                    lessons could be applied to U.S. foreign policy, particularly in the quest to
                    expand U.S. markets overseas.</p>
                <p>The 1890s were marked by social and economic unrest throughout the United States,
                    which culminated in the onset of an economic depression between 1893 and 1894.
                    The publication of Mahan’s books preceded much of the disorder associated with
                    the 1890s, but his work resonated with many leading intellectuals and
                    politicians concerned by the political and economic challenges of the period and
                    the declining lack of economic opportunity on the American continent.</p>
                <p>Mahan’s books complemented the work of one of his contemporaries, Professor
                        <persName>Frederick Jackson Turner</persName>, who is best known for his
                    seminal essay of 1893, “The Significance of the Frontier in American History.”
                    An American history professor at the University of Wisconsin, Turner postulated
                    that westward migration across the North American continent and the country’s
                    population growth had finally led to the “closing” of the American frontier,
                    with profound social and economic consequences. While Turner did not explicitly
                    argue for a shift towards commercial expansion overseas, he did note that calls
                    for a “vigorous foreign policy” were signs that Americans were increasingly
                    looking outside the continental United States in order to satiate their desire
                    for new economic opportunities and markets.</p>
                <p>Mahan was one of the foremost proponents of the “vigorous foreign policy”
                    referred to by Turner. Mahan believed that the U.S. economy would soon be unable
                    to absorb the massive amounts of industrial and commercial goods being produced
                    domestically, and he argued that the United States should seek new markets
                    abroad. What concerned Mahan most was ensuring that the U.S. Government could
                    guarantee access to these new international markets. Securing such access would
                    require three things: a merchant navy, which could carry American products to
                    new markets across the “great highway” of the high seas; an American battleship
                    navy to deter or destroy rival fleets; and a network of naval bases capable of
                    providing fuel and supplies for the enlarged navy, and maintaining open lines of
                    communications between the United States and its new markets.</p>
                <p>Mahan’s emphasis upon the acquisition of naval bases was not completely new.
                    Following the Civil War, Secretary of State William Seward had attempted to
                    expand the U.S. commercial presence in Asia by <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/alaska-purchase">purchasing Alaska in
                        1867</ref>, and increasing American influence over Hawaii by concluding a
                    reciprocity treaty that would bind the islands’ economy to that of the United
                    States. Seward also attempted to purchase suitable Caribbean naval bases.
                    Finally, he attempted to ratify a treaty with the Colombian Government that
                    would allow the United States to build an isthmian canal through the province of
                    Panama. In the wake of the Civil War, however, Congress became preoccupied with
                    Reconstruction in the South, and the Senate rejected all of Seward’s efforts to
                    create a network of American naval bases.</p>
                <p>In the 1890s, Mahan’s ideas resonated with leading politicians, including
                    Assistant Secretary of the Navy Theodore Roosevelt, and Secretary of the Navy
                    Herbert Tracy. After the outbreak of hostilities with Spain in May 1898,
                    President William McKinley finally secured the annexation of Hawaii by means of
                    joint resolution of Congress. Following the successful conclusion of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American War in
                        1898</ref>, the United States gained control of territories that could serve
                    as the coaling stations and naval bases that Mahan had discussed, such as Puerto
                    Rico, Guam, and the Philippines. Five years later, the United States obtained a
                    perpetual lease for a naval base at <placeName>Guantanamo Bay,
                    Cuba</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="blaine">
                <head>Blaine and Pan Americanism, <date from="1880" to="1890">1880s/1890s</date>
                </head>
                <p>President-elect <persName>Garfield</persName> named <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James G.
                        Blaine</ref>, his former rival for the Republican presidential nomination,
                    to his cabinet as Secretary of State. Blaine took office in 1881. As Secretary,
                    Blaine continued his long interest in Latin America, “first, to bring about
                    peace and prevent futile wars in North and South America; second, to cultivate
                    such friendly commercial ties with all American countries as would lead to a
                    large increase in the export trade of the United States.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="blaine-james.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State James Blaine</head>
                </figure>
                <p>He sought exclusive U.S. control over any canal to be built in the Central
                    American isthmus, a goal finally realized in the 1901 Hay-Pauncefote treaty with
                    Great Britain. He sought to keep Hawaii as “part of the American System,”
                    although Hawaii was not annexed until
                        1898. He tried and failed to resolve the 1879–1883 War of the Pacific
                    between Chile, Peru and Bolivia. President Garfield’s assassination in July 1881
                    elevated <persName>Chester Arthur</persName> to the presidency, and since Arthur
                    belonged to a different wing of the Republican party Blaine’s days in the
                    cabinet were numbered. After Arthur canceled a planned Pan American Congress,
                    Blaine resigned as Secretary of State in December 1881.</p>
                <p>When Benjamin Harrison was elected President in 1888, he invited Blaine to become
                    Secretary of State once again. In 1889, a Pan American Congress was finally
                    convened in Washington. Blaine followed up by campaigning tirelessly for
                    arbitration treaties with Latin American nations and for Congressional authority
                    to negotiate trade agreements on the basis of reciprocity. Blaine’s “spirited
                    foreign policy” also included settlement of a dispute with Germany and Great
                    Britain over the Samoan Islands, long-running negotiations with Great Britain
                    over the right of Canadian vessels to hunt seals in the Bering Sea, and
                    resolution of serious disputes with Chile and Italy over the murder of American
                    citizens. Blaine’s major accomplishment in his second tenure as Secretary was
                    the promotion of closer political and commercial relations between the United
                    States and the nations of Latin America. But even here these good feelings began
                    to deteriorate with rising jingoism in the United States, which stirred latent
                    Latin American suspicions of the “Colossus of the North.” Whether because of
                    worsening relations with President Harrison, deteriorating health, or ambition
                    to again secure the Republican nomination for the presidency, Blaine resigned in
                    June 1892. James G. Blaine, “the man from Maine,” died in January 1893 at age
                    63.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="venezuela">
                <head>Venezuela Boundary Dispute, <date from="1895" to="1899">1895–1899</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Venezuelan Boundary Dispute officially began in 1841, when the Venezuelan
                    Government protested alleged British encroachment on Venezuelan territory. In
                    1814, Great Britain had acquired British Guiana (now Guyana) by treaty with the
                    Netherlands. Because the treaty did not define a western boundary, the British
                    commissioned Robert Schomburgk, a surveyor and naturalist, to delineate that
                    boundary. His 1835 survey resulted in what came to be known as the Schomburgk
                    Line, a boundary that effectively claimed an additional 30,000 square miles for
                    Guiana.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="schmburgk.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Robert Schomburgk</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1841 Venezuela disputed the British delineation, claiming territorial
                    delineations established at the time of their independence from Spain. Venezuela
                    claimed its borders extended as far east as the Essequibo River—an effective
                    claim on two-thirds of British Guiana’s territory. When gold was discovered in
                    the disputed territory, Great Britain sought to further extend its reach,
                    claiming an additional 33,000 square miles west of the Schomburgk Line, an area
                    where gold had been discovered. In 1876 Venezuela protested, broke diplomatic
                    relations with Great Britain, and appealed to the United States for assistance,
                    citing the Monroe Doctrine as justification for U.S. involvement. For the next
                    19 years Venezuela repeatedly petitioned for U.S. assistance, calling on its
                    neighbor to the north to intervene by either sponsoring arbitration or
                    intervening with force. The United States responded by expressing concern, but
                    did little to facilitate a resolution.</p>
                <p>In 1895, invoking the Monroe Doctrine, newly appointed U.S. Secretary of State
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/olney-richard">Richard Olney</ref>
                    sent a strongly-worded note to British Prime Minister and Foreign Secretary Lord
                    Salisbury, demanding that the British submit the boundary dispute to
                    arbitration. Salisbury response was that the Monroe Doctrine had no validity as
                    international law. The United States found that response unacceptable and in
                    December 1895, President <persName>Grover Cleveland</persName> asked Congress
                    for authorization to appoint a boundary commission, proposing that the
                    commission’s findings be enforced “by every means.” Congress passed the measure
                    unanimously and talk of war with Great Britain began to circulate in the U.S.
                    press.</p>
                <p>Great Britain, under pressure in South Africa with the Boers and managing an
                    empire that spanned the globe, could ill afford another conflict. Lord
                    Salisbury’s government submitted the dispute to the American boundary commission
                    and said nothing else of the Monroe Doctrine. Venezuela enthusiastically
                    submitted to arbitration, certain that the commission would decide in its favor.
                    However, when the commission finally rendered a decision on October 3, 1899, it
                    directed that the border follow the Schomburgk Line. Although of rejection of
                    Great Britain’s increasingly extravagant claims, the ruling preserved the 1835
                    demarcation. Disappointed the Venezuelans quietly ratified the commission’s
                    finding. Of far greater significance, the Anglo-Venezuelan boundary dispute
                    incident asserted for the first time a more outward-looking American foreign
                    policy, particularly in the Western Hemisphere. Internationally the incident
                    marked the United States as a world power and gave notice that under the Monroe
                    Doctrine it would exercise its claimed prerogatives in the Western
                    Hemisphere.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="yellow-journalism">
                <head>U.S. Diplomacy and Yellow Journalism, <date from="1895" to="1898"
                        >1895–1898</date>
                </head>
                <p>Yellow journalism was a style of newspaper reporting that emphasized
                    sensationalism over facts. During its heyday in the late 19th century it was one
                    of many factors that helped push the United States and Spain into war in Cuba
                    and the Philippines, leading to the acquisition of overseas territory by the
                    United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="yellowjournalism.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Example of Yellow Journalism in the cover of the Pulitzer’s World</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The term originated in the competition over the New York City newspaper market
                    between major newspaper publishers <persName>Joseph Pulitzer</persName> and
                        <persName>William Randolph Hearst</persName>. At first, yellow journalism
                    had nothing to do with reporting, but instead derived from a popular cartoon
                    strip about life in New York’s slums called Hogan’s Alley, drawn by Richard F.
                    Outcault. Published in color by Pulitzer’s New York World, the comic’s most
                    well-known character came to be known as the Yellow Kid, and his popularity
                    accounted in no small part for a tremendous increase in sales of the World. In
                    1896, in an effort to boost sales of his New York Journal, Hearst hired Outcault
                    away from Pulitzer, launching a fierce bidding war between the two publishers
                    over the cartoonist. Hearst ultimately won this battle, but Pulitzer refused to
                    give in and hired a new cartoonist to continue drawing the cartoon for his
                    paper. This battle over the Yellow Kid and a greater market share gave rise to
                    the term yellow journalism.</p>
                <p>Once the term had been coined, it extended to the sensationalist style employed
                    by the two publishers in their profit-driven coverage of world events,
                    particularly developments in Cuba. Cuba had long been a Spanish colony and the
                    revolutionary movement, which had been simmering on and off there for much of
                    the 19th century, intensified during the 1890s. Many in the United States called
                    upon Spain to withdraw from the island, and some even gave material support to
                    the Cuban revolutionaries. Hearst and Pulitzer devoted more and more attention
                    to the Cuban struggle for independence, at times accentuating the harshness of
                    Spanish rule or the nobility of the revolutionaries, and occasionally printing
                    rousing stories that proved to be false. This sort of coverage, complete with
                    bold headlines and creative drawings of events, sold a lot of papers for both
                    publishers.</p>
                <p>The peak of yellow journalism, in terms of both intensity and influence, came in
                    early 1898, when a U.S. battleship, the Maine, sunk in Havana harbor. The naval
                    vessel had been sent there not long before in a display of U.S. power and, in
                    conjunction with the planned visit of a Spanish ship to New York, an effort to
                    defuse growing tensions between the United States and Spain. On the night of
                    February 15, an explosion tore through the ship’s hull, and the Maine went down.
                    Sober observers and an initial report by the colonial government of Cuba
                    concluded that the explosion had occurred on board, but Hearst and Pulitzer, who
                    had for several years been selling papers by fanning anti-Spanish public opinion
                    in the United States, published rumors of plots to sink the ship. When a U.S.
                    naval investigation later stated that the explosion had come from a mine in the
                    harbor, the proponents of yellow journalism seized upon it and called for war.
                    By early May, the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war"
                        >Spanish-American War had begun</ref>.</p>
                <p>The rise of yellow journalism helped to create a climate conducive to the
                    outbreak of international conflict and the expansion of U.S. influence overseas,
                    but it did not by itself cause the war. In spite of Hearst’s often quoted
                    statement—“You furnish the pictures, I’ll provide the war!”—other factors played
                    a greater role in leading to the outbreak of war. The papers did not create
                    anti-Spanish sentiments out of thin air, nor did the publishers fabricate the
                    events to which the U.S. public and politicians reacted so strongly. Moreover,
                    influential figures such as Theodore Roosevelt led a drive for U.S. overseas
                    expansion that had been gaining strength since the 1880s. Nevertheless, yellow
                    journalism of this period is significant to the history of U.S. foreign
                    relations in that its centrality to the history of the Spanish American War
                    shows that the press had the power to capture the attention of a large
                    readership and to influence public reaction to international events. The
                    dramatic style of yellow journalism contributed to creating public support for
                    the Spanish-American War, a war that would ultimately expand the global reach of
                    the United States. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="spanish-american-war">
                <head>The Spanish-American War, <date when="1898">1898</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Spanish-American War of 1898 ended Spain’s colonial empire in the Western
                    Hemisphere and secured the position of the United States as a Pacific power.
                    U.S. victory in the war produced a peace treaty that compelled the Spanish to
                    relinquish claims on Cuba, and to cede sovereignty over Guam, Puerto Rico, and
                    the Philippines to the United States. The United States also annexed the
                    independent state of Hawaii during the conflict. Thus, the war enabled the
                    United States to establish its predominance in the Caribbean region and to
                    pursue its strategic and economic interests in Asia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="spanishwar.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Charge of the 24th and 25th Colored Infantry and Rescue of Rough Riders at
                        San Juan Hill, July 2nd 1898 (Kurz and Allison)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The war that erupted in 1898 between the United States and Spain was preceded by
                    three years of fighting by Cuban revolutionaries to gain independence from
                    Spanish colonial rule. From 1895–1898, the violent conflict in Cuba captured the
                    attention of Americans because of the economic and political instability that it
                    produced in a region within such close geographical proximity to the United
                    States. The long-held U.S. interest in ridding the Western Hemisphere of
                    European colonial powers and American public outrage over brutal Spanish tactics
                    created much sympathy for the Cuban revolutionaries. By early 1898, tensions
                    between the United States and Spain had been mounting for months. After the U.S.
                    battleship Maine exploded and sank in Havana harbor under mysterious
                    circumstances on February 15, 1898, U.S. military intervention in Cuba became
                    likely.</p>
                <p>On April 11, 1898, President <persName>William McKinley</persName> asked Congress
                    for authorization to end the fighting in Cuba between the rebels and Spanish
                    forces, and to establish a “stable government” that would “maintain order” and
                    ensure the “peace and tranquility and the security” of Cuban and U.S. citizens
                    on the island. On April 20, the U.S. Congress passed a joint resolution that
                    acknowledged Cuban independence, demanded that the Spanish government give up
                    control of the island, foreswore any intention on the part of the United States
                    to annex Cuba, and authorized McKinley to use whatever military measures he
                    deemed necessary to guarantee Cuba’s independence.</p>
                <p>The Spanish government rejected the U.S. ultimatum and immediately severed
                    diplomatic relations with the United States. McKinley responded by implementing
                    a naval blockade of Cuba on April 22 and issued a call for 125,000 military
                    volunteers the following day. That same day, Spain declared war on the United
                    States, and the U.S. Congress voted to go to war against Spain on April 25.</p>
                <p>The future Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref> described
                    the ensuing conflict as a “splendid little war.” The first battle was fought on
                    May 1, in Manila Bay, where Commodore George Dewey’s Asiatic Squadron defeated
                    the Spanish naval force defending the Philippines. On June 10, U.S. troops
                    landed at Guantanamo Bay in Cuba and additional forces landed near the harbor
                    city of Santiago on June 22 and 24. After isolating and defeating the Spanish
                    Army garrisons in Cuba, the U.S. Navy destroyed the Spanish Caribbean squadron
                    on July 3 as it attempted to escape the U.S. naval blockade of Santiago.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hay-john.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State John Hay</head>
                </figure>
                <p>On July 26, at the behest of the Spanish government, the French ambassador in
                    Washington, Jules Cambon, approached the McKinley Administration to discuss
                    peace terms, and a cease-fire was signed on August 12. The war officially ended
                    four months later, when the U.S. and Spanish governments signed the Treaty of
                    Paris on December 10, 1898. Apart from guaranteeing the independence of Cuba,
                    the treaty also forced Spain to cede Guam and Puerto Rico to the United States.
                    Spain also agreed to sell the Philippines to the United States for the sum of
                    $20 million. The U.S. Senate ratified the treaty on February 6, 1899, by a
                    margin of only one vote.</p>
                <p>The McKinley Administration also used the war as a pretext to annex the independent state of
                        Hawaii. In 1893, a group of Hawaii-based planters and businessmen led
                    a coup against Queen Liliuokalani and established a new government. They
                    promptly sought annexation by the United States, but President <persName>Grover
                        Cleveland</persName> rejected their requests. In 1898, however, President
                    McKinley and the American public were more favorably disposed toward acquiring
                    the islands. Supporters of annexation argued that Hawaii was vital to the U.S.
                    economy, that it would serve as a strategic base that could help protect U.S.
                    interests in Asia, and that other nations were intent on taking over the islands
                    if the United States did not. At McKinley’s request, a joint resolution of
                    Congress made Hawaii a U.S. territory on August 12, 1898.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
