<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1899–1913</title>
                <title type="short">1899–1913</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1899" to="1913">1899–1913</date>: Defending U.S. International
                    Interests</head>
                <p>Following the defeat Spain in the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish0american-war">Spanish-American War of
                        1898</ref>, the United States acquired overseas colonies in the Caribbean
                    and the Pacific. In its new status as an imperial power, the United States
                    pursued a series of policies designed to protect American territories and
                    aggressively expand its international commercial interests.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="imperialism.jpg" height="200px" width="000px"/>
                    <head>“Ten Thousand Miles From Tip to Tip.” This political cartoon depicted the
                        United States’ growing territories in 1898.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>These policies included the promotion of the “Open Door” policy in China and the
                    attachment of the Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine that formally
                    announced the intention to use military force to defend the Western Hemisphere
                    against European incursions. At the same time, President Theodore Roosevelt
                    oversaw the construction of the Panama Canal, which would have profound economic
                    implications for American trade, and engaged in great power diplomacy in the
                    wake of the Russo-Japanese War. In just over a decade, the United States had
                    redefined its national and international interests to include a large overseas
                    military presence, overseas possessions, and direct engagement in setting
                    priorities in international affairs.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="war">
                <head>The Philippine-American War, <date from="1899" to="1902">1899–1902</date>
                </head>
                <p>After its defeat in the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American War of 1898</ref>, <placeName>Spain</placeName> ceded its
                    longstanding colony of the <placeName>Philippines</placeName> to the United
                    States in the Treaty of Paris. On February 4, 1899, just two days before the
                    U.S. Senate ratified the treaty, fighting broke out between American forces and
                    Filipino nationalists led by Emilio Aguinaldo who sought independence rather
                    than a change in colonial rulers. The ensuing Philippine-American War lasted
                    three years and resulted in the death of over 4,200 American and over 20,000
                    Filipino combatants. As many as 200,000 Filipino civilians died from violence,
                    famine, and disease.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="philippines.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>“Battle of Manila Bay”</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The decision by U.S. policymakers to annex the Philippines was not without
                    domestic controversy. Americans who advocated annexation evinced a variety of
                    motivations: desire for commercial opportunities in Asia, concern that the
                    Filipinos were incapable of self-rule, and fear that if the United States did
                    not take control of the islands, another power (such as Germany or Japan) might
                    do so. Meanwhile, American opposition to U.S. colonial rule of the Philippines
                    came in many forms, ranging from those who thought it morally wrong for the
                    United States to be engaged in colonialism, to those who feared that annexation
                    might eventually permit the non-white Filipinos to have a role in American
                    national government. Others were wholly unconcerned about the moral or racial
                    implications of imperialism and sought only to oppose the policies of President
                        <persName>William McKinley</persName>’s administration.</p>
                <p>After the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American War</ref>, while the American public and politicians
                    debated the annexation question, Filipino revolutionaries under Aguinaldo seized
                    control of most of the Philippines’ main island of Luzon and proclaimed the
                    establishment of the independent Philippine Republic. When it became clear that
                    U.S. forces were intent on imposing American colonial control over the islands,
                    the early clashes between the two sides in 1899 swelled into an all-out war.
                    Americans tended to refer to the ensuing conflict as an “insurrection” rather
                    than acknowledge the Filipinos’ contention that they were fighting to ward off a
                    foreign invader.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="aguinaldo.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Emilio Aguinaldo</head>
                </figure>
                <p>There were two phases to the Philippine-American War. The first phase, from
                    February to November of 1899, was dominated by Aguinaldo’s ill-fated attempts to
                    fight a conventional war against the better-trained and equipped American
                    troops. The second phase was marked by the Filipinos’ shift to guerrilla-style
                    warfare. It began in November of 1899, lasted through the capture of Aguinaldo
                    in 1901 and into the spring of 1902, by which time most organized Filipino
                    resistance had dissipated. President Theodore Roosevelt proclaimed a general
                    amnesty and declared the conflict over on July 4, 1902, although minor uprisings
                    and insurrections against American rule periodically occurred in the years that
                    followed.</p>
                <p>The United States entered the conflict with undeniable military advantages that
                    included a trained fighting force, a steady supply of military equipment, and
                    control of the archipelago’s waterways. Meanwhile, the Filipino forces were
                    hampered by their inability to gain any kind of outside support for their cause,
                    chronic shortages of weapons and ammunition, and complications produced by the
                    Philippines’ geographic complexity. Under these conditions, Aguinaldo’s attempt
                    to fight a conventional war in the first few months of the conflict proved to be
                    a fatal mistake; the Filipino Army suffered severe losses in men and material
                    before switching to the guerrilla tactics that might have been more effective if
                    employed from the beginning of the conflict.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="roosevelt-t.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Theodore Roosevelt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The war was brutal on both sides. U.S. forces at times burned villages,
                    implemented civilian reconcentration policies, and employed torture on suspected
                    guerrillas, while Filipino fighters also tortured captured soldiers and
                    terrorized civilians who cooperated with American forces. Many civilians died
                    during the conflict as a result of the fighting, cholera and malaria epidemics,
                    and food shortages caused by several agricultural catastrophes.</p>
                <p>Even as the fighting went on, the colonial government that the United States
                    established in the Philippines in 1900 under future President William Howard
                    Taft launched a pacification campaign that became known as the “policy of
                    attraction.” Designed to win over key elites and other Filipinos who did not
                    embrace Aguinaldo’s plans for the Philippines, this policy permitted a
                    significant degree of self-government, introduced social reforms, and
                    implemented plans for economic development. Over time, this program gained
                    important Filipino adherents and undermined the revolutionaries’ popular appeal,
                    which significantly aided the United States’ military effort to win the war.</p>
                <p>In 1907, the Philippines convened its first elected assembly, and in 1916, the
                    Jones Act promised the nation eventual independence. The archipelago became an
                    autonomous commonwealth in 1935, and the U.S. granted independence in 1946.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="hay-and-china">
                <head>Secretary of State <persName>John Hay</persName> and the Open Door in
                        <placeName>China</placeName>, <date from="1899" to="1900">1899–1900</date>
                </head>
                <p>Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John
                        Hay</ref> first articulated the concept of the “Open Door” in China in a
                    series of notes in 1899–1900. These Open Door Notes aimed to secure
                    international agreement to the U.S. policy of promoting equal opportunity for
                    international trade and commerce in China, and respect for China’s
                    administrative and territorial integrity. British and American policies toward
                    China had long operated under similar principles, but once Hay put them into
                    writing, the “Open Door” became the official U.S. policy towards the Far East in
                    the first half of the 20th century.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hay-john.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State John Hay</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The idea behind the Open Door Notes originated with British and American China
                    experts, <persName>Alfred E. Hippisley</persName> and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/rockhill-william-woodville">William W.
                        Rockhill</ref>. Both men believed that their countries’ economic interests
                    in China would be best protected and promoted by a formal agreement among the
                    European powers on the principle of maintaining an Open Door for trade and
                    commercial activity. Under their influence, Secretary Hay sent the first of the
                    Open Door Notes on September 6, 1899, to the other great powers that had an
                    interest in China, including Great Britain, France, Russia, Germany, and Japan.
                    These nations maintained significant physical and commercial presences in China,
                    and were protective of their various spheres of influence and trading privileges
                    there, and elsewhere in Asia.</p>
                <p>Hay proposed a free, open market and equal trading opportunity for merchants of
                    all nationalities operating in China, based in part on the most favored nation
                    clauses already established in the <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-1">Treaties of Wangxia</ref> and <ref target="/milestones/1830-1860/china-2">Tianjin</ref>. Hay argued that establishing equal access to commerce would
                    benefit American traders and the U.S. economy, and hoped that the Open Door
                    would also prevent disputes between the powers operating in China. For the
                    United States, which held relatively little political clout and no territory in
                    China, the principle of non-discrimination in commercial activity was
                    particularly important. Hay called for each of the powers active in China to do
                    away with economic advantages for their own citizens within their spheres of
                    influence, and also suggested that the Chinese tariffs apply universally and be
                    collected by the Chinese themselves. Although the other powers may not have
                    agreed fully with these ideas, none openly opposed them.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="empressofchina.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Empress Dowager Cixi (Tz’u Hsi) of China</head>
                </figure>
                <p>First, Hay sought the approval of the British and Japanese Governments, both of
                    which considered the American suggestion to be in their interests, although both
                    conditioned their acceptance of the terms on the agreement of all the powers
                    involved. France followed the British and Japanese example. This British,
                    Japanese, and French endorsement of Hay’s suggestion pressured Germany and
                    Russia to adhere to the terms of the note, although Russia did so with so many
                    caveats that it practically negated the Note’s central principles. Nevertheless,
                    Hay declared that all the powers had accepted the ideas with responses that were
                    “final and definitive.”</p>
                <p>In 1900, however, internal events in China threatened the idea of the Open Door.
                    An anti-foreign movement known as the Boxer Rebellion, named for the martial
                    artists that led the movement, gathered strength, and began attacking foreign
                    missionaries and Chinese converts to Christianity. With the backing of Empress
                        <persName>Dowager Cixi (Tz’u Hsi)</persName> and the Imperial Army, the
                    Boxer Rebellion turned into a violent conflict that claimed the lives of
                    hundreds of foreign missionaries and thousands of Chinese nationals. As the
                    Boxers descended upon Beijing, foreign nationals living in that city—including
                    embassy staff—clustered together in the besieged foreign legations, and called
                    upon their home governments for assistance.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="boxer-rebellion.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Photograph of Boxer Rebels</head>
                </figure>
                <p>With foreign armies fighting their way from the Chinese coast to rescue their
                    citizens in the capital, in some cases securing their own concessions and areas
                    of special interest along the way, the principle of the Open Door seemed to be
                    in grave danger. On July 3, 1900, Hay circulated another message to the foreign
                    powers involved in China, this time noting the importance of respecting the
                    “territorial and administrative integrity” of China. Although the goal was to
                    prevent the powers from using the Boxer Rebellion as an excuse to carve China
                    into individual colonies, the Open Door Circular requested no formal agreement
                    or assurances from the other powers.</p>
                <p>Together, the Open Door Notes served the important purpose of outlining U.S.
                    policy toward China and expressing U.S. hopes for cooperation with the other
                    foreign powers with a stake in the region. They were of lasting importance in
                    U.S.-East Asian relations, and contributed to the idea of a Sino-American
                    “special relationship.” However, because they were non-binding, the Notes did
                    not prevent the United States—or any other power—from one day seeking Chinese
                    territory, or acting in any way that was preferential to their own interests,
                    even at the expense of the Chinese Government. Hay himself even briefly
                    considered a seizure of Chinese territory, although he quickly rejected the
                    idea. Although the Notes were not binding, Hay’s successors nonetheless adhered
                    to the policy of maintaining the Open Door in China. The articulation of the
                    Open Door policy represented the growing American interest and involvement in
                    East Asia at the turn of the century.</p>
                <p>Ironically, Hay articulated the Open Door policy at a time when the U.S.
                    Government was doing everything in its power to close the door on Chinese
                    immigration to the United States. This effectively stifled opportunities for
                    Chinese merchants and workers in the United States. (See Chinese Immigration and
                    the Chinese Exclusion Acts.)</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="japanese-relations">
                <head>Japanese-American Relations at the Turn of the Century, <date from="1900" to="1922">1900–1922</date>
                </head>
                <p>In the first two decades of the twentieth century, the relationship between the
                    United States and Japan was marked by increasing tension and corresponding
                    attempts to use diplomacy to reduce the threat of conflict. Each side had
                    territory and interests in Asia that they were concerned the other might
                    threaten. U.S. treatment of Japanese immigrants, and competition for economic
                    and commercial opportunities in China also heightened tensions. At the same
                    time, each country’s territorial claims in the Pacific formed the basis for
                    several agreements between the two nations, as each government sought to protect
                    its own strategic and economic interests.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="katsura-taro.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Prime Minister Katsura Taro</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At the turn of the century, U.S. and Japanese interests appeared to be aligned.
                    Both nations supported the idea of an “open door” for commercial expansion in
                    China. After the Russo-Japanese War of 1904–05, U.S. President
                        <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName> acted as a mediator at Japan’s
                    request, and the two sides of the conflict met on neutral territory in
                    Portsmouth, New Hampshire. In the same year, U.S. Secretary of War William
                    Howard Taft met with Prime Minister Katsura Taro in Japan. The two concluded the
                    secret Taft-Katsura Agreement, in which the United States acknowledged Japanese
                    rule over Korea and condoned the Anglo-Japanese alliance of 1902. At the same
                    time, Japan recognized U.S. control of the Philippines.</p>
                <p>In the years that followed, however, tensions rose over Japanese actions in
                    northeast China and immigration to the United States. In 1905, the Japanese
                    started to establish more formal control over South Manchuria by forcing China
                    to give Japan ownership rights to the South Manchurian Railway. The Japanese
                    used this opening to make further inroads into northeast China, causing the
                    Roosevelt Administration concern that this violated the ideals of free
                    enterprise and the preservation of China’s territorial integrity.
                    Simultaneously, leading Japanese officials expressed frustration with the
                    treatment of Japanese immigrants in the United States. A U.S.-Japanese treaty
                    signed in 1894 had guaranteed the Japanese the right to immigrate to the United
                    States, and to enjoy the same rights in the country as U.S. citizens. In 1906,
                    however, the San Francisco Board of Education enacted a measure to send Japanese
                    and Chinese children to segregated schools. The Government of Japan was outraged
                    by this policy, claiming that it violated the 1894 treaty. In a series of notes
                    exchanged between late 1907 and early 1908, known collectively as the
                    Gentlemen’s Agreement, the U.S. Government agreed to pressure the San Francisco
                    authorities to withdraw the measure, and the Japanese Government promised to
                    restrict the immigration of laborers to the United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="root-elihu.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Elihu Root</head>
                </figure>
                <p>With the immigration problem temporarily settled, the two countries met to
                    provide mutual reassurances about their territories and interests in East Asia.
                    In 1908, U.S Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu">Elihu Root</ref> and Japanese
                    Ambassador Takahira Kogoro formed an agreement in which Japan promised to
                    respect U.S. territorial possessions in the Pacific, its Open Door policy in
                    China, and the limitation of immigration to the United States as outlined in the
                    Gentlemen’s Agreement. The Government of Japan redirected its labor emigrants to
                    its holdings in Manchuria, maintaining that these were not a part of China. For
                    its part, the United States recognized Japanese control of Taiwan and the
                    Pescadores, and the Japanese special interest in Manchuria. By reiterating each
                    country’s position in the region, the Root-Takahira Agreement served to lessen
                    the threat of a misunderstanding or war between the two nations.</p>
                <p>This series of agreements still did not resolve all of the outstanding issues.
                    U.S. treatment of Japanese residents continued to cause tension between the two
                    nations. The Alien Land Act of 1913, for example, barred Japanese from owning or
                    leasing land for longer than three years and adversely affected U.S.-Japanese
                    relations in the years leading up to World War I. Economic competition in China,
                    which the United States feared would result in increasing Japanese control, was
                    another issue that increased tensions between the two nations. In 1915, the
                    Japanese issued its “Twenty-One Demands” of China, in which it asked that China
                    recognize its territorial claims, prevent other powers from obtaining new
                    concessions along its coast, and take a series of actions designed to benefit
                    the Japanese economically. China turned to the United States for assistance, and
                    U.S. officials responded with a declaration that they would not recognize any
                    agreement that threatened the Open Door. Although this was consistent with past
                    policies, this announcement was of little use to the Chinese. However, President
                    Woodrow Wilson was not willing to take a stronger stand given his need for
                    assistance in protecting U.S. interests in Asia, addressing the growing conflict
                    in Europe, and managing racial issues in California.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="rlansing.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Robert Lansing</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The potential for conflict between the United States and Japan, especially over
                    China, led the two governments to negotiate yet again. In the Ishii-Lansing
                    Agreement of 1917, Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing</ref>
                    acknowledged that Manchuria was under Japanese control, while Japanese Foreign
                    Minister Ishii Kikujiro agreed not to place limitations on U.S. commercial
                    opportunities elsewhere in China. The two powers also agreed not to take
                    advantage of the war in Europe to seek additional rights and privileges. Though
                    non-binding, Lansing considered the agreement an important measure in promoting
                    mutual interests in Asia, but it proved short-lived. Ultimately, the two nations
                    agreed to cancel the Ishii-Lansing Agreement after concluding the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference">Nine-Power Treaty</ref>,
                    which they signed in 1922 at the Washington Conference.</p>
                <p>Japan and the United States clashed again during the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of Nations negotiations in
                    1919</ref>. The United States refused to accept the Japanese request for a
                    racial equality clause or an admission of the equality of the nations. In
                    addition, the Versailles Treaty granted Japan control over valuable German
                    concessions in Shandong, which led to an outcry in China. This coupled with the
                    growing fear of a militant Japan, contributed to the defeat of the League
                    Covenant in the U.S. Senate. The persistent issues preventing accommodation
                    continued to be racial equality (especially with regard to the treatment of
                    Japanese immigrants in the United States) and differences in how to address
                    expansion in Asia. In spite of the many efforts to reach agreements on these
                    points, by the early 1920s Japan and the United States were again at odds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="platt">
                <head>The United States, Cuba, and the Platt Amendment, <date when="1901">1901</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Platt Amendment, an amendment to a U.S. Army appropriations bill, established
                    the terms under which the United States would end its military occupation of
                    Cuba (which had begun in 1898 during the <ref target="/milestones/1866-1898/spanish-american-war">Spanish-American
                    War</ref>) and “leave the government and control of the island of Cuba to its
                    people.” While the amendment was named after Senator Orville Platt of
                    Connecticut, it was drafted largely by Secretary of War <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/root-elihu">Elihu Root</ref>. The Platt
                    Amendment laid down eight conditions to which the Cuban Government had to agree
                    before the withdrawal of U.S. forces and the transfer of sovereignty would
                    begin.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="platt.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Platt Amendment (page one)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Platt Amendment’s conditions prohibited the Cuban Government from entering
                    into any international treaty that would compromise Cuban independence or allow
                    foreign powers to use the island for military purposes. The United States also
                    reserved the right to intervene in Cuban affairs in order to defend Cuban
                    independence and to maintain “a government adequate for the protection of life,
                    property, and individual liberty.” Other conditions of the Amendment demanded
                    that the Cuban Government implement plans to improve sanitary conditions on the
                    island, relinquish claims on the Isle of Pines (now known as the Isla de la
                    Juventud), and agree to sell or lease territory for coaling and naval stations
                    to the United States. (This clause ultimately led to the perpetual lease by the
                    United States of Guantánamo Bay.) Finally, the amendment required the Cuban
                    Government to conclude a treaty with the United States that would make the Platt
                    amendment legally binding, and the United States pressured the Cubans to
                    incorporate the terms of the Platt Amendment in the Cuban constitution.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="platt2.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Platt Amendment (page two)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The rationale behind the Platt Amendment was straightforward. The United States
                    Government had intervened in Cuba in order to safeguard its significant
                    commercial interests on the island in the wake of Spain’s inability to preserve
                    law and order. As U.S. military occupation of the island was to end, the United
                    States needed some method of maintaining a permanent presence and order.
                    However, anti-annexationists in Congress had incorporated the Teller Amendment
                    in the 1898 war resolution authorizing President William McKinley to take action
                    against Spain in the Spanish-American War. This Teller Amendment committed the
                    U.S. Government to granting Cuba its independence following the removal of
                    Spanish forces. By directly incorporating the requirements of the Platt
                    Amendment into the Cuban constitution, the McKinley Administration was able to
                    shape Cuban affairs without violating the Teller Amendment.</p>
                <p>General <persName>Leonard Wood</persName>, commander of the U.S. occupation
                    forces and military governor of Cuba, presented the terms of the Platt Amendment
                    to the delegates of the Cuban Constitutional Convention in late 1900. Although
                    the Cuban delegates realized that the amendment significantly limited Cuban
                    sovereignty, and originally refused to include it within their constitution, the
                    U.S. Government promised them a trade treaty that would guarantee Cuban sugar
                    exports access to the U.S. market. After several failed attempts by the Cubans
                    to reject or modify the terms of the Platt amendment, the Cuban Constitutional
                    Convention finally succumbed to American pressure and ratified it on June 12,
                    1901, by a vote of 16 to 11. The Platt Amendment remained in force until 1934
                    when both sides agreed to cancel the treaties that enforced it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="roosevelt-and-monroe-doctrine">
                <head>Roosevelt Corollary to the Monroe Doctrine, <date when="1904">1904</date>
                </head>
                <p>President <persName>Theodore Roosevelt’s</persName> assertive approach to Latin
                    America and the Caribbean has often been characterized as the “Big Stick,” and
                    his policy came to be known as the Roosevelt Corollary to the <ref target="/milestones/1801-1829/monroe">Monroe Doctrine</ref>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="roosevelt-t.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Theodore Roosevelt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although the Monroe Doctrine of 1823 was essentially passive (it asked that
                    Europeans not increase their influence or recolonize any part of the Western
                    Hemisphere), by the 20th century a more confident United States was willing to
                    take on the role of regional policeman. In the early 1900s Roosevelt grew
                    concerned that a crisis between Venezuela and its creditors could spark an
                    invasion of that nation by European powers. The Roosevelt Corollary of December
                    1904 stated that the United States would intervene as a last resort to ensure
                    that other nations in the Western Hemisphere fulfilled their obligations to
                    international creditors, and did not violate the rights of the United States or
                    invite “foreign aggression to the detriment of the entire body of American
                    nations.” As the corollary worked out in practice, the United States
                    increasingly used military force to restore internal stability to nations in the
                    region. Roosevelt declared that the United States might “exercise international
                    police power in ‘flagrant cases of such wrongdoing or impotence.’” Over the long
                    term the corollary had little to do with relations between the Western
                    Hemisphere and Europe, but it did serve as justification for U.S. intervention
                    in Cuba, Nicaragua, Haiti, and the Dominican Republic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="portsmouth-treaty">
                <head>The Treaty of Portsmouth and the Russo-Japanese War, <date from="1904" to="1905">1904–1905</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Treaty of Portsmouth formally ended the Russo-Japanese War of 1904–05. The
                    negotiations took place in August in Portsmouth, New Hampshire, and were
                    brokered in part by U.S. President Theodore Roosevelt. The final agreement was
                    signed in September of 1905, and it affirmed the Japanese presence in south
                    Manchuria and Korea and ceded the southern half of the island of Sakhalin to
                    Japan.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="russo-japanese-war.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Photograph from the Russo-Japanese War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>By 1904, Russia and Japan had endured several years of disputes over control of
                    Manchuria. The Russians had entered the region during the Sino-Japanese War of
                    1894–95 and, along with Germany and France, was a part of the “Triple
                    Intervention” that forced Japan to give up its demands for ports in South
                    Manchuria and the Liaodong Peninsula in the wake of its victory in China.
                    Instead, Russia moved into the area and took control of Port Arthur, a warm
                    water port with strategic and commercial significance. A Japanese attempt to
                    stage a coup in adjacent Korea was thwarted in part by the Russian presence in
                    the region, and the two nations’ divergent interests appeared more and more
                    likely to clash.</p>
                <p>In 1904, the Japanese attacked the Russian fleet at Port Arthur before the formal
                    declaration of war was received in Moscow, surprising the Russian navy and
                    earning an early victory. Over the course of the next year, the two forces
                    clashed in Korea and the Sea of Japan, with the Japanese scoring significant,
                    but costly, victories. War casualties were high on both sides. At the battle
                    over Mukden, the Russians lost 60,000 soldiers and the Japanese lost 41,000
                    soldiers. The military costs were high as well. A Russian fleet made the long
                    trip from the Baltic Sea around Africa and India, only to be half destroyed by
                    the Japanese upon its arrival in Northeast Asia. By 1905, the combination of
                    these losses and the economic cost of financing the war led both countries to
                    seek an end to the war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="port-arthur.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Photograph of Attack on Port Arthur</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Japanese asked U.S. President Roosevelt to negotiate a peace agreement, and
                    representatives of the two nations met in Portsmouth, New Hampshire in 1905. For
                    the sake of maintaining the balance of power and equal economic opportunity in
                    the region, Roosevelt preferred that the war end on terms that left both Russia
                    and Japan a role to play in Northeast China. Though excited by the Japanese
                    military victories, Roosevelt worried about the consequences to American
                    interests if Japan managed to drive Russia out entirely.</p>
                <p>The negotiations centered on access to ports and territories in Manchuria and
                    Korea, control of Sakhalin Island, and the question of who was responsible for
                    paying war costs. The chief aims of the Japanese negotiator included first
                    control in Korea and South Manchuria, then the negotiation of an indemnity and
                    control of Sakhalin Island. The Russians wanted to maintain Sakhalin Island,
                    refused to pay a war costs indemnity to the Japanese, and hoped to maintain
                    their fleet in the Pacific. The indemnity issue, along with the dispensation of
                    Sakhalin Island, were the major sticking points in the negotiation, although
                    given its financial straits in 1905, Russia was likely unable to pay an
                    indemnity even if required by a treaty to do so.</p>
                <p>When negotiations reached an impasse, Roosevelt stepped in with the proposal that
                    Russia “buy back” the northern part of Sakhalin from Japanese control. The
                    Russians were adamant that they would not pay any amount of money, which would
                    act as a disguised indemnity, when the territory ought to be theirs. After long
                    internal debate, Japan eventually agreed to take only the southern half of the
                    island, without any kind of payment. Theirs had not been a decisive enough
                    victory to force the point.</p>
                <p>The Treaty ultimately gave Japan control of Korea and much of South Manchuria,
                    including Port Arthur and the railway that connected it with the rest of the
                    region, along with the southern half of Sakhalin Island; Russian power was
                    curtailed in the region, but it was not required to pay Japan’s war costs.
                    Because neither nation was in a strong financial position to continue the war
                    easily, both were forced to compromise in the terms of the peace. Still, the
                    Japanese public felt they had won the war, and they considered the lack of an
                    indemnity to be an affront. There was a brief outbreak of protests and rioting
                    in Tokyo when the terms of the agreement were made public. Similarly, the
                    Russian people were also dissatisfied, angry about giving up half of Sakhalin.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="treatyofportsmouth.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Individuals gathered to work out what became the Treaty of
                    Portsmouth</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Throughout the war and the peace talks, American public opinion largely sided
                    with Japan. Believing that the Japanese were fighting a “just war” against
                    Russian aggression, and that the island nation was equally committed to the Open
                    Door and the territorial integrity of China, the American people were anxious to
                    support it. This sense did not really change over the course of the
                    negotiations, in spite of the best efforts of the Russian negotiator to improve
                    the press coverage of his nation’s position. The final decision of the Japanese
                    to forgo an indemnity only served to strengthen U.S. approval of Japan’s actions
                    throughout the conflict. The anti-treaty and, at times, anti-American
                    demonstrations in Tokyo that followed the ratification of the treaty caught many
                    Americans off-guard.</p>
                <p>The Treaty of Portsmouth marked the last real event in an era of U.S.-Japanese
                    cooperation that began with the Meiji Restoration in 1868. Instead, competition
                    between the two nations in the Pacific grew over the years that followed.
                    Conversely, Japanese relations with Russia improved in the wake of the treaty.
                    Although the actual importance of Roosevelt’s mediation and personal pressure on
                    the leadership in Moscow and Tokyo to the final agreement is unclear, he won the
                    Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts in moderating the talks and pushing toward
                    peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="dollar-diplo">
                <head>Dollar Diplomacy, <date from="1909" to="1913">1909–1913</date>
                </head>
                <p>From 1909 to 1913, President <persName>William Howard Taft</persName> and
                    Secretary of State <persName>Philander C. Knox</persName> followed a foreign
                    policy characterized as “dollar diplomacy.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="taft-william-howard.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>William Howard Taft</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Taft shared the view held by Knox, a corporate lawyer who had founded the giant
                    conglomerate U.S. Steel, that the goal of diplomacy was to create stability and
                    order abroad that would best promote American commercial interests. Knox felt
                    that not only was the goal of diplomacy to improve financial opportunities, but
                    also to use private capital to further U.S. interests overseas. “Dollar
                    diplomacy” was evident in extensive U.S. interventions in the Caribbean and
                    Central America, especially in measures undertaken to safeguard American
                    financial interests in the region. In China, Knox secured the entry of an
                    American banking conglomerate, headed by J.P. Morgan, into a European-financed
                    consortium financing the construction of a railway from Huguang to Canton. In
                    spite of successes, “dollar diplomacy” failed to counteract economic instability
                    and the tide of revolution in places like Mexico, the Dominican Republic,
                    Nicaragua, and China.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="chinese-rev">
                <head>The Chinese Revolution of <date when="1911">1911</date>
                </head>
                <p>In October of 1911, a group of revolutionaries in southern China led a successful
                    revolt against the Qing Dynasty, establishing in its place the Republic of China
                    and ending the imperial system.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chinese-revolution.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Photograph of Revolutionaries in Shanghai</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the Nineteenth Century, the Qing Empire faced a number of challenges to its
                    rule, including a number of foreign incursions into Chinese territory. The two
                    Opium Wars against Western powers led by Great Britain resulted in the loss of
                    Hong Kong, forced opening of “treaty ports” for international trade, and large
                    foreign “concessions” in major cities privileged with extraterritorial rule.
                    After its loss in the Sino-Japanese War (1894–95), Imperial China was forced to
                    relinquish control over still more of its territory, losing Taiwan and parts of
                    Manchuria and ending its suzerainty over Korea. The <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/portsmouth-treaty">Russo-Japanese War
                    (1904–05)</ref> firmly established Japanese claims to the Northeast and further
                    weakened Qing rule. The combination of increasing imperialist demands (from both
                    Japan and the West), frustration with the foreign Manchu Government embodied by
                    the Qing court, and the desire to see a unified China less parochial in outlook
                    fed a growing nationalism that spurred on revolutionary ideas.</p>
                <p>As Qing rule fell into decline, it made a few last-ditch efforts at
                    constitutional reform. In 1905, the court abolished the examination system,
                    which had limited political power to elites who passed elaborate exams on
                    Chinese classics. Faced with increasing foreign challenges, it worked to
                    modernize its military. With its central power weakening, the court also
                    attempted a limited decentralization of power, creating elected assemblies and
                    increasing provincial self-government.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="qing.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Qing Soldiers</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although the Qing court maintained a degree of control within China in these
                    years, millions of Chinese living overseas, especially in Southeast Asia and the
                    Americas, began pressing for either widespread reform or outright revolution.
                    Kang Youwei and Liang Qichao emerged as leaders of those proposing the creation
                    of a constitutional monarchy. Sun Yat-sen led the amalgam of groups that
                    together formed the Revolutionary Alliance or Tongmenghui. The Revolutionary
                    Alliance advocated replacing Qing rule with a republican government; Sun himself
                    was a nationalist with some socialist tendencies.</p>
                <p>Both the revolutionary leaders and the overseas Chinese bankrolling their efforts
                    had their roots in southern China. The Revolutionary Alliance attempted seven or
                    more different revolts against the Qing in the years leading up to the
                    revolution, most of which originated in south China and all of which were
                    ultimately stopped by the Qing army.</p>
                <p>Finally, in the autumn of 1911, the right set of conditions turned an uprising in
                    Wuchang into a nationalist revolt. As its losses mounted, the Qing court
                    responded positively to a set of demands intended to transform authoritarian
                    imperial rule into a Constitutional monarchy. They named Yuan Shikai the new
                    premier of China, but before he was able to retake the captured areas from the
                    revolutionaries, the provinces started to declare their allegiance to the
                    Revolutionary Alliance. Dr. Sun was in the United States on a fundraising tour
                    at the time of the initial revolt; he hastened first to London and Paris to
                    ensure that neither country would give financial or military support to the Qing
                    government in its struggle. By the time he returned to China, the
                    revolutionaries had taken Nanjing, a former capital under the Ming Dynasty, and
                    representatives from the provinces began to arrive for the first national
                    assembly. Together, they elected Dr. Sun the provisional president of the newly
                    declared Republic of China.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="sun-yat-sen.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Sun Yat-Sen</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Sun Yat-sen telegrammed Yuan Shikai to promise that, should Yuan agree to the
                    formation of a republic, the position of president would be his. With the
                    military position of the Qing weakening and provisions made for the maintenance
                    of the royal family at court, the emperor and the royal family abdicated the
                    throne in February of 1912.</p>
                <p>The 1911 revolution was only the first steps in a process that would require the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/chinese-rev">1949 revolution</ref> to
                    complete. Though the new government created the Republic of China and
                    established the seat of government in Nanjing, it failed to unify the country
                    under its control. The Qing withdrawal led to a power vacuum in certain regions,
                    resulting in the rise of warlords. These warlords often controlled their
                    territories without acknowledging the nationalist government. Additionally, the
                    reforms set in place by the new government were not nearly as sweeping as the
                    revolutionary rhetoric had intended; unifying the country took precedent over
                    fundamental changes.</p>
                <p>International reaction to the revolution was guarded. Foreign nations with
                    investments in China remained neutral throughout the upheaval, though they were
                    anxious to protect the treaty rights they gained from the Qing through the first
                    and second opium wars. Still, the United States was largely supportive of the
                    republican project, and in 1913, the United States was among the first countries
                    to establish full diplomatic relations with the new Republic. Britain, Japan,
                    and Russia soon followed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="panama-canal">
                <head>Building the Panama Canal, <date from="1903" to="1914">1903–1914</date>
                </head>
                <p>President <persName>Theodore Roosevelt</persName> oversaw the realization of a
                    long-term United States goal—a trans-isthmian canal. Throughout the 1800s,
                    American and British leaders and businessmen wanted to ship goods quickly and
                    cheaply between the Atlantic and Pacific coasts.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="panama-canal3.jpg" height="450px" width="306px"/>
                    <head>Roosevelt on a digging machine during construction of the Panama
                        Canal, circa 1908. (Library of Congress, Prints and Photographs Division)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>To that end, in 1850 the United States and Great Britain negotiated the
                    Clayton-Bulwer Treaty to rein in rivalry over a proposed canal through the
                    Central American Republic of Nicaragua. The Anglo-American canal, however, never
                    went beyond the planning stages. French attempts to build a canal through Panama
                    (province of Colombia) advanced further. Led by Ferdinand de Lesseps—the builder
                    of the Suez Canal in Egypt—the French began excavating in 1880. Malaria, yellow
                    fever, and other tropical diseases conspired against the de Lesseps campaign and
                    after 9 years and a loss of approximately 20,000 lives, the French attempt went
                    bankrupt. In spite of such setbacks, American interest in a canal continued
                    unabated. The Hay-Pauncefote Treaty of 1901 abrogated the earlier Clayton-Bulwer
                    Treaty and licensed the United States to build and manage its own canal.
                    Following heated debate over the location of the proposed canal, on June 19,
                    1902, the U.S. Senate voted in favor of building the canal through Panama.
                    Within 6 months, Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/hay-john-milton">John Hay</ref> signed a
                    treaty with Colombian Foreign Minister Tomás Herrán to build the new canal. The
                    financial terms were unacceptable to Colombia’s congress, and it rejected the
                    offer.</p>
                <p>President Roosevelt responded by dispatching U.S. warships to Panama City (on the
                    Pacific) and Colón (on the Atlantic) in support of Panamanian independence.
                    Colombian troops were unable to negotiate the jungles of the Darien Strait and
                    Panama declared independence on November 3, 1903. The newly declared Republic of
                    Panama immediately named Philippe Bunau-Varilla (a French engineer who had been
                    involved in the earlier de Lesseps canal attempt) as Envoy Extraordinary and
                    Minister Plenipotentiary. In his new role, Bunau-Varilla negotiated the
                    Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty of 1903, which provided the United States with a
                    10-mile wide strip of land for the canal, a one-time $10 million payment to
                    Panama, and an annual annuity of $250,000. The United States also agreed to
                    guarantee the independence of Panama. Completed in 1914, the Panama Canal
                    symbolized U.S. technological prowess and economic power. Although U.S. control
                    of the canal eventually became an irritant to U.S.-Panamanian relations, at the
                    time it was heralded as a major foreign policy achievement.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>