<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1914–1920</title>
                <title type="short">1914–1920</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1914" to="1920">1914–1920</date>: World War One and Wilsonian
                    Diplomacy</head>
                <p>During his tenure as President, <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> encouraged
                    the country to look beyond its economic interests and to define and set foreign
                    policy in terms of ideals, morality, and the spread of democracy abroad.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilson-woodrow.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Woodrow Wilson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States continued its efforts to become an active player on the
                    international scene. It engaged in action both in its traditional “sphere of
                    influence” in the Western Hemisphere and in Europe during the First World War.
                    The Wilsonian vision for collective security through U.S. leadership in
                    international organizations, like the newly established League of Nations,
                    appealed to the public. However, the United States ultimately declined
                    membership in the League due to Article X of its charter that committed the
                    United States to defend any League member in the event of an attack. In voting
                    down U.S. participation, Congress challenged the informal tradition of the
                    executive branch determining U.S. foreign policy. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="haiti">
                <head>U.S. Invasion and Occupation of Haiti, <date from="1915" to="1934"
                        >1915–34</date>
                </head>
                <p>Following the assassination of the Haitian President in July of 1915, President
                        <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> sent the United States Marines into
                    Haiti to restore order and maintain political and economic stability in the
                    Caribbean. This occupation continued until 1934.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilson-w.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Woodrow Wilson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States Government's interests in <placeName>Haiti</placeName> existed
                    for decades prior to its occupation. As a potential naval base for the United
                    States, Haiti’s stability concerned U.S. diplomatic and defense officials who
                    feared Haitian instability might result in foreign rule of Haiti. In 1868,
                    President <persName>Andrew Johnson</persName> suggested the annexation of the
                    island of Hispaniola, consisting of Haiti and the Dominican Republic, to secure
                    a U.S. defensive and economic stake in the West Indies. From 1889 to 1891,
                    Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/blaine-james-gillespie">James Blaine</ref>
                    unsuccessfully sought a lease of Mole-Saint Nicolas, a city on Haiti’s northern
                    coast strategically located for a naval base. In 1910, President William Howard
                    Taft granted Haiti a large loan in hopes that Haiti could pay off its
                    international debt, thus lessening foreign influence. The attempt failed due to
                    the enormity of the debt and the internal instability of the country.</p>
                <p>France, as the former colonizer of Haiti, retained strong economic and diplomatic
                    ties with the Haitian Government. In the 1824 Franco-Haitian Agreement, France
                    agreed to recognize Haitian independence if Haiti paid a large indemnity. This
                    kept Haiti in a constant state of debt and placed France in a position of power
                    over Haiti’s trade and finances.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="haiti-coatofarms.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Haitian Coat of Arms</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although unhappy about the Haitians' close connection to France, the United
                    States became increasingly concerned with heightened German activity and
                    influence in Haiti. At the start of the 20th century, German presence increased
                    with German merchants establishing trading branches in Haiti that dominated
                    commercial business in the area. German men married Haitian women to get around
                    laws denying foreigners land ownership and established roots in the community.
                    The United States considered Germany its chief rival in the Caribbean and feared
                    German control of Haiti would give them a powerful advantage in the region.</p>
                <p>As a result of increased instability in Haiti in the years before 1915, the
                    United States heightened its activity to deter foreign influence. Between 1911
                    and 1915, seven presidents were assassinated or overthrown in Haiti, increasing
                    U.S. policymakers’ fear of foreign intervention. In 1914, the Wilson
                    administration sent U.S. Marines into Haiti. They removed $500,000 from the
                    Haitian National Bank in December of 1914 for safe-keeping in New York, thus
                    giving the United States control of the bank. In 1915, Haitian President Jean
                    Vilbrun Guillaume Sam was assassinated and the situation in Haiti quickly became
                    unstable. In response, President Wilson sent the U.S. Marines to Haiti to
                    prevent anarchy. In actuality, the act protected U.S. assets in the area and
                    prevented a possible German invasion.</p>
                <p>The invasion ended with the Haitian-American Treaty of 1915. The articles of this
                    agreement created the Haitian Gendarmerie, essentially a military force made up
                    of U.S. citizens and Haitians and controlled by the U.S. Marines. The United
                    States gained complete control over Haitian finances, and the right to intervene
                    in Haiti whenever the U.S. Government deemed necessary. The U.S. Government also
                    forced the election of a new pro-American President, Philippe Sudré
                    Dartiguenave, by the Haitian legislature in August 1915. The selection of a
                    President that did not represent the choice of the Haitian populace increased
                    unrest in Haiti.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="haitian-pres.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Philippe Sudré Dartiguenave</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Following the successful manipulation of the 1915 elections, the Wilson
                    administration attempted to strong-arm the Haitian legislature into adopting a
                    new constitution in 1917. This constitution allowed foreign land ownership,
                    which had been outlawed since the Haitian Revolution as a way to prevent foreign
                    control of the country. Extremely reluctant to change the long-standing law, the
                    legislature rejected the new constitution. Law-makers began drafting a new
                    anti-American constitution, but the United States forced President Dartiguenave
                    dissolve the legislature, which did not meet again until 1929.</p>
                <p>Some of the Gendarmerie’s more unpopular policies—including racial segregation,
                    press censorship and forced labor—led to a peasant rebellion from 1919 to 1920.
                    The U.S. Senate sent an investigative committee into Haiti in 1921 to examine
                    claims of abuse, and subsequently the U.S. Senate reorganized and centralized
                    power in Haiti. After the reorganization, Haiti remained fairly stable and a
                    select group achieved economic prosperity, though most Haitians remained in
                    poverty.</p>
                <p>In 1929, a series of strikes and uprisings led the United States to begin
                    withdrawal from Haiti. In 1930, U.S. officials began training Haitian officials
                    to take control of the government. In 1934, the United States, in concert with
                    President <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName>’s <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/good-neighbor">Good Neighbor Policy</ref>,
                    officially withdrew from Haiti while retaining economic connections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="wwi">
                <head>U.S. Entry into World War I, <date when="1917">1917</date>
                </head>
                <p>On April 2, 1917, President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> went before a
                    joint session of Congress to request a declaration of war against Germany.
                    Wilson cited Germany’s violation of its pledge to suspend unrestricted submarine
                    warfare in the North Atlantic and the Mediterranean, as well as its attempts to
                    entice Mexico into an alliance against the United States, as his reasons for
                    declaring war. On April 4, 1917, the U.S. Senate voted in support of the measure
                    to declare war on <placeName>Germany</placeName>. The House concurred two days
                    later. The United States later declared war on German ally Austria-Hungary on
                    December 7, 1917.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wwi.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>World War I Trenches in France</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Germany’s resumption of submarine attacks on passenger and merchant ships in 1917
                    became the primary motivation behind Wilson’s decision to lead the United States
                    into World War I. Following the sinking of an unarmed French boat, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sussex</hi>, in the English Channel in March 1916, Wilson
                    threatened to sever diplomatic relations with Germany unless the German
                    Government refrained from attacking all passenger ships and allowed the crews of
                    enemy merchant vessels to abandon their ships prior to any attack. On May 4,
                    1916, the German Government accepted these terms and conditions in what came to
                    be known as the “<hi rend="italic">Sussex</hi> pledge.”</p>
                <p>By January 1917, however, the situation in Germany had changed. During a wartime
                    conference that month, representatives from the German Navy convinced the
                    military leadership and Kaiser Wilhelm II that a resumption of unrestricted
                    submarine warfare could help defeat Great Britain within five months. German
                    policymakers argued that they could violate the “<hi rend="italic">Sussex</hi>
                    pledge” since the United States could no longer be considered a neutral party
                    after supplying munitions and financial assistance to the Allies. Germany also
                    believed that the United States had jeopardized its neutrality by acquiescing to
                    the Allied blockade of Germany.</p>
                <p>German Chancellor <persName>Theobald von Bethmann-Hollweg</persName> protested
                    this decision, believing that resuming submarine warfare would draw the United
                    States into the war on behalf of the Allies. This, he argued, would lead to the
                    defeat of Germany. Despite these warnings, the German Government decided to
                    resume unrestricted submarine attacks on all Allied and neutral shipping within
                    prescribed war zones, reckoning that German submarines would end the war long
                    before the first U.S. troopships landed in Europe. Accordingly, on January 31,
                    1917, German Ambassador to the United States Count Johann von Bernstorff
                    presented U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert Lansing</ref> a
                    note declaring Germany’s intention to restart unrestricted submarine warfare the
                    following day.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="german-chancellor.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>German Chancellor Theobald von Bethmann-Hollweg</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Stunned by the news, President Wilson went before Congress on February 3 to
                    announce that he had severed diplomatic relations with Germany. However, he
                    refrained from asking for a declaration of war because he doubted that the U.S.
                    public would support him unless he provided ample proof that Germany intended to
                    attack U.S. ships without warning. Wilson left open the possibility of
                    negotiating with Germany if its submarines refrained from attacking U.S.
                    shipping. Nevertheless, throughout February and March 1917, German submarines
                    targeted and sank several U.S. ships, resulting in the deaths of numerous U.S.
                    seamen and citizens.</p>
                <p>On February 26, Wilson asked Congress for the authority to arm U.S. merchant
                    ships with U.S. naval personnel and equipment. While the measure would probably
                    have passed in a vote, several anti-war Senators led a successful filibuster
                    that consumed the remainder of the congressional session. As a result of this
                    setback, President Wilson decided to arm U.S. merchant ships by executive order,
                    citing an old anti-piracy law that gave him the authority to do so.</p>
                <p>While Wilson weighed his options regarding the submarine issue, he also had to
                    address the question of Germany’s attempts to cement a secret alliance with
                    Mexico. On January 19, 1917, British naval intelligence intercepted and
                    decrypted a telegram sent by German Foreign Minister Arthur Zimmermann to the
                    German Ambassador in Mexico City. The “Zimmermann Telegram” promised the Mexican
                    Government that Germany would help Mexico recover the territory it had ceded to
                    the United States following the Mexican-American War. In return for this
                    assistance, Germany asked for Mexican support in the war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="zimmerman-telegram.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The “Zimmermann Telegram”</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Initially, the British had not shared the news of the Zimmermann Telegram with
                    U.S. officials because they did not want the Germans to discover that British
                    code breakers had cracked the German code. However, following Germany’s
                    resumption of unrestricted submarine warfare in February, the British decided to
                    use the note to help sway U.S. official and public opinion in favor of joining
                    the war. The British finally forwarded the intercepted telegram to President
                    Wilson on February 24. The U.S. press carried the story the following week.</p>
                <p>Despite the shocking news of the Zimmermann Telegram, Wilson still hesitated
                    asking for a declaration of war. He waited until March 20 before convening a
                    Cabinet meeting to broach the matter—almost a month after he had first seen the
                    telegram. The precise reasons for Wilson’s decision to choose war in 1917 remain
                    the subject of debate among historians, especially in light of his efforts to
                    avoid war in 1915 after the sinking of the British passenger liners <hi
                        rend="italic">Lusitania</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Arabic</hi>, which had
                    led to the deaths of 131 U.S. citizens.</p>
                <p>However, by 1917, the continued submarine attacks on U.S. merchant and passenger
                    ships, and the “Zimmermann Telegram’s” implied threat of a German attack on the
                    United States, swayed U.S. public opinion in support of a declaration of war.
                    Furthermore, international law stipulated that the placing of U.S. naval
                    personnel on civilian ships to protect them from German submarines already
                    constituted an act of war against Germany. Finally, the Germans, by their
                    actions, had demonstrated that they had no interest in seeking a peaceful end to
                    the conflict. These reasons all contributed to President Wilson’s decision to
                    ask Congress for a declaration of war against Germany. They also encouraged
                    Congress to grant Wilson’s request and formally declare war on Germany.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="fourteen-points">
                <head>Wilson’s Fourteen Points, <date when="1918">1918</date>
                </head>
                <p>The immediate cause of <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/wwi">the United States’
                        entry into World War I</ref> in April 1917 was the German announcement of
                    unrestricted submarine warfare and the subsequent sinking of ships with U.S.
                    citizens on board. But President Woodrow Wilson’s war aims went beyond the
                    defense of U.S. maritime interests. In his War Message to Congress, President
                    Wilson declared that the U.S. objective was “to vindicate the principles of
                    peace and justice in the life of the world.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilson-14points.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Woodrow Wilson delivering his Fourteen Points to Congress</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In several speeches earlier in the year, President Wilson sketched out his vision
                    of an end to the war that would bring a “just and secure peace,” not merely “a
                    new balance of power.” He then appointed a committee of experts known as The
                    Inquiry to help him refine his ideas for peace. In December 1917, he asked The
                    Inquiry to draw up specific recommendations for a comprehensive peace
                    settlement. Using these recommendations, Wilson presented a program of fourteen
                    points to a joint session of Congress on January 8, 1918. Eight of the fourteen
                    points treated specific territorial issues among the combatant nations. Five of
                    the other six concerned general principles for a peaceful world: open covenants
                    (i.e. treaties or agreements) openly arrived at; freedom of the seas; free
                    trade; reduction of armaments; and adjustment of colonial claims based on the
                    principles of self-determination. The fourteenth point proposed what was to
                    become the League of Nations to guarantee the “political independence and
                    territorial integrity [of] great and small states alike.” </p>
                <p>Though Wilson’s idealism pervades the Fourteen Points, he also had more practical
                    objectives in mind. He hoped to keep Russia in the war by convincing the
                    Bolsheviks that they would receive a better peace from the Allies, to bolster
                    Allied morale, and to undermine German war support. The address was immediately
                    hailed in the United States and Allied nations, and even by Bolshevik leader
                    Vladimir Lenin, as a landmark of enlightenment in international relations.
                    Wilson subsequently used the Fourteen Points as the basis for negotiating the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Treaty of Versailles</ref>
                    that ended the war. Although the Treaty did not fully realize Wilson’s unselfish
                    vision, the Fourteen Points still stand as the most powerful expression of the
                    idealist strain in United States diplomacy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bullitt-mission">
                <head>The Bullitt Mission to Soviet Russia, <date when="1919">1919</date>
                </head>
                <p>In March of 1919, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/bullitt-william-christian">William
                        Christian Bullitt</ref>, an attaché to the U.S. delegation to the Paris
                    Peace Conference, visited Soviet Russia on a clandestine mission. Although
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/lansing-robert">Robert
                        Lansing</ref> only authorized him to report on political and economic
                    conditions, Bullitt’s actual objective was far more ambitious: to broker an
                    agreement between the Allies and Russia’s Bolshevik government that would end
                    the Russian Civil War, lift the Allied blockade of that country, and allow the
                    Allies to withdraw the troops dispatched to Russia in 1918. Bullitt eventually
                    received a proposal from the Bolshevik government that would have realized these
                    goals, but the Allied leaders at the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace Conference</ref> were
                    unwilling to accept the offer.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bullitt-william-christian.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>William Christian Bullitt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Following the withdrawal of Allied diplomats from Petrograd and Moscow in 1918,
                    the Allied leaders – U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>, British
                    Prime Minister <persName>David Lloyd George</persName>, French Prime Minister
                        <persName>Georges Clemenceau</persName>, and Italian Prime Minister
                        <persName>Vittorio Emmanuele Orlando</persName> – grappled with the question
                    of how to address the Russian Civil War that erupted between the Bolsheviks and
                    White Russian forces following the Russian Revolution. After the signing of the
                    Treaty of Brest-Litovsk on March 3, 1918, Japanese and Allied forces, including
                    U.S. troops, occupied parts of Northern Russia, the Ukraine, and Siberia to
                    protect vital areas from falling into the hands of the Germans, as well as to
                    provide assistance to the White Russians. When the First World War ended,
                    however, Allied leaders found it difficult to justify leaving tens of thousands
                    of war-weary troops in Russia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="world-powers.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Meeting of World Leaders in Paris</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In early 1919, both Lloyd George and President Wilson suggested that the leaders
                    of the warring Russian factions should meet in order to hammer out a peace
                    accord. In spite of fierce French opposition, President Wilson succeeded in
                    proposing that the Russians would meet on Prinkipo Island off the coast of
                    Turkey. While the Bolsheviks accepted Wilson’s proposal, the conference failed
                    to materialize due to French resistance and the unwillingness of Russian
                    anti-Bolsheviks to attend negotiations that would include the Bolshevik
                    government.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, Lloyd George and President Wilson remained interested in working
                    toward resolving the Russian situation. Because Bullitt urged that a mission be
                    dispatched to Russia, Wilson’s chief adviser, Colonel Edward M. House, asked
                    Bullitt if he would be willing to lead such an endeavor. Bullitt then drew up a
                    list of peace proposals to present to the Bolshevik government that included an
                    armistice, the re-establishment of economic relations, and the withdrawal of
                    Allied troops. Additionally, House encouraged Bullitt to secure a promise from
                    the Bolsheviks that they would honor Tsarist Russia’s debts to the Allied
                    powers. However, while Bullitt secured House’s assent to his proposals, neither
                    Wilson nor Lloyd George knew of them.</p>
                <p>On March 6, 1919, the Bullitt Mission (comprised of Bullitt, journalist Lincoln
                    Steffens, and a U.S. Army intelligence officer) crossed the Russian border.
                    Following a meeting with Deputy Soviet Foreign Minister Maxim Litvinov in
                    Petrograd, Bullitt and Steffens left for Moscow, where they met with Bolshevik
                    leader Vladimir Lenin and his Foreign Minister, Georgi Chicherin. Although there
                    was opposition to negotiations with the United States within the Bolshevik
                    leadership, on March 14, Bullitt received a Russian proposal that demanded that
                    the Allies call for a ceasefire within the former Russian Empire and agree to a
                    peace conference in a neutral nation. The proposed terms for discussion at the
                    conference included allowing all de facto governments within the borders of
                    Russia to retain the territory they held prior to the armistice, the lifting of
                    the Allied blockade, the withdrawal of Allied troops from Russia, disarmament of
                    the warring Russian factions, and a commitment by the Bolshevik government to
                    honor Russia’s financial obligations to the Allies.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lenin.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Bolshevik Leader, Vladimir Lenin</head>
                </figure>
                <p>During his week in Russia, Bullitt also compiled an extensive report on
                    conditions there. While acknowledging the economic hardships facing the Russian
                    people, Bullitt asserted that the violent phase of the Bolshevik Revolution had
                    ended and that the Bolsheviks enjoyed popular support. Furthermore, he reported
                    that Lenin and a large segment of the Bolshevik Party were willing to compromise
                    with the United States. In fact, Bullitt believed that the greatest danger
                    confronting the United States was the possibility that continued Allied
                    interventions and support of the Whites Russians would lead to the rise of more
                    radical political factions. Consequently, Bullitt concluded that “[no]
                    Government save a Socialist Government can be set up in Russia today except by
                    bayonets,” and that Lenin’s faction of the Bolshevik was “as moderate as any
                    Socialist Government which can control Russia.”</p>
                <p>Bullitt returned to Paris on March 25, where he faced Allied resistance to the
                    proposal he received from Lenin. Although Lloyd George privately assured Bullitt
                    that he was sympathetic to the Bolsheviks’ offer, he repudiated it once news of
                    Bullitt’s Mission leaked to the British press. Clemenceau had opposed any
                    overtures to Lenin from the start. Wilson was in poor health and was focused on
                    achieving a breakthrough in negotiations with the French concerning the peace
                    treaty with Germany. Furthermore, the President’s relations with House,
                    Bullitt’s original patron, had soured greatly. Finally, news from Russia
                    indicated that anti-Bolshevik forces would soon capture Moscow, thus obviating
                    the need to negotiate with Lenin. Consequently, the April 10th deadline for the
                    Allies to respond to Lenin’s offer passed without any word from the Allied side,
                    and Bullitt angrily resigned from the U.S. delegation on May 17. The failure of
                    the Allies to agree to the proposal secured by the Bullitt Mission delayed
                    official U.S. recognition of Soviet Russia for many years.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="paris-peace">
                <head>The Paris Peace Conference and the Treaty of Versailles</head>
                <p>The Paris Peace Conference convened in January 1919 at
                        <placeName>Versailles</placeName> just outside <placeName>Paris</placeName>.
                    The conference was called to establish the terms of the peace after World War I.
                    Though nearly thirty nations participated, the representatives of the United
                    Kingdom, France, the United States, and Italy became known as the “Big Four.”
                    The “Big Four” dominated the proceedings that led to the formulation of the
                    Treaty of Versailles, a treaty that ended World War I. </p>
                <p>The Treaty of Versailles articulated the compromises reached at the conference.
                    It included the planned formation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of Nations</ref>, which would
                    serve both as an international forum and an international collective security
                    arrangement. U.S. President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> was a strong
                    advocate of the League as he believed it would prevent future wars.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="versailles-treaty.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Treaty of Versailles</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Negotiations at the Paris Peace Conference were complicated. The United Kingdom,
                    France, and Italy fought together as the Allied Powers during the First World
                    War. The United States, entered the war in April 1917 as an Associated Power.
                    While it fought alongside the Allies, the United States was not bound to honor
                    pre-existing agreements among the Allied Powers. These agreements focused on
                    postwar redistribution of territories. U.S. President Woodrow Wilson strongly
                    opposed many of these arrangements, including Italian demands on the Adriatic.
                    This often led to significant disagreements among the “Big Four.”</p>
                <p>Treaty negotiations were also weakened by the absence of other important nations.
                    Russia had fought as one of the Allies until December 1917, when its new
                    Bolshevik Government withdrew from the war. The Bolshevik decision to repudiate
                    Russia’s outstanding financial debts to the Allies and to publish the texts of
                    secret agreements between the Allies concerning the postwar period angered the
                    Allies. The Allied Powers refused to recognize the new Bolshevik Government and
                    thus did not invite its representatives to the Peace Conference. The Allies also
                    excluded the defeated Central Powers (Germany, Austria-Hungary, Turkey, and
                    Bulgaria).</p>
                <p>According to French and British wishes, the Treaty of Versailles subjected
                    Germany to strict punitive measures. The Treaty required the new German
                    Government to surrender approximately 10 percent of its prewar territory in
                    Europe and all of its overseas possessions. It placed the harbor city of Danzig
                    (now Gdansk) and the coal-rich Saarland under the administration of the League
                    of Nations, and allowed France to exploit the economic resources of the Saarland
                    until 1935. It limited the German Army and Navy in size, and allowed for the
                    trial of Kaiser Wilhelm II and a number of other high-ranking German officials
                    as war criminals. Under the terms of Article 231 of the Treaty, the Germans
                    accepted responsibility for the war and the liability to pay financial
                    reparations to the Allies. The Inter-Allied Commission determined the amount and
                    presented its findings in 1921. The amount they determined was 132 billion gold
                    Reichmarks, or 32 billion U.S. dollars, on top of the initial $5 billion payment
                    demanded by the Treaty. Germans grew to resent the harsh conditions imposed by
                    the Treaty of Versailles.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="henrycabotlodget.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Henry Cabot Lodge</head>
                </figure>
                <p>While the Treaty of Versailles did not satisfy all parties concerned, by the time
                    President Woodrow Wilson returned to the United States in July 1919, U.S. public
                    opinion overwhelmingly favored ratification of the Treaty, including the
                    Covenant of the League of Nations. However, in spite of the fact that 32 state
                    legislatures passed resolutions in favor of the Treaty, the U.S. Senate strongly
                    opposed it.</p>
                <p>Senate opposition cited Article 10 of the Treaty, which dealt with collective
                    security and the League of Nations. This article, opponents argued, ceded the
                    war powers of the U.S. Government to the League’s Council. The opposition came
                    from two groups: the “Irreconcilables,” who refused to join the League of
                    Nations under any circumstances, and “Reservationists,” led by Senate Foreign
                    Relations Committee Chairman, Henry Cabot Lodge, who wanted amendments made
                    before they would ratify the Treaty. While Chairman Lodge's attempt to pass
                    amendments to the Treaty was unsuccessful in September, he did manage to attach
                    14 “reservations” to it in November. In a final vote on March 19, 1920, the
                    Treaty of Versailles fell short of ratification by seven votes. Consequently,
                    the U.S. Government signed the Treaty of Berlin on August 25, 1921. This
                    separate peace treaty with Germany stipulated that the United States would enjoy
                    all “rights, privileges, indemnities, reparations or advantages” conferred to it
                    by the Treaty of Versailles, but left out any mention of the League of Nations,
                    which the United States never joined. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="league">
                <head>The League of Nations, <date when="1920">1920</date>
                </head>
                <p>The League of Nations was an international organization, headquartered in
                        <placeName>Geneva, Switzerland</placeName>, created after the First World
                    War to provide a forum for resolving international disputes. Though first
                    proposed by President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName> as part of his
                    Fourteen Points plan for an equitable peace in Europe, the United States never
                    became a member.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="league-cartoon.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Cartoon critizing U.S. lack of participation in the League of
                        Nations</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Speaking before the U.S. Congress on January 8, 1918, President <persName>Woodrow
                        Wilson</persName> enumerated the last of his <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/fourteen-points">Fourteen Points</ref>, which
                    called for a “general association of nations…formed under specific covenants for
                    the purpose of affording mutual guarantees of political independence and
                    territorial integrity to great and small states alike.” Many of Wilson’s
                    previous points would require regulation or enforcement. In calling for the
                    formation of a "general association of nations," Wilson voiced the wartime
                    opinions of many diplomats and intellectuals on both sides of the Atlantic who
                    believed there was a need for a new type of standing international organization
                    dedicated to fostering international cooperation, providing security for its
                    members, and ensuring a lasting peace. With Europe’s population exhausted by
                    four years of total war, and with many in the United States optimistic that a
                    new organization would be able to solve the international disputes that had led
                    to war in 1914, Wilson’s articulation of a League of Nations was wildly popular.
                    However, it proved exceptionally difficult to create, and Wilson left office
                    never having convinced the United States to join it.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="davidlloydgeorge.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>David Lloyd George of the United Kingdom</head>
                </figure>
                <p> The idea of the League was grounded in the broad, international revulsion
                    against the unprecedented destruction of the First World War and the
                    contemporary understanding of its origins. This was reflected in all of Wilson’s
                    Fourteen Points, which were themselves based on theories of collective security
                    and international organization debated amongst academics, jurists, socialists
                    and utopians before and during the war. After adopting many of these ideas,
                    Wilson took up the cause with evangelical fervor, whipping up mass enthusiasm
                    for the organization as he traveled to the Paris Peace Conference in January
                    1919, the first President to travel abroad in an official capacity.</p>
                <p>Wilson used his tremendous influence to attach the Covenant of the League, its
                    charter, to the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Treaty of
                        Versailles</ref>. An effective League, he believed, would mitigate any
                    inequities in the peace terms. He and the other members of the “Big Three,”
                        <persName>Georges Clemenceau</persName> of France and <persName>David Lloyd
                        George</persName> of the United Kingdom, drafted the Covenant as Part I of
                    the Treaty of Versailles. The League’s main organs were an Assembly of all
                    members, a Council made up of five permanent members and four rotating members,
                    and an International Court of Justice. Most important for Wilson, the League
                    would guarantee the territorial integrity and political independence of member
                    states, authorize the League to take “any action…to safeguard the peace,”
                    establish procedures for arbitration, and create the mechanisms for economic and
                    military sanctions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="georgeclemenceau.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Georges Clemenceau of France</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The struggle to ratify the Treaty of Versailles and the Covenant in the U.S.
                    Congress helped define the most important political division over the role of
                    the United States in the world for a generation. A triumphant Wilson returned to
                    the United States in February 1919 to submit the Treaty and Covenant to Congress
                    for its consent and ratification. Unfortunately for the President, while popular
                    support for the League was still strong, opposition within Congress and the
                    press had begun building even before he had left for Paris. Spearheading the
                    challenge was the Senate majority leader and chairman of the Foreign Relations
                    Committee, Henry Cabot Lodge.</p>
                <p>Motivated by Republican concerns that the League would commit the United States
                    to an expensive organization that would reduce the United States’ ability to
                    defend its own interests, Lodge led the opposition to joining the League. Where
                    Wilson and the League’s supporters saw merit in an international body that would
                    work for peace and collective security for its members, Lodge and his supporters
                    feared the consequences of involvement in Europe’s tangled politics, now even
                    more complex because of the 1919 peace settlement. They adhered to a vision of
                    the United States returning to its traditional aversion to commitments outside
                    the Western Hemisphere. Wilson and Lodge’s personal dislike of each other
                    poisoned any hopes for a compromise, and in March 1920, the Treaty and Covenant
                    were defeated by a 49-35 Senate vote. Nine months later, <persName>Warren
                        Harding</persName> was elected President on a platform opposing the
                    League.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lodge-henry-cabot.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Henry Cabot Lodge</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States never joined the League. Most historians hold that the League
                    operated much less effectively without U.S. participation than it would have
                    otherwise. However, even while rejecting membership, the Republican Presidents
                    of the period, and their foreign policy architects, agreed with many of its
                    goals. To the extent that Congress allowed, the Harding, Coolidge, and Hoover
                    administrations associated the United States with League efforts on several
                    issues. Constant suspicion in Congress, however, that steady U.S. cooperation
                    with the League would lead to de facto membership prevented a close relationship
                    between Washington and Geneva. Additionally, growing disillusionment with the
                    Treaty of Versailles diminished support for the League in the United States and
                    the international community. Wilson’s insistence that the Covenant be linked to
                    the Treaty was a blunder; over time, the Treaty was discredited as
                    unenforceable, short-sighted, or too extreme in its provisions, and the League’s
                    failure either to enforce or revise it only reinforced U.S. congressional
                    opposition to working with the League under any circumstances. However, the
                    coming of World War II once again demonstrated the need for an effective
                    international organization to mediate disputes, and the United States public and
                    the Roosevelt administration supported and became founding members of the new
                        <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/un">United Nations</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
