<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/milestones.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1921–1936</title>
                <title type="short">1921–1936</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31" target="#dawes"/>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1921" to="1936">1921–1936</date>: Interwar Diplomacy</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Disillusionment with World War I, international commitments that could lead to
                    another war, and economic uncertainty discouraged ambitious U.S. involvement in
                    global affairs during the interwar period.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lady-liberty.jpg" height="228px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Cartoon depicting uncertainties felt by U.S. citizens in the Interwar
                        Period</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States, however, did not retreat into complete isolation. The
                    necessities of commercial growth dictated continued government support for
                    overseas private investment. That, in turn, drove the United States to further
                    engage with both with Latin America and the rebuilding of Europe in the 1920s.
                    The United States also played important roles in both international negotiations
                    to set arms limitations and the creation of pacts that aimed at securing a
                    lasting peace. By the mid-1920s, however, a general feeling of economic
                    uncertainty reinforced isolationist tendencies and encouraged new legislation
                    that placed severe limits on immigration to the United States, particularly from
                    Asia. During the 1930s, the rise of fascism as a threat to international peace
                    sparked concern in the United States, but the Great Depression curtailed U.S.
                    willingness to act. In this environment, keeping the nation out of the brewing
                    tension in Europe and Asia became an important foreign policy goal.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="naval-conference">
                <head>The Washington Naval Conference, <date from="1921" to="1922">1921–1922</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Between 1921 and 1922, the world’s largest naval powers gathered in
                        <placeName>Washington, D.C.</placeName> for a conference to discuss naval
                    disarmament and ways to relieve growing tensions in East Asia.</p>
                <p>In the wake of World War I, leaders in the international community sought to
                    prevent the possibility of another war. Rising Japanese militarism and an
                    international arms race heightened these concerns. As a result, policymakers
                    worked to reduce the rising threat. Senator <persName>William E.
                        Borah</persName> (R–Idaho) led a congressional effort to demand that the
                    United States engage its two principal competitors in the naval arms race, Japan
                    and the United Kingdom, in negotiations for disarmament.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="borah-william.jpg" height="224px" width="175px"/>
                    <head>Senator William E. Borah</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1921, U.S. Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hughes-charles-evans">Charles Evans
                        Hughes</ref> invited nine nations to Washington, D.C. to discuss naval
                    reductions and the situation in the Far East. The United Kingdom, Japan, France
                    and Italy were invited to take part in talks on reducing naval capacity, while
                    Belgium, China, Portugal, and the Netherlands were invited to join in
                    discussions on the situation in the Far East. Three major treaties emerged out
                    of the Washington Naval Conference: the Five-Power Treaty, the Four-Power
                    Treaty, and the Nine-Power Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Five-Power Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Five-Power Treaty, signed by the United States, the United Kingdom, Japan,
                    France and Italy was the cornerstone of the naval disarmament program. It called
                    for each of the countries involved to maintain a set ratio of warship tonnage
                    which allowed the United States and the United Kingdom 500,000 tons, Japan
                    300,000 tons, and France and Italy each 175,000 tons. Japan preferred that
                    tonnage be allotted at a 10:10:7 ratio, while the U.S. Navy preferred a 10:10:5
                    ratio. The conference ultimately adopted the 5:5:3 ratio limits. Since the
                    United States and the United Kingdom maintained navies in both the Pacific and
                    Atlantic Oceans to support their colonial territories, the Five-Power Treaty
                    allotted both countries the highest tonnage allowances. The treaty also called
                    on all five signatories to stop building capital ships and reduce the size of
                    their navies by scrapping older ships. </p>
                <p>Though the treaty was widely regarded as a success, the inclusion of Article XIX,
                    which recognized the status quo of U.S., British, and Japanese bases in the
                    Pacific but outlawed their expansion, created a controversy amongst U.S.
                    policymakers. Many members of the U.S. Navy in particular worried that limiting
                    the expansion of fortifications in the Pacific would endanger U.S. holdings in
                    Hawaii, Guam, and the Philippines.</p>
                <p>Additionally, although the Five-Power Treaty controlled tonnage of each navy’s
                    warships, some classes of ships were left unrestricted. As a result, a new race
                    to build cruiser ships emerged after 1922, leading the five nations to return to
                    the negotiating table in 1927 and 1930 in an effort to close the remaining
                    loopholes in the Treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Four-Power Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the Four-Power Treaty, the United States, France, the United Kingdom, and
                    Japan agreed to consult with each other in the event of a future crisis in East
                    Asia before taking action. This treaty replaced the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of
                    1902, which had been a source of some concern for the United States. In the
                    years following World War I, U.S. policymakers saw Japan as the greatest rising
                    military threat. Heavily militarized and looking to expand its influence and
                    territory, Japan had the potential to threaten U.S. colonial possessions in Asia
                    and the profitable China trade. Because of the 1902 agreement between the United
                    Kingdom and Japan, however, if the United States and Japan entered into a
                    conflict, the United Kingdom might be obligated to join Japan against the United
                    States. By ending that treaty and creating a Four-Power agreement, the countries
                    involved ensured that none would be obligated to engage in a conflict, but a
                    mechanism would exist for discussions if one emerged.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Nine-Power Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The final multilateral agreement made at the Washington Naval Conference, the
                    Nine-Power Treaty, marked the internationalization of the U.S. Open Door Policy
                    in China. The treaty promised that each of the signatories—the United States,
                    the United Kingdom, Japan, France, Italy, Belgium, the Netherlands, Portugal,
                    and China—would respect the territorial integrity of China. The treaty
                    recognized Japanese dominance in Manchuria but otherwise affirmed the importance
                    of equal opportunity for all nations doing business in the country. For its
                    part, China agreed not to discriminate against any country seeking to do
                    business there. Like the Four-Power Treaty, this treaty on China called for
                    further consultations amongst the signatories in the event of a violation. As a
                    result, it lacked a method of enforcement to ensure that all powers abided by
                    its terms.</p>
                <p>In addition to the multilateral agreements, the participants completed several
                    bilateral treaties at the conference. Japan and China signed a bilateral
                    agreement, the Shangtung (Shandong) Treaty, which returned control of that
                    province and its railroad to China. Japan had taken control of the area from the
                    Germans during World War I and maintained control of it over the years that
                    followed. The combination of the Shangtung Treaty and the Nine-Power Treaty was
                    meant to reassure China that its territory would not be further compromised by
                    Japanese expansion. Additionally, Japan agreed to withdraw its troops from
                    Siberia and the United States and Japan formally agreed to equal access to
                    cable and radio facilities on the Japanese-controlled island of Yap.</p>
                <p>Together, the treaties signed at the Washington Naval Conference served to uphold the
                    status quo in the Pacific: they recognized existing interests and did not make
                    fundamental changes to them. At the same time, the United States secured
                    agreements that reinforced its existing policy in the Pacific, including the
                    Open Door Policy in China and the protection of the Philippines, while limiting the
                    scope of Japanese imperial expansion as much as possible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="immigration-act">
                <head>The Immigration Act of <date when="1924">1924</date> (The Johnson-Reed
                    Act)</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Immigration Act of 1924 limited the number of immigrants allowed entry into
                    the United States through a national origins quota. The quota provided
                    immigration visas to two percent of the total number of people of each
                    nationality in the United States as of the 1890 national census. It completely
                    excluded immigrants from Asia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="johnson-reed.jpg" height="125px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>President Coolidge signing the Johnson-Reed Act</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Literacy Tests and “Asiatic Barred Zone”</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In 1917, the U.S. Congress enacted the first widely restrictive immigration law.
                    The uncertainty generated over national security during World War I made it
                    possible for Congress to pass this legislation, and it included several important
                    provisions that paved the way for the 1924 Act. The 1917 Act implemented a
                    literacy test that required immigrants over 16 years old to demonstrate basic
                    reading comprehension in any language. It also increased the tax paid by new
                    immigrants upon arrival and allowed immigration officials to exercise more
                    discretion in making decisions over whom to exclude. Finally, the Act excluded
                    from entry anyone born in a geographically defined “Asiatic Barred Zone” except
                    for Japanese and Filipinos. In 1907, the Japanese Government had voluntarily
                    limited Japanese immigration to the United States in the Gentlemen’s Agreement. The
                    Philippines was a U.S. colony, so its citizens were U.S. nationals and
                    could travel freely to the United States. China was not included in the Barred
                    Zone, but the Chinese were already denied immigration visas under the Chinese
                    Exclusion Act.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Immigration Quotas</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The literacy test alone was not enough to prevent most potential immigrants from
                    entering, so members of Congress sought a new way to restrict immigration in the
                    1920s. Immigration expert and Republican Senator from Vermont <persName>William
                        P. Dillingham</persName> introduced a measure to create immigration quotas,
                    which he set at three percent of the total population of the foreign-born of
                    each nationality in the United States as recorded in the 1910 census. This put
                    the total number of visas available each year to new immigrants at 350,000. It
                    did not, however, establish quotas of any kind for residents of the Western
                    Hemisphere. President Wilson opposed the restrictive act, preferring a more
                    liberal immigration policy, so he used the pocket veto to prevent its passage.
                    In early 1921, the newly inaugurated President Warren Harding called Congress
                    back to a special session to pass the law. In 1922, the act was renewed for
                    another two years.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="dillingham-william.jpg" height="216px" width="171px"/>
                    <head>Senator William P. Dillingham</head>
                </figure>
                <p>When the congressional debate over immigration began in 1924, the quota system
                    was so well-established that no one questioned whether to maintain it, but
                    rather discussed how to adjust it. Though there were advocates for raising
                    quotas and allowing more people to enter, the champions of restriction
                    triumphed. They created a plan that lowered the existing quota from three to two
                    percent of the foreign-born population. They also pushed back the year on which
                    quota calculations were based from 1910 to 1890.</p>
                <p>Another change to the quota altered the basis of the quota calculations. The
                    quota had been based on the number of people born outside of the United States,
                    or the number of immigrants in the United States. The new law traced the origins
                    of the whole of the U.S. population, including natural-born citizens. The
                    new quota calculations included large numbers of people of British descent whose
                    families had long resided in the United States. As a result, the percentage of
                    visas available to individuals from the British Isles and Western Europe
                    increased, but newer immigration from other areas like Southern and Eastern
                    Europe was limited.</p>
                <p>The 1924 Immigration Act also included a provision excluding from entry any alien
                    who by virtue of race or nationality was ineligible for citizenship. Existing
                    nationality laws dating from 1790 and 1870 excluded people of Asian lineage from
                    naturalizing. As a result, the 1924 Act meant that even Asians not previously
                    prevented from immigrating – the Japanese in particular – would no longer be
                    admitted to the United States. Many in Japan were very offended by the new law,
                    which was a violation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/japanese-relations">Gentlemen’s
                        Agreement</ref>. The Japanese government protested, but the law remained,
                    resulting in an increase in existing tensions between the two nations. Despite the increased tensions, it
                    appeared that the U.S. Congress had decided that preserving the racial
                    composition of the country was more important than promoting good ties with Japan.</p>
                <p>The restrictive principles of the Act could have resulted in strained
                    relations with some European countries as well, but these potential problems did
                    not appear for several reasons. The global
                    depression of the 1930s, World War II, and stricter enforcement of U.S.
                    immigration policy served to curtail European emigration. When these crises had
                    passed, emergency provisions for the resettlement of displaced persons in 1948
                    and 1950 helped the United States avoid conflict over its new immigration
                    laws.</p>
                <p>In all of its parts, the most basic purpose of the 1924 Immigration Act was to
                    preserve the ideal of U.S. homogeneity. Congress revised the Act in
                    1952.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="dawes">
                <head>The Dawes Plan, the Young Plan, German Reparations, and Inter-allied War
                    Debts</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the years following the First World War, issues of debt repayment and
                    reparations troubled relations between the Allies and the now defeated Germany.
                    The U.S.-sponsored Dawes and Young Plans offered a possible solution to
                    these challenges.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="dawes-charles.jpg" height="350px" width="466px"/>
                    <head>Charles G. Dawes (Prints and Photographs Division, Library of
                        Congress)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At the end of the First World War, the victorious European powers demanded that
                    Germany compensate them for the devastation wrought by the four-year conflict,
                    for which they held Germany and its allies responsible. Unable to agree upon the
                    amount that Germany should pay at the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Paris Peace Conference</ref> in
                    1919, the United States, the United Kingdom, France, and the other Allies
                    established a Reparation Commission to settle the question. In the spring of
                    1921, the Commission set the final bill at 132 billion gold marks, approximately
                    $31.5 billion. When Germany defaulted on a payment in January 1923, France and
                    Belgium occupied the Ruhr in an effort to force payment. Instead, they met a
                    government-backed campaign of passive resistance. Inflation in Germany, which
                    had begun to accelerate in 1922, spiraled into hyperinflation. The value of the
                    German currency collapsed; the battle over reparations had reached an
                    impasse.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S. Loans to Allied Powers</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Meanwhile, a second wartime financial issue was causing tension among the former
                    co-belligerents. While the United States had little interest in collecting
                    reparations from Germany, it was determined to secure repayment of the more than
                    $10 billion it had loaned to the Allies over the course of the war. Time and
                    again, Washington rejected calls to cancel these debts in the name of the common
                    wartime cause; it also resisted efforts to link reparations to inter-allied war
                    debts. In 1922, London made this link explicit in the Balfour Note, which stated
                    that it would seek reparations and wartime debt repayments from its European
                    allies equal to its debt to the United States. That same year, Congress created
                    the United States War Debt Commission to negotiate repayment plans, on
                    concessionary terms, with the 17 countries that had borrowed money from the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Dawes Plan</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In late 1923, with the European powers stalemated over German reparations, the
                    Reparation Commission formed a committee to review the situation. Headed by
                        <persName>Charles G. Dawes</persName> (Chicago banker, former Director of
                    the Bureau of the Budget, and future Vice President), the committee presented
                    its proposal in April 1924. Under the Dawes Plan, Germany’s annual reparation
                    payments would be reduced, increasing over time as its economy improved; the
                    full amount to be paid, however, was left undetermined. Economic policy making
                    in Berlin would be reorganized under foreign supervision and a new currency, the
                    Reichsmark, adopted. France and Belgium would evacuate the Ruhr and foreign
                    banks would loan the German government $200 million to help encourage economic
                    stabilization. U.S. financier <persName>J. P. Morgan</persName> floated the
                    loan on the U.S. market, which was quickly oversubscribed. Over the next four
                    years, U.S. banks continued to lend Germany enough money to enable it to meet
                    its reparation payments to countries such as France and the United Kingdom.
                    These countries, in turn, used their reparation payments from Germany to service
                    their war debts to the United States. In 1925, Dawes was a co-recipient of the
                    Nobel Peace Prize in recognition of his plan’s contribution to the resolution of
                    the crisis over reparations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Young Plan</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the autumn of 1928, another committee of experts was formed, this one to
                    devise a final settlement of the German reparations problem. In 1929, the
                    committee, under the chairmanship of Owen D. Young, the head of General Electric
                    and a member of the Dawes committee, proposed a plan that reduced the total
                    amount of reparations demanded of Germany to 121 billion gold marks, almost $29
                    billion, payable over 58 years. Another loan would be floated in foreign
                    markets, this one totaling $300 million. Foreign supervision of German finances
                    would cease and the last of the occupying troops would leave German soil. The
                    Young Plan also called for the establishment of a Bank for International
                    Settlements, designed to facilitate the payment of reparations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="young-committee.jpg" height="450px" width="349px"/>
                    <head>Reparations Committee confers with Secretary of State Henry L. Stimson.
                        Committee chairman Owen D. Young sits to Stimson’s left. (Harris &amp;
                        Ewing; Prints and Photographs Division, Library of Congress)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The advent of the Great Depression doomed the Young Plan from the start. Loans
                    from U.S. banks had helped prop up the German economy until 1928; when these
                    loans dried up, Germany’s economy floundered. In 1931, as the world sunk ever
                    deeper into depression, a one-year moratorium on all debt and reparation
                    payments was declared at the behest of President Herbert Hoover; an effort to
                    renew the moratorium the following year failed. At the Lausanne Conference in
                    1932, European nations agreed to cancel their reparation claims against Germany,
                    save for a final payment. After the November 1932 election of Franklin D.
                    Roosevelt, France and the United Kingdom resurrected the link between
                    reparations and war debts, tying their Lausanne Conference pledge to cancel
                    their claims against Germany to the cancellation of their debts to the United
                    States. The United States would not accept the proposal. By mid-1933, all
                    European debtor nations except Finland had defaulted on their loans from the
                    United States.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, the Dawes and Young Plans were important U.S. efforts that had
                    lasting consequences. Coming so soon after the U.S. rejection of the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/paris-peace">Treaty
                    of Versailles</ref> and the <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">League of Nations</ref>, the Dawes and Young Plans were
                    significant instances of U.S. reengagement with European affairs. The Young Plan
                    also had a more lasting effect: the Bank for International Settlements, or BIS,
                    continues to operate to this day as a forum for central bank consultation and
                    cooperation. The United States’ experience with inter-allied war debts continued
                    to influence its foreign policy for years to come; this influence is evident in
                    the Johnson Act in 1934, the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/neutrality-acts">Neutrality Acts</ref> of the 1930s, and the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/lend-lease">Lend-Lease</ref>
                    program in the Second World War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="geneva">
                <head>The Geneva Naval Conference, <date when="1927">1927</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Geneva Naval Conference of 1927 was a gathering of the United States, Great
                    Britain and Japan, to discuss making joint limitations to their naval
                    capacities. The conference was a failure because the parties did not reach an
                    agreement and the naval arms race continued unabated after the conference.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="coolidge-calvin.jpg" height="293px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>President Calvin Coolidge</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Initial Arms Limits</hi>
                </p>
                <p>After World War I, many nations became concerned about the threat of another war
                    and the possibility of an arms race. To address these issues in the naval arena,
                    in 1922, Great Britain, the United States, Japan, France, and Italy signed the
                    Five Powers Treaty at the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference"
                        >Washington Conference</ref>. In the treaty, the powers agreed to a
                    5:5:3:1.75:1.75 ratio of naval tonnage and restrictions with regard to new
                    building of both ships and bases. This meant that while the United States and
                    Great Britain remained on par with each other in the size of their navies, Japan
                    was held to a navy 60 percent as large. France and Italy were restricted to
                    navies 35 percent the size of the British and American forces. In 1927, U.S.
                    President <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName> invited these powers to meet
                    again to discuss extending the agreement to include other classes of vessels not
                    included in the original treaty, such as cruisers, destroyers, and submarines.
                    France and Italy declined the invitation to participate in the conference. The
                    League of Nations was already engaged in preparing a more comprehensive
                    disarmament conference (which took place in Geneva in 1932), and the two powers
                    preferred to wait until that event to discuss air, land, and sea armaments all
                    at once.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Geneva Conference</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The other three powers met in Geneva and began negotiations on the extension of
                    naval limitations. The United States proposed that the existing 5:5:3 ratios
                    between the three powers be extended to include auxiliary vessels; that the
                    maximum size of cruisers remain at less than 10,000 tons with 8-inch guns; and
                    that the total tonnage of cruisers be limited to 400,000 for the United States
                    and Great Britain (240,000 tons for Japan). The latter measure was designed to
                    prevent the United States from having to embark on a massive building program to
                    keep its fleet in line with the ratios established at the conference; as it was,
                    to reach 400,000 tons it would have to build several new ships. Great Britain
                    proposed dividing the classes of cruisers into “heavy” and “light,” so that
                    heavy cruisers did not exceed 10,000 tons, but light cruisers did not exceed
                    7,000. As the British had a far greater need for light cruisers, it proposed
                    limiting production of heavy cruisers, while including more freedom for building
                    those in the lighter class. They also proposed an overall cruiser limit of 70
                    ships and 600,000 tons. This plan would have required the United States to build
                    as many as thirty new heavy cruisers just to maintain parity between the two
                    nations, thus sparking an arms race instead of disarmament. Japan proved to be
                    the most flexible party with regard to the cruiser limitations, but preferred
                    that a 10:10:7 ratio be applied to auxiliary craft, rather than the Washington
                    Conference ratio of 5:5:3.</p>
                <p>The differences between the parties emerged in several areas. First, there was a
                    dispute about whether “parity” should be measured based on tonnage or number of
                    vessels. The United States preferred tonnage, while the British preferred to
                    count the fleet. To keep overall tonnage below the established limits, the
                    British preferred to build light cruisers, but because light cruisers were
                    essentially useless in battle against heavy cruisers, they wanted the United
                    States and Japan to build the lighter variety as well. The United States had
                    virtually no use for light cruisers and felt that as long as they stayed below
                    the tonnage limit, they should be able to build as many heavy cruisers as they
                    liked. It was a fundamental impasse. Second, Great Britain set forth what it
                    called the “doctrine of requirements,” which asserted that the size of a
                    nation’s naval fleet should be based on what it required to defend its
                    territory; this idea was in opposition to the American preference that the size
                    of the fleet required should be proportional to the size of the navies of other
                    nations in the world. Accepting the “doctrine of requirements” would mean
                    agreeing to the British demand for a large number of cruisers and then
                    undertaking a massive American building program to achieve parity, so neither
                    the United States nor Japan approved of it. Although the three countries made
                    some progress in their discussions over other classes of auxiliary ships, the
                    powers were agreed that there would only be a new treaty if the “cruiser
                    controversy” was solved. As a result, the stalemate over the cruiser question
                    ended the conference without a new treaty.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Failure to Form a Treaty</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The failure of the conference can be attributed to the inability of the
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> and <placeName>Great
                        Britain</placeName> to come to terms on these issues; one side or both
                    needed to make substantial compromises to solve the problem. Far from allowing
                    the “friendship” of their shared heritage to bring cooperation, it seemed that
                    few at the conference on either side had definitively ruled out the possibility
                    of the two nations engaging on opposite sides of a future conflict, so each
                    hoped to maintain as much of an edge as possible in naval capacity. In the wake
                    of the failed talks at Geneva, the United States passed a bill to build fifteen
                    new cruisers and an aircraft carrier, and thereby joined the naval arms race.
                    This led <placeName>Japan</placeName> and <placeName>Britain</placeName> to
                    consider their own building programs, making the result of the conference a
                    potential new arms race, rather than limitation. The United States and Great
                    Britain realized that without an agreement, the cruiser issue would block
                    advancements at any future conferences, so they continued discussions in the
                    years that followed. In 1929, the two sides agreed on a limit of 50 cruisers and
                    339,000 tons, with a limit to the maximum number of heavy cruisers. Both sides
                    compromised heavily to reach this deal, but the issue of how many heavy cruisers
                    would be permitted was not yet settled. The countries addressed the issue once
                    again at the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/london-naval-conf">London Naval
                        Conference in 1930</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="kellogg">
                <head>The Kellogg-Briand Pact, <date when="1928">1928</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Kellogg-Briand Pact was an agreement to outlaw war signed on <date
                        when="1928-09-27">August 27, 1928</date>. Sometimes called the Pact of Paris
                    for the city in which it was signed, the pact was one of many international
                    efforts to prevent another World War, but it had little effect in stopping the
                    rising militarism of the 1930s or preventing World War II.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="kellogg-briand.jpg" height="201px" width="400px"/>
                    <head>Photograph with representatives who signed the Kellogg-Briand Pact in the
                        White House</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S. Peace Advocates</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the wake of World War I, U.S. officials and private citizens made significant
                    efforts to guarantee that the nation would not be drawn into another war. Some
                    focused on disarmament, such as the series of naval conferences that began in
                    Washington in 1921, and some focused on cooperation with the League of Nations
                    and the newly formed World Court. Others initiated a movement to try to outlaw
                    war outright. Peace advocates <persName>Nicholas Murray Butler</persName> and
                        <persName>James T. Shotwell</persName> were part of this movement. Both men
                    were affiliated with the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, an
                    organization dedicated to promoting internationalism that was established in
                    1910 by leading American industrialist <persName>Andrew Carnegie</persName>.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">French Involvement</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With the influence and assistance of Shotwell and Butler, French Minister of
                    Foreign Affairs <persName>Aristide Briand</persName> proposed a peace pact as a
                    bilateral agreement between the United States and France to outlaw war between
                    them. Particularly hard hit by World War I, <placeName>France</placeName> faced
                    continuing insecurity from its German neighbor and sought alliances to shore up
                    its defenses. Briand published an open letter in April of 1927 containing the
                    proposal. Though the suggestion had the enthusiastic support of some members of
                    the American peace movement, U.S. President <persName>Calvin Coolidge</persName>
                    and Secretary of State <persName>Frank B. Kellogg</persName> were less eager
                    than Briand to enter into a bilateral arrangement. They worried that the
                    agreement against war could be interpreted as a bilateral alliance and require
                    the United States to intervene if France was ever threatened. To avoid this,
                    they suggested that the two nations take the lead in inviting all nations to
                    join them in outlawing war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="kellogg.jpg" height="140px" width="120px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Frank B. Kellogg</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The extension of the pact to include other nations was well-received
                    internationally. After the severe losses of the First World War, the idea of
                    declaring war to be illegal was immensely popular in international public
                    opinion. Because the language of the pact established the important point that
                    only wars of aggression – not military acts of self-defense – would be covered
                    under the pact, many nations had no objections to signing it. If the pact served
                    to limit conflicts, then everyone would benefit; if it did not, there were no
                    legal consequences. In early 1928, negotiations over the agreement expanded to
                    include all of the initial signatories. In the final version of the pact, they
                    agreed upon two clauses: the first outlawed war as an instrument of national
                    policy and the second called upon signatories to settle their disputes by
                    peaceful means.</p>
                <p>On August 27, 1928, fifteen nations signed the pact at Paris. Signatories
                    included France, the United States, the United Kingdom, Ireland, Canada,
                    Australia, New Zealand, South Africa, India, Belgium, Poland, Czechoslovakia,
                    Germany, Italy and Japan. Later, an additional forty-seven nations followed
                    suit, so the pact was eventually signed by most of the established nations in
                    the world. The U.S. Senate ratified the agreement by a vote of 85–1, though it
                    did so only after making reservations to note that U.S. participation did not
                    limit its right to self-defense or require it to act against signatories
                    breaking the agreement.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Mukden Incident</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The first major test of the pact came just a few years later in 1931, when the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/mukden-incident">Mukden Incident</ref>
                    led to the Japanese invasion of <placeName>Manchuria</placeName>. Though Japan
                    had signed the pact, the combination of the worldwide depression and a limited
                    desire to go to war to preserve China prevented the League of Nations or the
                    United States from taking any action to enforce it. Further threats to the Peace
                    Agreement also came from fellow signatories Germany, Austria and Italy. It soon
                    became clear that there was no way to enforce the pact or sanction those who
                    broke it; it also never fully defined what constituted “self-defense,” so there
                    were many ways around its terms. In the end, the Kellogg-Briand Pact did little
                    to prevent World War II or any of the conflicts that followed. Its legacy
                    remains as a statement of the idealism expressed by advocates for peace in the
                    interwar period. <persName>Frank Kellogg</persName> earned the Nobel Peace Prize
                    in 1929 for his work on the Peace Pact.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="red-line">
                <head>The <date when="1928">1928</date> Red Line Agreement</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The 1928 Group Agreement (better known as the “Red Line” Agreement) was a deal
                    struck between several American, British, and French oil companies concerning
                    the oil resources within territories that formerly comprised the Ottoman Empire
                    within the Middle East. The origins of the Red Line Agreement can be traced back
                    to the initial formation of the Turkish Petroleum Company (TPC) in <date
                        when="1912">1912</date>.</p>
                <p>The TPC was formed as a joint venture between Royal Dutch/Shell, the Deutsche
                    Bank, and the Turkish National Bank, in order to promote oil exploration and
                    production within the Ottoman Empire. In March 1914, however, the British
                    Government, which controlled the Turkish National Bank, managed to have its
                    shares within the TPC transferred to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. The
                    following June, the Ottoman Grand Vizier promised an oil concession to the
                    reconstituted TPC to develop oil fields within the Ottoman provinces of Baghdad
                    and Mosul.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Seven Sisters</hi>
                </p>
                <p>During World War I, the Allies expropriated Deutsche Bank’s share in the TPC and
                    transferred them to the French Government during the San Remo Conference of
                    1920. At the time, Royal Dutch/Shell hoped that it could purchase the French
                    Government’s shares so as to balance out Anglo-Persian’s 50% stake within the
                    TPC. Prime Minister Raymond Poincaré of France, however, brushed aside any such
                    suggestions, since he was determined to create an independent French oil company
                    that could compete with major British and American oil companies, which became
                    known collectively as the seven sisters. The seven sisters were the Standard Oil
                    Company of New Jersey (later Exxon), the Standard Oil Company of New York
                    (Socony, later Mobil, which eventually merged with Exxon), the Standard Oil
                    Company of California (Socal, later renamed Chevron), the Texas Oil Company
                    (later renamed Texaco), Gulf Oil (which later merged with Chevron),
                    Anglo-Persian (later British Petroleum), and Royal Dutch/Shell.</p>
                <p>The San Remo Oil Agreement excluded American oil companies from participation in
                    the TPC. This fact provoked strong protests from both American oil companies,
                    who feared that the Europeans would deny them access to foreign oil sources and
                    dump cheap Middle Eastern oil on the world market, and the U.S. Department of
                    State, which opposed any attempts by foreign governments and businesses to
                    discriminate against American firms in their search for new markets and business
                    opportunities. In order to discourage the Europeans from treating American oil
                    companies unfairly, the U.S. Congress passed the Mineral Leasing Act in February
                    of 1920, which denied drilling rights on publicly-owned land in the United
                    States to any foreign company whose parent government discriminated against
                    American businesses. Neither the British nor the U.S. Government, however,
                    wished to jeopardize relations over the issue. In 1928, the TPC was reorganized
                    to include the Near East Development Corporation, an American oil syndicate that
                    included Jersey Standard, Socony, Gulf Oil, the Pan-American Petroleum and
                    Transport Company, and Atlantic Refining (later Arco). Jersey Standard and
                    Socony later assumed total control over the NEDC after they bought out their
                    partners during the 1930s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Signing the Red Line Agreement</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On July 31, 1928, following the discovery of an immense oil field in Iraq and TPC
                    negotiating regarding the division of crude oil output between the partners,
                    representatives from the Anglo-Persian, Royal Dutch/Shell, the Compagnie
                    Française des Pétroles (CFP, later Total), and the Near East Development
                    Corporation signed the Red Line Agreement in Ostend, Belgium. Under the terms of
                    the agreement, each of the four parties received a 23.75% share of all the crude
                    oil produced by TPC, which was allowed to operate anywhere in the Middle East
                    between the Suez Canal and Iran, with the exception of Kuwait. The remaining 5%
                    share went to Calouste Gulbenkian, an Armenian businessman who was a partial
                    stakeholder within the TPC. The most important feature of the Red Line
                    Agreement, however, was its ‘self-denying’ clause. It stipulated that the
                    participating companies would agree not to develop oilfields within the
                    territory comprising the TPC unless they secured the support of the other
                    members.</p>
                <p>The deal became known as the Red Line agreement because, supposedly, during the
                    negotiations between TPC members, none of the participants was exactly certain
                    of the pre-war boundaries of the Ottoman Empire. Consequently, during one of the
                    final meetings, Gulbenkian drew the boundaries from memory on a map of the
                    Middle East with a red pencil. In fact, the question had been resolved well
                    before, during negotiations between the British and French foreign ministries.
                    Nevertheless, the name stuck.</p>
                <p>The Red Line Agreement proved to be a difficult arrangement, since it could not
                    keep non-member companies from seeking concessions within the area covered by
                    the TPC (which was renamed the Iraqi Petroleum Company in 1929). In 1928, Socal
                    secured a concession to search for oil in Bahrain and, in 1933, they managed to
                    gain another concession from the Saudi Government that encompassed the province
                    of al-Hasa. In 1936, the Texas Oil Company purchased a 50% share within the
                    California Arabian Standard Oil Company (the Saudi subsidiary of Socal, which
                    was renamed Aramco in 1944) in order to further develop Socal’s concession
                    within Saudi Arabia.</p>
                <p>In 1946, Socal and Texaco invited Jersey Standard and Socony to join them as
                    partners in Aramco, but the latter two were barred from doing so under the terms
                    of the Red Line Agreement unless they invited the other members of the TPC to
                    join them. Consequently, Jersey Standard and Socony joined the U.S. Government
                    in pressuring the other members of the IPC to abrogate the terms of the Red Line
                    Agreement. Although the French Government and Gulbenkian protested, both had
                    withdrawn their objections by November 1948, in exchange for a greater share of
                    the output of the IPC, whose boundaries were now redrawn to exclude Saudi
                    Arabia, Yemen, Bahrain, Egypt, Israel, and the western-half of Jordan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="great-depression">
                <head>The Great Depression and U.S. Foreign Policy</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Great Depression of the 1930s was a global event that derived in part from
                    events in the United States and U.S. financial policies. As it lingered through
                    the decade, it influenced U.S. foreign policies in such a way that the United
                    States Government became even more isolationist.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="depression-img.jpg" height="234px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>Dorothea Lange’s Migrant Mother</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The origins of the Great Depression were complicated and have been much debated
                    among scholars. The initial factor was the First World War, which upset
                    international balances of power and caused a dramatic shock to the global
                    financial system. The gold standard, which had long served as the basis for
                    national currencies and their exchange rates, had to be temporarily suspended in
                    order to recover from the costs of the Great War, but the United States,
                    European nations, and Japan put forth great effort to reestablish it by the end
                    of the decade. However, this introduced inflexibility into domestic and
                    international financial markets, which meant that they were less able to deal
                    with additional shocks when they came in the late 1920s and early 1930s. The
                    U.S. stock market crash of 1929, an economic downturn in Germany, and financial
                    difficulties in France and Great Britain all coincided to cause a global
                    financial crisis. Dedication to the gold standard in each of these nations and
                    Japan, which only managed to return to it in 1930, only made the problem worse
                    and hastened the slide into what is now known as the Great Depression.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The International Depression</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The key factor in turning national economic difficulties into worldwide
                    Depression seems to have been a lack of international coordination as most
                    governments and financial institutions turned inwards. Great Britain, which had
                    long underwritten the global financial system and had led the return to the gold
                    standard, was unable to play its former role and became the first to drop off
                    the standard in 1931. The United States, preoccupied with its own economic
                    difficulties, did not step in to replace Great Britain as the creditor of last
                    resort and dropped off the gold standard in 1933. At the London Economic
                    Conference in 1933, leaders of the world’s main economies met to resolve the
                    economic crisis, but failed to reach any major collective agreements. As a
                    result, the Depression dragged on through the rest of the 1930s.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Isolationism</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Depression caused the United States to retreat further into its <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/american-isolationism">post-World War I
                        isolationism</ref>. A series of international incidents occurred during the
                    1930s—the Japanese seizure of northeast China in 1931, the Italian invasion of
                    Ethiopia in 1935, and German expansionism in Central and Eastern Europe—but the
                    United States did not take any major action in response or opposition. When
                    these and other incidents occurred, the United States Government issued
                    statements of disapproval but took limited action beyond that. On a more
                    positive note, isolationism manifested in Latin America in the form of the Good
                    Neighbor Policy of Presidents <persName>Herbert Hoover</persName> and
                        <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName>, under which the United States
                    reduced its military presence in the region and improved relations between
                    itself and its neighbors to the south. Presidents Hoover and Roosevelt were to
                    an extent constrained by public opinion, which demanded that primary attention
                    be given to domestic problems. The Hoover and Roosevelt Administrations
                    concentrated upon rebuilding the U.S. economy and dealing with widespread
                    unemployment and social dislocation at home and as a result international
                    affairs took a back seat.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hoover-herbert.jpg" height="286px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>President Herbert Hoover</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Rise of Fascism</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As the United States turned inwards to deal with the lingering effects of the
                    Depression, militaristic regimes came to power in Germany, Italy, and Japan
                    promising economic relief and national expansion. While they achieved some
                    measure of success on the economic front, these regimes began to push their
                    territorial ambitions and received minimal opposition from the rest of the
                    world. The lack of a strong U.S. response to <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/pearl-harbor">Japan’s invasion of China in
                        1937</ref> and Germany’s annexation of Czechoslovakia in 1938 encouraged the
                    Japanese and German governments to enlarge their military campaigns. At the
                    time, most U.S. leaders believed their decision to avoid a more active role was
                    justified because of the domestic context, but some began to realize that U.S.
                    inaction allowed the conflict to grow. After the fall of France in June 1940,
                    the United States increasingly committed itself to the fight against fascism.
                    Ironically, it was World War II, which had arisen in part out of the Great
                    Depression, that finally pulled the United States out of its decade-long
                    economic crisis.</p>
                <p>The Great Depression caused the United States Government to pull back from major
                    international involvement during the 1930s, but in the long run it contributed
                    to the emergence of the United States as a world leader thereafter. The
                    perception that the turn inwards had in some part contributed to perpetuating
                    the horrors of World War II caused U.S. foreign policy makers to play a major
                    role in world affairs after the war in order to avert similar disasters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="protectionism">
                <head>Protectionism in the Interwar Period</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the decade after the end of the First World War, the United States continued
                    to embrace the high tariffs that had characterized its trade policy since the
                    Civil War. These were enacted, in part, to appease domestic constituencies, but
                    ultimately they served to hinder international economic cooperation and trade in
                    the late 1920s and early 1930s.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="underwood.jpg" height="245px" width="180px"/>
                    <head>Congressman Oscar W. Underwood</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S. Tarrifs Through the 1920s</hi>
                </p>
                <p>High tariffs were a means not only of protecting infant industries, but of
                    generating revenue for the federal government. They were also a mainstay of the
                    Republican Party, which dominated the Washington political scene after the Civil
                    War. After the Democrats, who supported freer trade, captured Congress and the
                    White House in the elections of 1910 and 1912, the stage was set for a change in
                    tariff policy. With the 1913 Underwood-Simmons Tariff, the United States broke
                    with its tradition of protectionism, enacting legislation that lowered tariffs
                    (and also instituted an income tax). The reversion of Congress to Republican
                    control during the First World War and the 1920 election of Republican
                        <persName>Warren Harding</persName> to the presidency signaled an end to the
                    experiment with lower tariffs. To provide protection for American farmers, whose
                    wartime markets in Europe were disappearing with the recovery of European
                    agricultural production, as well as U.S. industries that had been stimulated by
                    the war, Congress passed the temporary Emergency Tariff Act in 1921, followed a
                    year later by the Fordney-McCumber Tariff Act of 1922. The Fordney-McCumber
                    Tariff Act raised tariffs above the level set in 1913; it also authorized the
                    president to raise or lower a given tariff rate by 50% in order to even out
                    foreign and domestic production costs. One unintended consequence of the
                    Fordney-McCumber tariff was that it made it more difficult for European nations
                    to export to the United States and so earn dollars to service their war
                    debts.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fordney.jpg" height="301px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Congressman Joseph W. Fordney</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Despite the Fordney-McCumber tariff, the plight of the American farmer continued.
                    The wartime expansion of non-European agricultural production had led, with the
                    recovery of European producers, to overproduction during the 1920s. This in turn
                    had led to declining farm prices during the second half of the decade. During
                    the 1928 election campaign, Republican presidential candidate Herbert Hoover
                    pledged to help the beleaguered farmer by, among other things, raising tariff
                    levels on agricultural products. But once the tariff schedule revision process
                    got started, it proved impossible to stop. Calls for increased protection
                    flooded in from industrial sector special interest groups and soon a bill meant
                    to provide relief for farmers became a means to raise tariffs in all sectors of
                    the economy. When the dust had settled, Congress had produced a piece of
                    legislation, the Tariff Act of 1930, more commonly known as the Smoot-Hawley
                    tariff, that entrenched the protectionism of the Fordney-McCumber tariff.</p>
                <p>Scholars disagree over the extent of protection actually afforded by the
                    Smoot-Hawley tariff; they also differ over the issue of whether the tariff
                    provoked a wave of foreign retaliation that plunged the world deeper into the
                    Great Depression. What is certain, however, is that Smoot-Hawley did nothing to
                    foster cooperation among nations in either the economic or political realm
                    during a perilous era in international relations. It quickly became a symbol of
                    the “beggar-thy-neighbor” policies of the 1930s. Such policies, which were
                    adopted by many countries during this time, contributed to a drastic contraction
                    of international trade. For example, U.S. imports from Europe declined from a
                    1929 high of $1,334 million to just $390 million in 1932, while U.S. exports to
                    Europe fell from $2,341 million in 1929 to $784 million in 1932. Overall, world
                    trade declined by some 66% between 1929 and 1934.</p>
                <p>Smoot-Hawley marked the end of the line for high tariffs in 20th century American
                    trade policy. Thereafter, beginning with the 1934 Reciprocal Trade Agreements
                    Act, the United States generally sought trade liberalization through bilateral
                    or multilateral tariff reductions. To this day, the phrase “Smoot-Hawley”
                    remains a watchword for the perils of protectionism.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="london-naval-conf">
                <head>The London Naval Conference, <date when="1930">1930</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The London Naval Conference of 1930 was the third in a series of five meetings,
                    formed with the purpose of placing limits on the naval capacity of the world’s
                    largest naval powers. The purpose of the meetings was to promote disarmament in
                    the wake of the devastation of the First World War; they began with the
                    Washington Conference of 1921–22 and concluded with the London Conference of
                    1935. After an unsuccessful meeting in Geneva in 1927, Great Britain, the United
                    States, Japan, France, and Italy gathered in London in 1930 to make a new
                    attempt at revising and extending the terms of the Five Power Treaty of
                    1922.</p>
                <p>In 1927, Great Britain and the United States could not agree on naval cruiser
                    limits; however, representatives of the two governments continued to work on a
                    compromise measure. By 1930 both sides were anxious to reach a deal to avoid an
                    all out arms race and, importantly, forced their naval officers to take a back
                    seat to their diplomats in the negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Tonnage Restrictions</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The restrictions on tonnage on Great Britain, the United States, and Japan
                    relative to one another were an important issue for discussion. The Washington
                    conference established a ratio of 5:5:3 for capital ships—for every five capital
                    ships the Americans and British had, the Japanese were allowed to have three. As
                    in 1927, Japan insisted that the ratio for auxiliary vessels be increased to
                    10:10:7, rather than maintaining the 5:5:3 ratio. If the United States was to
                    have 18 heavy cruisers, the latter ratio placed the Japanese limit at 10
                    cruisers; however, at the time of the conference, Japan had built or was
                    building 12 new ships. The United States was the power most opposed to granting
                    the higher ratio, although it ultimately conceded the point; the official terms
                    of the treaty granted the 10:7 ratio on light cruisers and destroyers and
                    maintained the 10:6 ratio on heavy cruisers, but with a compromise under which
                    the United States delayed its shipbuilding program to give Japan a grace period
                    with a 10:7 ratio in heavy cruisers as well.</p>
                <p>The other key issue of the 1930 conference was the maximum tonnage for light
                    cruisers. The United States was adamantly opposed to any maximum lower than
                    10,000 tons, because given the nature of its international commitments—in
                    particular, its involvement in the Philippines and East Asia and the limited
                    number of refueling stations available in the Pacific—lighter cruisers would not
                    be of much use. Although it compromised on the Japanese ratio and the heavy
                    cruisers, the United States refused to yield on this issue, in spite of the fact
                    that the other powers were far more willing to accept the British maximum of
                    7,000 tons. In the end, the U.S. position prevailed.</p>
                <p>The final treaty limited tonnage of auxiliary ships, as well as the size and gun
                    power of submarines and destroyers. In all but “offensive” ship categories, it
                    granted the Japanese their long-sought 10:10:7 ratio. The treaty also set
                    maximum tonnage for cruisers at 339,000 tons for Great Britain, 323,500 tons for
                    the United States, and 208,850 tons for Japan. The maximum numbers of heavy
                    cruisers were set at 18 for America, 15 for Great Britain, and 12 for Japan. The
                    Treaty upheld and extended the provision in the 1922 treaty that prohibited the
                    powers from building new capital ships for 5 years. The provisions in both the
                    Five-Power Treaty of 1922 and the 1930 treaty were set to expire in 1936.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">U.S. Shipbuilding After the Conference</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Although it was described as an “arms limitation conference,” in actuality, the
                    London Naval Treaty set limits above the current capacity of some of the powers
                    involved. The U.S. Senate approved the treaty in July of 1930 over the
                    objections of key naval officers concerned that the naval limitations would
                    inhibit the American ability to defend its control of the Philippine islands.
                    Then the United States actually embarked on a shipbuilding program to make up
                    the difference between its existing cruiser tonnage and what it was allotted
                    under the treaty. That building ultimately helped to alleviate some unemployment
                    caused by the Great Depression.</p>
                <p>In 1935, the powers met for a second London Naval Conference to renegotiate the
                    Washington and London treaties before their expiration the following year. The
                    Japanese walked out of that conference, but Great Britain, France, and the
                    United States signed an agreement declaring a six-year holiday on building large
                    light cruisers in the 8,000 to 10,000 ton range. That final decision marked the
                    end to the decade-long controversy over cruisers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="mukden-incident">
                <head>The Mukden Incident of <date when="1931">1931</date> and the Stimson
                    Doctrine</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In 1931, a dispute near the Chinese city of Mukden (Shenyang) precipitated events
                    that led to the Japanese conquest of Manchuria. In response, U.S. Secretary of
                    State <persName>Henry Stimson</persName> issued what would become known as the
                    Stimson Doctrine, stating that the United States would not recognize any
                    agreements between the Japanese and Chinese that limited free commercial
                    intercourse in the region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="stimson-henry.jpg" height="319px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Henry Stimson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the 1920s and 1930s, the United States had a number of interests in the Far
                    East. The United States engaged in trade and investment in China. American
                    missionaries representing many denominations worked within the region. The
                    United States also claimed Pacific territories, including the Philippines, Guam,
                    and Hawaii. The United States defended its interests in the region through a
                    three-pronged Far Eastern policy: it included the principle of the Open Door for
                    guaranteeing equal access to commercial opportunities in China, a belief in the
                    importance of maintaining the territorial integrity of China, and a commitment
                    to cooperation with other powers with interests in the region.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Japanese Invasion of China</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the 1930s, events transpired that challenged all of these policies. On
                    September 18, 1931, an explosion destroyed a section of railway track near the
                    city of Mukden. The Japanese, who owned the railway, blamed Chinese nationalists
                    for the incident and used the opportunity to retaliate and invade Manchuria.
                    However, others speculated that the bomb may have been planted by mid-level
                    officers in the Japanese Army to provide a pretext for the subsequent military
                    action. Within a few short months, the Japanese Army had overrun the region,
                    having encountered next to no resistance from an untrained Chinese Army, and it
                    went about consolidating its control on the resource-rich area. The Japanese
                    declared the area to be the new autonomous state of Manchukuo, though the new
                    nation was in fact under the control of the local Japanese Army.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="mukden.jpg" height="200px" width="250px"/>
                    <head>Japanese Soldiers during the Mukden Incident</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States and other western powers were at a loss on how to respond to
                    the rapidly developing crisis. Even as the Japanese moved far from the original
                    site of the “attack” at Mukden to bomb the city of Jinzhou (Chinchow), there was
                    little sense that U.S. interests in the area were anywhere near profound enough
                    to make military intervention necessary or desirable. Given the 1930s worldwide
                    depression, there was little support for economic sanctions to punish the
                    Japanese. Instead, the United States sat in on League of Nations council
                    meetings for the first time to try to convince the League to enforce the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/kellogg">Kellogg-Briand Pact</ref>, which both
                    Japan and China had signed. Appeals based on the pact, however, proved
                    ineffective.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Stimson Doctrine</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Therefore Secretary Stimson issued the Stimson Doctrine in early 1932. This
                    Doctrine stated that the United States would not recognize any treaty or
                    agreement between Japan and China that violated U.S. rights or agreements to
                    which the United States subscribed.</p>
                <p>This doctrine of non-recognition proved incredibly ineffectual in the face of
                    on-going Japanese aggression and expansion. Japan had been expanding its
                    influence in Manchuria for years, and now it formally controlled the territory.
                    Moreover, after its successful conquest of Manchuria, the Japanese attacked the
                    city of Shanghai in 1932. As Shanghai was home to the largest international
                    settlements in China, the sudden invasion threatened foreign concessions as
                    well. Stimson responded to this development by declaring that as a result of
                    Japanese violation of the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/naval-conference"
                        >Nine Power Treaty</ref>, the United States would no longer consider itself
                    bound by the naval limitations agreements. This meant a potential new naval arms
                    race in the Pacific that would inevitably draw in the Japanese, but it did not
                    change the situation in Manchuria.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Lytton Report</hi>
                </p>
                <p>While the United States sought its own solution, it also sent an unofficial
                    delegate along with the League of Nations group investigating the incident. The
                    resulting report, written by the Lytton Commission, divided blame for the
                    conflict in Manchuria equally between Chinese nationalism and Japanese
                    militarism. Still, the report stated that it would not recognize the new state
                    of Manchukuo on the grounds that its establishment violated the territorial
                    integrity of China, and therefore the Nine-Power Treaty to which many of the
                    prominent league members subscribed. When the Lytton Report was ratified by the
                    League in 1933, the Japanese delegation walked out and never returned to the
                    League Council. The Chinese and Japanese signed a truce, but that agreement left
                    the Japanese firmly in control of Manchuria.</p>
                <p>The Manchurian Crisis of 1931–33 demonstrated the futility of the 1920s-era
                    agreements on peace, nonaggression and disarmament in the face of a power
                    determined to march forward. Responses like the Stimson Doctrine of
                    non-recognition similarly had little effect. In the years following the crisis,
                    changing alliances, economic necessities and altered policies would result in an
                    all-out Sino-Japanese War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="good-neighbor">
                <head>Good Neighbor Policy, <date when="1933">1933</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName>Franklin Delano Roosevelt</persName> took office determined
                    to improve relations with the nations of Central and South America. Under his
                    leadership the United States emphasized cooperation and trade rather than
                    military force to maintain stability in the hemisphere. In his inaugural address
                    on March 4, 1933, Roosevelt stated: “In the field of world policy I would
                    dedicate this nation to the policy of the good neighbor—the neighbor who
                    resolutely respects himself and, because he does so, respects the rights of
                    others.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fdr.jpg" height="265px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>President Franklin D. Roosevelt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Roosevelt’s Secretary of State, <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/hull-cordell">Cordell Hull</ref>,
                    participated in the Montevideo Conference of December 1933, where he backed a
                    declaration favored by most nations of the Western Hemisphere: “No state has the
                    right to intervene in the internal or external affairs of another”. In December
                    Roosevelt stated, “The definite policy of the United States from now on is one
                    opposed to armed intervention.” In 1934 at Roosevelt’s direction the 1903 treaty
                    with Cuba (based on the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/platt">Platt
                        Amendment</ref>) that gave the United States the right to intervene to
                    preserve internal stability or independence was abrogated. Although domestic
                    economic problems and World War II diverted attention from the Western
                    Hemisphere, Roosevelt’s Good Neighbor policy represented an attempt to distance
                    the United States from earlier interventionist policies, such as the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1899-1913/roosevelt-and-monroe-doctrine">Roosevelt
                        Corollary</ref> and military interventions in the region during the 1910s
                    and 1920s. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="ussr">
                <head>Recognition of the Soviet Union, <date when="1933">1933</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On November 16, 1933, President <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName> ended
                    almost 16 years of American non-recognition of the Soviet Union following a
                    series of negotiations in Washington, D.C. with the Soviet Commissar for Foreign
                    Affairs, <persName>Maxim Litvinov</persName>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="litvinov.jpg" height="229px" width="140px"/>
                    <head>Maxim Litvinov</head>
                </figure>
                <p>On December 6, 1917, the U.S. Government broke off diplomatic relations with
                    Russia, shortly after the Bolshevik Party seized power from the Tsarist regime
                    after the “October Revolution.” President Woodrow Wilson decided to withhold
                    recognition at that time because the new Bolshevik government had refused to
                    honor prior debts to the United States incurred by the Tsarist government,
                    ignored pre-existing treaty agreements with other nations, and seized American
                    property in Russia following the October Revolution. The Bolsheviks had also
                    concluded a separate peace with Germany at Brest-Litovsk in March 1918, ending
                    Russian involvement in World War I. Despite extensive commercial links between
                    the United States and the Soviet Union throughout the 1920s, Wilson’s successors
                    upheld his policy of not recognizing the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Roosevelt Pushes for Recognition</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Almost immediately upon taking office, however, President Roosevelt moved to
                    establish formal diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet
                    Union. His reasons for doing so were complex, but the decision was based on
                    several primary factors. Roosevelt hoped that recognition of the Soviet Union
                    would serve U.S. strategic interests by limiting Japanese expansionism in Asia,
                    and he believed that full diplomatic recognition would serve American commercial
                    interests in the Soviet Union, a matter of some concern to an Administration
                    grappling with the effects of the Great Depression. Finally, the United States
                    was the only major power that continued to withhold official diplomatic
                    recognition from the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>President Roosevelt decided to approach the Soviets in October 1933 through two
                    personal intermediaries: <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/morgenthau-henry">Henry Morgenthau</ref>
                    (then head of the Farm Credit Administration and Acting Secretary of the
                    Treasury) and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bullitt-william-christian"
                        >William C. Bullitt</ref> (a former diplomat who, as a Special Assistant to
                    the Secretary of State, was informally serving as one of Roosevelt’s chief
                    foreign policy advisers). The two approached Boris Shvirsky, the Soviet Union’s
                    unofficial representative in Washington, with an unsigned letter from Roosevelt
                    to the Soviet Union’s official head of state, Chairman of the Central Executive
                    Committee, Mikhail Kalinin. The letter intimated that the U.S. Government would
                    be willing to negotiate the terms for recognizing the Soviet Union, and
                    requested that Kalinin dispatch an emissary to Washington. In response,
                    Commissar for Foreign Affairs Litvinov journeyed to Washington in November 1933
                    in order to begin talks.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="henry-morg.jpg" height="250px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>Henry Morgenthau</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Roosevelt-Livitnov Conversations</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Initially, the talks made little headway due to several outstanding issues: the
                    unpaid debt owed by the Soviet Union to the United States, the restriction of
                    religious freedoms and legal rights of U.S. citizens living in the Soviet Union,
                    and Soviet involvement in Communist subversion and propaganda within the United
                    States. Following a series of one-on-one negotiations known as the
                    “Roosevelt-Litvinov Conversations,” however, Litvinov and the President worked
                    out a “gentleman’s agreement” on <date when="1933-11-15">November 15,
                        1933</date>, that overcame the major obstacles blocking recognition.</p>
                <p>According to the terms of the Roosevelt-Litvinov agreements, the Soviets pledged
                    to participate in future talks to settle their outstanding financial debt to the
                    United States. Four days earlier, after another private meeting with Litvinov,
                    Roosevelt also managed to secure guarantees that the Soviet Government would
                    refrain from interfering in American domestic affairs (i.e. aiding the American
                    Communist Party), and would grant certain religious and legal rights for U.S.
                    citizens living in the Soviet Union. Following the conclusion of these
                    agreements, President Roosevelt appointed <persName>William C.
                        Bullitt</persName> as the first U.S. Ambassador to the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Violence in the USSR</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Unfortunately, the cooperative spirit embodied in the Roosevelt-Litvinov
                    agreements proved to be short-lived. Shortly after his arrival in Moscow in
                    December 1933, Bullitt became disillusioned with the Soviets as an agreement on
                    the issue of debt repayment failed to materialize. Moreover, evidence emerged
                    that the Soviet Government had violated its pledge not to interfere in American
                    domestic affairs. Finally, the killing of the Leningrad Communist Party boss,
                    Sergey Kirov, launched the first of the “Great Purges” that led to the death or
                    imprisonment of millions of Soviet citizens as the Stalinist regime liquidated
                    any potential critics of the government. The wide scope and public nature of the
                    purges horrified both American diplomatic personnel stationed in the Soviet
                    Union, and the world at large.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the hope of improving relations, President Roosevelt dispatched businessman
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/davies-joseph-edward">Joseph E.
                        Davies</ref> to Moscow as Bullitt’s replacement in 1936. While Davies
                    managed to reestablish amicable relations with the Soviet leadership, his
                    dismissive attitude concerning the purges alienated other American diplomats.
                    Moreover, Davies faced unprecedented new challenges as a result of the worsening
                    political situation in Europe. U.S.-Soviet relations reached their nadir in
                    August 1939, when the Soviets signed the Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact with Nazi
                    Germany after the British and French rejected Soviet offers to establish a
                    military alliance against Germany. Not until the German invasion of Soviet Union
                    began in June 1941 would the United States and the Soviet Union once again find
                    a way to make common cause on any meaningful issue. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="export-import-bank">
                <head>New Deal Trade Policy: The Export-Import Bank &amp; the Reciprocal Trade
                    Agreements Act, <date when="1934">1934</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>When President <persName>Franklin Delano Roosevelt</persName> took office in
                        <date when="1933-04">March 1933</date>, he immediately focused his attention
                    on the domestic economic situation created by the Great Depression. Believing
                    that recovery would come from measures taken at home rather than abroad, he
                    secured Congressional passage of a series of far-reaching domestic economic
                    reforms that would come to be known as the first New Deal. His doubts about the
                    ability of foreign economic policy to contribute to domestic recovery were
                    reflected in his approach to the London Economic Conference. In <date
                        when="1933-06">June 1933</date>, representatives from 66 countries gathered
                    in London to try to find a way out of the Depression through cooperation in
                    areas such as the reduction of trade barriers and the stabilization of exchange
                    rates. Countries that remained on the gold standard, such as
                        <placeName>France</placeName>, sought to convince countries that had left
                    the gold standard, particularly the <placeName>United Kingdom</placeName> (in
                        <date when="1931-09">September 1931</date>) and the United States (in April
                    1933), to agree to stabilize the par values of their currencies. The chances for
                    success were already slim when, on July 3, Roosevelt rejected such an agreement
                    as “a purely artificial and temporary experiment,” asserting that a “sound
                    internal economic situation” was more important to a country’s prosperity than
                    the external value of its currency. The conference ended less than a month later
                    with little to show for its efforts.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Creation of Export-Import Bank</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In 1934, the Roosevelt Administration undertook two initiatives that signaled a
                    desire to reengage economically with the rest of the world. The first was the
                    creation of the Export-Import Bank. In <date when="1934-02">February
                    1934</date>, Roosevelt established the bank as an institution designed to
                    finance U.S. trade with the newly-recognized Soviet Union. He created a second
                    Export-Import Bank the following month, this one intended to finance trade with
                    Cuba; in July 1934, the second bank’s field of operations was expanded to
                    include all countries save the Soviet Union. In 1935, the two banks were
                    combined and Congress passed legislation granting the newly unified bank more
                    powers and more capital. In the years before the start of the Second World War,
                    while it did extend credits to countries outside the Western Hemisphere such as
                    Italy and China, the Export-Import Bank concentrated its efforts in Latin
                    America, where it proved an important component of the Good Neighbor policy.</p>
                <p>The second major foreign economic policy initiative of 1934 was the
                        <orgName>Reciprocal Trade Agreements Act (RTAA)</orgName>. In March 1934,
                    proclaiming “that a full and permanent domestic recovery depends in part upon a
                    revived and strengthened international trade,” Roosevelt asked Congress for
                    authority to negotiate trade agreements based upon reciprocal tariff reductions
                    with other countries. Signed into law on <date when="1934-06-12">June 12,
                        1934</date>, the RTAA represented a fundamental shift in U.S. trade policy.
                    The Constitution gives Congress the right to regulate foreign commerce and
                    establish tariff rates. Under the RTAA, Congress granted the president the right
                    – on a temporary basis, subject to renewal after three years – to decrease or
                    increase U.S. tariffs by up to 50% of the levels set by the 1930 Smoot-Hawley
                    tariff in exchange for tariff concessions by other countries. Such tariff
                    reductions would be brought into force through executive agreements, rather than
                    treaties requiring Senate approval. U.S. tariff cuts negotiated under the RTAA
                    would also be extended to all third countries to which the United States had
                    accorded most favored nation status.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Reciprocal Trade Agreement Act</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Between 1934 and 1939, the <persName>Roosevelt</persName> Administration
                    concluded trade agreements with 19 countries under the Reciprocal Trade
                    Agreements Act: Belgium, Brazil, Canada, Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba,
                    Czechoslovakia, Ecuador, El Salvador, Finland, France, Guatemala, Haiti,
                    Honduras, the Netherlands, Nicaragua, Sweden, Switzerland, and the United
                    Kingdom. After 1945, the tariff negotiating procedure established under the RTAA
                    program provided the model for that of the General Agreement on Tariffs and
                    Trade (GATT), the agreement signed by 23 countries in 1947 that has provided the
                    framework for multilateral trade liberalization in the post-WWII era.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="neutrality-acts">
                <head>The Neutrality Acts, <date when="1930">1930s</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>In the 1930s, the United States Government enacted a series of laws designed to
                    prevent the United States from being embroiled in a foreign war by clearly
                    stating the terms of U.S. neutrality. Although many Americans had rallied to
                    join President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s crusade to make the world
                    “safe for democracy” in 1917, by the 1930s critics argued that U.S. involvement
                    in the First World War had been driven by bankers and munitions traders with
                    business interests in Europe. These findings fueled a growing <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/american-isolationism">“isolationist”</ref>
                    movement that argued the United States should steer clear of future wars and
                    remain neutral by avoiding financial deals with countries at war.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilson-woodrow.jpg" height="274px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>President Woodrow Wilson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">First Neutrality Act</hi>
                </p>
                <p>By the mid-1930s, events in Europe and Asia indicated that a new world war might
                    soon erupt and the U.S. Congress took action to enforce U.S. neutrality. On
                    August 31, 1935, Congress passed the first Neutrality Act prohibiting the export
                    of “arms, ammunition, and implements of war” from the United States to foreign
                    nations at war and requiring arms manufacturers in the United States to apply
                    for an export license. American citizens traveling in war zones were also
                    advised that they did so at their own risk. President <persName>Franklin D.
                        Roosevelt</persName> originally opposed the legislation, but relented in the
                    face of strong Congressional and public opinion. On February 29, 1936, Congress
                    renewed the Act until May of 1937 and prohibited Americans from extending any
                    loans to belligerent nations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fdr.jpg" height="265px" width="225px"/>
                    <head>President Franklin D. Roosevelt</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Neutrality Act of 1937</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The outbreak of the Spanish Civil War in 1936 and the rising tide of fascism in
                    Europe increased support for extending and expanding the Neutrality Act of 1937.
                    Under this law, U.S.citizens were forbidden from traveling on belligerent ships,
                    and American merchant ships were prevented from transporting arms to
                    belligerents even if those arms were produced outside of the United States. The
                    Act gave the President the authority to bar all belligerent ships from U.S.
                    waters, and to extend the export embargo to any additional “articles or
                    materials.” Finally, civil wars would also fall under the terms of the Act.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="spanishcivilwar.jpg" height="211px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>Photograph from the Spanish Civil War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Neutrality Act of 1937 did contain one important concession to Roosevelt:
                    belligerent nations were allowed, at the discretion of the President, to acquire
                    any items except arms from the United States, so long as they immediately paid
                    for such items and carried them on non-American ships—the so-called
                    “cash-and-carry” provision. Since vital raw materials such as oil were not
                    considered “implements of war,” the “cash-and-carry” clause would be quite
                    valuable to whatever nation could make use of it. Roosevelt had engineered its
                    inclusion as a deliberate way to assist Great Britain and France in any war
                    against the Axis Powers, since he realized that they were the only countries
                    that had both the hard currency and ships to make use of “cash-and-carry.”
                    Unlike the rest of the Act, which was permanent, this provision was set to
                    expire after two years.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Neutrality Act of 1939</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Following Germany’s occupation of Czechoslovakia in March of 1939, Roosevelt
                    suffered a humiliating defeat when Congress rebuffed his attempt to renew
                    “cash-and-carry” and expand it to include arms sales. President Roosevelt
                    persisted and as war spread in Europe, his chances of expanding “cash-and-carry”
                    increased. After a fierce debate in Congress, in November of 1939, a final
                    Neutrality Act passed. This Act lifted the arms embargo and put all trade with
                    belligerent nations under the terms of “cash-and-carry.” The ban on loans
                    remained in effect, and American ships were barred from transporting goods to
                    belligerent ports.</p>
                <p>In October of 1941, after the United States had committed itself to aiding the
                    Allies through <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/lend-lease">Lend-Lease</ref>,
                    Roosevelt gradually sought to repeal certain portions of the Act. On October 17,
                    1941, the House of Representatives revoked section VI, which forbade the arming
                    of U.S. merchant ships, by a wide margin. Following a series of deadly U-boat
                    attacks against U.S. Navy and merchant ships, the Senate passed another bill in
                    November that also repealed legislation banning American ships from entering
                    belligerent ports or “combat zones.”</p>
                <p>Overall, the Neutrality Acts represented a compromise whereby the United States
                    Government accommodated the isolationist sentiment of the American public, but
                    still retained some ability to interact with the world. In the end, the terms of
                    the Neutrality Acts became irrelevant once the United States joined the Allies
                    in the fight against Nazi Germany and Japan in December 1941.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
