<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1937–1945</title>
                <title type="short">1937–1945</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1937" to="1945">1937–1945</date>: Diplomacy and the Road to Another
                    War</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">Introduction</hi>
                </p>
                <p>By the late 1930s, the United States continued its efforts to stay out of the
                    wars in Europe and Asia. As the failure of disarmament, the peace movement, and
                    the doctrine of appeasement became clear, Congress passed a series of neutrality
                    acts designed to prevent the United States from being drawn into the widespread
                    international conflict that the U.S. Government believed to be inevitable.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="pearlhabor.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Aerial View of Pearl Harbor</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1940, U.S. policy slowly began to shift from neutrality to non-belligerency by
                    providing aid to the nations at war with the Axis Powers—Germany, Italy and
                    Japan. In response to the growing emergency, President <persName>Franklin D.
                        Roosevelt</persName> called upon the American people to prepare for war. On
                        <date when="1941-12-07">December 7, 1941</date>, the Japanese attacked the
                    U.S. naval installation at Pearl Harbor, and the United States formally entered
                    the Second World War. Meetings between those powers allied in the war against
                    the Axis powers provided the framework for the postwar world. Two major issues
                    would become of major importance to postwar foreign policy, the prevention of
                    another global conflict and the influence of nuclear weapons on the
                    international balance of power.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="pearl-harbor">
                <head>Japan, China, the United States and the Road to Pearl Harbor, <date
                        from="1937" to="1941">1937–41</date>
                </head>
                <p>Between 1937 and 1941, escalating conflict between <placeName>China</placeName>
                    and <placeName>Japan</placeName> influenced U.S. relations with both nations,
                    and ultimately contributed to pushing the United States toward full-scale war
                    with Japan and <placeName>Germany</placeName>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="marcopolo.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Photograph of the Marco Polo Bridge Incident</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At the outset, U.S. officials viewed developments in China with ambivalence. On
                    the one hand, they opposed <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/mukden-incident"
                        >Japanese incursions into northeast China</ref> and the rise of Japanese
                    militarism in the area, in part because of their sense of a longstanding
                    friendship with China. On the other hand, most U.S. officials believed that it
                    had no vital interests in China worth going to war over with Japan. Moreover,
                    the domestic conflict between Chinese Nationalists and Communists left U.S.
                    policymakers uncertain of success in aiding such an internally divided nation.
                    As a result, few U.S. officials recommended taking a strong stance prior to
                    1937, and so the United States did little to help China for fear of provoking
                    Japan. U.S. likelihood of providing aid to China increased after July 7, 1937,
                    when Chinese and Japanese forces clashed on the Marco Polo Bridge near Beijing,
                    throwing the two nations into a full-scale war. As the United States watched
                    Japanese forces sweep down the coast and then into the capital of Nanjing,
                    popular opinion swung firmly in favor of the Chinese. Tensions with Japan rose
                    when the Japanese Army bombed the U.S.S. Panay as it evacuated American citizens
                    from Nanjing, killing three. The U.S. Government, however, continued to avoid
                    conflict and accepted an apology and indemnity from the Japanese. An uneasy
                    truce held between the two nations into 1940.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fdr-signing-ll.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>FDR signing Lend-Lease</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In 1940 and 1941, President <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> formalized
                    U.S. aid to China. The U.S. Government extended credits to the Chinese
                    Government for the purchase of war supplies, as it slowly began to tighten
                    restrictions on Japan. The United States was the main supplier of the oil,
                    steel, iron, and other commodities needed by the Japanese military as it became
                    bogged down by Chinese resistance but, in January, 1940, Japan abrogated the
                    existing treaty of commerce with the United States. Although this did not lead
                    to an immediate embargo, it meant that the Roosevelt Administration could now
                    restrict the flow of military supplies into Japan and use this as leverage to
                    force Japan to halt its aggression in China.</p>
                <p>After January 1940, the United States combined a strategy of increasing aid to
                    China through larger credits and the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/lend-lease">Lend-Lease program</ref> with a
                    gradual move towards an embargo on the trade of all militarily useful items with
                    Japan. The Japanese Government made several decisions during these two years
                    that exacerbated the situation. Unable or unwilling to control the military,
                    Japan’s political leaders sought greater security by establishing the “Greater
                    East Asia Co-Prosperity Sphere” in August, 1940. In so doing they announced
                    Japan’s intention to drive the Western imperialist nations from Asia. However,
                    this Japanese-led project aimed to enhance Japan’s economic and material wealth
                    so that it would not be dependent upon supplies from the West, and not to
                    “liberate” the long-subject peoples of Asia. In fact, Japan would have to launch
                    a campaign of military conquest and rule, and did not intend to pull out of
                    China. At the same time, several pacts with Western nations only made Japan
                    appear more of a threat to the United States. First, Japan signed the Tripartite
                    Pact with Germany and Italy on September 27, 1940 and thereby linked the
                    conflicts in Europe and Asia. This made China a potential ally in the global
                    fight against fascism. Then in mid-1941, Japan signed a Neutrality Pact with the
                    Soviet Union, making it clear that Japan’s military would be moving into
                    Southeast Asia, where the United States had greater interests. A third agreement
                    with Vichy France enabled Japanese forces to move into Indochina and begin their
                    Southern Advance. The United States responded to this growing threat by
                    temporarily halting negotiations with Japanese diplomats, instituting a full
                    embargo on exports to Japan, freezing Japanese assets in U.S. banks, and sending
                    supplies into China along the Burma Road. Although negotiations restarted after
                    the United States increasingly enforced an embargo against Japan, they made
                    little headway. Diplomats in Washington came close to agreements on a couple of
                    occasions, but pro-Chinese sentiments in the United States made it difficult to
                    reach any resolution that would not involve a Japanese withdrawal from China,
                    and such a condition was unacceptable to Japan’s military leaders.</p>
                <p>Faced with serious shortages as a result of the embargo, unable to retreat, and
                    convinced that the U.S. officials opposed further negotiations, Japan’s leaders
                    came to the conclusion that they had to act swiftly. For their part, U.S.
                    leaders had not given up on a negotiated settlement, and also doubted that Japan
                    had the military strength to attack the U.S. territory. Therefore they were
                    stunned when the unthinkable happened and Japanese planes bombed the U.S. fleet
                    at Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941. The following day, the United States
                    declared war on Japan, and it soon entered into a military alliance with China.
                    When Germany stood by its ally and declared war on the United States, the
                    Roosevelt Administration faced war in both Europe and Asia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="mexican-oil">
                <head>Mexican Expropriation of Foreign Oil, <date when="1938">1938</date>
                </head>
                <p>On March 18, 1938, Mexican President Lázaro Cárdenas signed an order that
                    expropriated the assets of nearly all of the foreign oil companies operating in
                    Mexico. He later created Petróleos Mexicanos (PEMEX), a state-owned firm that
                    held a monopoly over the Mexican oil industry, and barred all foreign oil
                    companies from operating in Mexico. The U.S. Government responded with a policy
                    that backed efforts by American companies to obtain payment for their
                    expropriated properties but supported Mexico’s right to expropriate foreign
                    assets as long as prompt and effective compensation was provided.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cardenas.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Mexican President Lazaro Cardenas</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prior to expropriation in 1938, the oil industry in Mexico had been dominated by
                    the Mexican Eagle Company (a subsidiary of the Royal Dutch/Shell Company), which
                    accounted for over 60% of Mexican oil production, and by American-owned oil
                    firms including Jersey Standard and Standard Oil Company of California (SOCAL –
                    now Chevron), which accounted for approximately 30% of total production.
                    However, in Article 27 of the Constitution of 1917, the Mexican Government
                    asserted ownership of the “subsoil,” including any natural resources discovered
                    below ground. The possibility that the Mexican political leadership might
                    exercise its rights complicated relations with the United States until the
                    Calles-Morrow agreement of 1928, which temporarily alleviated tensions by
                    reaffirming the rights of oil companies in the territories they had worked prior
                    to 1917.</p>
                <p>Despite the political difficulties, Mexico became the world’s second largest
                    producer of oil in the 1920s. Nevertheless, the foreign-owned oil companies were
                    the object of much popular resentment. Since Mexico was an agrarian nation with
                    only a tiny domestic market, these companies exported most of the oil they
                    produced during the 1920s and very little of their profits remained Mexico. The
                    situation was exacerbated during the 1930s, when the Mexican Government’s share
                    of oil revenues declined and domestic oil production dropped due to the Great
                    Depression and a glut in the global oil supply. These developments, combined
                    with the fact that the large oil companies often paid their Mexican workers only
                    half as much as other employees working in the same capacity, ultimately led to
                    massive labor unrest.</p>
                <p>A strike by oil workers in 1937 ultimately led the Mexican Government to act.
                    Initially, President Cárdenas attempted to mediate a settlement by having a
                    government commission draw up a new labor agreement. After the foreign companies
                    defied both the commission and the Mexican Supreme Court, however, Cárdenas
                    promulgated the expropriation decree on March 18, 1938.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cordell-hull.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Cordell Hull</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The expropriation act had international repercussions. The foreign-owned oil
                    companies retaliated by instituting an embargo against Mexican oil. Mexican oil
                    exports decreased by 50% and the Mexican Government’s primary customer for oil
                    became Nazi Germany. Expropriation also led the British to take a very strong
                    stand against Mexico's actions, which prompted the Cárdenas government to sever
                    diplomatic relations.</p>
                <p>The U.S. reaction to Mexican expropriation of oil assets was mixed. On the one
                    hand, it had no objection to expropriation as long as the Mexicans agreed to
                    compensate the oil companies. Furthermore, U.S. President Franklin Roosevelt
                    wanted to maintain good relations with the United States’ immediate neighbor,
                    lest a hostile U.S. response to expropriation drive Mexico to align itself with
                    the Axis Powers. On the other hand, some U.S. officials urged a tough response
                    because they understood that that the United States would eventually become a
                    major importer of oil and because the rights of U.S. economic interests were
                    involved. As such, they believed that it was essential for American oil
                    companies to retain direct access to the oil resources of the Western Hemisphere
                    outside of the United States.</p>
                <p>Secretary of State Cordell Hull initially supported a strong stance against
                    Cárdenas’ actions. Although Cárdenas informed the U.S. Government that he
                    intended to pay compensation, on March 26, Hull dispatched a note to the
                    Mexicans announcing that the U.S. Government would suspend further purchases of
                    silver from Mexico. The U.S. Ambassador in Mexico realized that such action
                    might provoke a diplomatic rupture and asked the Mexicans to consider the note
                    undelivered until a more moderate policy could be formulated in Washington.
                    Further opposition from the Treasury Department eventually forced Hull and the
                    State Department to back down.</p>
                <p>Although Hull’s attempts to directly challenge the Mexican Government fell out of
                    favor, U.S. companies fought the expropriation in their own way. For over two
                    years following expropriation, the oil companies made extravagant demands for
                    compensation, which the Mexicans repeatedly rejected. The U.S. Government
                    supported the oil companies until the Second World War began in Europe, at which
                    point it pressured them to accept a settlement. Finally, on April 18, 1942, the
                    U.S. and Mexican Governments signed the Cooke-Zevada agreement, whereby the
                    Mexicans agreed to pay roughly $29 million in compensation to several American
                    firms, including Jersey Standard and Socal. The British, however, held out until
                    1947, when they received $130 million.</p>
                <p>Efforts to secure the re-admission of the foreign oil companies in Mexico proved
                    to be a failure, however. After Cárdenas left office in 1940, the Mexicans were
                    willing to consider the possibility, but only on condition that Mexico retained
                    ownership of the subsoil, and PEMEX its domestic monopoly. This proved
                    unacceptable to both the U.S. Government and oil companies. Finally, in 1950,
                    the U.S. Government abandoned its efforts to re-open the Mexican oil industry
                    after several failed attempts to use government loans as leverage. By this time,
                    American oil companies had begun losing interest in Mexico and preferred
                    operating under the more favorable conditions found in the Middle East and
                    Venezuela.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="american-isolationism">
                <head>American Isolationism in the <date when="1930">1930s</date>
                </head>
                <p>During the 1930s, the combination of the Great Depression and the memory of
                    tragic losses in World War I contributed to pushing American public opinion and
                    policy toward isolationism. Isolationists advocated non-involvement in European
                    and Asian conflicts and non-entanglement in international politics. Although the
                    United States took measures to avoid political and military conflicts across the
                    oceans, it continued to expand economically and protect its interests in Latin
                    America. The leaders of the isolationist movement drew upon history to bolster
                    their position. In his Farewell Address, President George Washington had
                    advocated non-involvement in European wars and politics. For much of the
                    nineteenth century, the expanse of the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans had made it
                    possible for the United States to enjoy a kind of “free security” and remain
                    largely detached from Old World conflicts. During World War I, however,
                    President <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>
                    <ref target="/milestones/1914-1920/foreword"> made a case for U.S.
                        intervention</ref> in the conflict and a U.S. interest in maintaining a
                    peaceful world order. Nevertheless, the American experience in that war served
                    to bolster the arguments of isolationists; they argued that marginal U.S.
                    interests in that conflict did not justify the number of U.S. casualties.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wilson-woodrow.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Woodrow Wilson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the wake of the World War I, a report by Senator <persName>Gerald P.
                        Nye,</persName> a Republican from North Dakota, fed this belief by claiming
                    that American bankers and arms manufacturers had pushed for U.S. involvement for
                    their own profit. The 1934 publication of the book <hi rend="italic">Merchants
                        of Death</hi> by <persName>H.C. Engelbrecht</persName> and <persName>F. C.
                        Hanighen</persName>, followed by the 1935 tract “War Is a Racket” by
                    decorated Marine Corps General <persName>Smedley D. Butler</persName> both
                    served to increase popular suspicions of wartime profiteering and influence
                    public opinion in the direction of neutrality. Many Americans became determined
                    not to be tricked by banks and industries into making such great sacrifices
                    again. The reality of a worldwide economic depression and the need for increased
                    attention to domestic problems only served to bolster the idea that the United
                    States should isolate itself from troubling events in Europe. During the
                    interwar period, the U.S. Government repeatedly chose non-entanglement over
                    participation or intervention as the appropriate response to international
                    questions. Immediately following the First World War, <ref
                        target="/milestones/1914-1920/league">Congress rejected U.S. membership in
                        the League of Nations</ref>. Some members of Congress opposed membership in
                    the League out of concern that it would draw the United States into European
                    conflicts, although ultimately the collective security clause sank the
                    possibility of U.S. participation. During the 1930s, the League proved
                    ineffectual in the face of growing militarism, partly due to the U.S. decision
                    not to participate.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="nye-gerald.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Senator Gerald Nye</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Japanese invasion of Manchuria and subsequent push to gain control over
                    larger expanses of Northeast China in 1931 led President <persName>Herbert
                        Hoover</persName> and his Secretary of State, <persName>Henry
                        Stimson</persName>, to establish the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/mukden-incident">Stimson Doctrine</ref>, which
                    stated that the United States would not recognize the territory gained by
                    aggression and in violation of international agreements. With the Stimson
                    Doctrine, the United States expressed concern over the aggressive action without
                    committing itself to any direct involvement or intervention. Other conflicts,
                    including the Italian invasion of Ethiopia and the Spanish Civil War, also
                    resulted in virtually no official commitment or action from the United States
                    Government. Upon taking office, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt tended to
                    see a necessity for the United States to participate more actively in
                    international affairs, but his ability to apply his personal outlook to foreign
                    policy was limited by the strength of isolationist sentiment in the U.S.
                    Congress. In 1933, President Roosevelt proposed a Congressional measure that
                    would have granted him the right to consult with other nations to place pressure
                    on aggressors in international conflicts. The bill ran into strong opposition
                    from the leading isolationists in Congress, including progressive politicians
                    such as Senators Hiram Johnson of California, William Borah of Idaho, and Robert
                    La Follette of Wisconsin. In 1935, controversy over U.S. participation in the
                    World Court elicited similar opposition. As tensions rose in Europe over Nazi
                    Germany’s aggressive maneuvers, Congress pushed through a series of <ref
                        target="/milestones/1921-1936/neutrality-acts">Neutrality Acts</ref>, which
                    served to prevent American ships and citizens from becoming entangled in outside
                    conflicts. Roosevelt lamented the restrictive nature of the acts, but because he
                    still required Congressional support for his domestic New Deal policies, he
                    reluctantly acquiesced.</p>
                <p>The isolationists were a diverse group, including progressives and conservatives,
                    business owners and peace activists, but because they faced no consistent,
                    organized opposition from internationalists, their ideology triumphed time and
                    again. Roosevelt appeared to accept the strength of the isolationist elements in
                    Congress until 1937. In that year, as the situation in Europe continued to grow
                    worse and the Second Sino-Japanese War began in Asia, the President gave a
                    speech in which he likened international aggression to a disease that other
                    nations must work to “quarantine.” At that time, however, Americans were still
                    not prepared to risk their lives and livelihoods for peace abroad. Even the
                    outbreak of war in Europe in 1939 did not suddenly diffuse popular desire to
                    avoid international entanglements. Instead, public opinion shifted from favoring
                    complete neutrality to supporting limited U.S. aid to the Allies short of actual
                    intervention in the war. The surprise Japanese attack on the U.S. Navy at
                        <placeName>Pearl Harbor</placeName> in December of 1941 served to convince
                    the majority of Americans that the United States should enter the war on the
                    side of the Allies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="internationalism">
                <head>Henry Luce and 20th Century U.S. Internationalism</head>
                <p>During the middle of the 20th century, <persName>Henry R. Luce</persName>
                    (1898–1967) became one of the most influential American advocates for
                    internationalism among figures working in the private sector. The founder of <hi
                        rend="italic">Time</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fortune</hi> magazines, Luce presented a powerful vision of the United
                    States leading and transforming the world.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="luce.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Henry Luce</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Born in <placeName>China</placeName> in 1898 to missionary parents, from a young
                    age Henry Luce developed a strong faith in the transformative power of U.S.
                    ideals. His father was part of a growing group of U.S. missionaries who believed
                    that it was their calling to save China through a combination of Christianity,
                    modern science, democracy, and the sorts of freedoms enshrined in the U.S.
                    Constitution. Raised among people who shared in this belief, Luce internalized a
                    similar view of China as a place that both needed and wanted U.S. assistance to
                    bring it into the modern world. Subsequent experiences studying in England and
                    the United States, and training to fight with U.S. forces in Europe at the end
                    of World War I, cemented Luce’s conviction that the United States must play an
                    active and leading role in world affairs.</p>
                <p>Following his graduation from Yale in 1920 and a year at Oxford, Luce turned to
                    journalism as a means to promote his internationalist vision. Luce and a
                    classmate from Yale, Briton Hadden, gathered financial backing, and on March 3,
                    1923, issued the first installment of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi>, which quickly
                    became the cornerstone of his publishing empire. A combination of serious news
                    and trivial matters initially culled from the daily papers, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Time</hi> also presented a strong editorial stance on world events. The
                    magazine came out strongly in favor of U.S. involvement overseas and democratic
                    reform in China, and against Soviet Russia, Bolshevism, and domestic
                    Prohibition. <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> quickly gained popularity and its
                    success allowed Luce to subsequently launch two more publications: <hi
                        rend="italic">Fortune</hi>, a monthly journal intended to raise
                    internationalist sentiments among the business community, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Life</hi>, a weekly image-based magazine that sought to bring the world
                    home to its readers through vivid photographs.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="timemag.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Cover of <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> Magazine in 1950</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Luce’s efforts to rally popular and government support for U.S. global leadership
                    peaked with his editorial “The American Century,” published in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Life</hi> in February 1941. This document had two main objectives: on one
                    hand it called upon the United States to directly engage in the conflict in
                    Europe by joining Britain in its battle against Germany; on the other, and more
                    importantly, it said that the United States must replace Britain as the world
                    leader and completely transform the system of international relations through
                    the global application of “American principles.” Drawing upon his background in
                    China, as well as on the internationalism of <persName>Theodore
                        Roosevelt</persName> and <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>, Luce argued
                    that the United States had both the right and the moral obligation to use its
                    military and economic might in the service of promoting higher ideals of freedom
                    and democracy around the world. Luce’s vision of the American Century had
                    important implications for U.S. foreign policy in both the short and long
                    term.</p>
                <p>Henry Luce advanced his agenda in the service of numerous causes, but he was most
                    interested in U.S. policies toward Asia. After the outbreak of full-scale war
                    between China and Japan in 1937, Luce called for greater U.S. support of China’s
                    war effort, and particularly for the Nationalist government led by Chiang
                    Kai-shek. After the end of World War II, Luce became a leader in the China lobby
                    that urged massive assistance to the supposedly democratic and reform-minded
                    Nationalists over the Communists led by Mao Zedong. When the U.S. Government did
                    not heed his calls, he turned his efforts to criticizing the weak foreign policy
                    of President Harry Truman and the Democrats, castigating those he believed had
                    “lost” China to communism. After <persName>Chiang Kai-shek</persName>’s defeat,
                    Luce turned his attention to Korea and then Vietnam, where he insisted that the
                    United States must defend the anti-Communist regimes. Blind to the shortcomings
                    of these anti-Communists, Luce consistently saw them as the means through which
                    the United States could transform the world by spreading its values.</p>
                <p>Throughout his professional life, Henry Luce was one of the most prominent
                    internationalists in the United States. He used his magazines as high-profile
                    venues to promote U.S. involvement overseas and developed exceptional political
                    connections, even with adversaries such as <persName>Franklin
                        Roosevelt</persName>, in an effort to shape foreign policy. Moreover, his
                    vision of the American Century marked the full ascendance of internationalism
                    over isolationism in U.S. foreign policy thinking. His call for the United
                    States to use its power to shape and lead the international system has had an
                    enduring influence during the Cold War and beyond.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="atlantic-conf">
                <head>The Atlantic Conference &amp; Charter, <date when="1941">1941</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Atlantic Charter was a joint declaration released by U.S. President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> and British Prime Minister
                        <persName>Winston Churchill</persName> on August 14, 1941 following a
                    meeting of the two heads of government in Newfoundland. The Atlantic Charter provided
                    a broad statement of U.S. and British war aims.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="winston.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>British Prime Minister Winston Churchill</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The meeting had been called in response to the geopolitical situation in Europe
                    by mid-1941. Although Great Britain had been spared from a German invasion in
                    the fall of 1940 and, with the passage of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1937-1945/lend-lease">U.S. Lend Lease Act</ref> in March
                    1941, was assured U.S. material support, by the end of May, German forces had
                    inflicted humiliating defeats upon British, Greek, and, Yugoslav forces in the
                    Balkans and were threatening to overrun Egypt and close off the Suez Canal,
                    thereby restricting British access to its possessions in India. When the Germans
                    invaded the Soviet Union on June 22, 1941, few policymakers in Washington or
                    London believed that the Soviets would be able to resist the Nazi onslaught for
                    more than six weeks. While the British Government focused its efforts on dealing
                    with the Germans in Europe, they were also concerned that Japan might take
                    advantage of the situation to seize British, French, and Dutch territories in
                    Southeast Asia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="atlanticcharter.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Churchill’s copy of the Atlantic Charter</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Churchill and Roosevelt met on August 9 and 10, 1941 aboard the U.S.S. <hi
                        rend="italic">Augusta</hi> in Placentia Bay, Newfoundland, to discuss their
                    respective war aims for the Second World War and to outline a postwar
                    international system. The Charter they drafted included eight “common
                    principles” that the United States and Great Britain would be committed to
                    supporting in the postwar world. Both countries agreed not to seek territorial
                    expansion; to seek the liberalization of international trade; to establish
                    freedom of the seas, and international labor, economic, and welfare standards.
                    Most importantly, both the United States and Great Britain were committed to
                    supporting the restoration of self-governments for all countries that had been
                    occupied during the war and allowing all peoples to choose their own form of
                    government</p>
                <p>While the meeting was successful in drafting these aims, it failed to produce the
                    desired results for either leader. President Roosevelt had hoped that the
                    Charter might encourage the American people to back U.S. intervention in World
                    War II on behalf of the Allies; however, public opinion remained adamantly
                    opposed to such a policy until the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor in December
                    1941. Churchill’s primary goal in attending the Atlantic Conference was “to get
                    the Americans into the war.” Barring that, he hoped that the United States would
                    increase its amount of military aid to Great Britain and warn Japan against
                    taking any aggressive actions in the Pacific.</p>
                <p>Roosevelt, on the other hand, wanted the British Government to affirm publicly
                    that it was not involved in any secret treaties, particularly ones concerning
                    territorial questions, such as those concluded by the Allies during the First
                    World War concerning the division of enemy territory at war’s end. Roosevelt
                    also wished to arrange the terms by which Great Britain would repay the United
                    States for its Lend Lease assistance. Roosevelt wanted the British to pay
                    compensation by dismantling their system of Imperial Preference, which had been
                    established by the British Government during the Great Depression and was
                    designed to encourage trade within the British Empire by lowering tariff rates
                    between members, while maintaining discriminatory tariff rates against
                    outsiders.</p>
                <p>Churchill was extremely disappointed by Roosevelt’s refusal to discuss American
                    entry into the war. Furthermore, Churchill understood that several aspects of
                    the proposed joint declaration might be politically damaging for the Prime
                    Minister. Churchill worried that the abandonment of Imperial Preference would
                    anger the protectionist wing of his Conservative Party. The Americans also
                    proved unwilling to warn Japan too strongly against any future military action
                    against British possessions in Southeast Asia. Finally, both Churchill and many
                    members of his Cabinet were alarmed by the third point of the Charter, which
                    mentions the rights of all peoples to choose their own government. Churchill was
                    concerned that this clause acknowledged the right of colonial subjects to
                    agitate for decolonization, including those in Great Britain’s empire.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, Churchill realized that the joint declaration was the most he could
                    accomplish during the conference. While the United States would remain neutral,
                    the declaration would raise the morale of the British public and, most
                    importantly, bind the United States closer to Great Britain. Therefore, when
                    Churchill forwarded the text of the declaration to his Cabinet on August 11, he
                    warned them that would it be “imprudent” to raise unnecessary difficulties. The
                    Cabinet followed Churchill’s recommendation and approved the Charter.</p>
                <p>While the Atlantic Charter of August 1941 was not a binding treaty, it was,
                    nonetheless, significant for several reasons. First, it publicly affirmed the
                    sense of solidarity between the U.S. and Great Britain against Axis aggression.
                    Second, it laid out President Roosevelt’s Wilsonian-vision for the postwar
                    world; one that would be characterized by freer exchanges of trade,
                    self-determination, disarmament, and collective security. Finally, the Charter
                    ultimately did serve as an inspiration for colonial subjects throughout the
                    Third World, from Algeria to Vietnam, as they fought for independence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="lend-lease">
                <head>Lend-Lease and Military Aid to the Allies in the Early Years of World War
                    II</head>
                <p>During World War II, the United States began to provide significant military
                    supplies and other assistance to the Allies in September 1940, even though the
                    United States did not enter the war until December 1941. Much of this aid flowed
                    to the United Kingdom and other nations already at war with Germany and Japan
                    through an innovative program known as Lend-Lease.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="fdr-signing-ll.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>FDR Signing the Lend-Lease Bill</head>
                </figure>
                <p>When war broke out in Europe in September 1939, President <persName>Franklin D.
                        Roosevelt</persName> declared that while the United States would remain
                    neutral in law, he could “not ask that every American remain neutral in thought
                    as well.” Roosevelt himself made significant efforts to help nations engaged in
                    the struggle against Nazi Germany and wanted to extend a helping hand to those
                    countries that lacked the supplies necessary to fight against the Germans. The
                    United Kingdom, in particular, desperately needed help, as it was short of hard
                    currency to pay for the military goods, food, and raw materials it needed from
                    the United States.</p>
                <p>Though President Roosevelt wanted to provide assistance to the British, both
                    American law and public fears that the United States would be drawn into the
                    conflict blocked his plans. The Neutrality Act of 1939 allowed belligerents to
                    purchase war materiel from the United States, but only on a “cash and carry”
                    basis. The Johnson Act of 1934 also prohibited the extension of credit to
                    countries that had not repaid U.S. loans made to them during World War I—which
                    included Great Britain. The American military opposed the diversion of military
                    supplies to the United Kingdom. The Army’s Chief of Staff, General George C.
                    Marshall, anticipated that Britain would surrender following the collapse of
                    France, and thus American supplies sent to the British would fall into German
                    hands. Marshall and others therefore argued that U.S. national security would be
                    better served by reserving military supplies for the defense of the Western
                    Hemisphere. American public opinion also limited Roosevelt’s options. Many
                    Americans opposed involving the United States in another war. Even though
                    American public opinion generally supported the British rather than the Germans,
                    President Roosevelt had to develop an initiative that was consistent with the
                    legal prohibition against the granting of credit, satisfactory to military
                    leadership, and acceptable to an American public that generally resisted
                    involving the United States in the European conflict.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="wc.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>British Prime Minister Winston Churchill</head>
                </figure>
                <p>On September 2, 1940, President Roosevelt signed a “Destroyers for Bases”
                    agreement. Under the terms of the agreement, the United States gave the British
                    more than 50 obsolete destroyers, in exchange for 99-year leases to territory in
                    Newfoundland and the Caribbean, which would be used as U.S. air and naval bases.
                    British Prime Minister Winston Churchill had originally requested that Roosevelt
                    provide the destroyers as a gift, but the President knew that the American
                    public and Congress would oppose such a deal. He therefore decided that a deal
                    that gave the United States long-term access to British bases could be justified
                    as essential to the security of the Western Hemisphere—thereby assuaging the
                    concerns of the public and the U.S. military</p>
                <p>In December 1940, Churchill warned Roosevelt that the British were no longer able
                    to pay for supplies. On December 17, President Roosevelt proposed a new
                    initiative that would be known as Lend-Lease. The United States would provide
                    Great Britain with the supplies it needed to fight Germany, but would not insist
                    upon being paid immediately</p>
                <p>Instead, the United States would “lend” the supplies to the British, deferring
                    payment. When payment eventually did take place, the emphasis would not be on
                    payment in dollars. The tensions and instability engendered by inter-allied war
                    debts in the 1920s and 1930s had demonstrated that it was unreasonable to expect
                    that virtually bankrupt European nations would be able to pay for every item
                    they had purchased from the United States. Instead, payment would primarily take
                    the form of a “consideration” granted by Britain to the United States. After
                    many months of negotiation, the United States and Britain agreed, in Article VII
                    of the Lend-Lease agreement they signed, that this consideration would primarily
                    consist of joint action directed towards the creation of a liberalized
                    international economic order in the postwar world.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lendleasememorial.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Lend-Lease Memorial</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United Kingdom was not the only nation to strike such a deal with the United
                    States. Over the course of the war, the United States contracted Lend-Lease
                    agreements with more than 30 countries, dispensing some $50 billion in
                    assistance. Although British Prime Minister <persName>Winston
                        Churchill</persName> later referred to the initiative as “the most unsordid
                    act” one nation had ever done for another, Roosevelt’s primary motivation was
                    not altruism or disinterested generosity. Rather, Lend-Lease was designed to
                    serve America’s interest in defeating Nazi Germany without entering the war
                    until the American military and public was prepared to fight. At a time when the
                    majority of Americans opposed direct participation in the war, Lend-Lease
                    represented a vital U.S. contribution to the fight against Nazi Germany.
                    Moreover, the joint action called for under Article VII of the Lend-Lease
                    agreements signed by the United States and the recipient nations laid the
                    foundation for the creation of a new international economic order in the postwar
                    world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="us-soviet">
                <head>U.S.-Soviet Alliance, <date from="1941" to="1945">1941–1945</date>
                </head>
                <p>Although relations between the Soviet Union and the United States had been
                    strained in the years before World War II, the U.S.-Soviet alliance of 1941–1945
                    was marked by a great degree of cooperation and was essential to securing the
                    defeat of Nazi Germany. Without the remarkable efforts of the Soviet Union on
                    the Eastern Front, the United States and Great Britain would have been hard
                    pressed to score a decisive military victory over Nazi Germany.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="soviet-poster.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Department of Defense Pro-Soviet Poster</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As late as 1939, it seemed highly improbable that the United States and the
                    Soviet Union would forge an alliance. U.S.-Soviet relations had soured
                    significantly following Stalin’s decision to sign a non-aggression pact with
                    Nazi Germany in August of 1939. The Soviet occupation of eastern Poland in
                    September and the “Winter War” against Finland in December led President
                        <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName> to condemn the Soviet Union publicly
                    as a “dictatorship as absolute as any other dictatorship in the world,” and to
                    impose a “moral embargo” on the export of certain products to the Soviets.
                    Nevertheless, in spite of intense pressure to sever relations with the Soviet
                    Union, Roosevelt never lost sight of the fact that Nazi Germany, not the Soviet
                    Union, posed the greatest threat to world peace. In order to defeat that threat,
                    Roosevelt confided that he “would hold hands with the devil” if necessary.</p>
                <p>Following the Nazi defeat of France in June of 1940, Roosevelt grew wary of the
                    increasing aggression of the Germans and made some diplomatic moves to improve
                    relations with the Soviets. Beginning in July of 1940, a series of negotiations
                    took place in Washington between Under-Secretary of State <ref
                        target="/departmenthistory/people/welles-benjamin-sumner">Sumner
                        Welles</ref> and Soviet Ambassador Constantine Oumansky. Welles refused to
                    accede to Soviet demands that the United States recognize the changed borders of
                    the Soviet Union after the Soviet seizure of territory in Finland, Poland, and
                    Romania and the reincorporation of the Baltic Republics in August 1940, but the
                    U.S. Government did lift the embargo in January 1941. Furthermore, in March of
                    1941, Welles warned Oumansky of a future Nazi attack against the Soviet Union.
                    Finally, during the Congressional debate concerning the passage of the
                    Lend-Lease bill in early 1941, Roosevelt blocked attempts to exclude the Soviet
                    Union from receiving U.S. assistance.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="sumnerwelles.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Under-Secretary of State Sumner Welles</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The most important factor in swaying the Soviets eventually to enter into an
                    alliance with the United States was the Nazi decision to launch its invasion of
                    the Soviet Union in June 1941. President Roosevelt responded by dispatching his
                    trusted aide <persName>Harry Lloyd Hopkins</persName> to Moscow in order to
                    assess the Soviet military situation. Although the War Department had warned the
                    President that the Soviets would not last more than six weeks, after two
                    one-on-one meetings with Soviet Premier <persName>Josef Stalin</persName>,
                    Hopkins urged Roosevelt to assist the Soviets. By the end of October, the first
                        <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/lend-lease">Lend-Lease aid</ref> to the
                    Soviet Union was on its way. The United States entered the war as a belligerent
                    in late 1941 and thus began coordinating directly with the Soviets, and the
                    British, as allies.</p>
                <p>Several issues arose during the war that threatened the alliance. These included
                    the Soviet refusal to aide the Polish Home Army during the Warsaw Uprising of
                    August 1944, and the decision of British and U.S. officials to exclude the
                    Soviets from secret negotiations with German officers in March of 1945 in an
                    effort to secure the surrender of German troops in Italy. The most important
                    disagreement, however, was over the opening of a second front in the West.
                    Stalin’s troops struggled to hold the Eastern front against the Nazi forces, and
                    the Soviets began pleading for a British invasion of France immediately after
                    the Nazi invasion in 1941. In 1942, Roosevelt unwisely promised the Soviets that
                    the Allies would open the second front that autumn. Although Stalin only
                    grumbled when the invasion was postponed until 1943, he exploded the following
                    year when the invasion was postponed again until May of 1944. In retaliation,
                    Stalin recalled his ambassadors from London and Washington and fears soon arose
                    that the Soviets might seek a separate peace with Germany.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hlhopkins.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Harry Lloyd Hopkins</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In spite of these differences, the defeat of Nazi Germany was a joint endeavor
                    that could not have been accomplished without close cooperation and shared
                    sacrifices. Militarily, the Soviets fought valiantly and suffered staggering
                    casualties on the Eastern Front. When Great Britain and the United States
                    finally invaded northern France in 1944, the Allies were finally able to drain
                    Nazi Germany of its strength on two fronts. Finally, two devastating atomic bomb
                    attacks against Japan by the United States, coupled with the Soviets’ decision
                    to break their neutrality pact with Japan by invading Manchuria, finally led to
                    the end of the war in the Pacific.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, during the wartime conferences at Tehran and Yalta, Roosevelt
                    secured political concessions from Stalin and Soviet participation in the United
                    Nations. While President Roosevelt harbored no illusions about Soviet designs in
                    Eastern Europe, it was his great hope that if the United States made a sincere
                    effort to satisfy legitimate Soviet security requirements in Eastern Europe and
                    Northeast Asia, and to integrate the U.S.S.R. into the United Nations, the
                    Soviet regime would become an international team player and moderate its
                    authoritarian regime. Unfortunately, soon after the war, the alliance between
                    the United States and the Soviet Union began to unravel as the two nations faced
                    complex postwar decisions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="chinese-exclusion-act-repeal">
                <head>Repeal of the Chinese Exclusion Act, <date when="1943">1943</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1943, Congress passed a measure to repeal the discriminatory exclusion laws
                    against Chinese immigrants and to establish an immigration quota for China of
                    around 105 visas per year. As such, the Chinese were both the first to be
                    excluded in the beginning of the era of immigration restriction and the first
                    Asians to gain entry to the United States in the era of liberalization. The
                    repeal of this act was a decision almost wholly grounded in the exigencies of
                    World War II, as Japanese propaganda made repeated reference to Chinese
                    exclusion from the United States in order to weaken the ties between the United
                    States and its ally, the Republic of China. The fact that in addition to general
                    measures preventing Asian immigration, the Chinese were subject to their own,
                    unique prohibition had long been a source of contention in Sino‑American
                    relations. There was little opposition to the repeal, because the United States
                    already had in place a number of measures to ensure that, even without the
                    Chinese Exclusion Laws explicitly forbidding Chinese immigration, Chinese still
                    could not enter. The Immigration Act of 1924 stated that aliens ineligible for
                    U.S. citizenship were not permitted to enter the United States, and this
                    included the Chinese.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chinese-exclusion-repeal.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Repeal of the Chinese Exclusion Act</head>
                </figure>
                <p>More controversial than repeal was the proposal to go one step further and place
                    the Chinese on a quota basis for future entry to the United States. By finally
                    applying the formulas created in the 1924 Immigration Act, the total annual
                    quota for Chinese immigrants to the United States (calculated as a percentage of
                    the total population of people of Chinese origin living in the United States in
                    1920) would be around 105. In light of the overall immigration to the United
                    States, at first glance the new quota seemed insignificant. Yet, those concerned
                    about an onslaught of Chinese (or Asian) immigration and its potential impact on
                    American society and racial composition believed that even this small quota
                    represented an opening wedge through which potentially thousands of Chinese
                    could enter the United States. Because migration within the Western Hemisphere
                    was not regulated by the quota system, it seemed possible that Chinese residents
                    in Central and South America would re-migrate to the United States. Moreover, if
                    the Chinese of Hong Kong were to apply under the vast, largely unused British
                    quota, thousands could enter each year on top of the number of available Chinese
                    visas. </p>
                <p>Fears about the economic, social, and racial effect of a “floodtide” of Chinese
                    immigrants led to a compromise bill—fears that mirrored the xenophobic arguments
                    that had led to Chinese Exclusion in the first place, some sixty years
                    previously. Under this bill, there would be a quota on Chinese immigration, but,
                    unlike European quotas based on country of citizenship, the Chinese quota would
                    be based on ethnicity. Chinese immigrating to the United States from anywhere in
                    the world would be counted against the Chinese quota, even if they had never
                    been to China or had never held Chinese nationality. Creating this special,
                    ethnic quota for the Chinese was a way for the United States to combat Japanese
                    propaganda by proclaiming that Chinese were welcome, but at the same time, to
                    ensure that only a limited number of Chinese actually entered the country. </p>
                <p>President <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> threw the weight of his
                    office behind the compromise measure, connecting the importance of the measure
                    to American wartime goals. In a letter to Congress, Roosevelt wrote that passing
                    the bill was vital to correcting the “historic mistake” of Chinese exclusion,
                    and he emphasized that the legislation was “important in the cause of winning
                    the war and of establishing a secure peace.” </p>
                <p>The repeal of Chinese exclusion paved the way for measures in 1946 to admit
                    Filipino and Asian-Indian immigrants. The exclusion of both of these groups had
                    long damaged U.S. relations with the Philippines and India. Eventually, Asian
                    exclusion ended with the 1952 Immigration Act, although that Act followed the
                    pattern of the Chinese quota and assigned racial, not national, quotas to all
                    Asian immigrants. This system did not end until Congress did away with the
                    National Origins quota system altogether in the Immigration Act of 1965.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="war-time-conferences">
                <head>Wartime Conferences, <date from="1941" to="1945">1941–1945</date>
                </head>
                <p>The first involvement of the United States in the wartime conferences between the
                    Allied nations opposing the Axis powers actually occurred before the nation
                    formally entered World War II. In August 1941, President <persName>Franklin
                        Roosevelt</persName> and British Prime Minister <persName>Winston
                        Churchill</persName> met secretly and devised an eight-point statement of
                    war aims known as the Atlantic Charter, which included a pledge that the Allies
                    would not accept territorial changes resulting from the war in Europe. Following
                    the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor, the wartime conferences focused on
                    establishing a second front.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="roosevelt-churchill.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Franklin Roosevelt and British Prime Minister Winston Churchill
                        at the Wartime Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At Casablanca in January 1943, Roosevelt and Churchill agreed to fight until the
                    Axis powers surrendered unconditionally. </p>
                <p>In a November 1943 meeting in Egypt with Chinese leader <persName>Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName>, Roosevelt and Churchill agreed to a pre-eminent role
                    for China in postwar Asia. </p>
                <p>The next major wartime conference included Roosevelt, Churchill, and the leader
                    of the Soviet Union, Joseph Stalin. Meeting at Tehran following the Cairo
                    Conference, the “Big Three” secured confirmation on the launching of the
                    cross-channel invasion and a promise from Stalin that the Soviet Union would
                    eventually enter the war against Japan. </p>
                <p>In 1944, conferences at Bretton Woods and Dumbarton Oaks created the framework
                    for international cooperation in the postwar world.</p>
                <p>In February 1945, the “Big Three” met at the former Russian czar’s summer palace
                    in the Crimea. Yalta was the most important and by far the most controversial of
                    the wartime meetings. Recognizing the strong position that the Soviet Army
                    possessed on the ground, Churchill and an ailing Roosevelt agreed to a number of
                    compromises with Stalin that allowed Soviet hegemony to remain in Poland and
                    other Eastern European countries, granted territorial concessions to the Soviet
                    Union, and outlined punitive measures against Germany, including an occupation
                    and reparations in principle. Stalin did guarantee that the Soviet Union would
                    declare war on Japan within six months.</p>
                <p>The last meeting of the “Big Three” occurred at Potsdam in July 1945, where the
                    tension that would erupt into the cold war was evident. Despite the end of the
                    war in Europe and the revelation of the existence of the atomic bomb to the
                    Allies, neither President Harry Truman, Roosevelt’s successor, nor Clement
                    Atlee, who mid-way through the conference replaced Churchill, could come to
                    agreement with Stalin on any but the most minor issues. The most significant
                    agreement was the issuance of the Potsdam Declaration to Japan demanding an
                    immediate and unconditional surrenderand threatening Japan with destruction if
                    they did not comply. With the Axis forces defeated, the wartime alliance soon
                    devolved into suspicion and bitterness on both sides. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="casablanca">
                <head>The Casablanca Conference, <date when="1943">1943</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Casablanca Conference was a meeting between U.S. President <persName>Franklin
                        D. Roosevelt</persName> and British Prime Minister <persName>Winston
                        Churchill</persName> in the city of Casablanca, Morocco that took place from
                    January 14–24, 1943. While Soviet Premier <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName>
                    received an invitation, he was unable to attend because the Red Army was engaged
                    in a major offensive against the German Army at the time. The most notable
                    developments at the Conference were the finalization of Allied strategic plans
                    against the Axis powers in 1943, and the promulgation of the policy of
                    “unconditional surrender.” </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="casablanca-conference.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>World Leaders at the Casablanca Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Casablanca Conference took place just two months after the Anglo-American
                    landings in French North Africa in November 1942. At this meeting, Roosevelt and
                    Churchill focused on coordinating Allied military strategy against the Axis
                    powers over the course of the coming year. They resolved to concentrate their
                    efforts against Germany in the hopes of drawing German forces away from the
                    Eastern Front, and to increase shipments of supplies to the Soviet Union. While
                    they would begin concentrating forces in England in preparation for an eventual
                    landing in northern France, they decided that first they would concentrate their
                    efforts in the Mediterranean by launching an invasion of Sicily and the Italian
                    mainland designed to knock Italy out of the war. They also agreed to strengthen
                    their strategic bombing campaign against Germany. Finally, the leaders agreed on
                    a military effort to eject Japan from Papua New Guinea and to open up new supply
                    lines to China through Japanese-occupied Burma. </p>
                <p>On the final day of the Conference, President Roosevelt announced that he and
                    Churchill had decided that the only way to ensure postwar peace was to adopt a
                    policy of unconditional surrender. The President clearly stated, however, that
                    the policy of unconditional surrender did not entail the destruction of the
                    populations of the Axis powers but rather, “the destruction of the philosophies
                    in those countries which are based on conquest and the subjugation of other
                    people.” </p>
                <p>The policy of demanding unconditional surrender was an outgrowth of Allied war
                    aims, most notably the Atlantic Charter of August 1941, which called for an end
                    to wars of aggression and the promotion of disarmament and collective security.
                    Roosevelt wanted to avoid the situation that had followed the First World War,
                    when large segments of German society supported the position, so deftly
                    exploited by the Nazi party, that Germany had not been defeated militarily, but
                    rather, had been “stabbed in the back” by liberals, pacifists, socialists,
                    communists, and Jews. Roosevelt also wished to make it clear that neither the
                    United States nor Great Britain would seek a separate peace with the Axis
                    powers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="tehran-conf">
                <head>The Tehran Conference, <date when="1943">1943</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Tehran Conference was a meeting between U.S. President <persName>Franklin
                        Delano Roosevelt</persName>, British Prime Minister <persName>Winston
                        Churchill</persName>, and Soviet Premier <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName>
                    in Tehran, Iran, between November 28 and December 1, 1943.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tehran-conference.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Stalin, Roosevelt and Churchill at the Tehran Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>During the Conference, the three leaders coordinated their military strategy
                    against Germany and Japan and made a number of important decisions concerning
                    the post World War II era. The most notable achievements of the Conference
                    focused on the next phases of the war against the Axis powers in Europe and
                    Asia. Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin engaged in discussions concerning the
                    terms under which the British and Americans finally committed to launching
                    Operation Overlord, an invasion of northern France, to be executed by May of
                    1944. The Soviets, who had long been pushing the Allies to open a second front,
                    agreed to launch another major offensive on the Eastern Front that would divert
                    German troops away from the Allied campaign in northern France. Stalin also
                    agreed in principle that the Soviet Union would declare war against Japan
                    following an Allied victory over Germany. In exchange for a Soviet declaration
                    of war against Japan, Roosevelt conceded to Stalin’s demands for the Kurile
                    Islands and the southern half of Sakhalin, and access to the ice-free ports of
                    Dairen (Dalian) and Port Arthur (Lüshun Port) located on the Liaodong Peninsula
                    in northern China. The exact details concerning this deal were not finalized,
                    however, until the Yalta Conference of 1945. </p>
                <p> At Tehran, the three Allied leaders also discussed important issues concerning
                    the fate of Eastern Europe and Germany in the postwar period. Stalin pressed for
                    a revision of Poland’s eastern border with the Soviet Union to match the line
                    set by British Foreign Secretary Lord Curzon in 1920. In order to compensate
                    Poland for the resulting loss of territory, the three leaders agreed to move the
                    German-Polish border to the Oder and Neisse rivers. This decision was not
                    formally ratified, however, until the Potsdam Conference of 1945. During these
                    negotiations Roosevelt also secured from Stalin his assurance that the Republics
                    of Lithuania, Latvia, and Estonia would be reincorporated into the Soviet Union
                    only after the citizens of each republic voted on the question in a referendum.
                    Stalin stressed, however, that the matter would have to be resolved “in
                    accordance with the Soviet constitution,” and that he would not consent to any
                    international control over the elections. Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin also
                    broached the question of the possible postwar partition of Germany into Allied
                    zones of occupation and agreed to have the European Advisory Commission
                    “carefully study the question of dismemberment” before any final decision was
                    taken. </p>
                <p> Broader international cooperation also became a central theme of the
                    negotiations at Tehran. Roosevelt and Stalin privately discussed the composition
                    of the United Nations. During the Moscow Conference of the Foreign Ministers in
                    October and November of 1943, the United States, Britain, China, and the Soviet
                    Union had signed a four-power declaration whose fourth point called for the
                    creation of a “general international organization” designed to promote
                    “international peace and security.” At Tehran, Roosevelt outlined for Stalin his
                    vision of the proposed organization in which the future United Nations would be
                    dominated by “four policemen” (the United States, Britain, China, and Soviet
                    Union) who “would have the power to deal immediately with any threat to the
                    peace and any sudden emergency which requires action.” </p>
                <p> Finally, the three leaders issued a “Declaration of the Three Powers Regarding
                    Iran.” Within it, they thanked the Iranian Government for its assistance in the
                    war against Germany and promised to provide it with economic assistance both
                    during and after the war. Most importantly, the U.S., British, and Soviet
                    Governments stated that they all shared a “desire for the maintenance of the
                    independence, sovereignty, and territorial integrity of Iran.” </p>
                <p> Roosevelt secured many of his objectives during the Conference. The Soviet Union
                    had committed to joining the war against Japan and expressed support for
                    Roosevelt’s plans for the United Nations. Most importantly, Roosevelt believed
                    that he had won Stalin’s confidence by proving that the United States was
                    willing to negotiate directly with the Soviet Union and, most importantly, by
                    guaranteeing the opening of the second front in France by the spring of 1944.
                    However, Stalin also gained tentative concessions on Eastern Europe that would
                    be confirmed during the later wartime conferences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bretton-woods"
                ana="roosevelt-franklin-d hull-cordell united-kingdom financial-and-monetary-policy trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">
                <head>Bretton Woods-GATT, 1941–1947</head>
                <p>During and immediately after the Second World War, the United States, the United
                    Kingdom, and other allied nations engaged in a series of negotiations to
                    establish the rules for the postwar international economy. The result was the
                    creation of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank at the July 1944
                    Bretton Woods Conference and the signing of the General Agreement on Tariffs and
                    Trade at an international conference in Geneva in October 1947.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bretton-woods.jpg" height="350px" width="441px"/>
                    <head>Harry Dexter White and John Maynard Keynes at the inaugural meeting of the
                        International Monetary Fund’s Board of Governors, March 8, 1946.
                        (International Monetary Fund)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The lessons drawn by U.S. policymakers from the interwar period informed their
                    approach to the postwar global economy. President <persName>Franklin D.
                        Roosevelt</persName> and officials such as Secretary of State
                        <persName>Cordell Hull</persName> were adherents of the Wilsonian belief
                    that free trade promoted not just prosperity, but also peace. The experience of
                    the 1930s certainly suggested as much. The policies adopted by governments to
                    combat the Great Depression—high tariffs, competitive currency devaluations,
                    discriminatory trading blocs—helped destabilize the international environment
                    without improving the economic situation. This experience led leaders throughout
                    the anti-Axis United Nations alliance to conclude that economic cooperation was
                    the only way to achieve both peace and prosperity, at home and abroad.</p>
                <p>This vision was articulated in the Atlantic Charter, issued by Roosevelt and
                    British Prime Minister <persName>Winston Churchill</persName> at the conclusion
                    of the August 1941 Atlantic Conference. The Charter’s fourth point committed the
                    United States and the United Kingdom “to further the enjoyment by all States,
                    great or small, victor or vanquished, of access, on equal terms, to the trade
                    and to the raw materials of the world which are needed for their economic
                    prosperity,” while its fifth point expressed their commitment to “the fullest
                    collaboration between all nations in the economic field with the object of
                    securing, for all, improved labor standards, economic advancement and social
                    security.” The two countries elaborated upon these principles in Article VII of
                    their February 1942 agreement on lend-lease aid. In that article, the United
                    Kingdom agreed that in return for U.S. lend-lease assistance, it would cooperate
                    with the United States in devising measures to expand “production, employment,
                    and the exchange and consumption of goods,” to eliminate “all forms of
                    discriminatory treatment in international commerce,” to reduce barriers to
                    trade, and generally to achieve the goals laid out in the Atlantic Charter.</p>
                <p>By early 1942, U.S. and British officials began preparing proposals that would
                    foster economic stability and prosperity in the postwar world. <persName>Harry
                        Dexter White</persName>, Special Assistant to the U.S. Secretary of the
                    Treasury, and <persName>John Maynard Keynes</persName>, an advisor to the
                    British Treasury, each drafted plans creating organizations that would provide
                    financial assistance to countries experiencing short-term balance of payments
                    deficits; this assistance was meant to ensure that such countries did not adopt
                    protectionist or predatory economic policies to improve their balance of
                    payments position. While both plans envisioned a world of fixed exchange rates,
                    believed to be more conducive to the expansion of international trade than
                    floating exchange rates, they differed in several significant respects. As a
                    result, from 1942 until 1944, bilateral and multilateral meetings of allied
                    financial experts were held in order to settle upon a common approach. Agreement
                    was finally reached at the July 1944 United Nations Monetary and Financial
                    Conference, a gathering of delegates from 44 nations that met in Bretton Woods,
                    New Hampshire. The two major accomplishments of the Bretton Woods conference
                    were the creation of the International Monetary Fund (IMF) and the International
                    Bank for Reconstruction and Development (IBRD), commonly known as the World
                    Bank. The IMF was charged with overseeing a system of fixed exchange rates
                    centered on the U.S. dollar and gold, serving as a forum for consultation and
                    cooperation and a provider of short-term financial assistance to countries
                    experiencing temporary deficits in their balance of payments. The IBRD was
                    responsible for providing financial assistance for the reconstruction of
                    war-ravaged nations and the economic development of less developed countries. In
                    July 1945, Congress passed the Bretton Woods Agreements Act, authorizing U.S.
                    entry into the IMF and World Bank, and the two organizations officially came
                    into existence five months later. The fixed exchange rate system established at
                    Bretton Woods endured for the better part of three decades; only after the
                    exchange crises of August 1971, when President <persName>Richard M.
                        Nixon</persName> suspended the dollar’s convertibility into gold, and
                    February/March 1973 did floating exchange rates become the norm for the major
                    industrialized democracies.</p>
                <p>Agreement on international trade proved more difficult to achieve. One of the
                    most contentious issues was the system of preferential tariffs established among
                    the members of the British Commonwealth in 1932, whereby trade within the
                    Commonwealth was subject to lower tariffs than trade between the Commonwealth
                    nations and the rest of the world. U.S. officials such as Cordell Hull opposed
                    imperial preferences on both ideological and practical grounds—the United
                    Kingdom and Canada, both members of the system, were the United States’ two
                    largest trading partners—and called for their abolition; however, many U.K. and
                    other Commonwealth officials favored keeping the preferences, at least until the
                    United States agreed to reduce the high Smoot-Hawley tariffs set in 1930. After
                    more than four years of negotiations on this and other issues—such as the rules
                    that would govern tariff negotiations and the structure of a proposed new
                    organization to oversee international trade—agreement was finally reached in
                    1947. Twenty-three nations meeting in Geneva from April to October 1947
                    concluded the first postwar round of tariff negotiations, leading to reductions
                    in tariffs and imperial preferences, as well as a draft charter for a new
                    institution, the International Trade Organization (ITO). Participants also
                    signed the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade (GATT), designed not only to
                    implement the agreed tariff cuts but to serve as an interim codification of the
                    rules governing commercial relations among its signatories until the ITO was
                    created. In November 1947, the United Nations Conference on Trade and Employment
                    convened in Havana to consider the draft ITO charter; four months of
                    negotiations later, the representatives of 53 countries signed the finished
                    charter in March 1948. However, strong opposition in the U.S. Congress meant
                    that the ITO never came into existence. Instead, it was the GATT that governed
                    postwar international trade relations for almost fifty years. Under the GATT’s
                    aegis, eight rounds of trade negotiations resulted in significant tariff
                    reductions among its members before it was superseded by the World Trade
                    Organization in 1995.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="yalta-conf">
                <head>The Yalta Conference, <date when="1945">1945</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Yalta Conference took place in a Russian resort town in the Crimea from
                    February 4–11, 1945, during World War Two. At Yalta, U.S. President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName>, British Prime Minister
                        <persName>Winston Churchill</persName>, and Soviet Premier <persName>Joseph
                        Stalin</persName> made important decisions regarding the future progress of
                    the war and the postwar world.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="yalta-conference.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>World Leaders at the Yalta Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Allied leaders came to Yalta knowing that an Allied victory in Europe was
                    practically inevitable but less convinced that the Pacific war was nearing an
                    end. Recognizing that a victory over Japan might require a protracted fight, the
                    United States and Great Britain saw a major strategic advantage to Soviet
                    participation in the Pacific theater. At Yalta, Roosevelt and Churchill
                    discussed with Stalin the conditions under which the Soviet Union would enter
                    the war against Japan and all three agreed that, in exchange for potentially
                    crucial Soviet participation in the Pacific theater, the Soviets would be
                    granted a sphere of influence in Manchuria following Japan’s surrender. This
                    included the southern portion of Sakhalin, a lease at Port Arthur (now
                    Lüshunkou), a share in the operation of the Manchurian railroads, and the Kurile
                    Islands. This agreement was the major concrete accomplishment of the Yalta
                    Conference. </p>
                <p>The Allied leaders also discussed the future of Germany, Eastern Europe and the
                    United Nations. Roosevelt, Churchill, and Stalin agreed not only to include
                    France in the postwar governing of Germany, but also that Germany should assume
                    some, but not all, responsibility for reparations following the war. The
                    Americans and the British generally agreed that future governments of the
                    Eastern European nations bordering the Soviet Union should be “friendly” to the
                    Soviet regime while the Soviets pledged to allow free elections in all
                    territories liberated from Nazi Germany. Negotiators also released a declaration
                    on Poland, providing for the inclusion of Communists in the postwar national
                    government. In discussions regarding the future of the United Nations, all
                    parties agreed to an American plan concerning voting procedures in the Security
                    Council, which had been expanded to five permanent members following the
                    inclusion of France. Each of these permanent members was to hold a veto on
                    decisions before the Security Council. </p>
                <p>Initial reaction to the Yalta agreements was celebratory. Roosevelt and many
                    other Americans viewed it as proof that the spirit of U.S.-Soviet wartime
                    cooperation would carry over into the postwar period. This sentiment, however,
                    was short lived. With the death of Franklin D. Roosevelt on April 12, 1945,
                    Harry S. Truman became the thirty-third president of the United States. By the
                    end of April, the new administration clashed with the Soviets over their
                    influence in Eastern Europe, and over the United Nations. Alarmed at the
                    perceived lack of cooperation on the part of the Soviets, many Americans began
                    to criticize Roosevelt’s handling of the Yalta negotiations. To this day, many
                    of Roosevelt’s most vehement detractors accuse him of “handing over” Eastern
                    Europe and Northeast Asia to the Soviet Union at Yalta despite the fact that the
                    Soviets did make many substantial concessions. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="potsdam-conf">
                <head>The Potsdam Conference, <date when="1945">1945</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Big Three—Soviet leader <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName>, British Prime
                    Minister <persName>Winston Churchill</persName> (replaced on July 26 by Prime
                    Minister <persName>Clement Attlee</persName>), and U.S. President
                        <persName>Harry Truman</persName>—met in <placeName>Potsdam,
                        Germany</placeName>, from July 17 to August 2, 1945, to negotiate terms for
                    the end of World War II. After the Yalta Conference of February 1945, Stalin,
                    Churchill, and U.S. President Franklin D. Roosevelt had agreed to meet following
                    the surrender of Germany to determine the postwar borders in Europe. Germany
                    surrendered on May 8, 1945, and the Allied leaders agreed to meet over the
                    summer at Potsdam to continue the discussions that had begun at Yalta. Although
                    the Allies remained committed to fighting a joint war in the Pacific, the lack
                    of a common enemy in Europe led to difficulties reaching consensus concerning
                    postwar reconstruction on the European continent. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="truman-stalin.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head> Soviet Leader Joseph Stalin and President Harry Truman</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The major issue at Potsdam was the question of how to handle Germany. At Yalta,
                    the Soviets had pressed for heavy postwar reparations from Germany, half of
                    which would go to the Soviet Union. While Roosevelt had acceded to such demands,
                    Truman and his Secretary of State, <persName>James Byrnes</persName>, were
                    determined to mitigate the treatment of Germany by allowing the occupying
                    nations to exact reparations only from their own zone of occupation. Truman and
                    Byrnes encouraged this position because they wanted to avoid a repetition of the
                    situation created by the Treaty of Versailles, which had exacted high
                    reparations payments from Germany following World War One. Many experts agreed
                    that the harsh reparations imposed by the Versailles Treaty had handicapped the
                    German economy and fueled the rise of the Nazis. </p>
                <p>Despite numerous disagreements, the Allied leaders did manage to conclude some
                    agreements at Potsdam. For example, the negotiators confirmed the status of a
                    demilitarized and disarmed Germany under four zones of Allied occupation.
                    According to the Protocol of the Conference, there was to be “a complete
                    disarmament and demilitarization of Germany”; all aspects of German industry
                    that could be utilized for military purposes were to be dismantled; all German
                    military and paramilitary forces were to be eliminated; and the production of
                    all military hardware in Germany was forbidden. Furthermore, German society was
                    to be remade along democratic lines by repeal of all discriminatory laws from
                    the Nazi era and by the arrest and trial of those Germans deemed to be “war
                    criminals.” The German educational and judicial systems were to be purged of any
                    authoritarian influences, and democratic political parties would be encouraged
                    to participate in the administration of Germany at the local and state level.
                    The reconstitution of a national German Government was, however, postponed
                    indefinitely, and the Allied Control Commission (which was comprised of four
                    occupying powers, the United States, Britain, France, and the Soviet Union)
                    would run the country during the interregnum. </p>
                <p>One of the most controversial matters addressed at the Potsdam Conference dealt
                    with the revision of the German-Soviet-Polish borders and the expulsion of
                    several million Germans from the disputed territories. In exchange for the
                    territory it lost to the Soviet Union following the readjustment of the
                    Soviet-Polish border, Poland received a large swath of German territory and
                    began to deport the German residents of the territories in question, as did
                    other nations that were host to large German minority populations. The
                    negotiators at Potsdam were well-aware of the situation, and even though the
                    British and Americans feared that a mass exodus of Germans into the western
                    occupation zones would destabilize them, they took no action other than to
                    declare that “any transfers that take place should be effected in an orderly and
                    humane manner” and to request that the Poles, Czechoslovaks and Hungarians
                    temporarily suspend additional deportations. </p>
                <p>In addition to settling matters related to Germany and Poland, the Potsdam
                    negotiators approved the formation of a Council of Foreign Ministers that would
                    act on behalf of the United States, Great Britain, the Soviet Union, and China
                    to draft peace treaties with Germany’s former allies. Conference participants
                    also agreed to revise the 1936 Montreux Convention, which gave Turkey sole
                    control over the Turkish Straits. Furthermore, the United States, Great Britain,
                    and China released the “Potsdam Declaration,” which threatened Japan with
                    “prompt and utter destruction” if it did not immediately surrender (the Soviet
                    Union did not sign the declaration because it had yet to declare war on Japan). </p>
                <p>The Potsdam Conference is perhaps best known for President Truman’s July 24, 1945
                    conversation with Stalin, during which time the President informed the Soviet
                    leader that the United States had successfully detonated the first atomic bomb
                    on July 16, 1945. Historians have often interpreted Truman’s somewhat firm
                    stance during negotiations to the U.S. negotiating team’s belief that U.S.
                    nuclear capability would enhance its bargaining power. Stalin, however, was
                    already well-informed about the U.S. nuclear program thanks to the Soviet
                    intelligence network; so he also held firm in his positions. This situation made
                    negotiations challenging. The leaders of the United States, Great Britain, and
                    the Soviet Union, who, despite their differences, had remained allies throughout
                    the war, never met again collectively to discuss cooperation in postwar
                    reconstruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="un">
                <head>The Formation of the United Nations, <date when="1945">1945</date>
                </head>
                <p>On January 1, 1942, representatives of 26 nations at war with the Axis powers met
                    in <placeName>Washington</placeName> to sign the Declaration of the United
                    Nations endorsing the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/atlantic-conf">Atlantic
                        Charter</ref>, pledging to use their full resources against the Axis and
                    agreeing not to make a separate peace.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="founding-un.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The Founding of the UN in San Francisco</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At the Quebec Conference in August 1943, Secretary of State Cordell Hull and
                    British Foreign Secretary Anthony Eden agreed to draft a declaration that
                    included a call for “a general international organization, based on the
                    principle sovereign equality of all nations.” An agreed declaration was issued
                    after a Foreign Ministers Conference in Moscow in October 1943. When President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> met with Soviet Premier
                        <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName> in <placeName>Tehran, Iran</placeName>,
                    in November 1943, he proposed an international organization comprising an
                    assembly of all member states and a 10-member executive committee to discuss
                    social and economic issues. The United States, Great Britain, Soviet Union, and
                    China would enforce peace as “the four policemen.” Meanwhile Allied
                    representatives founded a set of task-oriented organizations: the Food and
                    Agricultural Organization (May 1943), the United Nations Relief and
                    Rehabilitation Administration (November 1943), the United Nations Educational,
                    Scientific, and Cultural Organization (April 1944), the International Monetary
                    Fund and the World Bank (July 1944), and the International Civil Aviation
                    Organization (November 1944). </p>
                <p> U.S., British, Soviet, and Chinese representatives met at Dumbarton Oaks in
                    Washington in August and September 1944 to draft the charter of a postwar
                    international organization based on the principle of collective security. They
                    recommended a General Assembly of all member states and a Security Council
                    consisting of the Big Four plus six members chosen by the Assembly. Voting
                    procedures and the veto power of permanent members of the Security Council were
                    finalized at the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/yalta-conf">Yalta Conference
                        in 1945</ref> when Roosevelt and Stalin agreed that the veto would not
                    prevent discussions by the Security Council. Roosevelt agreed to General
                    Assembly membership for Ukraine and Byelorussia while reserving the right, which
                    was never exercised, to seek two more votes for the United States. </p>
                <p>Representatives of 50 nations met in San Francisco April-June 1945 to complete
                    the Charter of the United Nations. In addition to the General Assembly of all
                    member states and a Security Council of 5 permanent and 6 non-permanent members,
                    the Charter provided for an 18-member Economic and Social Council, an
                    International Court of Justice, a Trusteeship Council to oversee certain
                    colonial territories, and a Secretariat under a Secretary General. The Roosevelt
                    administration strove to avoid <persName>Woodrow Wilson</persName>’s mistakes in
                    selling the League of Nations to the Senate. It sought bipartisan support and in
                    September 1943 the Republican Party endorsed U.S. participation in a postwar
                    international organization, after which both houses of Congress overwhelmingly
                    endorsed participation. Roosevelt also sought to convince the public that an
                    international organization was the best means to prevent future wars. The Senate
                    approved the UN Charter on July 28, 1945, by a vote of 89 to 2. The United
                    Nations came into existence on October 24, 1945, after 29 nations had ratified
                    the Charter. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
