<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schemas/milestones.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1945–1952</title>
                <title type="short">1945–1952</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc> 
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31" target="#berlin-airlift"/>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1945" to="1952">1945–1952</date>: The Early Cold War</head>
                <p>The United States emerged from World War II as one of the foremost economic,
                    political, and military powers in the world. Wartime production pulled the
                    economy out of depression and propelled it to great profits. In the interest of
                    avoiding another global war, for the first time the United States began to use
                    economic assistance as a strategic element of its foreign policy and offered
                    significant assistance to countries in Europe and Asia struggling to rebuild
                    their shattered economies.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="churchill-speach.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>British Prime Minister Winston Churchill and President Harry Truman at the famous
                        “Iron Curtain” Speech</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In contrast to American unwillingness to politically or militarily entangle
                    itself in the League of Nations, the United States became one of the first
                    members of the international organization designed to promote international
                    security, commerce, and law, the United Nations. The United States also took an
                    active interest in the fate of the colonies the European powers were having
                    difficulty maintaining. In addition to these challenges, the United States faced
                    increasing resistance from the Soviet Union which had rescinded on a number of
                    wartime promises. As the Soviets demonstrated a keen interest in dominating
                    Eastern Europe, the United States took the lead in forming a Western alliance to
                    counterbalance the communist superpower to contain the spread of communism. At
                    the same time, the United States restructured its military and intelligence
                    forces, both of which would have a significant influence in U.S. Cold War
                    policy.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="atomic">
                <head>Atomic Diplomacy</head>
                <p>Atomic diplomacy refers to attempts to use the threat of nuclear warfare to
                    achieve diplomatic goals. After the first successful test of the atomic bomb in
                        <date when="1945">1945</date>, U.S. officials immediately considered the
                    potential non-military benefits that could be derived from the American nuclear
                    monopoly. In the years that followed, there were several occasions in which
                    government officials used or considered atomic diplomacy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="a-bomb.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Atomic bombing of Nagasaki on August 9, 1945</head>
                </figure>
                <p>During the Second World War, the United States, Britain, Germany and the U.S.S.R.
                    were all engaged in scientific research to develop the atomic bomb. By mid-1945,
                    however, only the United States had succeeded, and it used two atomic weapons on
                    the cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki to bring a rapid and conclusive end to the
                    war with Japan. U.S. officials did not debate at length whether to use the
                    atomic bomb against Japan, but argued that it was a means to a faster end to the
                    Pacific conflict that would ensure fewer conventional war casualties. They did,
                    however, consider the role that the bomb’s impressive power could play in
                    postwar U.S. relations with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p> While presiding over the U.S. development of nuclear weapons, President
                        <persName>Franklin Roosevelt</persName> made the decision not to inform the
                    Soviet Union of the technological developments. After Roosevelt’s death,
                    President <persName>Harry Truman</persName> had to decide whether to continue
                    this policy of guarding nuclear information. Ultimately, Truman mentioned the
                    existence of a particularly destructive bomb to Soviet Premier Joseph Stalin at
                    the Allied meeting at Postdam, but he did not provide specifics about the weapon
                    or its uses. By mid-1945, it was clear the Soviet Union would enter into the war
                    in the Pacific and thereby be in a position to influence the postwar balance of
                    power in the region. U.S. officials recognized there was little chance of
                    preventing this, although they preferred a U.S.-led occupation of Japan rather
                    than a co-occupation as had been arranged for Germany. Some U.S. policymakers
                    hoped that the U.S. monopoly on nuclear technology and the demonstration of its
                    destructive power in Japan might influence the Soviets to make concessions,
                    either in Asia or in Europe. Truman did not threaten Stalin with the bomb,
                    recognizing instead that its existence alone would limit Soviet options and be
                    considered a threat to Soviet security.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="potsdam.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>The Potsdam Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Scholars debate the extent to which Truman’s mention of the bomb at <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/potsdam-conf">Potsdam</ref> and his use of the
                    weapon in Japan represent atomic diplomacy. In 1965, historian Gar Alperovitz
                    published a book which argued that the use of nuclear weapons on the Japanese
                    cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki was intended to gain a stronger position for
                    postwar diplomatic bargaining with the Soviet Union, as the weapons themselves
                    were not needed to force the Japanese surrender. Other scholars disagree, and
                    suggest that Truman thought the bomb necessary to achieve the unconditional
                    surrender of recalcitrant Japanese military leaders determined to fight to the
                    death. Even if Truman did not intend to use the implied threat of the weapon to
                    gain the upper hand over Stalin, the fact of the U.S. atomic monopoly following
                    the successful atomic test at Alamogordo, New Mexico in July of 1945 seemed to
                    have bolstered his confidence at subsequent meetings, making him more determined
                    to obtain compromises from the Soviet government. Even so, if U.S. officials
                    hoped that the threat of the bomb would soften Soviet resistance to American
                    proposals for free elections in Eastern Europe or reduced Soviet control over
                    the Balkans, they were disappointed, as the security issues raised by the dawn
                    of the atomic age likely made the Soviet Union even more anxious to protect its
                    borders with a controlled buffer zone.</p>
                <p>In the years that immediately followed the Second World War, the U.S. confidence
                    in its nuclear monopoly had ramifications for its diplomatic agenda. The fact of
                    the bomb was useful in ensuring that Western Europe would rely on the United
                    States to guarantee its security rather than seeking an outside accommodation
                    with the Soviet Union, because even if the United States did not station large
                    numbers of troops on the continent, it could protect the region by placing it
                    under the American “nuclear umbrella” of areas that the United States professed
                    to be willing to use the bomb to defend. The U.S. insistence on hegemony in the
                    occupation and rehabilitation of Japan stemmed in part from the confidence of
                    being the sole nuclear power and in part from what that nuclear power had
                    gained: Japan’s total surrender to U.S. forces. Though it inspired greater
                    confidence in the immediate postwar years, the U.S. nuclear monopoly was not of
                    long duration; the Soviet Union successfully exploded its first atomic bomb in
                    1949, the United Kingdom in 1952, France in 1960 and the People’s Republic of
                    China in 1964.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="b-29.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>B-29 Bomber</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the first two decades of the Cold War, there were a number of occasions during
                    which a form of atomic diplomacy was employed by either side of the conflict.
                    During the Berlin Blockade of <date from="1948" to="1949">1948–49</date>,
                    President Truman transferred several B-29 bombers capable of delivering nuclear
                    bombs to the region to signal to the Soviet Union that the United States was
                    both capable of implementing a nuclear attack and willing to execute it if it
                    became necessary. During the Korean War, President Truman once again deployed
                    the B-29s to signal U.S. resolve. In 1953, President <persName>Dwight D.
                        Eisenhower</persName> considered, but ultimately rejected the idea of using
                    nuclear coercion to further negotiations on the cease fire agreement that ended
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/korean-war">war in Korea</ref>. In an
                    about face, in 1962, the Soviet deployment of nuclear missiles to Cuba in order
                    to try to force U.S. concessions on Europe became another example of atomic
                    diplomacy.</p>
                <p>By the time the United States was attempting to disengage from the war in
                    Vietnam, however, the idea of atomic diplomacy had lost credibility. By the
                    mid-1960s, the United States and the Soviet Union had achieved approximate
                    parity, and their security was based on the principle of mutually assured
                    destruction. Because neither could make the first strike without the threat of a
                    counterstrike, the benefits of using nuclear weapons in a conflict—even in a
                    proxy war—were greatly diminished. So although President Nixon briefly
                    considered using the threat of the bomb to help bring about an end to the war in
                    Vietnam, he realized that that there remained the threat that the Soviet Union
                    would retaliate against the United States on behalf of North Vietnam and that
                    both international and domestic public opinion would never accept the use of the
                    bomb.</p>
                <p>In spite of the many threats made over the course of the Cold War, atomic weapons
                    were not used in any conflict after the Second World War. Although the existence
                    of nuclear weapons could continue to act as a deterrent, their diplomatic
                    utility had its limits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="nuremberg">
                <head>The Nuremberg Trial and the Tokyo War Crimes Trials (1945–1948) </head>
                <p>Following World War II, the victorious Allied governments established the first
                    international criminal tribunals to prosecute high-level political officials and
                    military authorities for war crimes and other wartime atrocities. The four major
                    Allied powers—France, the Soviet Union, the United Kingdom, and the United
                    States—set up the International Military Tribunal (IMT) in Nuremberg, Germany,
                    to prosecute and punish “the major war criminals of the European Axis.” The IMT
                    presided over a combined trial of senior Nazi political and military leaders, as
                    well as several Nazi organizations. The lesser-known International Military
                    Tribunal for the Far East (IMTFE) was created in Tokyo, Japan, pursuant to a
                    1946 proclamation by U.S. Army General Douglas MacArthur, Supreme Commander for
                    the Allied Powers in occupied Japan. The IMTFE presided over a series of trials
                    of senior Japanese political and military leaders pursuant to its authority “to
                    try and punish Far Eastern war criminals.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url=""/>
                    <head>Needs caption</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The origins, composition, and jurisdiction of the Nuremberg and Tokyo tribunals
                    differed in several important respects beyond their geographical differences and
                    personalities. Plans to prosecute German political and military leaders were
                    announced in the 1942 St. James Declaration. In the declaration, the United
                    States joined Australia, Canada, China, India, New Zealand, the Union of South
                    Africa, the Soviet Union, and nine exiled governments of German-occupied
                    countries to condemn Germany’s “policy of aggression.” The Declaration stated
                    that these governments “placed among their principal war aims the punishment,
                    through the channel of organized justice, of those guilty of or responsible for
                    these crimes, whether they have ordered them, perpetrated them or participated
                    in them.”</p>
                <p>In August 1945, the four major Allied powers therefore signed the 1945 London
                    Agreement, which established the IMT. The following additional countries
                    subsequently “adhered” to the agreement to show their support: Australia,
                    Belgium, Czechoslovakia, Denmark, Ethiopia, Greece, Haiti, Honduras, India,
                    Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Panama, Paraguay, Poland,
                    Uruguay, and Yugoslavia.</p>
                <p>The Charter of the International Military Tribunal (or Nuremberg Charter) was
                    annexed to the 1945 London Agreement and outlined the tribunal’s constitution,
                    functions, and jurisdiction. The Nuremberg tribunal consisted of one judge from
                    each of the Allied powers, which each also supplied a prosecution team. The
                    Nuremberg Charter also provided that the IMT had the authority to try and punish
                    persons who “committed any of the following crimes:”</p>
                <list type="simple">
                    <item>(a) Crimes Against Peace: namely, planning, preparation, initiation or
                        waging of a war of aggression, or a war in violation of international
                        treaties, agreements or assurances, or participation in a Common Plan or
                        Conspiracy for the accomplishment of any of the foregoing;</item>
                    <item>(b) War Crimes: namely, violations of the laws or customs of war. Such
                        violations shall include, but not be limited to, murder, ill-treatment or
                        deportation to slave labor or for any other purpose of civilian population
                        of or in occupied territory, murder or ill-treatment of prisoners of war or
                        persons on the seas, killing of hostages, plunder of public or private
                        property, wanton destruction of cities, towns, or villages, or devastation
                        not justified by military necessity;</item>
                    <item>(c) Crimes Against Humanity: namely, murder, extermination, enslavement,
                        deportation, and other inhumane acts committed against any civilian
                        population, before or during the war, or persecutions on political, racial,
                        or religious grounds in execution of or in connection with any crime within
                        the jurisdiction of the Tribunal, whether or not in violation of domestic
                        law of the country where perpetrated.</item>
                </list>
                <p>The IMT prosecutors indicted twenty-two senior German political and military
                    leaders, including Hermann Goering, Rudolph Hess, Joachim von Ribbentrop, Alfred
                    Rosenberg, and Albert Speer. Nazi leader Adolf Hitler was not indicted because
                    he had committed suicide in April 1945, in the final days before Germany’s
                    surrender. Seven Nazi organizations also were indicted. The prosecutors sought
                    to have the tribunal declare that these organizations were “criminal
                    organizations” in order to facilitate the later prosecution of their members by
                    other tribunals or courts.</p>
                <p>The Nuremberg Trial lasted from November 1945 to October 1946. The tribunal found
                    nineteen individual defendants guilty and sentenced them to punishments that
                    ranged from death by hanging to fifteen years’ imprisonment. Three defendants
                    were found not guilty, one committed suicide prior to trial, and one did not
                    stand trial due to physical or mental illness. The Nuremberg Tribunal also
                    concluded that three of the seven indicted Nazi organizations were “criminal
                    organizations” under the terms of the Charter: the Leadership Corps of the Nazi
                    party; the elite “SS” unit, which carried out the forced transfer, enslavement,
                    and extermination of millions of persons in concentration camps; and the Nazi
                    security police and the Nazi secret police, commonly known as the ‘SD’ and
                    ‘Gestapo,’ respectively, which had instituted slave labor programs and deported
                    Jews, political opponents, and other civilians to concentration camps.</p>
                <p>Unlike the IMT, the IMTFE was not created by an international agreement, but it
                    nonetheless emerged from international agreements to try Japanese war criminals.
                    In July 1945, China, the United Kingdom, and the United States signed the
                    Potsdam Declaration, in which they demanded Japan’s “unconditional surrender”
                    and stated that “stern justice shall be meted out to all war criminals.” At the
                    time that the Potsdam Declaration was signed, the war in Europe had ended but
                    the war with Japan was continuing. The Soviet Union did not sign the declaration
                    because it did not declare war on Japan until weeks later, on the same day that
                    the United States dropped the second atomic bomb at Nagasaki. Japan surrendered
                    six days later, on August 14, 1945.</p>
                <p>At the subsequent Moscow Conference, held in December 1945, the Soviet Union, the
                    United Kingdom, and the United States (with concurrence from China) agreed to a
                    basic structure for the occupation of Japan. General MacArthur, as Supreme
                    Commander of the Allied Powers, was granted authority to “issue all orders for
                    the implementation of the Terms of Surrender, the occupation and control of
                    Japan, and all directives supplementary thereto.”</p>
                <p>In January 1946, acting pursuant to this authority, General MacArthur issued a
                    special proclamation that established the IMTFE. The Charter for the
                    International Military Tribunal for the Far East was annexed to the
                    proclamation. Like the Nuremberg Charter, it laid out the composition,
                    jurisdiction, and functions of the tribunal.</p>
                <p>The Charter provided for MacArthur to appoint judges to the IMTFE from the
                    countries that had signed Japan’s instrument of surrender: Australia, Canada,
                    China, France, India, the Netherlands, Philippines, the Soviet Union, the United
                    Kingdom, and the United States. Each of these countries also had a prosecution
                    team.</p>
                <p> As with the IMT, the IMTFE had jurisdiction to try individuals for Crimes
                    Against Peace, War Crimes, and Crimes Against Humanity, and the definitions were
                    nearly verbatim to those contained in the Nuremberg Charter. The IMTFE
                    nonetheless had jurisdiction over crimes that occurred over a greater period of
                    time, from the 1931 Japanese invasion of Manchuria to Japan’s 1945
                    surrender.</p>
                <p>The IMTFE presided over the prosecution of nine senior Japanese political leaders
                    and eighteen military leaders. A Japanese scholar also was indicted, but charges
                    against him were dropped during the trial because he was declared unfit due to
                    mental illness. Japanese Emperor Hirohito and other members of the imperial
                    family were not indicted. In fact, the Allied powers permitted Hirohito to
                    retain his position on the throne, albeit with diminished status.</p>
                <p>The Tokyo War Crimes Trials took place from May 1946 to November 1948. The IMTFE
                    found all remaining defendants guilty and sentenced them to punishments ranging
                    from death to seven years’ imprisonment; two defendants died during the
                    trial.</p>
                <p>After the Nuremberg and Tokyo War Crimes trials, additional trials were held to
                    try “minor” war criminals. These subsequent trials, however, were not held by
                    international tribunals but instead by domestic courts or by tribunals operated
                    by a single Allied power, such as military commissions. In Germany, for example,
                    each of the Allied powers held trials for alleged war criminals found within
                    their respective zones of occupation. The United States held twelve such trials
                    from 1945 to 1949, each of which combined defendants who were accused of similar
                    acts or had participated in related events. These trials also were held in
                    Nuremberg and thus became known informally as the “subsequent Nuremberg trials.”
                    In Japan, several additional trials were held in cities outside Tokyo.</p>
                <p>The Nuremberg and Tokyo tribunals contributed significantly to the development of
                    international criminal law, then in its infancy. For several decades, these
                    tribunals stood as the only examples of international war crimes tribunals, but
                    they ultimately served as models for a new series of international criminal
                    tribunals that were established beginning in the 1990s. In addition, the
                    Nuremberg Charter’s reference to “crimes against peace,” “war crimes,” and
                    “crimes against humanity” represented the first time these terms were used and
                    defined in an adopted international instrument. These terms and definitions were
                    adopted nearly verbatim in the Charter of the IMTFE, but have been replicated
                    and expanded in a succession of international legal instruments since that
                    time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="japan-reconstruction">
                <head>Occupation and Reconstruction of Japan, <date from="1945" to="1952">1945–52</date>
                </head>
                <p>After the defeat of <placeName>Japan</placeName> in World War II, the United
                    States led the Allies in the occupation and rehabilitation of the Japanese
                    state. Between 1945 and 1952, the U.S. occupying forces, led by General Douglas
                    A. MacArthur, enacted widespread military, political, economic, and social
                    reforms.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="japan.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Allied Occupation in Japan after WWII</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The groundwork for the Allied occupation of a defeated Japan was laid during the
                    war. In a <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/war-time-conferences">series of
                        wartime conferences</ref>, the leaders of the Allied powers of Great
                    Britain, the Soviet Union, the Republic of China, and the United States
                    discussed how to disarm Japan, deal with its colonies (especially Korea and
                    Taiwan), stabilize the Japanese economy, and prevent the remilitarization of the
                    state in the future. In the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/potsdam-conf">Potsdam Declaration</ref>, they called for Japan’s unconditional surrender;
                    by August of 1945, that objective had been achieved.</p>
                <p>In September, 1945, General <persName>Douglas MacArthur</persName> took charge of
                    the Supreme Command of Allied Powers (SCAP) and began the work of rebuilding
                    Japan. Although Great Britain, the Soviet Union, and the Republic of China had
                    an advisory role as part of an “Allied Council,” MacArthur had the final
                    authority to make all decisions. The occupation of Japan can be divided into
                    three phases: the initial effort to punish and reform Japan, the work to revive
                    the Japanese economy, and the conclusion of a formal peace treaty and
                    alliance.</p>
                <p>The first phase, roughly from the end of the war in 1945 through 1947, involved
                    the most fundamental changes for the Japanese Government and society. The Allies
                    punished Japan for its past militarism and expansion by convening war crimes
                    trials in Tokyo. At the same time, SCAP dismantled the Japanese army and banned
                    former military officers from taking roles of political leadership in the new
                    government. In the economic field, SCAP introduced land reform, designed to
                    benefit the majority tenant farmers and reduce the power of rich landowners,
                    many of whom had advocated for war and supported Japanese expansionism in the
                    1930s. MacArthur also tried to break up the large Japanese business
                    conglomerates, or zaibatsu, as part of the effort to transform the economy into
                    a free market capitalist system. In 1947, Allied advisors essentially dictated a
                    new constitution to Japan’s leaders. Some of the most profound changes in the
                    document included downgrading the emperor’s status to that of a figurehead
                    without political control and placing more power in the parliamentary system,
                    promoting greater rights and privileges for women, and renouncing the right to
                    wage war, which involved eliminating all non-defensive armed forces.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="macarthur-hirohito.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>General MacArthur and Japanese Emperor Hirohito</head>
                </figure>
                <p>By late 1947 and early 1948, the emergence of an economic crisis in Japan
                    alongside concerns about the spread of communism sparked a reconsideration of
                    occupation policies. This period is sometimes called the “reverse course.” In
                    this stage of the occupation, which lasted until 1950, the economic
                    rehabilitation of Japan took center stage. SCAP became concerned that a weak
                    Japanese economy would increase the influence of the domestic communist
                    movement, and with a communist victory in China’s civil war increasingly likely,
                    the future of East Asia appeared to be at stake. Occupation policies to address
                    the weakening economy ranged from tax reforms to measures aimed at controlling
                    inflation. However the most serious problem was the shortage of raw materials
                    required to feed Japanese industries and markets for finished goods. The
                    outbreak of the Korean War in 1950 provided SCAP with just the opportunity it
                    needed to address this problem, prompting some occupation officials to suggest
                    that, <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/korean-war">“Korea came along and saved
                        us.”</ref> After the UN entered the Korean War, Japan became the principal
                    supply depot for UN forces. The conflict also placed Japan firmly within the
                    confines of the U.S. defense perimeter in Asia, assuring the Japanese leadership
                    that whatever the state of its military, no real threat would be made against
                    Japanese soil.</p>
                <p>In the third phase of the occupation, beginning in 1950, SCAP deemed the
                    political and economic future of Japan firmly established and set about securing
                    a formal peace treaty to end both the war and the occupation. The U.S.
                    perception of international threats had changed so profoundly in the years
                    between 1945 and 1950 that the idea of a re-armed and militant Japan no longer
                    alarmed U.S. officials; instead, the real threat appeared to be the creep of
                    communism, particularly in Asia. The final agreement allowed the United States
                    to maintain its bases in Okinawa and elsewhere in Japan, and the U.S. Government
                    promised Japan a bilateral security pact. In September of 1951, fifty-two
                    nations met in San Francisco to discuss the treaty, and ultimately, forty-nine
                    of them signed it. Notable holdouts included the USSR, Poland and
                    Czechoslovakia, all of which objected to the promise to support the Republic of
                    China and not do business with the People’s Republic of China that was forced on
                    Japan by U.S. politicians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="baruch-plans">
                <head>The Acheson-Lilienthal &amp; Baruch Plans, <date when="1946">1946</date>
                </head>
                <p>On June 14, 1946, before a session of the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission
                    (UNAEC), U.S. representative <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/baruch-herman-benjamin">Bernard
                        Baruch</ref>, presented a proposal for the creation of an international
                    Atomic Development Authority. The presentation of the Baruch Plan marked the
                    culmination of an effort to establish international oversight of the use of
                    atomic energy in the hopes of avoiding unchecked proliferation of nuclear power
                    in the post World War II period.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="churchill-baruch.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head> Winston Churchill and Bernard Baruch talk in car in front of Baruch’s
                        home, 14 April 1961</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The immediate origins of this effort can be traced to the Conference of Foreign
                    Ministers held in Moscow between December 16 and 26, 1945. There representatives
                    from the United States, Great Britain, and the Soviet Union created a United
                    Nations commission to advise on the destruction of all existing atomic weapons
                    and to work toward using atomic energy for peaceful purposes. The resulting
                    body, the UNAEC, was created on January 24, 1946, with six permanent members
                    (the United States, Britain, France, the Soviet Union, China, and Canada) and
                    six rotating members.</p>
                <p>That same month, U.S. Secretary of State <persName>James Byrnes</persName>
                    created a special advisory committee, whose members included Under-Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/acheson-dean-gooderham">Dean
                        Acheson</ref> and the Chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority David
                    Lilienthal, to compose a report that the U.S. Government would present to the
                    UNAEC. The committee presented their report to Secretary Byrnes in March.</p>
                <p>The so-called Acheson-Lilienthal report, written in large part by the committee’s
                    chief scientific consult, Robert Oppenheimer, called for the creation of the
                    Atomic Development Authority to oversee the mining and use of fissile materials,
                    the operation of all nuclear facilities that could produce weaponry, and the
                    right to dispense licenses to those countries wishing to pursue peaceful nuclear
                    research. The plan relied on Soviet-American cooperation, since its authors
                    recognized that the Soviet Union was unlikely to cede its veto power in the
                    United Nations Security Council over any matter. Moreover, it made no mention of
                    when the United States should destroy its nuclear arsenal, though it did
                    acknowledge that doing so was a necessity.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="sh-acheson-dean.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Dean Acheson</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The day before the United States submitted the Acheson-Lilienthal report to the
                    United Nations, President Truman appointed Bernard Baruch as the American
                    delegate to the UNAEC. Truman considered Baruch to be a capable negotiator who
                    would vigorously defend the interests of the United States. Given the cooling
                    relationship between the Soviet Union and the United States, President Truman
                    did not want to accept any international agreement that might force the United
                    States to abolish its nuclear weapons program without assurances that the Soviet
                    Union would be unable to produce its own atomic bomb.</p>
                <p>Baruch presented a slightly different plan to the UNEAC. Under the Baruch Plan
                    the Atomic Development Authority would oversee the development and use of atomic
                    energy, manage any nuclear installation with the ability to produce nuclear
                    weapons, and inspect any nuclear facility conducting research for peaceful
                    purposes. The plan also prohibited the illegal possession of an atomic bomb, the
                    seizure of facilities administered by the Atomic Development Authority, and
                    punished violators who interfered with inspections. The Atomic Development
                    Authority would answer only to the Security Council, which was charged with
                    punishing those nations that violated the terms of the plan by imposing
                    sanctions. Most importantly, the Baruch Plan would have stripped all members of
                    the United Nations Security Council of their veto power concerning the issue of
                    United Nations sanctions against nations that engaged in prohibited activities.
                    Once the plan was fully implemented, the United States was to begin the process
                    of destroying its nuclear arsenal.</p>
                <p>The Soviets strongly opposed any plan that allowed the United States to retain
                    its nuclear monopoly, not to mention international inspections of Soviet
                    domestic nuclear facilities. The Soviets also rejected the idea of surrendering
                    their Security Council veto over any issue as they argued that the council was
                    already stacked in favor the United States.</p>
                <p>By September 17, Baruch confessed to President Truman that he feared there was no
                    possibility of reaching an agreement before the end of the year, at which point
                    there would be a rotation of the non-permanent members of the UNAEC.
                    Nevertheless, Baruch worried that delaying a vote until after the rotation of
                    the members would destroy any chance of passing a resolution to create an Atomic
                    Development Authority. As such, Baruch pushed for a formal vote before the end
                    of the year in the hopes that, even if it did not pass, it would demonstrate the
                    unreasonableness of the Soviet Union’s objections to a proposal that would spare
                    the world a nuclear arms race. The vote was held on December 30, with 10 of the
                    UNAEC’s 12 members in favor, while the other two members (the Soviet Union and
                    Poland) abstained. The vote required unanimity to pass. As such, the Polish and
                    Soviet abstentions thwarted the adoption of the Baruch Plan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="truman-doctrine">
                <head>The Truman Doctrine, <date when="1947">1947</date>
                </head>
                <p>With the Truman Doctrine, President <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName>
                    established that the United States would provide political, military and
                    economic assistance to all democratic nations under threat from external or
                    internal authoritarian forces. The Truman Doctrine effectively reoriented U.S.
                    foreign policy, away from its usual stance of withdrawal from regional conflicts
                    not directly involving the United States, to one of possible intervention in far
                    away conflicts.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="truman-harry.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Harry Truman</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Truman Doctrine arose from a speech delivered by President Truman before a
                    joint session of Congress on <date when="1947-03-12">March 12, 1947</date>. The
                    immediate cause for the speech was a recent announcement by the British
                    Government that, as of March 31, it would no longer provide military and
                    economic assistance to the Greek Government in its civil war against the Greek
                    Communist Party. Truman asked Congress to support the Greek Government against
                    the Communists. He also asked Congress to provide assistance for Turkey, since
                    that nation, too, had previously been dependent on British aid.</p>
                <p>At the time, the U.S. Government believed that the Soviet Union supported the
                    Greek Communist war effort and worried that if the Communists prevailed in the
                    Greek civil war, the Soviets would ultimately influence Greek policy. In fact,
                    Soviet leader <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName> had deliberately refrained from
                    providing any support to the Greek Communists and had forced Yugoslav Prime
                    Minister <persName>Josip Tito</persName> to follow suit, much to the detriment
                    of Soviet-Yugoslav relations. However, a number of other foreign policy problems
                    also influenced President Truman’s decision to actively aid Greece and Turkey.
                    In 1946, four setbacks, in particular, had served to effectively torpedo any
                    chance of achieving a durable post-war rapprochement with the Soviet Union: the
                    Soviets’ failure to withdraw their troops from northern Iran in early 1946 (as
                    per the terms of the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945/tehran-conf">Tehran
                        Declaration of 1943</ref>); Soviet attempts to pressure the Iranian
                    Government into granting them oil concessions while supposedly fomenting
                    irredentism by Azerbaijani separatists in northern Iran; Soviet efforts to force
                    the Turkish Government into granting them base and transit rights through the
                    Turkish Straits; and, the Soviet Government’s rejection of the Baruch plan for
                    international control over nuclear energy and weapons in June 1946.</p>
                <p>In light of the deteriorating relationship with the Soviet Union and the
                    appearance of Soviet meddling in Greek and Turkish affairs, the withdrawal of
                    British assistance to Greece provided the necessary catalyst for the Truman
                    Administration to reorient American foreign policy. Accordingly, in his speech,
                    President Truman requested that Congress provide $400,000,000 worth of aid to
                    both the Greek and Turkish Governments and support the dispatch of American
                    civilian and military personnel and equipment to the region.</p>
                <p>Truman justified his request on two grounds. He argued that a Communist victory
                    in the Greek Civil War would endanger the political stability of Turkey, which
                    would undermine the political stability of the Middle East. This could not be
                    allowed in light of the region’s immense strategic importance to U.S. national
                    security. Truman also argued that the United States was compelled to assist
                    “free peoples” in their struggles against “totalitarian regimes,” because the
                    spread of authoritarianism would “undermine the foundations of international
                    peace and hence the security of the United States.” In the words of the Truman
                    Doctrine, it became “the policy of the United States to support free peoples who
                    are resisting attempted subjugation by armed minorities or by outside
                    pressures.”</p>
                <p>Truman argued that the United States could no longer stand by and allow the
                    forcible expansion of Soviet totalitarianism into free, independent nations,
                    because American national security now depended upon more than just the physical
                    security of American territory. Rather, in a sharp break with its traditional
                    avoidance of extensive foreign commitments beyond the Western Hemisphere during
                    peacetime, the Truman Doctrine committed the United States to actively offering
                    assistance to preserve the political integrity of democratic nations when such
                    an offer was deemed to be in the best interest of the United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="national-security-act">
                <head>National Security Act of <date when="1947">1947</date>
                </head>
                <p>The National Security Act of 1947 mandated a major reorganization of the foreign
                    policy and military establishments of the U.S. Government. The act created many
                    of the institutions that Presidents found useful when formulating and
                    implementing foreign policy, including the National Security Council (NSC).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="sh-nsa-act.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President signing the National Security Act into Law</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Council itself included the President, Vice President, Secretary of State,
                    Secretary of Defense, and other members (such as the Director of the Central
                    Intelligence Agency), who met at the White House to discuss both long-term
                    problems and more immediate national security crises. A small NSC staff was
                    hired to coordinate foreign policy materials from other agencies for the
                    President. Beginning in 1953 the President’s Assistant for National Security
                    Affairs directed this staff. Each President has accorded the NSC with different
                    degrees of importance and has given the NSC staff varying levels of autonomy and
                    influence over other agencies such as the Departments of State and Defense.
                    President Dwight D. Eisenhower, for example, used the NSC meetings to make key
                    foreign policy decisions, while <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and
                        <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> preferred to work more informally
                    through trusted associates. Under President Richard M. Nixon, the NSC staff,
                    then headed by <persName>Henry A. Kissinger</persName>, was transformed from a
                    coordinating body into an organization that actively engaged in negotiations
                    with foreign leaders and implementing the President’s decisions. The NSC
                    meetings themselves, however, were infrequent and merely confirmed decisions
                    already agreed upon by Nixon and Kissinger.</p>
                <p>The act also established the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), which grew out of
                    World War II era Office of Strategic Services and small post-war intelligence
                    organizations. The CIA served as the primary civilian intelligence-gathering
                    organization in the government. Later, the Defense Intelligence Agency became
                    the main military intelligence body. The 1947 law also caused far-reaching
                    changes in the military establishment. The War Department and Navy Department
                    merged into a single Department of Defense under the Secretary of Defense, who
                    also directed the newly created Department of the Air Force. However, each of
                    the three branches maintained their own service secretaries. In 1949 the act was
                    amended to give the Secretary of Defense more power over the individual services
                    and their secretaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="kennan">
                <head>Kennan and Containment, <date when="1947">1947</date>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kennan-george-frost">George F.
                        Kennan</ref>, a career Foreign Service Officer, formulated the policy of
                    “containment,” the basic United States strategy for fighting the cold war
                    (1947–1989) with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <!--<figure>
                    <graphic url="mkennan.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Artistic rendering of Secretary of State George F. Kennan</head>
                </figure>-->
                <p>Kennan’s ideas, which became the basis of the Truman administration’s foreign
                    policy, first came to public attention in 1947 in the form of an anonymous
                    contribution to the journal <hi rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi>, the
                    so-called “X-Article.” “The main element of any United States policy toward the
                    Soviet Union,” Kennan wrote, “must be that of a long-term, patient but firm and
                    vigilant containment of Russian expansive tendencies.” To that end, he called
                    for countering “Soviet pressure against the free institutions of the Western
                    world” through the “adroit and vigilant application of counter-force at a series
                    of constantly shifting geographical and political points, corresponding to the
                    shifts and maneuvers of Soviet policy.” Such a policy, Kennan predicted, would
                    “promote tendencies which must eventually find their outlet in either the
                    break-up or the gradual mellowing of Soviet power.”</p>
                <p>Kennan’s policy was controversial from the very beginning. Columnist
                        <persName>Walter Lippmann</persName> attacked the X-Article for failing to
                    differentiate between vital and peripheral interests. The United States,
                    Kennan’s article implied, should face down the Soviet Union and its Communist
                    allies whenever and wherever they posed a risk of gaining influence. In fact,
                    Kennan advocated defending above all else the world’s major centers of
                    industrial power against Soviet expansion: Western Europe, Japan, and the United
                    States. Others criticized Kennan’s policy for being too defensive. Most notably,
                        <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                        Dulles</ref> declared during the 1952 election campaign that the United
                    States’ policy should not be containment, but the “rollback” of Soviet power and
                    the eventual “liberation” of Eastern Europe. Even within the Truman
                    administration there was a rift over containment between Kennan and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/nitze-paul-henry">Paul Nitze</ref>,
                    Kennan’s successor as director of the Policy Planning Staff. Nitze, who saw the
                    Soviet threat primarily in military terms, interpreted Kennan’s call for “the
                    adroit and vigilant application of counter-force” to mean the use of military
                    power. In contrast, Kennan, who considered the Soviet threat to be primarily
                    political, advocated above all else economic assistance (e.g., the Marshall
                    Plan) and “psychological warfare” (overt propaganda and covert operations) to
                    counter the spread of Soviet influence. In 1950, Nitze’s conception of
                    containment won out over Kennan’s. NSC 68, a policy document prepared by the
                    National Security Council and signed by Truman, called for a drastic expansion
                    of the U.S. military budget. The paper also expanded containment’s scope beyond
                    the defense of major centers of industrial power to encompass the entire world.
                    “In the context of the present polarization of power,” it read, “a defeat of
                    free institutions anywhere is a defeat everywhere.”</p>
                <p>Despite all the criticisms and the various policy defeats that Kennan suffered in
                    the early 1950’s, containment in the more general sense of blocking the
                    expansion of Soviet influence remained the basic strategy of the United States
                    throughout the cold war. On the one hand, the United States did not withdraw
                    into isolationism; on the other, it did not move to “roll back” Soviet power, as
                    John Foster Dulles briefly advocated. It is possible to say that each succeeding
                    administration after Truman’s, until the collapse of communism in 1989, adopted
                    a variation of Kennan’s containment policy and made it their own.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="marshall-plan">
                <head>Marshall Plan, <date when="1948">1948</date>
                </head>
                <p>In the immediate post-World War II period, Europe remained ravaged by war and
                    thus susceptible to exploitation by an internal and external Communist threat.
                    In a June 5, 1947, speech to the graduating class at Harvard University,
                    Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/marshall-george-catlett">George C.
                        Marshall</ref> issued a call for a comprehensive program to rebuild Europe.
                    Fanned by the fear of Communist expansion and the rapid deterioration of
                    European economies in the winter of 1946–1947, Congress passed the Economic
                    Cooperation Act in March 1948 and approved funding that would eventually rise to
                    over $12 billion for the rebuilding of Western Europe.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="marshall-plan.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>First page of the Marshall Plan</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Marshall Plan generated a resurgence of European industrialization and
                    brought extensive investment into the region. It was also a stimulant to the
                    U.S. economy by establishing markets for American goods. Although the
                    participation of the Soviet Union and East European nations was an initial
                    possibility, Soviet concern over potential U.S. economic domination of its
                    Eastern European satellites and Stalin’s unwillingness to open up his secret
                    society to westerners doomed the idea. Furthermore, it is unlikely that the U.S.
                    Congress would have been willing to fund the plan as generously as it did if aid
                    also went to Soviet Bloc Communist nations.</p>
                <p>Thus the Marshall Plan was applied solely to <placeName>Western
                        Europe</placeName>, precluding any measure of Soviet Bloc cooperation.
                    Increasingly, the economic revival of Western Europe, especially West Germany,
                    was viewed suspiciously in Moscow. Economic historians have debated the precise
                    impact of the Marshall Plan on Western Europe, but these differing opinions do
                    not detract from the fact that the Marshall Plan has been recognized as a great
                    humanitarian effort. Secretary of State Marshall became the only general ever to
                    receive a Nobel Prize for peace. The Marshall Plan also institutionalized and
                    legitimized the concept of U.S. foreign aid programs, which have become a
                    integral part of U.S. foreign policy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="berlin-airlift" ana="truman-harry-s marshall-george-catlett germany russia collective-security foreign-aid north-atlantic-treaty-organization alliances quarantine-blockade">
                <head>The Berlin Airlift, 1948–1949</head>
                <p>At the end of the Second World War, U.S., British, and Soviet military forces
                    divided and occupied Germany. Also divided into occupation zones, Berlin was
                    located far inside Soviet-controlled eastern Germany. The United States, United
                    Kingdom, and France controlled western portions of the city, while Soviet troops
                    controlled the eastern sector. As the wartime alliance between the Western
                    Allies and the Soviet Union ended and friendly relations turned hostile, the
                    question of whether the western occupation zones in Berlin would remain under
                    Western Allied control or whether the city would be absorbed into
                    Soviet-controlled eastern Germany led to the first Berlin crisis of the Cold
                    War. The crisis started on June 24, 1948, when Soviet forces blockaded rail,
                    road, and water access to Allied-controlled areas of Berlin. The United States
                    and United Kingdom responded by airlifting food and fuel to Berlin from Allied
                    airbases in western Germany. The crisis ended on May 12, 1949, when Soviet
                    forces lifted the blockade on land access to western Berlin.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="berlin-airlift.jpg" height="450px" width="360px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Navy and Air Force aircrafts unload at Tempelhof Airport during the
                        Berlin Airlift. (U.S. Air Force)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The crisis was a result of competing occupation policies and rising tensions
                    between Western powers and the Soviet Union. After the end of the Second World
                    War, the future of postwar Germany was plagued by the divisions within and
                    between Allied powers. The only decision of significance that emerged from
                    wartime planning was the agreement of zones of occupation. Even after the end of
                    hostilities, the problem of what to do about Germany was not successfully
                    addressed at the July 1945 Potsdam Conference. Not only was there a lack of
                    consistency in the political leadership and policymaking among the British and
                    the Americans, occupation policy on the ground also confronted unforeseen
                    challenges. Two and a half million Berliners, spread between four zones of
                    occupation, faced profound privations: Allied bombing had reduced the city to
                    rubble, shelter and warmth were scarce, the black market dominated the city’s
                    economic life, and starvation loomed. While mired in such conditions, Berlin
                    emerged as a forward salient in the Western struggle against the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>The year 1947 saw major shifts in occupation policy in Germany. On January 1, the
                    United States and United Kingdom unified their respective zones and formed <hi rend="italic">Bizonia</hi>, which caused tensions between East and West to
                    escalate. In March, the breakdown of the Moscow Conference of Foreign Ministers
                    and the enunciation of the Truman Doctrine served to harden the lines of an
                    increasingly bipolar international order. In June, Secretary of State George
                    Marshall announced the European Recovery Program. The purpose of the Marshall
                    Plan—as the program came to be called—was not only to support economic recovery
                    in Western Europe, but also to create a bulwark against Communism by drawing
                    participating states into the United States’ economic orbit.</p>
                <p>In early 1948, the United States, United Kingdom, and France secretly began to
                    plan the creation of a new German state made up of the Western Allies’
                    occupation zones. In March, when the Soviets discovered these designs, they
                    withdrew from the Allied Control Council, which had met regularly since the end
                    of the war in order to coordinate occupation policy between zones. In June,
                    without informing the Soviets, U.S. and British policymakers introduced the new
                    Deutschmark to Bizonia and West Berlin. The purpose of the currency reform was
                    to wrest economic control of the city from the Soviets, enable the introduction
                    of Marshall Plan aid, and curb the city’s black market. Soviet authorities
                    responded with similar moves in their zone. Besides issuing their own currency,
                    the Ostmark, the Soviets blocked all major road, rail, and canal links to West
                    Berlin, thus starving it of electricity, as well as a steady supply of essential
                    food and coal</p>
                <p>The United States and United Kingdom had few immediate options if hostilities
                    broke out. Because of the draw down in U.S. and British combat forces since the
                    end of the Second World War, the Red Army stationed in and around Berlin dwarfed
                    the Western Allied military presence. On June 13, 1948, the administrator of
                    U.S.-occupied Germany <persName>General Lucius Clay</persName> reported to
                    Washington that “There is no practicability in maintaining our position in
                    Berlin and it must not be evaluated on that basis.... We are convinced that our
                    remaining in Berlin is essential to our prestige in Germany and in Europe.
                    Whether for good or bad, it has become a symbol of the American intent.” The
                    Truman administration agreed. Based upon written agreements with the Soviet
                    Union in 1945, the only connections to Berlin left to the Western Allies were
                    air corridors from West Germany used to supply Berlin by air. The administration
                    calculated that if the Soviets opposed the airlift with force, it would be an
                    act of aggression against an unarmed humanitarian mission and the violation of
                    an explicit agreement. Thus, the onus of igniting a conflict between the former
                    allies would be on the aggressor. </p>
                <p>The United States launched “Operation Vittles” on June 26, with the United
                    Kingdom following suit two days later with “Operation Plainfare.” Despite the
                    desire for a peaceful resolution to the standoff, the United States also sent to
                    the United Kingdom B-29 bombers, which were capable of carrying nuclear weapons.
                    The beginning of the airlift proved difficult and Western diplomats asked the
                    Soviets to seek a diplomatic solution to the impasse. The Soviets offered to
                    drop the blockade if the Western Allies withdrew the Deutschmark from West
                    Berlin. </p>
                <p>Even though the Allies rebuffed the Soviet offer, West Berlin’s position remained
                    precarious, and the standoff had political consequences on the ground. In
                    September 1948, the Socialist Unity Party of Germany (SED), the German Communist
                    Party of the Soviet zone of occupation, marched on the Berlin City Council and
                    forced it to adjourn. Fearing that the Western Allies might halt the airlift and
                    cede West Berlin to the Soviets, 300,000 West Berliners gathered at the
                    Reichstag to show their opposition to Soviet domination. The turnout convinced
                    the West to keep the airlift and the Deutschmark.</p>
                <p>In time, the airlift became ever more efficient and the number of aircraft
                    increased. At the height of the campaign, one plane landed every 45 seconds at
                    Tempelhof Airport. By spring 1949, the Berlin Airlift proved successful. The
                    Western Allies showed that they could sustain the operation indefinitely. At the
                    same time, the Allied counter-blockade on eastern Germany was causing severe
                    shortages, which, Moscow feared, might lead to political upheaval.</p>
                <p>On May 11, 1949, Moscow lifted the blockade of West Berlin. The Berlin Crisis of
                    1948–1949 solidified the division of Europe. Shortly before the end of the
                    blockade, the Western Allies created the North Atlantic Treaty Organization
                    (NATO). Two weeks after the end of the blockade, the state of West Germany was
                    established, soon followed by the creation of East Germany. The incident
                    solidified the demarcation between East and West in Europe; it was one of the
                    few places on earth that U.S. and Soviet armed forces stood face-to-face. It
                    also transformed Berlin, once equated with Prussian militarism and Nazism, into
                    a symbol of democracy and freedom in the fight against Communism.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="creation-israel">
                <head>Creation of Israel, <date when="1948">1948</date>
                </head>
                <p>On May 14, 1948, <persName>David Ben-Gurion</persName>, the head of the Jewish
                    Agency, proclaimed the establishment of the State of Israel. U.S. President
                        <persName>Harry S. Truman</persName> recognized the new nation on the same
                    day.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="truman-israel.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Eliahu Elath presenting ark to President Truman</head>
                </figure>
                <p> Although the United States supported the Balfour Declaration of 1917, which
                    favored the establishment of a Jewish national home in Palestine, President
                        <persName>Franklin D. Roosevelt</persName> had assured the Arabs in 1945
                    that the United States would not intervene without consulting both the Jews and
                    the Arabs in that region. The British, who held a colonial mandate for Palestine
                    until May 1948, opposed both the creation of a Jewish state and an Arab state in
                    Palestine as well as unlimited immigration of Jewish refugees to the region.
                    Great Britain wanted to preserve good relations with the Arabs to protect its
                    vital political and economic interests in Palestine.</p>
                <p>Soon after President Truman took office, he appointed several experts to study
                    the Palestinian issue. In the summer of 1946, Truman established a special
                    cabinet committee under the chairmanship of Dr. <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/grady-henry-francis">Henry F. Grady</ref>,
                    an Assistant Secretary of State, who entered into negotiations with a parallel
                    British committee to discuss the future of Palestine. In May 1946, Truman
                    announced his approval of a recommendation to admit 100,000 displaced persons
                    into Palestine and in October publicly declared his support for the creation of
                    a Jewish state. Throughout 1947, the United Nations Special Commission on
                    Palestine examined the Palestinian question and recommended the partition of
                    Palestine into a Jewish and an Arab state. On November 29, 1947 the United
                    Nations adopted Resolution 181 (also known as the Partition Resolution) that
                    would divide Great Britain’s former Palestinian mandate into Jewish and Arab
                    states in May 1948 when the British mandate was scheduled to end. Under the
                    resolution, the area of religious significance surrounding Jerusalem would
                    remain a corpus separatum under international control administered by the United
                    Nations.</p>
                <p>Although the United States backed Resolution 181, the U.S. Department of State
                    recommended the creation of a United Nations trusteeship with limits on Jewish
                    immigration and a division of Palestine into separate Jewish and Arab provinces
                    but not states. The State Department, concerned about the possibility of an
                    increasing Soviet role in the Arab world and the potential for restriction by
                    Arab oil producing nations of oil supplies to the United States, advised against
                    U.S. intervention on behalf of the Jews. Later, as the date for British
                    departure from Palestine drew near, the Department of State grew concerned about
                    the possibility of an all-out war in Palestine as Arab states threatened to
                    attack almost as soon as the UN passed the partition resolution.</p>
                <p>Despite growing conflict between Palestinian Arabs and Palestinian Jews and
                    despite the Department of State’s endorsement of a trusteeship, Truman
                    ultimately decided to recognize the state Israel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="arab-israeli-war">
                <head>The Arab-Israeli War of <date when="1948">1948</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Arab-Israeli War of 1948 broke out when five Arab nations invaded territory
                    in the former Palestinian mandate immediately following the announcement of the
                    independence of the state of Israel on May 14, 1948. In 1947, and again on May
                    14, 1948, the United States had offered de facto recognition of the Israeli
                    Provisional Government, but during the war, the United States maintained an arms
                    embargo against all belligerents.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="arab-israel-war.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Raising the Flag signified the Conclusion of the Conflict</head>
                </figure>
                <p>On November 29, 1947, the United Nations General Assembly adopted Resolution 181
                    (also known as the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/creation-israel">Partition
                        Resolution</ref>) that would divide Great Britain’s former Palestinian
                    mandate into Jewish and Arab states in May 1948. Under the resolution, the area
                    of religious significance surrounding Jerusalem would remain under international
                    control administered by the United Nations. The Palestinian Arabs refused to
                    recognize this arrangement, which they regarded as favorable to the Jews and
                    unfair to the Arab population that would remain in Jewish territory under the
                    partition. The United States sought a middle way by supporting the United
                    Nations resolution, but also encouraging negotiations between Arabs and Jews in
                    the Middle East.</p>
                <p>The United Nations resolution sparked conflict between Jewish and Arab groups
                    within Palestine. Fighting began with attacks by irregular bands of Palestinian
                    Arabs attached to local units of the Arab Liberation Army composed of volunteers
                    from Palestine and neighboring Arab countries. These groups launched their
                    attacks against Jewish cities, settlements, and armed forces. The Jewish forces
                    were composed of the Haganah, the underground militia of the Jewish community in
                    Palestine, and two small irregular groups, the Irgun, and LEHI. The goal of the
                    Arabs was initially to block the Partition Resolution and to prevent the
                    establishment of the Jewish state. The Jews, on the other hand, hoped to gain
                    control over the territory allotted to them under the Partition Plan.</p>
                <p>After Israel declared its independence on May 14, 1948, the fighting intensified
                    with other Arab forces joining the Palestinian Arabs in attacking territory in
                    the former Palestinian mandate. On the eve of May 14, the Arabs launched an air
                    attack on Tel Aviv, which the Israelis resisted. This action was followed by the
                    invasion of the former Palestinian mandate by Arab armies from Lebanon, Syria,
                    Iraq, and Egypt. Saudi Arabia sent a formation that fought under the Egyptian
                    command. British trained forces from Transjordan eventually intervened in the
                    conflict, but only in areas that had been designated as part of the Arab state
                    under the United Nations Partition Plan and the corpus separatum of Jerusalem.
                    After tense early fighting, Israeli forces, now under joint command, were able
                    to gain the offensive.</p>
                <p>Though the United Nations brokered two cease-fires during the conflict, fighting
                    continued into 1949. Israel and the Arab states did not reach any formal
                    armistice agreements until February. Under separate agreements between Israel
                    and the neighboring states of Egypt, Lebanon, Transjordan, and Syria, these
                    bordering nations agreed to formal armistice lines. Israel gained some territory
                    formerly granted to Palestinian Arabs under the United Nations resolution in
                    1947. Egypt and Jordan retained control over the Gaza Strip and the West Bank
                    respectively. These armistice lines held until <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/arab-israeli-war-1967">1967</ref>. The United
                    States did not become directly involved with the armistice negotiations, but
                    hoped that instability in the Middle East would not interfere with the
                    international balance of power between the Soviet Union and the United States.
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="nato">
                <head>North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), <date when="1949">1949</date>
                </head>
                <p>The North Atlantic Treaty Organization was created in 1949 by the United States,
                    Canada, and several Western European nations to provide collective security
                    against the Soviet Union.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="natosigning.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Signing of the NATO Treaty</head>
                </figure>
                <p>NATO was the first peacetime military alliance the United States entered into
                    outside of the Western Hemisphere. After the destruction of the Second World
                    War, the nations of Europe struggled to rebuild their economies and ensure their
                    security. The former required a massive influx of aid to help the war-torn
                    landscapes re-establish industries and produce food, and the latter required
                    assurances against a resurgent Germany or incursions from the Soviet Union. The
                    United States viewed an economically strong, rearmed, and integrated Europe as
                    vital to the prevention of communist expansion across the continent. As a
                    result, Secretary of State George Marshall proposed a program of large-scale
                    economic aid to Europe. The resulting European Recovery Program, or <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall Plan</ref>, not only
                    facilitated European economic integration but promoted the idea of shared
                    interests and cooperation between the United States and Europe. Soviet refusal
                    either to participate in the Marshall Plan or to allow its satellite states in
                    Eastern Europe to accept the economic assistance helped to reinforce the growing
                    division between east and west in Europe.</p>
                <p>In 1947–1948, a series of events caused the nations of Western Europe to become
                    concerned about their physical and political security and the United States to
                    become more closely involved with European affairs. The ongoing civil war in
                    Greece, along with tensions in Turkey, led President Harry S. Truman to <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">assert that the United States
                        would provide economic and military aid to both countries, as well as to any
                        other nation struggling against an attempt at subjugation</ref>. A
                    Soviet-sponsored coup in Czechoslovakia resulted in a communist government
                    coming to power on the borders of Germany. Attention also focused on elections
                    in Italy as the communist party had made significant gains among Italian voters.
                    Furthermore, events in Germany also caused concern. The occupation and governance
                    of Germany after the war had long been disputed, and in mid-1948, Soviet premier
                    Joseph Stalin chose to test Western resolve by implementing a blockade against
                    West Berlin, which was then under joint U.S., British, and French control but
                    surrounded by Soviet-controlled East Germany. This Berlin Crisis brought the
                    United States and the Soviet Union to the brink of conflict, although a massive
                    airlift to resupply the city for the duration of the blockade helped to prevent
                    an outright confrontation. These events caused U.S. officials to grow
                    increasingly wary of the possibility that the countries of Western Europe might
                    deal with their security concerns by negotiating with the Soviets. To counter
                    this possible turn of events, the Truman Administration considered the
                    possibility of forming a European-American alliance that would commit the United
                    States to bolstering the security of Western Europe.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="brusselstreaty.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Signing of the Brussels Treaty</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Western European countries were willing to consider a collective security
                    solution. In response to increasing tensions and security concerns,
                    representatives of several countries of Western Europe gathered together to
                    create a military alliance. Great Britain, France, Belgium, the Netherlands and
                    Luxembourg signed the Brussels Treaty in March, 1948. Their treaty provided
                    collective defense; if any one of these nations was attacked, the others were
                    bound to help defend it. At the same time, the Truman Administration instituted
                    a peacetime draft, increased military spending, and called upon the historically
                    isolationist Republican Congress to consider a military alliance with Europe. In
                    May of 1948, Republican Senator <persName>Arthur H. Vandenburg</persName>
                    proposed a resolution suggesting that the President seek a security treaty with
                    Western Europe that would adhere to the United Nations charter but exist outside
                    of the Security Council where the Soviet Union held veto power. The Vandenburg
                    Resolution passed, and negotiations began for the North Atlantic Treaty.</p>
                <p>In spite of general agreement on the concept behind the treaty, it took several
                    months to work out the exact terms. The U.S. Congress had embraced the pursuit
                    of the international alliance, but it remained concerned about the wording of
                    the treaty. The nations of Western Europe wanted assurances that the United
                    States would intervene automatically in the event of an attack, but under the
                    U.S. Constitution the power to declare war rested with Congress. Negotiations
                    worked toward finding language that would reassure the European states but not
                    obligate the United States to act in a way that violated its own laws.
                    Additionally, European contributions to collective security would require
                    large-scale military assistance from the United States to help rebuild Western
                    Europe’s defense capabilities. While the European nations argued for individual
                    grants and aid, the United States wanted to make aid conditional on regional
                    coordination. A third issue was the question of scope. The Brussels Treaty
                    signatories preferred that membership in the alliance be restricted to the
                    members of that treaty plus the United States. The U.S. negotiators felt there
                    was more to be gained from enlarging the new treaty to include the countries of
                    the North Atlantic, including Canada, Iceland, Denmark, Norway, Ireland, and
                    Portugal. Together, these countries held territory that formed a bridge between
                    the opposite shores of the Atlantic Ocean, which would facilitate military
                    action if it became necessary.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="mdaa.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>President Truman inspecting a tank produced under the Mutual Defense
                        Assistance Program</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The result of these extensive negotiations was the signing of the North Atlantic
                    Treaty in 1949. In this agreement, the United States, Canada, Belgium, Denmark,
                    France, Iceland, Italy, Luxemburg, the Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, and the
                    United Kingdom agreed to consider attack against one an attack against all,
                    along with consultations about threats and defense matters. This collective
                    defense arrangement only formally applied to attacks against the signatories
                    that occurred in Europe or North America; it did not include conflicts in
                    colonial territories. After the treaty was signed, a number of the signatories
                    made requests to the United States for military aid. Later in 1949, President
                    Truman proposed a military assistance program, and the Mutual Defense Assistance
                    Program passed the U.S. Congress in October, appropriating some $1.4 billion
                    dollars for the purpose of building Western European defenses.</p>
                <p>Soon after the creation of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, the outbreak
                    of the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/korean-war">Korean War</ref> led the
                    members to move quickly to integrate and coordinate their defense forces through
                    a centralized headquarters. The North Korean attack on South Korea was widely
                    viewed at the time to be an example of communist aggression directed by Moscow,
                    so the United States bolstered its troop commitments to Europe to provide
                    assurances against Soviet aggression on the European continent. In 1952, the
                    members agreed to admit Greece and Turkey to NATO and added the Federal Republic
                    of Germany in 1955. West German entry led the Soviet Union to retaliate with its
                    own regional alliance, which took the form of the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/warsaw-treaty">Warsaw Treaty
                        Organization</ref> and included the Soviet satellite states of Eastern
                    Europe as members.</p>
                <p>The collective defense arrangements in NATO served to place the whole of Western
                    Europe under the American “nuclear umbrella.” In the 1950s, one of the first
                    military doctrines of NATO emerged in the form of “massive retaliation,” or the
                    idea that if any member was attacked, the United States would respond with a
                    large-scale nuclear attack. The threat of this form of response was meant to
                    serve as a deterrent against Soviet aggression on the continent. Although formed
                    in response to the exigencies of the developing Cold War, NATO has lasted beyond
                    the end of that conflict, with membership even expanding to include some former
                    Soviet states. It remains the largest peacetime military alliance in the
                    world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="chinese-rev">
                <head>The Chinese Revolution of <date when="1949">1949</date>
                </head>
                <p>On October 1, 1949, Chinese Communist leader <persName>Mao Zedong</persName>
                    declared the creation of the People’s Republic of China (PRC). The announcement
                    ended the costly full-scale civil war between the Chinese Communist Party (CCP)
                    and the Nationalist Party, or Kuomintang (KMT), which broke out immediately
                    following World War II and had been preceded by on and off conflict between the
                    two sides since the 1920’s. The creation of the PRC also completed the long
                    process of governmental upheaval in China begun by the <ref target="/milestones/1899-1913/chinese-rev">Chinese Revolution of 1911</ref>.
                    The “fall” of mainland China to communism in 1949 led the United States to
                    suspend diplomatic ties with the PRC for decades.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="communists-beijing.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Communists entering Beijing in 1949.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Chinese Communist Party, founded in 1921 in <placeName>Shanghai</placeName>,
                    originally existed as a study group working within the confines of the First
                    United Front with the Nationalist Party. Chinese Communists joined with the
                    Nationalist Army in the Northern Expedition of 1926–27 to rid the nation of the
                    warlords that prevented the formation of a strong central government. This
                    collaboration lasted until the “White Terror” of 1927, when the Nationalists
                    turned on the Communists, killing them or purging them from the party.</p>
                <p>After the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/mukden-incident">Japanese invaded
                        Manchuria in 1931</ref>, the Government of the Republic of China (ROC) faced
                    the triple threat of Japanese invasion, Communist uprising, and warlord
                    insurrections. Frustrated by the focus of the Nationalist leader Chiang Kai-shek
                    on internal threats instead of the Japanese assault, a group of generals
                    abducted Chiang in 1937 and forced him to reconsider cooperation with the
                    Communist army. As with the first effort at cooperation between the Nationalist
                    government and the CCP, this Second United Front was short-lived. The
                    Nationalists expended needed resources on containing the Communists, rather than
                    focusing entirely on Japan, while the Communists worked to strengthen their
                    influence in rural society.</p>
                <p>During World War II, popular support for the Communists increased. U.S. officials
                    in China reported a dictatorial suppression of dissent in Nationalist-controlled
                    areas. These undemocratic polices combined with wartime corruption made the
                    Republic of China Government vulnerable to the Communist threat. The CCP, for
                    its part, experienced success in its early efforts at land reform and was lauded
                    by peasants for its unflagging efforts to fight against the Japanese
                    invaders.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chiang-kai-shek.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Chiang Kai-shek</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Japanese surrender set the stage for the resurgence of civil war in China. Though
                    only nominally democratic, the Nationalist Government of Chiang Kai-shek
                    continued to receive U.S. support both as its former war ally and as the sole
                    option for preventing Communist control of China. U.S. forces flew tens of
                    thousands of Nationalist Chinese troops into Japanese-controlled territory and
                    allowed them to accept the Japanese surrender. The Soviet Union, meanwhile,
                    occupied Manchuria and only pulled out when Chinese Communist forces were in
                    place to claim that territory.</p>
                <p>In 1945, the leaders of the Nationalist and Communist parties, Chiang Kai-shek
                    and Mao Zedong, met for a series of talks on the formation of a post-war
                    government. Both agreed on the importance of democracy, a unified military, and
                    equality for all Chinese political parties. The truce was tenuous, however, and,
                    in spite of repeated efforts by U.S. General <persName>George
                        Marshall</persName> to broker an agreement, by 1946 the two sides were
                    fighting an all-out civil war. Years of mistrust between the two sides thwarted
                    efforts to form a coalition government.</p>
                <p>As the civil war gained strength from 1947 to 1949, eventual Communist victory
                    seemed more and more likely. Although the Communists did not hold any major
                    cities after World War II, they had strong grassroots support, superior military
                    organization and morale, and large stocks of weapons seized from Japanese
                    supplies in Manchuria. Years of corruption and mismanagement had eroded popular
                    support for the Nationalist Government. Early in 1947, the ROC Government was
                    already looking to the island province of Taiwan, off the coast of Fujian
                    Province, as a potential point of retreat. Although officials in the Truman
                    Administration were not convinced of the strategic importance to the United
                    States of maintaining relations with Nationalist China, no one in the U.S.
                    Government wanted to be charged with facilitating the “loss” of China to
                    communism. Military and financial aid to the floundering Nationalists continued,
                    though not at the level that Chiang Kai-shek would have liked. In October of
                    1949, after a string of military victories, Mao Zedong proclaimed the
                    establishment of the PRC; Chiang and his forces fled to Taiwan to regroup and
                    plan for their efforts to retake the mainland.</p>
                <p>The ability of the PRC and the United States to find common ground in the wake of
                    the establishment of the new Chinese state was hampered by both domestic
                    politics and global tensions. In August of 1949, the Truman administration
                    published the “China White Paper,” which explained past U.S. policy toward China
                    based upon the principle that only Chinese forces could determine the outcome of
                    their civil war. Unfortunately for Truman, this step failed to protect his
                    administration from charges of having “lost” China. The unfinished nature of the
                    revolution, leaving a broken and exiled but still vocal Nationalist Government
                    and army on Taiwan, only heightened the sense among U.S. anti-communists that
                    the outcome of the struggle could be reversed. The outbreak of the Korean War,
                    which pitted the PRC and the United States on opposite sides of an international
                    conflict, ended any opportunity for accommodation between the PRC and the United
                    States. Truman’s desire to prevent the Korean conflict from spreading south led
                    to the U.S. policy of protecting the Chiang Kai-shek government on Taiwan.</p>
                <p>For more than twenty years after the Chinese revolution of 1949, there were few
                    contacts, limited trade and no diplomatic ties between the two countries. <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976">Until the 1970s</ref>, the United States
                    continued to recognize the Republic of China, located on Taiwan, as China’s true
                    government and supported that government’s holding the Chinese seat in the
                    United Nations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="NSC68">
                <head>NSC-68, <date when="1950">1950</date>
                </head>
                <p>National Security Council Paper NSC-68 (entitled “United States Objectives and
                    Programs for National Security” and frequently referred to as NSC-68) was a
                    Top-Secret report completed by the U.S. Department of State’s Policy Planning
                    Staff on April 7, 1950. The 58-page memorandum is among the most influential
                    documents composed by the U.S. Government during the Cold War, and was not
                    declassified until 1975. Its authors argued that one of the most pressing
                    threats confronting the United States was the “hostile design” of the Soviet
                    Union. The authors concluded that the Soviet threat would soon be greatly
                    augmented by the addition of more weapons, including nuclear weapons, to the
                    Soviet arsenal. They argued that the best course of action was to respond in
                    kind with a massive build-up of the U.S. military and its weaponry.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="truman-nsc.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Truman meeting with the NSC Staff</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Reeling from the recent victory of Communist forces in the Chinese Civil War and
                    the successful detonation of an atomic weapon by the Soviet Union, Secretary of
                    State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/acheson-dean-gooderham">Dean
                        Acheson</ref> asked the Policy Planning Staff, led by <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/nitze-paul-henry">Paul Nitze</ref>, to
                    undertake a comprehensive review of U.S. national security strategy. Building
                    upon the conclusions of an earlier National Security Council paper (NSC-20/4),
                    the authors of NSC-68 based their conclusions on the theory that the decline of
                    the Western European powers and Japan following World War II had left the United
                    States and the Soviet Union as the two dominant powers. Nitze’s group argued
                    that the Soviet Union was “animated by a new fanatic faith” antithetical to that
                    of the United States, and was driven “to impose its absolute authority over the
                    rest of the world.” Furthermore, they concluded that “violent and non-violent”
                    conflict between the United States and the Soviet Union had become
                    “endemic.”</p>
                <p>NSC-68 outlined a variety of possible courses of action, including a return to
                    isolationism; war; continued diplomatic efforts to negotiate with the Soviets;
                    or “the rapid building up of the political, economic, and military strength of
                    the free world.” This last approach would allow the United States to attain
                    sufficient strength to deter Soviet aggression. In the event that an armed
                    conflict with the Communist bloc did arise, the United States could then
                    successfully defend its territory and overseas interests.</p>
                <p>The authors of NSC-68 rejected a renewal of U.S. isolationism, fearing that this
                    would lead to the Soviet domination of Eurasia, and leave the United States
                    marooned on the Western Hemisphere, cut off from the allies and resources it
                    needed to fend off further Soviet encroachments. The report also ruled out a
                    preventive strike against the Soviet Union, because its authors reckoned that
                    such action would not destroy the Soviet military’s offensive capacities, and
                    would instead invite retaliatory strikes that would devastate Western Europe.
                    Moreover, U.S. experts did not believe that American public opinion would
                    support measures that might lead to a protracted war. NSC-68 did not rule out
                    the prospect of negotiating with the Soviet Union when it suited the objectives
                    of the United States and its allies; however, the report’s authors argued that
                    such an approach would only succeed if the United States could create “political
                    and economic conditions in the free world” sufficient to deter the Soviet Union
                    from pursuing a military solution to the Cold War rivalry.</p>
                <p>NSC-68 concluded that the only plausible way to deter the Soviet Union was for
                    President Harry Truman to support a massive build-up of both conventional and
                    nuclear arms. More specifically, such a program should seek to protect the
                    United States and its allies from Soviet land and air attacks, maintain lines of
                    communications, and enhance the technical superiority of the United States
                    through “an accelerated exploitation of [its] scientific potential.” In order to
                    fund the substantial increase in military spending this conclusion demanded, the
                    report suggested that the Government increase taxes and reduce other
                    expenditures.</p>
                <p>Initially, a number of U.S. officials strongly opposed NSC-68’s recommendations.
                    Critics such as Secretary of Defense Louis Johnson, and senior diplomats such as
                    Soviet experts and former ambassadors to the Soviet Union <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/kennan-george-frost">George Kennan</ref>
                    and <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/bohlen-charles-eustis">Charles
                        Bohlen</ref>, argued that the United States already had a substantial
                    military advantage over the Soviet Union. Kennan, in particular, disagreed with
                    Nitze’s assertion that the Soviet Union was bent on achieving domination through
                    force of arms, and argued that the United States could contain the Soviet Union
                    through political and economic measures, rather than purely military ones.
                    However, the invasion of South Korea by Soviet and Chinese-backed North Korean
                    forces in June 1950, and continuing charges by Congressional critics that the
                    Administration was soft on Communism, quickly settled matters in favor of the
                    report’s recommendations. NSC 68’s recommendations thereby became policy, and
                    the United States Government began a massive military build-up. While NSC-68 did
                    not make any specific recommendations regarding the proposed increase in defense
                    expenditures, the Truman Administration almost tripled defense spending as a
                    percentage of the gross domestic product between 1950 and 1953 (from 5 to 14.2
                    percent).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="asia-and-africa">
                <head>Decolonization of Asia and Africa, <date from="1945" to="1960">1945–1960</date>
                </head>
                <p>Between 1945 and 1960, three dozen new states in <placeName>Asia</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName> achieved autonomy or outright independence
                    from their European colonial rulers.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="macmillan.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Harold MacMillan, British Prime Minister, helped begin
                        decolonization</head>
                </figure>
                <p>There was no one process of decolonization. In some areas, it was peaceful, and
                    orderly. In many others, independence was achieved only after a protracted
                    revolution. A few newly independent countries acquired stable governments almost
                    immediately; others were ruled by dictators or military juntas for decades, or
                    endured long civil wars. Some European governments welcomed a new relationship
                    with their former colonies; others contested decolonization militarily. The
                    process of decolonization coincided with the new Cold War between the Soviet
                    Union and the United States, and with the early development of the new United
                    Nations. Decolonization was often affected by superpower competition, and had a
                    definite impact on the evolution of that competition. It also significantly
                    changed the pattern of international relations in a more general sense.</p>
                <p>The creation of so many new countries, some of which occupied strategic
                    locations, others of which possessed significant natural resources, and most of
                    which were desperately poor, altered the composition of the United Nations and
                    political complexity of every region of the globe. In the mid to late 19th
                    century, the European powers colonized much of Africa and Southeast Asia. During
                    the decades of imperialism, the industrializing powers of Europe viewed the
                    African and Asian continents as reservoirs of raw materials, labor, and
                    territory for future settlement. In most cases, however, significant development
                    and European settlement in these colonies was sporadic. However, the colonies
                    were exploited, sometimes brutally, for natural and labor resources, and
                    sometimes even for military conscripts. In addition, the introduction of
                    colonial rule drew arbitrary natural boundaries where none had existed before,
                    dividing ethnic and linguistic groups and natural features, and laying the
                    foundation for the creation of numerous states lacking geographic, linguistic,
                    ethnic, or political affinity.</p>
                <p>During World War II Japan, itself a significant imperial power, drove the
                    European powers out of Asia. After the Japanese surrender in 1945, local
                    nationalist movements in the former Asian colonies campaigned for independence
                    rather than a return to European colonial rule. In many cases, as in Indonesia
                    and French Indochina, these nationalists had been guerrillas fighting the
                    Japanese after European surrenders, or were former members of colonial military
                    establishments. These independence movements often appealed to the United States
                    Government for support.</p>
                <p>While the United States generally supported the concept of national
                    self-determination, it also had strong ties to its European allies, who had
                    imperial claims on their former colonies. The Cold War only served to complicate
                    the U.S. position, as U.S. support for decolonization was offset by American
                    concern over communist expansion and Soviet strategic ambitions in Europe.
                    Several of the NATO allies asserted that their colonial possessions provided
                    them with economic and military strength that would otherwise be lost to the
                    alliance. Nearly all of the United States’ European allies believed that after
                    their recovery from World War II their colonies would finally provide the
                    combination of raw materials and protected markets for finished goods that would
                    cement the colonies to Europe. Whether or not this was the case, the alternative
                    of allowing the colonies to slip away, perhaps into the United States’ economic
                    sphere or that of another power, was unappealing to every European government
                    interested in postwar stability. Although the U.S. Government did not force the
                    issue, it encouraged the European imperial powers to negotiate an early
                    withdrawal from their overseas colonies. The United States granted independence
                    to the Philippines in 1946.</p>
                <p>However, as the Cold War competition with the Soviet Union came to dominate U.S.
                    foreign policy concerns in the late 1940s and 1950s, the Truman and Eisenhower
                    Administrations grew increasingly concerned that as the European powers lost
                    their colonies or granted them independence, Soviet-supported communist parties
                    might achieve power in the new states. This might serve to shift the
                    international balance of power in favor of the Soviet Union and remove access to
                    economic resources from U.S. allies. Events such as the Indonesian struggle for
                    independence from the Netherlands (1945–50), the Vietnamese war against France
                    (1945–54), and the nationalist and professed socialist takeovers of Egypt (1952)
                    and Iran (1951) served to reinforce such fears, even if new governments did not
                    directly link themselves to the Soviet Union. Thus, the United States used aid
                    packages, technical assistance and sometimes even military intervention to
                    encourage newly independent nations in the Third World to adopt governments that
                    aligned with the West. The Soviet Union deployed similar tactics in an effort to
                    encourage new nations to join the communist bloc, and attempted to convince
                    newly decolonized countries that communism was an intrinsically non-imperialist
                    economic and political ideology. Many of the new nations resisted the pressure
                    to be drawn into the Cold War, joined in the “nonaligned movement,” which formed
                    after the Bandung conference of 1955, and focused on internal development.</p>
                <p>The newly independent nations that emerged in the 1950s and the 1960s became an
                    important factor in changing the balance of power within the United Nations. In
                    1946, there were 35 member states in the United Nations; as the newly
                    independent nations of the “third world” joined the organization, by 1970
                    membership had swelled to 127. These new member states had a few characteristics
                    in common; they were non-white, with developing economies, facing internal
                    problems that were the result of their colonial past, which sometimes put them
                    at odds with European countries and made them suspicious of European-style
                    governmental structures, political ideas, and economic institutions. These
                    countries also became vocal advocates of continuing decolonization, with the
                    result that the UN Assembly was often ahead of the Security Council on issues of
                    self-governance and decolonization. The new nations pushed the UN toward
                    accepting resolutions for independence for colonial states and creating a
                    special committee on colonialism, demonstrating that even though some nations
                    continued to struggle for independence, in the eyes of the international
                    community, the colonial era was ending.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="korean-war-2">
                <head>The Korean War, <date when="1950">1950–1953</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Korean War began as a civil war between <placeName>North and South
                        Korea</placeName>, but the conflict soon became international when, under
                    U.S. leadership, the United Nations joined to support <placeName>South
                        Korea</placeName> and the <placeName>People’s Republic of China
                        (PRC)</placeName> entered to aid <placeName>North Korea</placeName>. The war
                    left Korea divided and brought the Cold War to Asia.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="korea1.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>General MacArthur during the Korean War</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Despite its long national history and unique cultural and linguistic identity,
                    Korea suffered from frequent interference by its neighbors. China treated the
                    Kingdom of Korea as a tributary state for centuries and fought
                        <placeName>Japan</placeName> for influence on the Korean Peninsula in
                    1894–95. In 1904–05, the Russo-Japanese War was also fought largely on Korean
                    territory. After the Japanese victory in that conflict, Japan consolidated its
                    growing influence in Korea and in 1910, formally annexed it as a colony. Japan
                    ruled Korea from 1910 until the end of World War II.</p>
                <p>During World War II, the Allies discussed the future of Korea in the postwar
                    period. The United States, <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>, and the
                    Republic of China had met at <placeName>Cairo</placeName> in <date when="1943">1943</date>, where they agreed that after its defeat, Japan would be
                    stripped of all of its colonies, including Korea. As the war drew to a close in
                    August of 1945, two U.S. army colonels (one of whom, <persName>Dean
                        Rusk</persName>, would later become Secretary of State) proposed that the
                        <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> take responsibility for accepting the
                    surrender of Japanese troops in the part of the Korean peninsula north of the
                    38th parallel, whereas U.S. troops would receive the surrender south of that
                    line. This decision resulted in the division and separation of many villages
                    along the 38th parallel and families with ties across that line.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="rhee.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Syngman Rhee</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The postwar planners had intended that the division between North and South Korea
                    would be a temporary administrative solution. After the war, the United Nations
                    agreed to oversee elections in the North and South in 1947 in the hopes that it
                    would lead to the reunification of Korea under a democratically elected
                    government. However, the Soviet Union blocked the elections in its section and
                    instead, supported <persName>Kim Il Sung</persName> as leader of the
                        <placeName>Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK)</placeName>. In the
                    South, the United States supported <persName>Syngman Rhee</persName> as the
                    elected leader of the newly founded <placeName>Republic of Korea
                        (ROK)</placeName>. Both Kim and Rhee were nationalists dedicated to the idea
                    of reunification, although each ruled with a different ideological vision. In
                    1949, under a UN agreement, both the Soviet Union and the United States withdrew
                    their military forces from Korea, but both left large numbers of advisors on the
                    peninsula. The two sides were to continue negotiations over elections to reunify
                    the country, and although the United States preferred that the resulting
                    government not be communist, in 1949 it was still not prepared to commit
                    militarily to preventing that outcome.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="kimilsung.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Kim Il Sung</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Both sides periodically instigated skirmishes across the 38th parallel, but the
                    war formally began when the DPRK crossed the demarcation line and attacked the
                    ROK on June 25, 1950. Both Korean governments had been adamant about reunifying
                    the peninsula, and the Soviet-supported DPRK saw an opportunity to do so with a
                    swift strike. The DPRK army quickly pushed into South Korea, and by September,
                    it had engulfed almost the entire peninsula and had forced the ROK army into a
                    small area around Pusan. Upon hearing news of the attack, the United States
                    immediately called for a meeting of the <orgName>United Nations Security
                        Council</orgName>, which the Soviet Union was then boycotting over the issue
                    of Chinese representation. With the Soviets absent, the Security Council was
                    able to pass a resolution condemning the actions of the DPRK and demanding that
                    the Northern armies withdraw from the South. The United States viewed the attack
                    on the South as evidence that communism would actively challenge the free world
                    and revised its security perimeter to include maintaining a non-communist South
                    Korea. The UN sent forces composed of troops from 15 nations to the peninsula to
                    stop the communist advance.</p>
                <p>The UN entry into the conflict led to a swift internationalization of what had
                    been an internal struggle. Though the United States dedicated the greatest
                    number of troops, soldiers from Australia, Belgium, Canada, Colombia, Ethiopia,
                    France, Greece, Luxembourg, the Netherlands, New Zealand, the Philippines, South
                    Africa, Thailand, Turkey and the United Kingdom also sent troops. U.S. officials
                    emphasized that this joint military action was imperative to prevent the
                    conflict from spreading outside Korea.</p>
                <p>The <persName>Truman</persName> Administration remained concerned that recent
                    communist successes in Korea would encourage the People’s Republic of China
                    (PRC) to take action. After the communist forces triumphed on the Chinese
                    mainland, China’s Nationalist Government had retreated to the island of Taiwan,
                    and the threat had persisted that the PRC might cross the strait to consolidate
                    its power over all of China. President Harry Truman had proclaimed in early 1950
                    that he would not defend the Nationalists from a Communist attack, but after the
                    outbreak of hostilities in Korea he moved the U.S. Seventh Fleet into the
                        <placeName>Taiwan Strait</placeName> to discourage the spread of military
                    conflict in the region. The PRC considered this U.S. action as interference in
                    China’s internal affairs.</p>
                <p>In September of 1950, UN forces led by U.S. General <persName>Douglas A.
                        MacArthur</persName> managed to regain lost ground in South Korea and push
                    north, forcing a reaction from the Chinese. After landing at
                        <placeName>Incheon</placeName>, near <placeName>Seoul</placeName>,
                    MacArthur’s troops quickly moved to cut off the advancing DPRK army from its
                    North Korean supply lines. By the end of the month, UN forces were approaching
                    the 38th parallel, had liberated Seoul, and had restored the status quo that
                    existed before the war. The new question was whether to take this newfound
                    success a step further and attempt to liberate the North from the rule of the
                    DPRK. The leadership of the U.S. and UN forces believed that an attempt to
                    “rollback” the communist forces and unite the country under non-communist rule
                    was well within the parameters of the mission. Chinese leaders had warned the
                    international community that they would intervene in the conflict if UN forces
                    pushed north of the 38th parallel, but MacArthur and other members of the UN
                    command did not believe that either the PRC or Soviet Union would attempt to
                    halt UN forces. With authorization from Washington, UN forces pressed north, and
                    by October 1950 had nearly reached the Yalu River, which marks the border
                    between China and North Korea. Chinese officials viewed the UN forces
                    approaching the Chinese border as a genuine threat to its security, and late in
                    1950 they sent Chinese forces into North Korea. The U.S. and UN had also grossly
                    underestimated the size, strength, and determination of the Chinese forces. As a
                    result, MacArthur’s troops were quickly forced to retreat behind the 38th
                    parallel.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="matthewridgeway.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>General Matthew Ridgeway</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In early 1951, the territory around Seoul and central Korea changed hands several
                    times as the UN and Communist forces advanced and retreated. MacArthur insisted
                    on the extension of the conflict into China, and on April 11, 1951, he was
                    removed from his command on the charge of insubordination and replaced by
                    General Matthew Ridgeway. By July 1951, the conflict had reached a stalemate,
                    with the two sides fighting limited engagements, but with neither side in a
                    position to force the other’s surrender. Both the United States and China had,
                    at this point, achieved the short-term goal of maintaining the demarcation line
                    at the 38th parallel, while the North and South Koreans had failed in the larger
                    goal of uniting the country under their preferred political systems.
                    Representatives of all the parties began to discuss peace.</p>
                <p>For the next two years, small-scale skirmishes continued to break out, while the
                    various representatives argued over the peace terms. After agreeing on the
                    demarcation line and the settlement of airfields, the main issue blocking
                    progress in the talks was the repatriation of prisoners of war. On July 27,
                    1953, the DPRK, PRC and UN signed an armistice (the ROK abstained) agreeing to a
                    new border near the 38th parallel as the demarcation line between North and
                    South Korea. Both sides would maintain and patrol a demilitarized zone (DMZ)
                    surrounding that boundary line. The armistice also established a commission of
                    neutral nations to oversee the voluntary repatriation of POWs. According to the
                    agreement, each side would have to repatriate willing POWs within sixty days and
                    send unwilling repatriates to the commission to oversee their departure to their
                    preferred destinations. Under the supervision of the commission, some 14,227
                    Chinese and 7,582 North Koreas opted against repatriation; the Chinese were sent
                    to Taiwan rather than the Chinese mainland. A handful of U.S. and British POWs
                    in North Korea opted against repatriation as well, choosing instead to live in
                    Communist China or North Korea.</p>
                <p>The armistice was only a ceasefire agreement, not a formal peace treaty ending
                    the war. A final peace treaty was supposed to be on the agenda at the Geneva
                    Conference of 1954, but by the time that conference began, the French colonial
                    war in Indochina took precedence. Ultimately, the United States and the ROK
                    signed a mutual defense treaty, and U.S. troops became a part of the DMZ patrols
                    on a semi-permanent basis.</p>
                <p>The Korean War had long-lasting consequences for the entire region. Though it
                    failed to unify the country, the United States achieved its larger goals,
                    including preserving and promoting NATO interests and defending Japan. The war
                    also resulted in a divided Korea and complicated any possibility for
                    accommodation between the United States and China. The Korean War served to
                    encourage the U.S. Cold War policies of containment and militarization, setting
                    the stage for the further enlargement of the U.S. defense perimeter in Asia.
                    These Cold War policies would eventually lead the United States to regional
                    actions that included its attempts at preventing the fall of Vietnam to
                    communism. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="anzus">
                <head>The Australia, New Zealand and United States Security Treaty (ANZUS Treaty),
                        <date when="1951">1951</date>
                </head>
                <p>The <placeName>Australia</placeName>, <placeName>New Zealand</placeName> and
                        <placeName>United States</placeName> Security Treaty, or ANZUS Treaty, was
                    an agreement signed in 1951 to protect the security of the
                        <placeName>Pacific</placeName>. Although the agreement has not been formally
                    abrogated, the United States and New Zealand no longer maintain the security
                    relationship between their countries.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="acheson-anzus.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of State Dean Acheson speaking at an ANZUS Conference</head>
                </figure>
                <p>At the onset of the Second World War, both Australia and New Zealand were members
                    of the British Empire, so when Britain entered the conflict they did as well.
                    During the course of the war, these two geographically isolated nations faced
                    the threat of direct attack for the first time in their histories as modern
                    states. As the Japanese expanded south into the Pacific Ocean, mainland
                    Australia and especially the city of Darwin suffered frequent Japanese air raids
                    in 1942 and 1943. After the sudden fall of the strategically important British
                    colony of Singapore to the Japanese on February 15, 1942, the Antipodean nations
                    expressed concern that the British Government was too focused on the war in
                    Europe to protect its colonies properly and they began for the first time to
                    look to the United States to help ensure their security. </p>
                <p>As the other Allied powers turned their attention to the reconstruction of
                    postwar Europe and Japan in the post World War II era, the governments of
                    Australia and New Zealand remained concerned about the possibility of future
                    Japanese expansionism and grew apprehensive about the rise of communism,
                    particularly in East Asia. Even before the war ended, Australia and New Zealand
                    signed an agreement stating that they had common goals and would work together
                    in the international arena; at the time, the agreement was for both nations the
                    first treaty negotiated independently, and it reflected the concern that the
                    major powers of the United States and the United Kingdom may not take Australian
                    and New Zealander issues into account in their postwar planning. The signing of
                    the North Atlantic Treaty in 1949, in which the United Kingdom, Canada, and the
                    United States alongside the Western European powers committed to a mutual
                    defense arrangement, further prompted the geographically distant countries of
                    Australia and New Zealand to seek their own security guarantee and means of
                    integration in the international system in the postwar order. </p>
                <p>Australia initially considered the idea of a regional pact in the Pacific in the
                    1930s, and in 1946, at a meeting of the Commonwealth Prime Ministers, it
                    suggested that the major powers of the British Commonwealth form a regional
                    defense system. If such an organization were created, the members could then
                    invite the United States and other countries with strong interests in the
                    Pacific to join. At that time, however, the United States was not yet prepared
                    to commit itself to formal security arrangements in the Pacific. During the late
                    1940s, the United States was heavily engaged in the rebuilding of Japan, but the
                    United States did not extend its defense interests far beyond Japanese territory
                    before the Korean War. In response to Australian suggestions for a regional
                    coalition, U.S. Secretary of State <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/acheson-dean-gooderham">Dean Acheson</ref>
                    stated that formal treaties with the South Pacific nations were unnecessary, as
                    any real attack on Australia or New Zealand would elicit a U.S. response even
                    without formal treaties in place to guarantee it. Moreover, the situations in
                    the Atlantic and the Pacific were quite different, so there was no question of
                    simply creating a “Pacific Treaty Organization” to parallel NATO. The Pacific
                    Ocean was much larger, and the nations that bordered it were far more culturally
                    and linguistically diverse than the nations of the North Atlantic. Other
                    considerations led the United States to hesitate to commit to a regional
                    organization in the Pacific as well. A number of the countries in Southeast Asia
                    were still under colonial rule, or in the process of developing as independent
                    states, and therefore neither they nor their colonial governments were in a
                    position to make regional security commitments. At this time, the United States
                    was also faced with the critical situation in Europe, including the occupation
                    and support of West Germany and West Berlin and facing what it saw as the Soviet
                    threat on that continent. There were fewer immediate economic or political
                    threats to force equal attention to the security of the Southwest Pacific. </p>
                <p>Several developments in Asia between 1949 and 1951 helped to change U.S.
                    perceptions about the utility of a formal security arrangement. The communist
                    victory in the Chinese Revolution in 1949 seemed to confirm fears that communism
                    was spreading in East Asia as well as in Europe. In 1950s, the outbreak of the
                    Korean War led Australia and New Zealand to commit troops through the United
                    Nations and alongside the NATO allies, demonstrating both their concern over the
                    threat of communism and their commitment to doing their part to help contain it
                    in the region. Most importantly, the U.S. decision to end the occupation of
                    Japan and seek a peace treaty was met with great suspicion and disapproval from
                    officials in the South Pacific, and that made the United States more willing to
                    develop a security treaty to gain Antipodean support for the final peace
                    agreement. In April of 1951, U.S. President <persName>Harry Truman</persName>
                    announced that negotiations on a tripartite security treaty between the United
                    States, Australia and New Zealand would occur concurrently with the negotiations
                    for a final peace treaty with Japan. Both treaties were concluded in mid-1951,
                    and the ANZUS Treaty was ratified by the United States and entered into force in
                    1952. </p>
                <p>Although Britain also maintained an obligation to help defend Australian and New
                    Zealander security as the leader of the Commonwealth, it was not invited to join
                    the agreement. There were several reasons for the omission. One important
                    concern was that extending the invitation to Britain would have required the
                    signatories to open the opportunity to other European powers with colonial
                    interests in the region. Another was the fact that British forces were already
                    engaged in Europe and the Middle East, not to mention committed to the rest of
                    the Commonwealth, making their actual intervention in the South Pacific in the
                    event of a security crisis unlikely. Britain was also dealing with internal
                    instability in its Asian colonies, including Malaya and Hong Kong, and that made
                    the United States reluctant to sign an agreement that might obligate it to step
                    in to resolve British colonial concerns. In any case, the British were already
                    committed to U.S. security via NATO and to Australia and New Zealand via the
                    Commonwealth, so its participation in a Pacific security arrangement with the
                    United States, Australia, and New Zealand would have been somewhat redundant.
                    All parties assumed that if the ANZUS Treaty was eventually extended to include
                    other powers, however, the United Kingdom would be among the first to join. </p>
                <p>Although ANZUS was never expanded, the 1954 creation of the Southeast Asian
                    Treaty Organization (SEATO) included all of the ANZUS powers, as well as
                    Britain, France, and several other Asian powers, eliminating the impetus to
                    change the foundation of the ANZUS Treaty. Over the course of the decades that
                    followed the signing of the ANZUS Treaty, the members met annually to discuss
                    their shared interests and concerns. These concerns increasingly focused on the
                    spread of communism rather than the potential for Japanese militarization. Both
                    Australia and New Zealand sent forces to support the U.S. effort in Vietnam,
                    though without formally invoking the treaty. </p>
                <p>In 1984, the ANZUS Treaty began to unravel when New Zealand declared its country
                    a nuclear-free zone and refused to allow U.S. nuclear-powered submarines to
                    visit its ports. Two years later, U.S. Secretary of State George P. Shultz and
                    Australian Foreign Minister Bill Hayden concluded a series of bilateral talks by
                    confirming that their countries would continue to honor their obligations to one
                    another under the ANZUS Treaty, in spite of the fact that the trilateral aspects
                    of the Treaty had been halted. On September 17, 1986, the United States
                    suspended its treaty obligations toward New Zealand. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="immigration-act">
                <head>The Immigration and Nationality Act of <date when="1952">1952</date> (The
                    McCarran-Walter Act)</head>
                <p>The Immigration and Nationality Act of 1952 upheld the national origins quota
                    system established by the Immigration Act of 1924, reinforcing this
                    controversial system of immigrant selection.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="mccarran-pat.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Patrick McCarran</head>
                </figure>
                <p>It also ended Asian exclusion from immigrating to the United States and
                    introduced a system of preferences based on skill sets and family reunification.
                    Situated in the early years of the Cold War, the debate over the revision of
                    U.S. immigration law demonstrated a division between those interested in the
                    relationship between immigration and foreign policy, and those linking
                    immigration to concerns over national security. The former group, led by
                    individuals like Democrat Congressman from New York <persName>Emanuel
                        Cellar</persName>, favored the liberalization of immigration laws. Cellar
                    expressed concerns that the restrictive quota system heavily favored immigration
                    from Northern and Western Europe and therefore created resentment against the
                    United States in other parts of the world. He felt the law created the sense
                    that Americans thought people from Eastern Europe as less desirable and people
                    from Asia inferior to those of European descent. The latter group, led by
                    Republican Senator from Nevada <persName>Pat McCarran</persName> and Democrat
                    Congressman from Pennsylvania <persName>Francis Walter</persName>, expressed
                    concerns that the United States could face communist infiltration through
                    immigration and that unassimilated aliens could threaten the foundations of
                    American life. To these individuals, limited and selective immigration was the
                    best way to ensure the preservation of national security and national interests. </p>
                <p>Remarkably, economic factors were relatively unimportant in the debate over the
                    new immigration provisions. Although past arguments in favor of restrictionism
                    focused on the needs of the American economy and labor force, in 1952, the Cold
                    War seemed to take precedent in the discussion. Notably, the American Federation
                    of Labor and the Congress of Industrial Organizations took opposite sides in the
                    debate, demonstrating that there was not one, clear pro-labor position. </p>
                <p>At the basis of the Act was the continuation and codification of the National
                    Origins Quota System. It revised the <ref target="/milestones/1921-1936/immigration-act">1924 system</ref> to allow
                    for national quotas at a rate of one-sixth of one percent of each nationality’s
                    population in the United States in 1920. As a result, 85 percent of the 154,277
                    visas available annually were allotted to individuals of northern and western
                    European lineage. The Act continued the practice of not including countries in
                    the Western Hemisphere in the quota system, though it did introduce new length
                    of residency requirements to qualify for quota-free entry. </p>
                <p>The 1952 Act created symbolic opportunities for Asian immigration, though in
                    reality it continued to discriminate against them. The law repealed the last of
                    the existing measures to exclude Asian immigration, allotted each Asian nation a
                    minimum quota of 100 visas each year, and eliminated laws preventing Asians from
                    becoming naturalized American citizens. Breaking down the “Asiatic Barred Zone”
                    was a step toward improving U.S. relations with Asian nations. At the same time,
                    however, the new law only allotted new Asian quotas based on race, instead of
                    nationality. An individual with one or more Asian parent, born anywhere in the
                    world and possessing the citizenship of any nation, would be counted under the
                    national quota of the Asian nation of his or her ethnicity or against a generic
                    quota for the “Asian Pacific Triangle.” Low quota numbers and a uniquely racial
                    construction for how to apply them ensured that total Asian immigration after
                    1952 would remain very limited. </p>
                <p>There were other positive changes to the implementation of immigration policy in
                    the 1952 Act. One was the creation of a system of preferences which served to
                    help American consuls abroad prioritize visa applicants in countries with
                    heavily oversubscribed quotas. Under the preference system, individuals with
                    special skills or families already resident in the United States received
                    precedence, a policy still in use today. Moreover, the Act gave non-quota status
                    to alien husbands of American citizens (wives had been entering outside of the
                    quota system for several years by 1952) and created a labor certification
                    system, designed to prevent new immigrants from becoming unwanted competition
                    for American laborers. </p>
                <p>President <persName>Truman</persName> was concerned about the decisions to
                    maintain the national origins quota system and to establish racially constructed
                    quotas for Asian nations. He thought the new law was discriminatory, and he
                    vetoed it, but the law had enough support in Congress to pass over his veto.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="korean-war">
                <head>Korean War and Japan’s Recovery</head>
                <p>As the Cold War came to dominate U.S. foreign policy, America extended security
                    commitments to two nations in Northeast Asia—the Republic of Korea and Japan.
                    The Department of State under Secretary <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/acheson-dean-gooderham">Dean Acheson</ref>
                    forged a series of agreements to build a permanent American presence in the
                    region and support these two nations, creating alliances that have lasted to
                    today. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="korean-war.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>The 25th Infantry Division prepares to go to Korean War from Japan</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After Japan’s unconditional surrender to the Allied Powers in August 1945, the
                    United States military occupied the defeated nation and began a series of
                    far-reaching reforms designed to build a peaceful and democratic Japan by
                    reducing the power of the military and breaking up the largest Japanese business
                    conglomerates. However, growing concern over Communist power in East Asia,
                    particularly the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/chinese-rev">success of the
                        Chinese Communist Party</ref> in its struggle against <persName>Chiang
                        Kai-shek’s</persName> Nationalist forces, led the United States to halt
                    reforms in 1947 and 1948 in order to focus on the economic recovery and
                    political rehabilitation of Japan. In this “Reverse Course,” Supreme Commander
                    of the Allied Powers, General <persName>Douglas MacArthur</persName>, focused on
                    strengthening, not punishing, what would become a key cold war ally. </p>
                <p>The growing concern over Japanese security related directly to war in Korea.
                    During World War II the United States and the Soviet Union agreed to temporarily
                    divide Korea at the 38th parallel in order oversee the removal of Japanese
                    forces. It soon became clear, however, that neither of the cold war antagonists
                    would permit its Korea ally to be threatened by unification. The Soviets
                    supported Kim Il Song in the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea in the north;
                    the United States backed Syngman Rhee in the Republic of Korea in the south.
                    Nevertheless the United States did not make Korea a key part of its defensive
                    strategy for East Asia, and American forces withdrew from the south in the late
                    1940s. Assuming that the United States did not consider South Korea of vital
                    interest, Kim’s army attacked the South in June 1950 almost conquering the
                    entire peninsula. The U.S. military returned, leading a United
                    Nations-authorized force to push the North’s army back above the 38th parallel
                    and beyond. After the People’s Republic of China entered the war in late 1950,
                    the Department of State worked to isolate Peking and maintain the unity of the
                    U.S.-led coalition. Only in 1953 did the two sides reach an uneasy truce, thus
                    crystallizing the division between North and South that exists today. In 1953
                    the United States and South Korea signed a mutual security treaty designed to
                    protect this new nation from its neighbor to the north.</p>
                <p>U.S. efforts to save South Korea from Communist invasion accelerated Department
                    of State attempts to restore Japan to a respected international position, and
                    make that country a prosperous ally of the United States. Negotiated primarily
                    by <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster">John Foster
                        Dulles</ref> in 1950 and 1951, the Treaty of San Francisco ended the state
                    of war between Japan and 47 of the Allies (most nations allied with the Soviet
                    Union refused to sign), concluded the American Occupation, and excused the
                    Japanese from reparations for the war. Acheson signed the San Francisco Treaty
                    on September 8, 1951, the same day he and Japanese Prime Minister
                        <persName>Yoshida Shigeru</persName> signed the United States-Japanese
                    Security Treaty. The treaty allowed the United States to station troops in
                    Japan, and made the Japanese islands into an important facet of America’s global
                    containment structure. To American leaders, Japan has transformed from World War
                    II enemy to vital ally, and Korea went from a peripheral region to a key battle
                    ground in the Cold War. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>