<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../schemas/milestones.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1953–1960</title>
                <title type="short">1953–1960</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31" target="#east-german-uprising"/>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword">
                <head>
                    <date from="1953" to="1960">1953–1960</date>: Entrenchment of a Bi-Polar Foreign
                    Policy</head>
                <p>Concerns about the international spread of communism and the growing power of the
                    Soviet Union dominated most foreign policy decisions during the administration
                    of President <persName>Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName>.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="eisenhower-dwight-d.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President Dwight D. Eisenhower</head>
                </figure>
                <p>U.S. foreign policymakers observed with concern as the Soviets tightened their
                    hold on Eastern Europe. In Africa and Asia nationalist movements challenged
                    colonial governments. U.S. officials suspected that communists dominated these
                    movements and received support directly from the Soviet Union. In order to
                    counterbalance the Soviet threat, President Eisenhower supported a doctrine of
                    massive retaliation, which called for the development of technology necessary to
                    match and even surpass Soviet nuclear capability. Recognizing that nuclear war
                    was a last resort, U.S. officials supported engaging in conventional limited
                    wars. In an effort to prepare for potential military conflicts, President
                    Eisenhower exercised unprecedented executive authority in deploying the U.S.
                    military abroad, without specific authorization from the U.S. Congress. These
                    Cold War policies served to increase the foreign policymaking power of the
                    presidency and to expand U.S. international obligations.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="dien-bien-phu" ana="vietnam-conflict vietnam laos cambodia">
                <head>Dien Bien Phu &amp; the Fall of French Indochina, <date when="1954"
                        >1954</date>
                </head>
                <p>In the late 1940s, the French struggled to control its colonies in
                        <placeName>Indochina</placeName> - Vietnam, Cambodia, and Laos. Despite
                    financial assistance from the United States, nationalist uprisings against
                    French colonial rule began to take their toll. On May 7, 1954, the French-held
                    garrison at <placeName>Dien Bien Phu</placeName> in Vietnam fell after a four
                    month siege led by Vietnamese nationalist <persName>Ho Chi Minh</persName>.
                    After the fall of Dien Bien Phu, the French pulled out of the region. Concerned
                    about regional instability, the United States became increasingly committed to
                    countering communist nationalists in Indochina. The United States would not pull
                    out of Vietnam for another twenty years.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="french-indochina.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>French Foreign Legionnaire in French Indochina</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Southeast Asia, with Indochina at the center, had long been a region of interest
                    to outside powers. Most of the region fell under European colonial control after
                    the mid-19th century. During World War Two, Japan also sought the resources the
                    area had to offer. After Japanese defeat, many of the countries of Southeast
                    Asia occupied by Japan protested their return to colonial status, resulting in a
                    surge of nationalism. American officials involved in the U.S. occupation of
                    Japan also developed a strong interest in the region, which they viewed as a
                    potential market for Japanese goods and a source of raw materials (like tin,
                    oil, rubber, and rice) to supply Japanese manufacturing.</p>
                <p>Like the other colonial powers, France attempted to reestablish its position in
                    Indochina after 1945, but found that it was difficult. Laos gained its
                    independence in 1949, and Cambodia became independent in 1953. France promised
                    Vietnam its autonomy by 1949, but only offered limited independence, with France
                    continuing to oversee defense and foreign policy. To counter the influence of
                    popular nationalist Ho Chi Minh, the French attempted to reinstate former
                    emperor Bao Dai, but he was never as popular as Ho Chi Minh, and Vietnam’s
                    independence movement continued to grow. <persName>Bao Dai</persName> eventually
                    abdicated a second time and lived out his life in exile in France.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="hochiminh.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Ho Chi Minh</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although Ho Chi Minh would become famous for leading the North Vietnamese forces
                    against the United States in the 1960s, despite his communist leanings, he was
                    not at the outset anti-American. He had been disappointed by the lack of support
                    given native peoples struggling for independence from colonial rule at the
                    Versailles Conference that ended World War I. In the 1940s, he made repeated
                    requests for American aid and campaigned for independence. Following
                    unsuccessful discussions with the French in 1946, general war broke out between
                    Ho Chi Minh’s Viet Minh forces and French troops in the northern part of
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>U.S. interests in the late 1940s and early 1950s did not, however, include
                    supporting Vietnam’s effort to gain independence under a nationalist with
                    communist leanings. Active communist rebellions in Malaya and the Philippines,
                    and the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/chinese-rev">establishment of the
                        People’s Republic of China</ref> in 1949, caused U.S. officials great
                    concern. President <persName>Eisenhower</persName> explained the link between
                    Vietnam’s status and that of the rest of Southeast Asia through the metaphor of
                    falling dominoes: if one country fell to communism, the rest of them would
                    follow. The United States also required French assistance developing the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty Organization
                        (NATO)</ref> and rebuilding West Germany, and, as such, supported the
                    failing French regime in Indochina. By the time of the Korean War armistice in
                    1953, the United States was already irrevocably committed to defending the
                    French against the increasingly aggressive Viet Minh forces.</p>
                <p>In early 1954, the French army was encamped at Dien Bien Phu, a heavily fortified
                    base located deep in a valley and near communications links on the Laotian
                    border. By mid-March, it was clear that the French were struggling under a Viet
                    Minh seige and that only outside intervention in the form of fresh troops or
                    airstrikes could save them. Though President Eisenhower was determined to
                    prevent a communist victory in Vietnam, the U.S. Congress and officials in the
                    Administration were equally determined not to intervene unless they could do so
                    as a part of a larger coalition. Britain and other members of NATO declined to
                    participate in rescuing what they thought was a lost cause. Dien Bien Phu fell
                    in May, and the French retreated from Vietnam.</p>
                <p>In the wake of the French defeat, the French and Vietnamese, along with
                    representatives from the United States and China, met in Geneva in mid-1954 to
                    discuss the future of Indochina. They reached two agreements. First, the French
                    and the Viet Minh agreed to a cease-fire and a temporary division of the country
                    along the 17th parallel. French forces would remain in the South, and Ho Chi
                    Minh’s forces would control the North. The second agreement promised that
                    neither the North nor the South would join alliances with outside parties, and
                    called for general elections in 1956. Laos and Cambodia were to remain
                    neutral.</p>
                <p>The United States did not sign the second agreement, establishing instead its own
                    government in South Vietnam. As the French pulled out, the United States
                    appointed Ngo Dinh Diem to lead South Vietnam. Like Bao Dai, Diem was an
                    unpopular choice in Vietnam as he had waited out the nationalist struggle
                    against France abroad. Diem had also collaborated with the Japanese occupation,
                    but his Catholicism appealed to the Western powers. The United States also
                    supported the formation of the Southeast Asia Treaty Organization, designed to
                    respond if there was an armed attack on any nation in the region.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="east-german-uprising"
                ana="eisenhower-dwight-d dulles-john-foster germany russia north-atlantic-treaty-organization alliances">
                <head>The East German Uprising, 1953</head>
                <p>On June 16, 1953, workers in East Berlin rose in protest against government
                    demands to increase productivity. Within days, nearly a million East Germans
                    joined the protests and began rioting across hundreds of East German cities and
                    towns. In order to prolong the uprising and win support for the West, the United
                    States established an aid program to feed East Germans. The program, which
                    continued until October 1953, proved very popular with East Germans and
                    highlighted the repression and privations of life under communism.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="east-german-uprising.jpg" height="450px" width="318px"/>
                    <head>Russian Tank in front of the German Imperial Court of Justice, Leipzig,
                        June 17, 1953. (Deutsches Bundesarchiv)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The uprising was a product of Soviet and East German reaction to West Germany’s
                    formal alignment to the West. In May 1952, Western powers signed the General
                    (Bonn) and European Defense Community (EDC) treaties. These treaties were, in
                    essence, a rejection of Stalin’s March 1952 offer to agree to a unified Germany
                    on the condition that it remained unarmed. In response to West Germany’s
                    absorption and rearmament by the Western powers, the Soviets and the regime of
                    East German General Secretary Walter Ulbricht decided to unequivocally transform
                    East Germany into a Soviet satellite state.</p>
                <p>At the heart of East Germany’s transformation, a process dubbed “Constructing
                    Socialism” enacted forced collectivization of agriculture, a campaign against
                    private trade and Industry, and the development of heavy industry.
                    Collectivization produced severe food shortages, which began in the winter and
                    spring of 1953. Forced remilitarization, the suppression of churches, and the
                    persecution of opposition also added to the strain on the population. East
                    Germans emigrated en masse to West Germany via West Berlin, protest movements
                    flourished, and expressions of general dissatisfaction characterized public
                    life.</p>
                <p>In April 1953, after the death of Stalin, Soviet authorities sought to rein in
                    Ulbricht’s regime, which advocated even more collectivization. Moscow persuaded
                    Ulbricht to relax or discontinue parts of the “Constructing Socialism” movement
                    in a new campaign called the “New Course.” Because many people perceived the
                    “New Course” as a capitulation to the West, and also because the treatment of
                    manufacturing workers remained harsh, the relaxation of “Constructing Socialism”
                    transformed general discontent into open defiance. On June 16, a few hundred
                    workers called for a general strike. The next day, demonstrations and rioting
                    broke out throughout East Germany. The Soviet occupation forces declared martial
                    law and used massive military force to suppress the rioting and support the East
                    German regime.</p>
                <p>In response, the United States under the leadership of President Dwight D.
                    Eisenhower showed its support for the uprising by establishing a large scale
                    food relief program for East Germans, which was officially announced on July 10
                    and commenced on July 27. Under this program, the United States pledged to
                    distribute $15 million worth of food from 35 distribution centers established in
                    West Berlin, to which East Germans had access through East Berlin. The so called
                    “Eisenhower packages” contained lard, peas, flour, and pasteurized milk. The
                    United States distributed over 5 million packages through these centers to over
                    a million East Germans who were able to gain access to East Berlin. In response,
                    the East German Government cut off rail and bus traffic to West Berlin, which
                    further heightened tensions. The program put Ulbricht on the defensive and
                    extended the atmosphere of crisis across East Germany.</p>
                <p>In addition to achieving humanitarian objectives through this assistance program,
                    the United States sought to destabilize East Germany and weaken Ulbricht’s
                    regime. The Eisenhower administration also hoped to deter Soviet initiatives to
                    start talks on German reunification. Washington believed that any movement
                    toward unification on Soviet terms or even a lessening of the crisis would
                    threaten the delicate process of Western European military integration and
                    weaken an already tenuous French resolve to ratify the European Defense
                    Community (EDC) treaty. The United States was also concerned that unification
                    negations would undermine West German Chancellor Konrad Adenauer because he had
                    based his administration on alignment with the West. President Eisenhower and
                    Secretary of State John Foster Dulles attempted to exploit the uprising in East
                    Germany in order to undercut the Soviet Union’s post-Stalin “Peace and Unity”
                    campaign, bolster support for West German rearmament and the EDC, and weaken the
                    Soviets’ initiative toward German unification.</p>
                <p>As the food aid continued, Western European governments grew apprehensive that
                    Soviet military action against West Berlin was a real possibility. The campaign
                    also experienced diminishing returns as the East German regime tightened control
                    over the population and prevented people from receiving the aid. The campaign
                    ended in early October.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="seato">
                <head>Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (SEATO), <date when="1954">1954</date>
                </head>
                <p>In September of 1954, the United States, France, Great Britain, New Zealand,
                    Australia, the Philippines, Thailand and Pakistan formed the Southeast Asia
                    Treaty Organization, or SEATO.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="seato.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>SEATO Meeting in Manila</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The purpose of the organization was to prevent communism from gaining ground in
                    the region. Although called the “Southeast Asia Treaty Organization,” only two
                    Southeast Asian countries became members. The Philippines joined in part because
                    of its close ties with the United States and in part out of concern over the
                    nascent communist insurgency threatening its own government. Thailand,
                    similarly, joined after learning of a newly established “Thai Autonomous Region”
                    in Yunnan Province in South China, expressing concern about the potential for
                    Chinese communist subversion on its own soil. The rest of the region was far
                    less concerned about the threat of communism to internal stability. Burma and
                    Indonesia both preferred to maintain their neutrality rather than join the
                    organization. Malaya (including Singapore) found it politically difficult to
                    give formal support to the organization, though through its ties with Great
                    Britain it learned of key developments. Finally, the terms of the Geneva
                    Agreements of 1954 signed after the fall of French Indochina prevented Vietnam,
                    Cambodia and Laos from joining any international military alliance, though these
                    countries were ultimately included in the area protected under SEATO and granted
                    “observers” status.</p>
                <p>Most of the SEATO member states were countries located elsewhere but with an
                    interest in the region or the organization. Australia and New Zealand were
                    interested in Asian affairs because of their geographic position in the Pacific.
                    Great Britain and France had long maintained colonies in the region and were
                    interested in developments in the greater Indochina region. For Pakistan, the
                    appeal of the pact was the potential for receiving support in its struggles
                    against India, in spite of the fact that neither country was located in the area
                    under the organization’s jurisdiction. Finally, U.S. officials believed
                    Southeast Asia to be a crucial frontier in the fight against communist
                    expansion, so it viewed SEATO as essential to its global Cold War policy of
                    containment.</p>
                <p>Headquartered in <placeName>Bangkok, Thailand</placeName>, SEATO had only a few
                    formal functions. It maintained no military forces of its own, but the
                    organization hosted joint military exercises for member states each year. As the
                    communist threat appeared to change from one of outright attack to one of
                    internal subversion, SEATO worked to strengthen the economic foundations and
                    living standards of the Southeast Asian States. It sponsored a variety of
                    meetings and exhibitions on cultural, religious and historical topics, and the
                    non-Asian member states sponsored fellowships for Southeast Asian scholars.</p>
                <p>Beyond its activities, the SEATO charter was also vitally important to the
                    American rationale for the Vietnam War. The United States used the organization
                    as its justification for refusing to go forward with the 1956 elections intended
                    to reunify Vietnam, instead maintaining the divide between communist North
                    Vietnam and South Vietnam at the 17th parallel. As the conflict in Vietnam
                    unfolded, the inclusion of Vietnam as a territory under SEATO protection gave
                    the United States the legal framework for its continued involvement there.</p>
                <p>The organization had a number of weaknesses as well. To address the problems
                    attached to the guerrilla movements and local insurrections that plagued the
                    region in the post-colonial years, the SEATO defense treaty called only for
                    consultation, leaving each individual nation to react individually to internal
                    threats. Unlike the <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic
                        Treaty Organization (NATO)</ref>, SEATO had no independent mechanism for
                    obtaining intelligence or deploying military forces, so the potential for
                    collective action was necessarily limited. Moreover, because it incorporated
                    only three Asian members, SEATO faced charges of being a new form of Western
                    colonialism. Linguistic and cultural difficulties between the member states also
                    compounded its problems, making it difficult for SEATO to accomplish many of its
                    goals.</p>
                <p>By the early 1970s, members began to withdraw from the organization. Neither
                    Pakistan nor France supported the U.S. intervention in Vietnam, and both nations
                    were pulling away from the organization in the early 1970s. Pakistan formally
                    left SEATO in 1973, because the organization had failed to provide it with
                    assistance in its ongoing conflict against India. When the Vietnam War ended in
                    1975, the most prominent reason for SEATO’s existence disappeared. As a result,
                    SEATO formally disbanded in 1977.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="taiwan-strait-crises" ana="taiwan china">
                <head>The Taiwan Straits Crises: <date from="1954" to="1955">1954–55</date> and
                        <date when="1958">1958</date>
                </head>
                <p>Tensions between the <placeName>People’s Republic of China (PRC)</placeName> and
                    the <placeName>Republic of China (ROC)</placeName> in the 1950s resulted in
                    armed conflict over strategic islands in the <placeName>Taiwan
                        Strait</placeName>. On two separate occasions during the 1950s, the PRC
                    bombed islands controlled by the ROC. The United States responded by actively
                    intervening on behalf of the ROC.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="taiwan-strait.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Map of the Taiwan Strait</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The importance of the islands in the Taiwan Strait was rooted in their geographic
                    proximity to China and Taiwan and their role in the Chinese Civil War. Jinmen
                    (Quemoy), two miles from the mainland Chinese city of Xiamen, and Mazu, ten
                    miles from the city of Fuzhou, are located approximately one hundred miles west
                    of Taiwan. When the Nationalist Government of the ROC under <persName>Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> recognized that it had lost control of mainland China
                    during the Chinese Civil War, the officials and part of the Nationalist Army
                    fled to the island of Taiwan, establishing troops on these two islands and the
                    Dachen Islands further north. In the early 1950s, Chiang’s forces launched minor
                    attacks from Jinmen and Mazu against the coast of mainland China. Leadership on
                    both sides of the strait continued to view the islands as a potential launching
                    pad for an ROC invasion to retake the Chinese mainland and had an interest in
                    controlling the islands.</p>
                <p>U.S. policy toward East Asia in the early Cold War contributed to the tensions in
                    the Taiwan Strait. In late 1949 and early 1950, American officials were prepared
                    to let PRC forces cross the Strait and defeat Chiang, but after the outbreak of
                    the Korean War in June 1950, the United States sent its Seventh Fleet into the
                    Taiwan Strait to prevent the Korean conflict from spreading south. The
                    appearance of the Seventh Fleet angered the Chinese Communists, who transferred
                    their troops poised for an invasion of Taiwan to the Korean front. This served
                    to delay military conflict in the Strait until the United States withdrew its
                    fleet after the Korean War.</p>
                <p>Over the next few years, the U.S. Government took steps that allied it more
                    firmly to the ROC Government on Taiwan. In 1954, the United States led the
                    creation of the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/seato">Southeast Asia Treaty
                        Organization</ref>, which was designed to unify the region against the
                    perceived Communist threat. Moreover, U.S. officials openly debated the
                    possibility of signing a Mutual Defense Treaty with Chiang Kai-shek. The PRC
                    viewed these developments as threats to its national security and regional
                    leadership. In the interest of bolstering its strategic position in the Taiwan
                    Strait, the PRC began to bombard Jinmen in September 1954, and soon expanded its
                    targets to include Mazu and the Dachen Islands.</p>
                <p>U.S. policymakers considered sending part of the U.S. fleet into the Strait.
                    Discussions centered on whether this maneuver would reopen the Chinese Civil War
                    and, if so, what effect that would have on U.S. security concerns in the region.
                    U.S. policymakers did not want to be drawn into the conflict, but wanted the ROC
                    to maintain control of the islands. The loss of Jinmen and Mazu to the People’s
                    Republic might mean an irreparable blow to Nationalist Army morale and the
                    legitimacy of the ROC regime on Taiwan. To assert its continued support of that
                    regime, the United States signed the Mutual Defense Treaty with the ROC.
                    Although the treaty did not commit the United States to defending the off-shore
                    islands, it promised support if the ROC engaged in a broader conflict with the
                    PRC.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="enlai.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Zhou Enlai</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The situation in the Strait deteriorated in late 1954 and early 1955, prompting
                    the U.S. Government to act. In January 1955, the U.S. Congress passed the
                    “Formosa Resolution,” which gave President Eisenhower total authority to defend
                    Taiwan and the off-shore islands. The U.S. Government then announced its
                    determination to defend Taiwan against communist attack, although it did not
                    specify the territory included within its defensive perimeter. In exchange for a
                    private promise to defend Jinmen and Mazu, however, <persName>Chiang
                        Kai-shek</persName> agreed to withdraw his troops from Dachen, which was
                    strategically ambiguous and difficult to defend.</p>
                <p>The Eisenhower Administration considered many options, ranging from convincing
                    Chiang Kai-shek to give up the islands to employing nuclear weapons against the
                    PRC. Before any of these options became necessary, at the Afro-Asian Conference
                    in April 1955 in Bandung PRC Foreign Minister <persName>Zhou Enlai</persName>
                    announced a desire to negotiate with the United States. The PRC’s sudden shift
                    could have stemmed from pressure from the Soviet Union to ease tensions, concern
                    about the very real possibility of war with the United States, or changes in
                    internal politics. In September, 1955, the PRC and the United States began talks
                    at Geneva to address the issue of repatriation of nationals, but also to discuss
                    preventing the escalation of future conflicts.</p>
                <p>Although there were good reasons for the PRC to stand down in 1955, it resumed
                    its bombardment of Jinmen and Mazu in 1958. This time, the PRC took advantage of
                    the fact that international attention was focused on U.S. intervention in
                    Lebanon and barred ROC efforts to re-supply garrisons on the off-shore islands.
                    The PRC also wanted to protest continued U.S. support of the ROC regime. Once
                    again, President Eisenhower was concerned that the loss of the islands would
                    hurt Nationalist morale and might be a precursor to the Communist conquest of
                    Taiwan. The United States thus arranged to re-supply ROC garrisons on Jinmen and
                    Mazu. This brought an abrupt end to the bombardment and eased the crisis.
                    Eventually, the PRC and ROC came to an arrangement in which they shelled each
                    other’s garrisons on alternate days. This continued for twenty years until the
                    PRC and the United States normalized relations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="china-talks">
                <head>U.S.-China Ambassadorial Talks, <date from="1955" to="1970">1955–1970</date>
                </head>
                <p>On August 1, 1955, the United States and the <placeName>People’s Republic of
                        China (PRC)</placeName> opened a series of ambassadorial-level talks in
                    Geneva to discuss the repatriation of nationals and other issues of mutual
                    concern. Because the two countries did not have formal diplomatic relations, the
                    talks were the principle form of contact between them for sixteen years. The
                    Chinese proposed the negotiations because Sino-American tensions were high,
                    causing concern to bystanders throughout the region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ambassadorial-talks.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Henry Kissinger and Chairman Mao, with Zhou Enlai behind them in
                        Beijing</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In late 1954 and early 1955, <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/taiwan-strait-crises">the PRC’s bombardment of
                        the off-shore islands in the Taiwan Strait</ref> had brought the United
                    States and China to the brink of confrontation. The crisis ended when the
                    Chinese Foreign Minister suggested that the PRC would be willing to meet with
                    the United States for a series of bi-lateral talks. The United States proposed
                    that the two nations send individuals of ambassadorial rank to meet in Geneva.
                    When the talks began, the United States was represented by U.S. Ambassador to
                    Czechoslovakia <persName>U. Alexis Johnson</persName>, and the Chinese side by
                    Chinese Ambassador to Poland <persName>Wang Bingnan</persName>. At the outset,
                    there were two items on the agenda: to negotiate for the repatriation of
                    nationals in either country, and to address any “other practical matters of
                    concern to both sides.”</p>
                <p>The repatriation of nationals was the primary issue as the talks began. After the
                    Chinese Communist victory in 1949 and the outbreak of the Korean War in 1950,
                    citizens from both nations were stranded behind newly closed borders. Once it
                    became clear that the United States would not recognize the PRC, the Chinese
                    arrested or denied exit permits to U.S. missionaries, businessmen, and scholars
                    still living in China. These several dozen individuals were neither tried for
                    crimes nor given any indication of how long they would be held. By the same
                    token, the U.S. Government declared a “state of emergency” and prevented Chinese
                    students and scholars with technical skills capable of aiding China from
                    returning home. Of some 5,000 Chinese students in the United States in 1949, 105
                    were held for several years.</p>
                <p>After six weeks of discussions, on September 10, 1955, issued an “agreed
                    announcement” that acknowledged the right of Americans in China and Chinese in
                    the United States to return freely and “expeditiously” to their countries of
                    origin, and it permitted anyone who believed his or her return was being
                    prevented to seek assistance from a designated third party. For Americans
                    detained in China, the third party was the British Embassy, and for Chinese in
                    the United States, the Indian Embassy acted as the intermediary.</p>
                <p>After completing this agreement, the two sides faced obstacles in implementing
                    it. China proposed other topics for discussion, including ending the U.S.
                    embargo on China that had been in place since the start of the Korean War in
                    1950 and a future meeting of Chinese and U.S. foreign ministers. U.S.
                    policymakers, however, were unwilling to address these topics before all U.S.
                    citizens still in China were released and allowed to depart. As the two sides
                    failed to see eye to eye on the implementation of this agreement, the Geneva
                    talks became an open forum for accusations and recriminations over the next
                    several years. The Chinese representatives demanded the repatriation of all
                    Chinese citizens in the United States, but the U.S. Government claimed that it
                    did not prevent them from leaving and some chose to stay. Meanwhile, U.S.
                    officials accused the Chinese of ignoring the text of the announcement and
                    continuing to hold American citizens as political prisoners on false charges.
                    China insisted that it had the right to punish lawbreakers, and no criminal
                    could be released until his or her full sentence had been served.</p>
                <p>Other issues caused difficulties for the talks. The United States proved
                    unwilling to lift the embargo, to allow exchanges of journalists, or to engage
                    in high-level meetings until China agreed to renounce the use of force in
                    unifying Taiwan with the mainland. For China, Taiwan was strictly an internal
                    issue. The status of Taiwan became the major obstacle that prevented
                    accommodation between the United States and China until the early 1970s.
                    Protocol issues affected the talks as well. In late 1957, the United States
                    attempted to end the talks by transferring Ambassador Johnson to Thailand and
                    sending a representative of lower rank to meet with Wang. As a result of this
                    action, the two sides suspended the talks for nine months. In September of 1958,
                    the U.S. Government appointed its Ambassador to Poland, <persName>Jacob
                        Beam</persName>, as its representative and the talks continued, on and off,
                    in Warsaw.</p>
                <p>After the initial agreement on repatriation in the autumn of 1955, the talks
                    continued for sixteen years and 136 total meetings without making further
                    progress. They ended when President <persName>Richard Nixon</persName> visited
                    China and set the stage for eventual U.S. recognition of the People’s Republic.
                    Although they accomplished little in terms of formal agreements, the talks did
                    provide China and the United States with an avenue for negotiation, so that
                    misunderstandings did not escalate into outright conflict. In this way, the
                    U.S.-China Ambassadorial Talks served as an important factor in relieving
                    tension in East Asia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="warsaw-treaty">
                <head>The Warsaw Treaty Organization, <date when="1955">1955</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Warsaw Treaty Organization (also known as the Warsaw Pact) was a political
                    and military alliance established on May 14, 1955 between the <placeName>Soviet
                        Union</placeName> and several Eastern European countries. The Soviet Union
                    formed this alliance as a counterbalance to the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty Organization
                        (NATO)</ref>, a collective security alliance concluded between the United
                    States, Canada and Western European nations in 1949.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="warsawpact.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Presidential Palace in Warsaw where the Warsaw Pact was signed</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Warsaw Pact supplemented existing agreements. Following World War II, the
                    Soviet Union had concluded bilateral treaties with each of the East European
                    states except for East Germany, which was still part of the Soviet
                    occupied-territory of Germany. When the Federal Republic of Germany entered NATO
                    in early May 1955, the Soviets feared the consequences of a strengthened NATO
                    and a rearmed West Germany and hoped that the Warsaw Treaty Organization could
                    both contain West Germany and negotiate with NATO as an equal partner. Soviet
                    leadership also noted that civil unrest was on the rise in Eastern European
                    countries and determined that a unified, multilateral political and military
                    alliance would tie Eastern European capitals more closely to Moscow.</p>
                <p>The original signatories to the Warsaw Treaty Organization were the Soviet Union,
                    Albania, Poland, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Bulgaria, Romania, and the German
                    Democratic Republic. Although the members of the Warsaw Pact pledged to defend
                    each other if one or more of them came under attack, emphasized non-interference
                    in the internal affairs of its members, and supposedly organized itself around
                    collective decision-making, the Soviet Union ultimately controlled most of the
                    Pact’s decisions. The Soviet Union also used the Pact to contain popular dissent
                    in its European satellites, for example in Hungary in 1956, in Czechoslovakia in
                    1968, and in Poland in 1981.</p>
                <p>By the 1980s, the Warsaw Treaty Organization was beset by problems related to the
                    economic slowdown in all Eastern European countries. By the late 1980s political
                    changes in most of the member states made the Pact virtually ineffectual. In
                    September 1990, East Germany left the Pact in preparation for reunification with
                    West Germany. By October, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, and Poland had withdrawn from
                    all Warsaw Pact military exercises. The Warsaw Pact officially disbanded in
                    March and July of 1991 following the dissolution of the Soviet Union.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="cento" subtype="removed-pending-rewrite">
                <head>The Baghdad Pact (<date when="1955">1955</date>) and the Central Treaty
                    Organization (CENTO)</head>
                <p>The Baghdad Pact was a defensive organization for promoting shared political,
                    military and economic goals founded in 1955 by <placeName>Turkey</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Iraq</placeName>, <placeName>Great Britain</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> and <placeName>Iran</placeName>. Similar to
                    the North Atlantic Treaty Organization and the Southeast Asia Treaty
                    Organization, the main purpose of the Baghdad Pact was to prevent communist
                    incursions and foster peace in the Middle East. It was renamed the Central
                    Treaty Organization, or CENTO, in 1959 after Iraq pulled out of the Pact.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="centoflag.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>CENTO Flag</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the early 1950s, the United States Government expressed an interest in the
                    formation of a Middle East Command to protect the region against communist
                    encroachment. The nature of some of the ongoing tensions in the region, like
                    Arab-Israeli conflict and Egyptian-led anti-colonialism, made it difficult to
                    forge an alliance that would include both Israel and Western colonial powers.
                    Instead, the U.S shifted its focus to the “Northern Tier,” referring to the line
                    of countries that formed a border between the U.S.S.R. and the Middle East. The
                    idea was to conclude an alliance that would link the southernmost member of the
                        <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty Organization
                        (NATO)</ref>, Turkey, with the westernmost member of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/seato">Southeast Asia Treaty Organization
                        (SEATO)</ref>, Pakistan. Turkey and Pakistan signed an agreement in 1954 to
                    increase security and stability in the region. In February 1955, Iraq and Turkey
                    signed a “pact of mutual cooperation” in Baghdad to resist outside aggression,
                    and they opened it to other countries in the region as well. In April, the
                    United Kingdom announced its intention to adhere to the Pact, and it was
                    followed by Pakistan and finally, Iran. The King of Jordan considered joining,
                    but he could not overcome domestic opposition to the pact. The United States
                    signed individual agreements with each of the nations in the Pact, but it did
                    not formally join. Instead, the United States participated as an observer and
                    took part in committee meetings.</p>
                <p>Developments in the Middle East in the years that followed weakened the Pact. In
                    1956, Egyptian leader <persName>Gamal Abdel Nasser</persName> seized control of
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/suez">Suez Canal</ref>, an important
                    international waterway. Israel responded by invading the Sinai peninsula, and
                    British and French forces intervened. The outcome of the incident was a profound
                    loss of British prestige in the region, which in turn damaged its position of
                    leadership in the Baghdad Pact. A series of events in 1958, including an
                    Egyptian-Syrian union, an Iraqi revolution, and civil unrest in Lebanon
                    threatened regional stability. In response to these developments, the United
                    States invoked the 1957 Eisenhower Doctrine as justification for intervening in
                    Lebanon. The members of the Baghdad Pact except for Iraq endorsed the U.S.
                    intervention, and in 1959, Iraq announced it was formally leaving the
                    arrangement. As a result, the other signatories to the Baghdad Pact formed the
                    Central Treaty Organization, or CENTO. Although the United States was still not
                    a member of the organization, it did sign bilateral military aid treaties with
                    Pakistan, Iran and Turkey, ensuring that it would continue to be active in
                    supporting the CENTO members.</p>
                <p>CENTO never actually provided its members with a means for guaranteeing
                    collective defense. After the withdrawal of Iraq from the Baghdad Pact, CENTO
                    moved its headquarters to Ankara, Turkey, and the United States continued to
                    support the organization as an associate, but not as a member. CENTO never
                    created a permanent military command structure or armed forces, but the United
                    States provided assistance to its allies in the region. By the close of the
                    Eisenhower Administration, it had become clear to CENTO members that the
                    organization was a better conduit for economic and technical cooperation than it
                    was a military alliance. In 1979, the Iranian revolution led to the overthrow of
                    the shah and Iran’s withdrawal from CENTO. Pakistan also withdrew that year
                    after determining the organization no longer had a role to play in bolstering
                    its security. CENTO formally disbanded in 1979.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bandung-conf">
                <head>Bandung Conference (Asian-African Conference), <date when="1955">1955</date>
                </head>
                <p>In April, 1955, representatives from twenty-nine governments of Asian and African
                    nations gathered in <placeName>Bandung, Indonesia</placeName> to discuss peace
                    and the role of the Third World in the Cold War, economic development, and
                    decolonization.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bandung.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Gedung Merdeka in Bandung during the Asia-Africa Conference in 1955</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The core principles of the Bandung Conference were political self-determination,
                    mutual respect for sovereignty, non-aggression, non-interference in internal
                    affairs, and equality. These issues were of central importance to all
                    participants in the conference, most of which had recently emerged from colonial
                    rule. The governments of Burma, India, Indonesia, Pakistan and Sri Lanka
                    co-sponsored the Bandung Conference, and they brought together an additional
                    twenty-four nations from Asia, Africa and the Middle East. Because the
                    decolonization process was still ongoing, the delegates at the conference took
                    it upon themselves to speak for other colonized peoples (especially in Africa)
                    that had not yet established independent governments. The delegates built upon
                    the Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence, worked out in negotiations between
                    India and China in 1954, as they sought to build solidarity among recently
                    independent nations.</p>
                <p>At the close of the Bandung Conference attendees signed a communique that
                    included a range of concrete objectives. These goals included the promotion of
                    economic and cultural cooperation, protection of human rights and the principle
                    of self-determination, a call for an end to racial discrimination wherever it
                    occurred, and a reiteration of the importance of peaceful coexistence. The
                    leaders hoped to focus on the potential for collaboration among the nations of
                    the third world, promoting efforts to reduce their reliance on Europe and North
                    America.</p>
                <p>The Bandung Conference and its final resolution laid the foundation for the
                    nonaligned movement during the Cold War. Leaders of developing countries banded
                    together to avoid being forced to take sides in the Cold War contest. The
                    initial motivation for the movement was the promotion of peace. In the 1970s it
                    grew increasingly radical in its condemnation of the policies of the Cold War
                    super powers. Although the nonaligned movement continued until the end of the
                    Cold War, the solidarity produced by the “spirit of Bandung” had weakened by end
                    of the 1960s, by which time most of the original participants in the conference
                    were no longer in power in their respective countries.</p>
                <p>The United States Government initially viewed the Bandung Conference, and the
                    nonaligned movement that emerged from it, with caution. Observers in the United
                    States expressed concern that the meeting was a sign of a leftward shift in the
                    ideological leanings of the newly independent nations of Africa and Asia.
                    Moreover, the conference revealed two contradictions in U.S. foreign policy with
                    regard to decolonization in the Third World. First, the United States Government
                    found itself caught between its desire to support decolonization and
                    self-determination in Southeast Asia and Africa and its reliance on the colonial
                    powers of Western Europe as allies against the communist Eastern Bloc.
                    Cooperation with Britain, France and the Netherlands was vital to U.S. policy in
                    Europe, but supporting decolonization would be tantamount to opposing those
                    allies. Second, the conference coincided with a fundamental shift in U.S. race
                    relations. The 1954 <hi rend="italic">Brown v. the Board of Education</hi>
                    decision had declared school segregation unconstitutional, but the process of
                    ending the Jim Crow laws in the American South was long and difficult. Many
                    countries around the world, particularly newly independent nations, followed the
                    U.S. civil rights movement with interest and questioned the extent to which U.S.
                    rhetoric of equality and self-determination matched the status of civil rights
                    in the United States. U.S. leaders worried that the anti-colonialism of Bandung
                    and the discussion of global racial politics taking place there could turn
                    anti-American or anti-Western.</p>
                <p>In the end, however, the Bandung Conference did not lead to a general
                    denunciation of the West as U.S. observers had feared. Instead, the participants
                    displayed a wide range of ideologies and loyalties. U.S. allies in Asia were
                    able to represent their shared interests with the United States in the
                    conference meetings, and Chinese Premier <persName>Zhou Enlai</persName> took a
                    moderate line in his speeches to the delegates. Nevertheless, Bandung gave a
                    voice to emerging nations and demonstrated that they could be a force in future
                    world politics, inside or outside the Cold War framework.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="khrushchev-20th-congress">
                <head>Khrushchev and the Twentieth Congress of the Communist Party, <date
                        when="1956">1956</date>
                </head>
                <p>In February, 1956, Soviet leader <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName> made a
                    keynote address to international communist leaders at the Twentieth Congress of
                    the Communist Party of the Soviet Union. He used his speech to make unexpected
                    and unprecedented condemnations of the policies and excesses of his predecessor,
                        <persName>Joseph Stalin</persName>, setting off a chain of reaction that led
                    to calls for reform in <placeName>Eastern Europe</placeName> and a new policy in
                    the Soviet Union for dealing with the West.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="nk.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Nikita Khrushchev</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After Stalin died in 1953, four men joined together to lead the country:
                        <persName>Georgi Malenkov</persName>, <persName>Lavrenti Beria</persName>,
                        <persName>Vyacheslav Molotov</persName>, and <persName>Nikita
                        Khrushchev</persName>. As head of the <abbr>KGB</abbr>, Beria was perceived
                    as a threat to the other three, and they arranged for his execution. As Soviet
                    Premier in 1953, Malenkov oversaw the first signs of the Soviet “peace
                    offensive,” in which a series of overtures to the West indicated the beginning
                    of a change in party policies. By 1955, however, Khrushchev had consolidated his
                    power, forcing Malenkov to resign as Premier due to his close ties with Beria,
                    and Khrushchev emerged as the sole leader.</p>
                <p>The Party Congress was an organization that included some 1,500 Communist leaders
                    from fifty-six countries around the world, and its twentieth meeting opened in
                    Moscow on <date when="1956-02-14">February 14, 1956</date>. The Congress
                    convened roughly every four years, and it served as the major forum through
                    which the central leadership in <placeName>Moscow</placeName> informed
                    communists from across the world about policies and ideology. In a private
                    session of the Soviet representatives which was closed to foreign delegations,
                    Nikita Khrushchev gave a speech denouncing Stalin. The new Soviet leader had
                    spent many hours deliberating about his message to the gathering. In preparation
                    for his participation in the Party Congress, Khrushchev had joined the Presidium
                    of the Supreme Soviet, an executive governing body in the Soviet government, in
                    a two-month debate about Stalin’s legacy and the extent to which his successors
                    could be publicly critical of Stalinist policies. Khrushchev was keenly aware of
                    the fact that if he gave a speech that proved too critical of Stalin or which
                    seemed to criticize the Communist system rather than just the former leader and
                    the word of it spread, it could give Communism’s opponents and international
                    anti-communists ammunition against the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> and
                    the international movement as a whole. However, he saw the Party as being in
                    danger of stagnation from years of oppression and Stalinist purges, so calling
                    for decentralization and denouncing the areas in which Stalin had strayed from
                    socialist ideology was a way to revitalize the party and secure his own position
                    as its leader.</p>
                <p>When Khrushchev finally made his “secret speech,” he shocked the gathered
                    representatives at the Party Congress. Over the course of his address, he
                    condemned the brutality of the Stalinist regime, particularly the purges that
                    led to the torture and execution of some wholly innocent party loyalists.
                    Khrushchev was careful not to extend his condemnation to the persecution of
                    non-communists, because as a rising star of the Communist Party he too had
                    played a role in these purges. Instead, he noted the ways in which Stalin had
                    misinterpreted and misrepresented otherwise correct ideas and Marxist-Leninist
                    thought in a paranoid determination to stay in power. In terms of foreign
                    policy, Khrushchev reversed the Stalinist policy which assumed that a war with
                    the capitalist West was inevitable and instead advocated a new policy of
                    “peaceful coexistence.” Because it reconsidered Stalin’s legacy, the address
                    became known as “Stalin’s Second Funeral.” The speech became the opening salvo
                    in a larger effort at reforming the party and making it more efficient, but it
                    also had important consequences for Soviet external relations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="allen-dulles.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>CIA Chief, Allen Dulles</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Khrushchev’s speech was supposed to be private. It was intended only for internal
                    Communist Party consideration, but word of the events unfolding at the Twentieth
                    Party Congress quickly traveled across the Iron Curtain. In addition to the
                    rumors of what had been said, Israeli intelligence officers obtained a copy of
                    the complete speech and shared it with the <persName>Eisenhower</persName>
                    Administration. Reactions varied. U.S. CIA chief, <persName>Allen
                        Dulles</persName>, struck by the unexpected reversal in policy espoused in
                    the speech, wondered if Khrushchev had been drunk and speaking extemporaneously.
                    After an internal debate in the CIA, Dulles suggested to his brother and
                    Secretary of State, <ref target="/departmenthistory/people/dulles-john-foster"
                        >John Foster Dulles</ref>, that the United States leak the speech to the
                    press. Eisenhower agreed, and it was sent to the <hi rend="italic">New York
                        Times</hi>. </p>
                <p>In the immediate aftermath of the speech, the course of de-Stalinization suited
                    U.S. interests, as the internal crisis that was expected to emerge out of the
                    shift in policy temporarily paralyzed the Soviet Union. The Eisenhower
                    Administration watched, but did not interfere, as the speech became the impetus
                    for a series of grassroots movements demanding democratic reforms in
                        <placeName>Eastern Europe</placeName>. Protests broke out in
                        <placeName>Poland</placeName> and <placeName>Hungary</placeName> in the
                    summer and autumn of 1956, both with tragic consequences. In Poland, the
                    Communist Party leadership proved uncertain how to address the demonstrations,
                    and overreacted by sending in a military force to put down the protest. The
                    situation in Hungary was even more extreme and month-long demonstrations ended
                    with Soviet military intervention and thousands of casualties. In Asia,
                    Communist leaders in the <placeName>People’s Republic of China</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> expressed grave doubts about the reforms
                    indicated by Khrushchev.</p>
                <p>Although Khrushchev played a role in shutting down the rebellions in the Soviet
                    satellites in Eastern Europe, he followed up on his address to the Twentieth
                    Party Congress by continuing to advocate reforms and increased cooperation with
                    the West. As a result, there were early signs of détente in the late 1950s, even
                    though progress was delayed first by the U-2 incident and later by the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Cuban Missile
                        Crisis</ref>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="suez">
                <head>The Suez Crisis, <date when="1956">1956</date>
                </head>
                <p>On July 26, 1956, Egyptian President Gamal Abdel Nasser announced the
                    nationalization of the Suez Canal Company, the joint British-French enterprise
                    which had owned and operated the Suez Canal since its construction in 1869.
                    Nasser’s announcement came about following months of mounting political tensions
                    between Egypt, Britain, and France. Although Nasser offered full economic
                    compensation for the Company, the British and French Governments, long
                    suspicious of Nasser’s opposition to the continuation of their political
                    influence in the region, were outraged by the nationalization. The Egyptian
                    leader, in turn, resented what he saw as European efforts to perpetuate their
                    colonial domination.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="suez.jpg" height="450px" width="284px"/>
                    <head>Nine members of United Nations Security Council signify support of the
                        resolution endorsing operation of the Suez Canal on Oct. 14, 1956.(AP
                        Photo/Tom Fitzsimmons)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Eisenhower administration, worried by the prospect of the outbreak of
                    hostilities between its NATO allies and an emergent, influential Middle Eastern
                    power (and the possible intervention of the Soviet Union in such a conflict),
                    attempted to broker a diplomatic settlement of the British-French-Egyptian
                    dispute. On September 9, U.S. Secretary of State John Foster Dulles proposed the
                    creation of a Suez Canal Users’ Association (SCUA), an international consortium
                    of 18 of the world’s leading maritime nations, to operate the Canal. Although
                    SCUA would have given Britain, France, and Egypt an equal stake in the Canal,
                    this, and various other U.S. and international mediation efforts failed to win
                    the full support of any of the contending powers.</p>
                <p>In discussions with the United States between August and October, the British
                    Government repeatedly hinted that it might resort to force in dealing with
                    Nasser. At the same time, the British and French held secret military
                    consultations with Israel, who regarded Nasser as a threat to its security,
                    resulting in the creation of a joint plan to invade Egypt and overthrow its
                    President. In keeping with these plans, Israeli forces attacked across Egypt’s
                    Sinai Peninsula on October 29, 1956, advancing to within 10 miles of the Suez
                    Canal. Under the pretext of protecting the Canal from the two belligerents,
                    Britain and France landed troops of their own a few days later.</p>
                <p>In response, the Eisenhower administration, concerned about dissociating the
                    United States from European colonialism—especially in light of its strident
                    condemnation of the Soviet intervention in Hungary the same week—as well as the
                    possibility that the Soviets would intervene to assist Nasser, pressured Britain
                    and France to accept a United Nations ceasefire on November 6. Moreover, the
                    United States voted for U.N. resolutions publicly condemning the invasion and
                    approving the creation of a U.N. peacekeeping force. Washington’s public censure
                    of two of its most important allies temporarily soured relations with London and
                    Paris and helped contribute to the resignation of British Prime Minister Anthony
                    Eden in January 1957. Concurrently, U.S. worries about the continued viability
                    of European (particularly British) political and military power in the Middle
                    East in the aftermath of the Suez Crisis prompted the creation of the Eisenhower
                    Doctrine, which gave the administration increased power to aid countries in the
                    region. By March 1957, however, the U.S.–U.K. bilateral relationship had
                    recovered under Eden’s successor, Harold Macmillan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="sputnik">
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi>, <date when="1957">1957</date>
                </head>
                <p>On October 4, 1957, the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> launched the earth’s
                    first artificial satellite, <hi rend="italic">Sputnik-1</hi>. The successful
                    launch came as a shock to experts and citizens in the <placeName>United
                        States</placeName>, who had hoped that the United States would accomplish
                    this scientific advancement first.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="sputnick.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Russian stamp commemorating <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi> Journey</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The fact that the Soviets were successful fed fears that the U.S. military had
                    generally fallen behind in developing new technology. As a result, the launch of
                        <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi> served to intensify the arms race and raise
                    Cold War tensions. During the 1950s, both the United States and the Soviet Union
                    were working to develop new technology. Nazi Germany had been close to
                    developing the world’s first intercontinental ballistic missile (ICBM) near the
                    end of the Second World War, and German scientists aided research in both
                    countries in the wake of that conflict. Both countries were also engaged in
                    developing satellites as a part of a goal set by the International Council of
                    Scientific Unions, which had called for the launch of satellite technology
                    during late 1957 or 1958. Over the course of the decade, the United States
                    tested several varieties of rockets and missiles, but all of these tests ended
                    in failure.</p>
                <p>The Soviet launch of the first <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi> satellite was one
                    accomplishment in a string of technological successes. Few in the United States
                    had anticipated it, and even those who did were not aware of just how impressive
                    it would be. At 184 pounds, the Russian satellite was much heavier than anything
                    the United States was developing at the time, and its successful launch was
                    quickly followed by the launch of two additional satellites, including one that
                    carried a dog into space. Together, these orbited the earth every 90-minutes and
                    created fear that the United States lagged far behind in technological
                    capability. These concerns were compounded when the United States learned that
                    the Soviet Union also tested the first intercontinental ballistic missile that
                    year.</p>
                <p>Although President <persName>Dwight Eisenhower</persName> had tried to downplay
                    the importance of the <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi> launch to the American
                    people, he poured additional funds and resources into the space program in an
                    effort to catch up. The U.S. Government suffered a severe setback in December of
                    1957 when its first artificial satellite, named <hi rend="italic">Vanguard</hi>,
                    exploded on the launch pad, serving as a very visible reminder of how much the
                    country had yet to accomplish to be able to compete militarily with the Soviets.
                    At last, on January 31, 1958, the United States succeeded in launching its first
                    satellite, the <hi rend="italic">Explorer</hi>. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Explorer</hi> was still slighter than <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi>, but
                    its launch sent it deeper into space. The Soviets responded with yet another
                    launch, and the space race continued.</p>
                <p>The success of <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi> had a major impact on the Cold War
                    and the United States. Fear that they had fallen behind led U.S. policymakers to
                    accelerate space and weapons programs. In the late 1950s, Soviet Premier
                        <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName> boasted about Soviet technological
                    superiority and growing stockpiles of ICBMs, so the United States worked
                    simultaneously to develop its own ICBMs to counter what it assumed was a growing
                    stockpile of Soviet missiles directed against the United States. With both
                    countries researching new technology, talk of creating a treaty banning nuclear
                    testing faded away for several years. In this way, the launch of Sputnik fueled
                    both the space race and the arms race, in addition to increasing Cold War
                    tensions, as each country worked to prepare new methods of attacking the other.
                    Eventually, lawmakers and political campaigners in the United States
                    successfully exploited the fear of a “missile gap” developing between U.S. and
                    Soviet nuclear arsenals in the 1960 presidential election, which brought
                        <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> to power over Eisenhower’s vice
                    president, <persName>Richard Nixon</persName>. The Cuban Missile Crisis of 1962
                    served to remind both sides of the dangers of the weapons they were
                    developing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="eisenhower-doctrine">
                <head>The Eisenhower Doctrine, <date when="1957">1957</date>
                </head>
                <p>President <persName>Dwight D. Eisenhower</persName> announced the Eisenhower
                    Doctrine in January 1957, and Congress approved it in March of the same year.
                    Under the Eisenhower Doctrine, a country could request American economic
                    assistance and/or aid from U.S. military forces if it was being threatened by
                    armed aggression from another state. Eisenhower singled out the Soviet threat in
                    his doctrine by authorizing the commitment of U.S. forces “to secure and protect
                    the territorial integrity and political independence of such nations, requesting
                    such aid against overt armed aggression from any nation controlled by
                    international communism.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="eisenhower.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Portrait of Dwight D. Eisenhower</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Eisenhower Administration’s decision to issue this doctrine was motivated in
                    part by an increase in Arab hostility toward the West, and growing Soviet
                    influence in Egypt and Syria following the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/suez">Suez Crisis of 1956</ref>. The Suez
                    Crisis, which had resulted in military mobilization by Great Britain, France,
                    and Israel—as well as United Nations action—against
                    <placeName>Egypt</placeName>, had encouraged pan-Arab sentiment in the Middle
                    East, and elevated the popularity and influence of Egyptian President
                        <persName>Gamal Abdel Nasser</persName>. President Eisenhower believed that,
                    as a result of the Suez conflict, a power vacuum had formed in the Middle East
                    due to the loss of prestige of Great Britain and France. Eisenhower feared that
                    this had allowed Nasser to spread his pan-Arab policies and form dangerous
                    alliances with Jordan and Syria, and had opened the Middle East to Soviet
                    influence. Eisenhower wanted this vacuum filled by the United States before the
                    Soviets could step in to fill the void. Because Eisenhower feared that radical
                    nationalism would combine with international communism in the region and
                    threaten Western interests, he was willing to commit to sending U.S. troops to
                    the Middle East under certain circumstances.</p>
                <p>The first real test of the Eisenhower Doctrine came in 1958 in
                        <placeName>Lebanon</placeName>, where the threat was not armed aggression or
                    a direct Soviet incursion. Lebanon’s President, <persName>Camille
                        Chamoun</persName>, requested assistance from the United States in order to
                    prevent attacks from Chamoun’s political rivals, some of whom had communist
                    leanings and ties to Syria and Egypt. Eisenhower responded to Chamoun’s request
                    by sending U.S. troops into Lebanon to help maintain order. Although Eisenhower
                    never directly invoked the Eisenhower Doctrine, the American action in Lebanon
                    was meant not only to help Chamoun’s Government against its political opponents,
                    but also to send a signal to the Soviet Union that it would act to protect its
                    interests in the Middle East.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="berlin-crises">
                <head>The Berlin Crisis, <date from="1958" to="1961">1958–1961</date>
                </head>
                <p>On November 10, 1958, Soviet Premier <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName>
                    delivered a speech in which he demanded that the Western powers of the United
                    States, Great Britain and France pull their forces out of <placeName>West
                        Berlin</placeName> within six months. This ultimatum sparked a three year
                    crisis over the future of the city of Berlin that culminated in 1961 with the
                    building of the Berlin Wall. The division of Germany and its capital city of
                    Berlin among the four victors of the Second World War was frozen in time by the
                    onset of the Cold War despite the postwar agreements to unify the zones.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="berlincrises.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>President John F. Kennedy meeting with West Berlin Mayor Willy Brandt at
                        the White House</head>
                </figure>
                <p>West Berlin remained under western control, but it was located deep inside East
                    German territory, and that made its protection from communist takeover a
                    constant challenge for the western powers. In 1948, the Soviet Union sparked a
                    crisis in the city by cutting off land access between West Germany and West
                    Berlin, necessitating a year-long airlift of supplies to the stranded citizens
                    before the Soviets reopened the passageways. By 1958, however, a similar
                    situation would have doomed the city; it was already too populous and too
                    prosperous to be supplied via air. The United States heralded the economic
                    success and political freedom of West Berlin as a symbol of the success of the
                    capitalist system, and it was deeply committed to its security, so a Soviet
                    decision to cut off land access again had the potential to lead to a more
                    serious conflict between the two powers. At the same time, the existence of West
                    Berlin was increasingly becoming a liability for the Soviet Union and the East
                    German government. The divided city highlighted the sharp contrast between the
                    communist and capitalist systems, and the freedom of movement between the
                    sectors had resulted in a mass exodus from the eastern side.</p>
                <p>Looking for a way to stop the flow of people from east to west and a means to
                    check the growing military power of West Germany, Khrushchev insisted in his
                    November 1958 speech that it was time for the United States to pull out of the
                    city. The west interpreted his speech as an ultimatum, and U.S. President
                        <persName>Dwight Eisenhower</persName> became determined not to give in to
                    Soviet demands. Instead, the two sides opened a foreign minister’s conference at
                    Geneva in the summer of 1959 and made an attempt to negotiate a new agreement on
                    Berlin. Khrushchev wanted the Western garrisons out of West Berlin as a
                    precursor to reunifying the city, but Eisenhower believed that protecting the
                    freedom of West Berlin required an ongoing U.S. presence. Although Khrushchev
                    and Eisenhower made some progress toward mutual understanding during talks at
                    Camp David in the United States in 1959, relations became tense after the Soviet
                    Union shot down an American U-2 spy plane canvassing Soviet territory in 1960.
                    In the wake of this incident, there appeared to be little hope for
                    accommodation. At that point, talks ceased, and the Soviet premier appeared
                    willing to wait for the U.S. presidential elections to take place so he could
                    begin anew with the incoming administration.</p>
                <p>However, the first negotiations between the new U.S. President and Khrushchev did
                    not result in a resolution. In the summer of 1961, President John F. Kennedy met
                    with Khrushchev in Vienna to address the ongoing issue of Berlin, in addition to
                    the countries’ competing interests in Laos, and the question of disarmament.
                    Although they agreed to further discussions on Laos, they found no solution to
                    the Berlin problem. In the wake of the conference, Khrushchev once again gave
                    the United States six months to withdraw from Berlin. Kennedy responded by
                    activating 150,000 reservists and increasing defense expenditures, in
                    preparation for a potential conflict over the future of the city. Unwilling to
                    face a potential nuclear escalation over the city, Khrushchev prepared to take
                    his own form of action.</p>
                <p>On the morning of August 13, 1961, Berliners awoke to discover that on the orders
                    of East German leader <persName>Walter Ulbricht </persName>, a barbed wire fence
                    had gone up overnight separating West and East Berlin and preventing movement
                    between the two sides. The barbed wire fence was soon expanded to include cement
                    walls and guard towers. The Berlin Wall would prevent the West from having
                    further influence on the East, stop the flow of migrants out of the communist
                    sector, and ultimately become the most iconic image of the Cold War in Europe.
                    The United States quickly condemned the wall, which divided families and limited
                    freedom of movement.</p>
                <p>Shortly after the wall was erected, a standoff between U.S. and Soviet troops on
                    either side of the diplomatic checkpoint led to one of the tensest moments of
                    the Cold War in Europe. A dispute over whether East German or Soviet guards were
                    authorized to patrol the checkpoints and examine the travel documents of U.S.
                    diplomats passing through led the United States to station tanks on its side of
                    the checkpoint, pointing toward the East German troops just beyond the wall.
                    Concerns that U.S. forces would either attempt to take down the wall or force
                    their way through the checkpoint led the Soviet Union to station its own tanks
                    on the East German side. A wrong move during the face-off could have led to war,
                    and any conventional skirmish between two nuclear powers always brought with it
                    the risk of escalation. Instead, Kennedy made use of back channels to suggest
                    that Khrushchev remove his tanks, promising that if the Soviet Union did so, the
                    U.S. army would reciprocate. The standoff ended peacefully.</p>
                <p>The Berlin Wall remained in place until November 9, 1989, when the border between
                    East and West Berlin was reopened and the wall itself was finally
                    dismantled.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="u2-incident">
                <head> U-2 Overflights and the Capture of Francis Gary Powers, <date when="1960"
                        >1960</date>
                </head>
                <p> On <date when="1960-05-01">May 1, 1960</date>, the pilot of an American U-2
                    spyplane was shot down while flying though Soviet airspace. The fallout over the
                    incident resulted in the cancellation of the Paris Summit scheduled to discuss
                    the ongoing situation in divided Germany, the possibility of an arms control or
                    test ban treaty, and the relaxation of tensions between the
                        <placeName>USSR</placeName> and the United States.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="francisgarypowers.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>Francis Gary Powers with model of U-2 plane</head>
                </figure>
                <p> As early as 1955, officials in both <placeName>Moscow</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Washington</placeName> had grown concerned about the relative
                    nuclear capabilities of the Soviet Union and the United States. Given the threat
                    that the nuclear arms race posed to national security, leadership in both
                    countries placed a priority on information about the other side’s progress. At a
                    conference in Geneva in 1955, U.S. President <persName>Dwight
                        Eisenhower</persName> proposed an “open skies” plan, in which each country
                    would be permitted to make overflights of the other to conduct mutual aerial
                    inspections of nuclear facilities and launchpads. Soviet leader <persName>Nikita
                        Khrushchev</persName> refused the proposal, continuing the established
                    Soviet policy of rejecting international inspections in any form. Meanwhile,
                    Khrushchev also claimed that the Soviet Union had developed numerous
                    intercontinental ballistic missiles, which only motivated the United States
                    Government to look for new ways to verify developments in the Soviet nuclear
                    program.</p>
                <p> The U-2 spyplane program grew out of these concerns. The U-2 was a special
                    high-altitude plane that flew at a ceiling of 70,000 feet. Because it flew at
                    such heights, it was thought it would be possible for the planes to pass over
                    the Soviet Union undetected by radar on the ground. It was important that the
                    overflights be undetected, because normally an unauthorized invasion of another
                    country’s airspace was considered an act of war. Operated through the U.S.
                    Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), the first flight over Moscow and
                        <placeName>Leningrad</placeName> (<placeName>St. Petersburg</placeName>)
                    took place on <date when="1956-07-04">July 4, 1956</date>. The flights continued
                    intermittently over the next four years. It was later revealed that the Soviets
                    did pick up the flights on radar, and the United States lost a plane over the
                    Soviet Union in 1959, but as long as there was no definitive proof connecting
                    the flights to the United States there was no advantage for the Soviets to raise
                    the issue publicly lest it draw attention to the Soviet inability to shoot down
                    the offending flights.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="powerstrial.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Powers Trial</head>
                </figure>
                <p> On May 1, 1960, the situation changed. On the eve of the Paris Summit and during
                    the May Day holiday, <abbr>CIA</abbr> pilot <persName>Francis Gary
                        Powers</persName> took off from a base in Pakistan bound for another base in
                    Norway, with his planned flight path transgressing 2,900 miles of Soviet
                    airspace. Near the city of Sverdlovsk Oblast in the Ural Mountains, Powers'
                    plane was shot down by a Soviet surface-to-air missile. Powers ejected and
                    parachuted safely to the ground, where he was captured by the <abbr>KGB</abbr>,
                    and held for interrogation. The plane crashed, but parts of it were recovered
                    and placed on public display in Moscow as evidence of American deceit.</p>
                <p> Although the capture of Powers provided the Soviets the concrete proof that the
                    United States had been conducting the flights, it was not immediately clear what
                    the impact would be for the Paris Summit. At first, and before they had
                    confirmation that Powers had survived, U.S. officials claimed that the U-2 had
                    been conducting a routine weather flight but experienced a malfunction of its
                    oxygen delivery system that had caused the pilot to black out and drift over
                    Soviet air space. On May 7, however, Khrushchev revealed that Powers was alive
                    and uninjured, and clearly had not blacked out from oxygen deprivation.
                    Moreover, the Soviets recovered the plane mostly intact, including the aerial
                    camera system. It became instantly apparent that the weather survey story was a
                    cover-up for a spy program. Khrushchev had publicly committed himself to the
                    idea of “peaceful coexistence” with the United States and the pursuit of
                    détente, so from his perspective, if U.S. President Dwight Eisenhower denied any
                    knowledge of the spy program and the United States apologized, he would have
                    continued the summit. Spying was common, and of course, the Soviet Union had its
                    own agents reporting on developments in the United States. Eisenhower, however,
                    refused to issue a formal apology to the Soviet Union; he had taken a great
                    personal interest in the spyplane program, and considered the violation of
                    Soviet airspace and the reconnaissance of Soviet nuclear facilities serious
                    enough to personally approve each flight. On May 11, Eisenhower finally
                    acknowledged his full awareness of the entire program and of the Powers flight
                    in particular. Moreover, he explained that in the absence of an “open skies”
                    agreement, such spy flights were a necessary element in maintaining national
                    defense, and that he planned to continue them.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="u2-wreckage.jpg" width="200px" height="200px"/>
                    <head>Wreckage of crashed U-2 Plane</head>
                </figure>
                <p> Eisenhower’s statement left Khrushchev in a difficult position. If he did
                    nothing, that would be tantamount to acknowledging implicitly the right of the
                    United States to spy. But any action Khrushchev did take had the potential to
                    scuttle the upcoming conference and his larger plans for a Soviet-American
                    détente. Ultimately, he demanded that Eisenhower apologize for the past flights
                    and promise to discontinue them as a precondition for entering into the planned
                    negotiations on Germany. Eisenhower’s refusal led the Soviet delegation to leave
                    Paris just as the summit was about to begin.</p>
                <p> After extensive questioning by the KGB, Powers was convicted of spying and
                    sentenced to three years in prison and seven more of hard labor. In February,
                    1962, however, he and a detained American student were traded for a captured
                    Soviet spy, <persName>Rudolf Abel</persName>. Although Eisenhower refused to end
                    the U-2 program, it was quickly overtaken by new technology, as satellite images
                    replaced aerial photographs. For his part, Khrushchev abandoned his attempts to
                    cooperate with Eisenhower, opting instead to wait for the inauguration of the
                    new U.S. President, <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName>, elected to office in
                    November, 1960.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
