<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1961–1968</title>
                <title type="short">1961–1968</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#foreword #laos-crisis #pl-480 #bay-of-pigs #cuban-missile-crisis #arab-israeli-war-1967"
                />
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword"
                ana="kennedy-john-f johnson-lyndon-b laos vietnam russia cuba dominican-republic panama">
                <head>
                    <date from="1961" to="1968">1961–1968</date>: The Presidencies of John F.
                    Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson</head>
                <p>President <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> assumed office on January 20,
                    1961, following an eight-year career in the Senate. The first Catholic
                    president, Kennedy was also the second youngest to ever serve in the office. In
                    his inaugural address, Kennedy proclaimed “Let every nation know, whether it
                    wishes us well or ill, that we shall pay any price, bear any burden, meet any
                    hardship, support any friend, oppose any foe, in order to assure the survival
                    and the success of liberty.” Kennedy came into the presidency determined to
                    reenergize the foreign policy establishment. To that end, he assembled a team of
                    young White House and National Security Council advisers—the so-called “best and
                    the brightest”—which included <persName>McGeorge Bundy</persName>,
                        <persName>Walt Rostow</persName>, <persName>Ted Sorensen</persName> and
                        <persName>Arthur Schlesinger, Jr.</persName>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="kennedy-johnson.jpg" height="450px" width="356px"/>
                    <head>President John F. Kennedy and Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson at
                        Legislative Leaders Meeting, February 7, 1961. (Abbie Rowe. White House
                        Photographs. John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum, Boston)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Kennedy selected <persName>Dean Rusk</persName>, a taciturn Southerner and
                    president of the Rockefeller Foundation, as his Secretary of State. Respected
                    within foreign policy circles, Rusk had served in several positions at the
                    Department of State, including Deputy Under Secretary of State and Assistant
                    Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs. Rusk believed that the
                    Secretary of State served at the pleasure of the President and thus did not seek
                    control of foreign policy. Kennedy selected <persName>Robert S.
                        McNamara</persName>, the president of Ford Motor Company, as his Secretary
                    of Defense. Harvard dean McGeorge Bundy served as his National Security Adviser.
                    The Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, <persName>Allen W.
                        Dulles</persName>, continued in that position, which he had held since
                    1953.</p>
                <p>The Kennedy administration inherited the containment doctrine of the 1940s and
                    1950s, and maintained the belief that Communism was a threat to the United
                    States. However, the brinksmanship of the Eisenhower era seemed archaic to the
                    Kennedy idealists in their new international vision. Kennedy implemented the
                    “flexible response” defense strategy, one that relied on multiple options for
                    responding to the Soviet Union, discouraged massive retaliation, and encouraged
                    mutual deterrence.</p>
                <p>In April 1961, a short few months into his administration, Kennedy authorized a
                    clandestine invasion of Cuba by a brigade of Cuban exiles. The CIA covert
                    operation had been formulated and approved under President Eisenhower. Relying
                    on faulty intelligence, the operation collapsed in two days with the defeat and
                    capture of anti-Castro forces at the Bay of Pigs. The spectacular failure of
                    this Cold War confrontation was a setback for Kennedy, and one he became
                    determined to overcome. Though he took full responsibility for the failed
                    operation, the CIA’s reputation was tarnished and Kennedy soon replaced DCI
                    Allen W. Dulles with <persName>John A. McCone</persName>. Similarly, the Bay of
                    Pigs fiasco affected Kennedy’s respect for the advice of the Joint Chiefs of
                    Staff, placing a strain on the civil-military relationship that would remain
                    under stress throughout the administration. McNamara’s management reforms in the
                    Pentagon, the administration’s focus on counterinsurgency warfare, and finally
                    the policy toward the war in Vietnam all found the uniformed military leadership
                    in disagreement with the administration.</p>
                <p>Tensions with the Soviet Union dominated U.S. foreign policy. Kennedy first met
                    formally with Soviet Premier <persName>Nikita Khrushche</persName>v in June 1961
                    at the Vienna Summit to discuss Berlin, Laos, and disarmament. Ailing and
                    unprepared, Kennedy came across as an inexperienced adversary to his Russian
                    counterpart. The two continued a series of both formal and public exchanges as
                    well as more informal and very confidential exchanges—the “pen pal”
                    correspondence. The channel was intended to give the two men a chance to
                    informally exchange ideas under the heightened pressure of the Cold War. Still,
                    the construction of the Berlin Wall in late 1961 and the military standoff
                    between U.S. and Soviet troops there kept both nations on high alert.</p>
                <p>The Cold War reached a frightening apex when in late 1962 the Soviet Union gave
                    the Cuban Government medium-range ballistic missiles to defend against another
                    U.S. invasion. American intelligence photographed Cuban missile sites, leading
                    to a naval blockade and quarantine of Cuba. The tense thirteen days of the Cuban
                    Missile Crisis tested the mettle of the Kennedy administration and his team of
                    trusted advisers. Khrushchev agreed to remove the missiles, averting nuclear
                    war, but resolving little between the two nations.</p>
                <p>Kennedy avoided war in Laos, rejecting a military proposal to send American
                    troops to fend off a communist insurgency there. However, he authorized sending
                    troops and military advisers to the U.S.-backed nation of South Vietnam and
                    steadily increased their numbers throughout his presidency. The administration
                    was determined not to lose either the nation of South Vietnam or the broader
                    region of Southeast Asia to communism, cementing its military commitment to
                    Vietnam.</p>
                <p>Kennedy’s assassination in November 1963 brought his Vice President,
                        <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> to the presidency. Dean Rusk
                    continued to serve as Secretary of State and stressed to the new President the
                    necessity of continuity in foreign policy. President Johnson vowed to the nation
                    that it would keep its commitments “from South Vietnam to West Berlin.” Johnson
                    retained Kennedy’s close group of advisers and the National Security Council
                    under Bundy continued to prove vital to foreign policy decision-making. Walt
                    Rostow replaced Bundy as National Security Advisor in 1966.</p>
                <p>President Johnson continued the U.S. military commitment to South Vietnam.
                    Escalation followed with the August 1964 Gulf of Tonkin Resolution, which
                    authorized Johnson to take any measures he believed were necessary to retaliate
                    and to promote the maintenance of international peace and security in southeast
                    Asia. Johnson won the landslide election shortly after. In early 1965, the U.S.
                    military launched Operation Rolling Thunder, a bombing campaign against the
                    North. Shortly after, Johnson introduced U.S. ground combat forces with the
                    landing of Marines at Danang. By 1967, nearly 500,000 troops were in Vietnam.
                    Following the Tet Offensive in 1968 and facing dwindling public support for the
                    war, Johnson announced that he would not seek a second term as President.</p>
                <p>Though preoccupied with Vietnam, the Johnson administration faced challenges
                    elsewhere. In Latin America, riots in Panama in 1964 led to concessions that
                    still preserved U.S. control of the Panama Canal. In an unpopular move, Johnson
                    sent troops to the Dominican Republic in 1965 to intervene in their civil war
                    and prevent another Cuba. Tensions flared in the Middle East in 1967 during the
                    Arab-Israeli War. Johnson warned that the United States would oppose aggression
                    by any state in the area but encouraged diplomatic negotiations. In 1968, the
                    administration faced another major crisis when the Soviet Union led Warsaw Pact
                    troops in an invasion of Czechoslovakia. The Soviet crackdown tested détente,
                    but both powers avoided confrontation. Following the election of Republican
                    Richard M. Nixon, Johnson left office on January 20, 1969.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="laos-crisis"
                ana="kennedy-john-f rusk-david-dean laos thailand vietnam">
                <head>The Laos Crisis, 1960–1963</head>
                <p>The first foreign policy crisis faced by President-elect <persName>John F.
                        Kennedy</persName> was not centered in Berlin, nor in Cuba, nor in the
                    islands off the Chinese mainland, nor in Vietnam, nor in any of the better-known
                    hot spots of the Cold War, but in landlocked, poverty stricken Laos. This was
                    the major issue Kennedy and his foreign policy team—Secretary of State
                        <persName>Dean Rusk</persName>, Secretary of Defense <persName>Robert S.
                        McNamara</persName>, and National Security Advisor <persName>McGeorge
                        Bundy</persName>—focused on during the days leading up to Kennedy’s
                    inauguration on January 20, 1961.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="laotian-crisis.jpg" height="450px" width="352px"/>
                    <head>President Kennedy meets with Ambassador at Large Averell Harriman in the
                        Oval Office, March 29, 1961. (Abbie Rowe. White House Photographs. John F.
                        Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum, Boston) </head>
                </figure>
                <p>Kennedy met with President Eisenhower the day before his inauguration with two
                    goals in mind. He expected the meeting to “serve a specific purpose in
                    reassuring the public as to the harmony of the transition. Therefore
                    strengthening our hand.” His substantive focus was on Laos. “I was anxious,” he
                    recounted to his secretary, “to get some commitment from the outgoing
                    administration as to how they would deal with Laos which they were handing to
                    us. I thought particularly it would be useful to have some idea as to how
                    prepared they were for intervention.”</p>
                <p>The Eisenhower administration was leaving Kennedy a confused, complex, and
                    intractable situation. Laos was a victim of geography: a RAND study of the
                    period summarized the nation as “Hardly a nation except in the legal sense, Laos
                    lacked the ability to defend its recent independence. Its economy was
                    undeveloped, its administrative capacity primitive, its population divided both
                    ethnically and regionally, and its elite disunited, corrupt, and unfit to lead.”
                    But this surpassingly weak state was the “cork in the bottle,” as Eisenhower
                    summarized in his meeting with Kennedy; the outgoing President expected its loss
                    to be “the beginning of the loss of most of the Far East.”</p>
                <p>The Eisenhower administration had worked for years to create a strong
                    anti-Communist bastion in Laos, a bulwark against Communist China and North
                    Vietnam. While attractive on a map, this strategy was completely at odds with
                    the characteristics of the Laotian state and people. By 1961, Laos was
                    fragmented politically, with three factions vying for control. The United States
                    had thrown its support behind General Nosavan Phoumi, whose forces were engaged
                    in combat with a neutralist force under Kong Le. Soviet aircraft were conducting
                    resupply missions for Kong Le’s forces. Neutralist leader and former Prime
                    Minister Souvanna Phouma had gone into exile in Cambodia, but remained
                    influential and active in Laotian politics. His half-brother, Souphanouverong,
                    led the Communist-dominated Pathet Lao, which had established control over an
                    extensive area along the Laos-North Vietnam border. Phoumi’s forces had little
                    popular support, had proven ineffective in combat, and appeared to be well on
                    their way to a military defeat.</p>
                <p>The Eisenhower administration had led the creation of the Southeast Asia Treaty
                    Organization for precisely this sort of contingency. In this first major test,
                    however, the United States was unable to secure the alliance’s support for
                    intervention. Its major European powers, Great Britain and France, considered
                    Phoumi an illegitimate ruler and supported Souvanna Phouma; they were adamantly
                    opposed to taking military action in Laos. An interagency analysis prepared in
                    January 1961 summarized, “Since SEATO was created to act in circumstances such
                    as that now existing in Laos but has not acted, it casts doubt not only on its
                    own credibility but on the reliability of the United States as its originator .
                    . . SEATO becomes a means by which restraint is imposed on us by our allies.” As
                    the Eisenhower administration reached its final days, the United States was
                    faced with the prospect of unilateral military intervention in a desperate
                    attempt to salvage the situation. Beyond the vast logistics issues associated
                    with intervention, the insertion of U.S. forces raised the substantial risk of a
                    U.S.-Soviet military confrontation.</p>
                <p>Kennedy faced a choice between two unpromising strategies: pursue a military
                    solution, very likely demanding a unilateral intervention by U.S. forces; or
                    adapt a major shift in policy, seeking a cease-fire and a neutralization of
                    Laos. He rejected the military option, though he encouraged an offensive by
                    Phoumi designed to strengthen his negotiating position. It failed abjectly.
                    Kennedy opened his press conference on March 23, 1961, with an extended
                    discussion of Laos, calling for an end to hostilities and negotiations leading
                    to a neutralized and independent Laos. The Pathet Lao accepted the ceasefire
                    offer on May 3. This delay gave the North Vietnamese Army (NVA) the time to
                    conduct an offensive in southern Laos, capturing the crossroad village of
                    Tchepone and the terrain necessary to extend the Ho Chi Minh Trail to the
                    western side of the Annamite Mountains on the border between Laos and South
                    Vietnam. Laos was a major topic at the Vienna Summit on June 4, with Kennedy and
                    Soviet Premier Nikita Khruschev agreeing on a common goal of a ceasefire,
                    neutrality, and a coalition government; as Khruschev summarized, “the basic
                    question is to bring about agreement among the three forces in Laos, so that the
                    formation of a truly neutral government could be secured.” Kennedy considered
                    Laos a test case for the prospects of U.S.-Soviet cooperation, in areas where
                    the superpowers could reach common objectives and avoid confrontation.</p>
                <p>Kennedy appointed <persName>W. Averell Harriman</persName> as Ambassador at Large
                    in the first days of his administration, and then formalized Harriman’s policy
                    role in appointing him Assistant Secretary of State for Far Eastern Affairs the
                    following November. Harriman took the lead in orchestrating American policy
                    toward Laos as an international conference on Laos convened in Geneva on May 16.
                    The fourteen nations involved included the U.S.S.R., Laos, People’s Republic of
                    China, North Vietnam, South Vietnam, Poland, the United States, France, the
                    United Kingdom, India, Burma, Cambodia, Canada, and Thailand. Meanwhile the
                    three Laotian factions conducted negotiations on the composition of a coalition
                    government. By the following March Harriman had become disenchanted with Phoumi,
                    and decisively shifted American policy toward a coalition government led by
                    Souvanna Phouma. The Laotian groups reached agreement on the composition of the
                    coalition government on June 12, 1962, and the Geneva conference reached
                    agreement on the Declaration on the Neutrality of Laos on July 23.</p>
                <p>These agreements provided for a coalition government in Laos under
                        <persName>Souvanna Phouma</persName>, with cabinet positions distributed
                    among the three factions. The Declaration on the Neutrality of Laos and its
                    associated protocols called for the withdrawal of all “foreign regular and
                    irregular troops, foreign para-military formations and foreign military
                    personnel” under the supervision of the International Commission for Supervision
                    and Control in Laos (ICC), comprised of representatives of India, Poland, and
                    Canada. The ICC would operate on the principle of unanimity, a change from its
                    practice from 1954 to 1958, when it operated under majority rules. Integration
                    and demobilization of the three Laotian armies would be conducted by the
                    coalition government, with neither the ICC nor other international parties
                    overseeing or enforcing these critical activities.</p>
                <p>These agreements broke down quickly, with lasting consequences for Laos and its
                    neighbors. The NVA conducted a symbolic withdrawal of 15 troops on August 27,
                    and on October 9 North Vietnam notified the Laotian foreign ministry that their
                    troops had been withdrawn in accordance with the Geneva agreement. However,
                    North Vietnam continued its advisory, logistics, and combat in support of the
                    Pathet Lao in violation of the accords. North Vietnam also continued to extend
                    its territorial control in southern Laos to secure its logistics lines to the
                    battle areas in South Vietnam. The United States withdrew its military advisory
                    teams in compliance with the Geneva agreement, but in its aftermath responded to
                    the North Vietnamese violation by supporting Meo and Thai forces, and by
                    providing economic and military support to the Phouma government and its army.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="congo-decolonization"
                ana="kennedy-john-f johnson-lyndon-b democratic-republic-of-the-congo-kinshasa united-nations">
                <head>The Congo, Decolonization, and the Cold War, 1960–1965</head>
                <p>The decolonization of Sub-Saharan Africa from the late 1950s to the mid-1970s
                    resulted in several proxy Cold War confrontations between the United States and
                    the Soviet Union over the dozens of newly independent, non-aligned nations. The
                    first such confrontation occurred in the former Belgian Congo, which gained its
                    independence on June 30, 1960.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="congo.jpg" height="350px" width="449px"/>
                    <head>Colonel Joseph Mobutu, September 14, 1960. (AP Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the months leading up to independence, the Congolese elected a president,
                        <persName>Joseph Kasavubu</persName>, prime minister, <persName>Patrice
                        Lumumba</persName>, a senate and assembly, and similar bodies in the Congo’s
                    numerous provinces. The Eisenhower administration had high hopes that the
                    Republic of the Congo would form a stable, pro-Western, central government.
                    Those hopes vanished in a matter of days as the newly independent nation
                    descended into chaos. On July 5, Congolese soldiers in the Force Publique
                    mutinied against their white Belgian commanders at the Thysville military base,
                    seeking higher pay as well as greater opportunity and authority. The mutiny
                    quickly spread to other bases and violence soon broke out across the nation.
                    Thousands of Europeans (primarily Belgians) fled, and stories of atrocities
                    against whites surfaced in newspapers around the globe. Unable to control the
                    indigenous army (renamed the Congolese National Army), the Belgians brought in
                    troops to restore order without seeking permission to do so from either Kasavubu
                    or Lumumba. In response, the Congolese government appealed directly to the
                    United Nations to provide troops and demanded the removal of Belgian troops. On
                    July 13, the United Nations approved a resolution which authorized the creation
                    of an intervention force, the Organisations des Nations Unies au Congo (ONUC),
                    and called for the withdrawal of all Belgian troops. Two days earlier, the
                    wealthy Katanga province had declared its independence from the Republic of the
                    Congo, followed in August by South Kasai province.</p>
                <p>While the United States supported the U.N. effort, members of the Eisenhower
                    administration, increasingly concerned that the Congo crisis would provide an
                    opening for Soviet intervention, sought a diplomatic solution to the crisis.
                    Lumumba was invited to visit Washington in late July, in the hopes that the
                    United States could exert a moderating influence on the prime minister. The
                    visit underscored the futility of that effort. Reports from <persName>Lawrence
                        Devlin</persName>, the CIA Chief of Station in Leopoldville (Kinshasa),
                    described the situation in the Congo as a classic Communist takeover. The
                    reports, coupled with the arrival of Soviet bloc technicians and matériel,
                    convinced members of the national security team that Lumumba had to be removed.
                    A flurry of U.S. diplomatic activity in support of unseating Lumumba ensued.
                    Plans were also developed to assassinate Lumumba if necessary. On September 5,
                    Kasavubu dismissed Lumumba from the government. Lumumba ignored the decree and
                    dismissed Kasavubu. Lumumba’s supporters in the Congo and abroad were outraged
                    and pledged to support his return to office. In an attempt to avoid civil war,
                    Colonel <persName>Joseph Mobutu</persName> of the Congolese National Army (CNA)
                    orchestrated a coup d’état on September 14, and ordered the Soviets out of the
                    country. Mobutu’s early efforts to support a pro-Western government and his ties
                    to the military placed him in good stead with Devlin, who informed Mobutu of a
                    plot to assassinate him on September 18. Lumumba, who was blamed for the plot,
                    was arrested and ultimately killed on January 17, 1961. </p>
                <p>Over the next four years, as the Republic of the Congo installed a series of
                    prime ministers, the United States repeatedly attempted to create a stable,
                    pro-Western regime through vote buying and financial support for pro-Western
                    candidates. Mobutu also received funds to help him gain the loyalty of the CNA
                    and avoid rebellion in the ranks. Neither effort succeeded in quelling the
                    seemingly endless unrest in the volatile provinces. Concern over the instability
                    that would occur following the departure of U.N. troops led the Kennedy
                    administration to sign bilateral military agreements with the Republic of the
                    Congo and resulted in a May 1963 visit to Washington by Mobutu, who met with
                    President Kennedy on May 31.</p>
                <p>Support for the Congo continued unabated during the Johnson administration. U.S.
                    military assistance increased dramatically in response to the fall of
                    Stanleyville (Kisangani) to rebel forces on August 4, 1964. Planes provided by
                    the Department of Defense, flown by pilots supplied by the Central Intelligence
                    Agency, augmented the CNA’s efforts against an increasingly robust rebel
                    insurgency, which received support from neighboring African nations, the Soviet
                    bloc and Chinese Communists. The United States also made diplomatic approaches
                    to the Organization of African Unity (OAU) to secure support for the Republic of
                    the Congo. By late October, the situation in Stanleyville was dire. On October
                    28, the rebel Army commander placed all Westerners in the area (including a
                    number of Americans) under house arrest. Smaller but significant numbers of
                    hostages were seized in other cities under rebel control. A joint U.S.-Belgian
                    effort to rescue the hostages in late November, Operation Dragon Rouge,
                    succeeded but severely damaged Prime Minister Tshombe, who was viewed as
                    ineffectual by both Kasavubu and Mobutu. He was dismissed in October 1965 and
                    once again, the nation teetered on the brink of civil war. Mobutu orchestrated
                    another coup d’état on November 25, 1965, removed both the President and Prime
                    Minister, and took control of the government.</p>
                <p>Despite periodic uprisings and unrest, Mobutu ruled the Congo (renamed Zaire in
                    1971) until the mid-1990s. Viewed as mercurial and occasionally irrational,
                    Mobutu nonetheless proved to be a staunch ally against Communist encroachment in
                    Africa. As such, he received extensive U.S. financial, matériel, and political
                    support, which increased his stature in much of Sub-Saharan Africa where he
                    often served the interests of administrations from Johnson through Reagan.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="pl-480"
                ana="eisenhower-dwight-d kennedy-john-f johnson-lyndon-b rusk-david-dean vietnam united-kingdom india canada agriculture foreign-aid peace">
                <head>USAID and PL–480, 1961–1969</head>
                <p>The administrations of <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and <persName>Lyndon
                        B. Johnson</persName> marked a revitalization of the U.S. foreign assistance
                    program, signified a growing awareness of the importance of humanitarian aid as
                    a form of diplomacy, and reinforced the belief that American security was linked
                    to the economic progress and stability of other nations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="pl-480.jpg" height="450px" width="299px"/>
                    <head>Johnson with Gandhi, March 28, 1966. (White House Photo Office)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the aftermath of World War II, the United States provided economic assistance
                    to European nations to aid in their reconstruction, and extended security
                    assistance to these and other nations as a bulwark against a perceived communist
                    threat. The mechanisms for deploying this assistance were spread over several
                    government agencies and, as a result, problems arose concerning the coordination
                    of these efforts.</p>
                <p>Kennedy sought both to improve the administration of U.S. assistance and refocus
                    aid to meet the needs of the developing world. In September 1961, Kennedy signed
                    into law the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961 (Public Law 87–195), which mandated
                    the establishment of a single agency for the coordination of foreign assistance.
                    The Agency for International Development (AID)—established under Executive Order
                    10973—assumed responsibility for the disbursement of capital and technical
                    assistance to developing nations. AID symbolized Kennedy’s invigorated approach
                    to fostering the economic, political, and social development of recipient
                    nations.</p>
                <p>Kennedy also turned his attention to food aid, particularly the Food for Peace
                    program started during the Eisenhower administration. President <persName>Dwight
                        D. Eisenhower</persName> signed into law the Agricultural Trade Development
                    and Assistance Act of 1954, commonly known as PL–480 or Food for Peace. Prior to
                    that, the United States had extended food aid to countries experiencing natural
                    disasters and provided aid in times of war, but no permanent program existed
                    within the United States Government for the coordination and distribution of
                    commodities. Public Law 480, administered at that time by the Departments of
                    State and Agriculture and the International Cooperation Administration,
                    permitted the president to authorize the shipment of surplus commodities to
                    “friendly” nations, either on concessional or grant terms. It also allowed the
                    federal government to donate stocks to religious and voluntary organizations for
                    use in their overseas humanitarian programs. Public Law 480 established a broad
                    basis for U.S. distribution of foreign food aid, although reduction of
                    agricultural surpluses remained the key objective for the duration of the
                    Eisenhower administration. Eisenhower remained sensitive to the foreign policy
                    implications of a permanent program, as did Department of State officials who
                    expressed concerns that PL–480 would disrupt the export markets of several
                    allies, including Great Britain and Canada.</p>
                <p>As with his overall efforts to streamline foreign assistance, Kennedy also
                    intended to reinvigorate the Food for Peace program and redirect it away from
                    surplus liquidation. Shortly after his inauguration, Kennedy issued Executive
                    Order 10915, which affirmed the foreign policy dimension of PL–480. Kennedy also
                    appointed George McGovern as his Food for Peace Director—a position located
                    within the Executive Office of the President—and tasked him with supervising and
                    coordinating the functions of the various agencies administering the program,
                    including AID, the Department of State, and the Department of Agriculture.
                    Kennedy directed McGovern to orient the program toward the use of “agricultural
                    abundance” in combating malnutrition. Kennedy insisted that the United States
                    must “narrow the gap between abundance here at home and near starvation
                    abroad.”</p>
                <p>Johnson emphasized the Food for Peace program as a cornerstone of U.S. foreign
                    assistance, and intended to pursue revisions to the program to strengthen its
                    foreign policy orientation. While Johnson believed that the United States should
                    extend food aid for humanitarian reasons, he also favored conditioning food aid
                    agreements on the recipient nation’s ability to implement necessary agricultural
                    reforms. “Self-help” provisions, applied to both PL–480 agreements and other AID
                    assistance, would contribute to the economic development of recipient nations by
                    strengthening their agricultural sectors. The Food for Peace Act of 1966 (PL
                    89–808) required that PL–480 agreements contain language describing the steps a
                    recipient had already made, or planned to make, toward increasing food
                    production and improving storage and distribution. Johnson pursued these
                    revisions at the same time he announced a “war on hunger,” designed to
                    accelerate agricultural production, improve nutrition, eradicate disease, and
                    curb population growth. It remained incumbent upon the United States to
                    demonstrate leadership and recreate Johnson’s domestic Great Society reforms on
                    a global scale.</p>
                <p>Johnson also understood that food aid served diplomatic ends and bolstered U.S.
                    strategic interests. To strengthen Food for Peace’s foreign policy orientation,
                    he pursued the transfer of the Food for Peace director’s functions from the
                    White House to the Department of State, where the director would serve as a
                    special assistant to Secretary of State Dean Rusk. Although the Johnson
                    administration programmed PL–480 commodities to meet critical hunger needs, in
                    several instances Johnson authorized food aid shipments to nations in order to
                    allow recipients to redirect spending for military equipment or for security
                    purposes. The administration also negotiated PL–480 agreements with countries in
                    an attempt to dissuade these leaders from accepting assistance from U.S.
                    adversaries. Johnson used PL–480 agreements as leverage in securing support for
                    U.S. foreign policy goals, even placing critical famine aid to India on a
                    limited basis, until he received assurance that the Indian Government would
                    implement agricultural reforms and temper criticism of U.S. policy regarding
                    Vietnam. While PL–480 commodities continued to serve humanitarian aims, the
                    program had limitations as a tool of U.S. foreign policy, especially given
                    Congressional reductions in foreign aid outlays by the end of the decade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bay-of-pigs"
                ana="eisenhower-dwight-d kennedy-john-f russia cuba covert-actions">
                <head>The Bay of Pigs Invasion and its Aftermath, April 1961–October 1962</head>
                <p>A left-wing revolution in Cuba had ended in 1959 with the ouster of President
                    Fulgencia Batista and the establishment of a new government under Premier Fidel
                    Castro. The Castro regime quickly severed the country’s formerly strong ties
                    with the United States by expropriating U.S. economic assets in Cuba and
                    developing close links with the Soviet Union.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="bay-pigs.jpg" height="450px" width="353px"/>
                    <head>Skyhawks from the USS Essex fly sorties over combat areas during the Bay
                        of Pigs. (Robert L. Lawson Photograph Collection)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>These developments proved a source of grave concern to the United States given
                    Cuba’s geographical proximity to the United States and brought Cuba into play as
                    a new and significant factor in the Cold War. In March 1960, President Dwight D.
                    Eisenhower directed the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) to develop a plan for
                    the invasion of Cuba and overthrow of the Castro regime. The CIA organized an
                    operation in which it trained and funded a force of exiled counter-revolutionary
                    Cubans serving as the armed wing of the Democratic Revolutionary Front, known as
                    Brigade 2506.</p>
                <p>Following his election in November 1960, President John F. Kennedy learned of the
                    invasion plan, concluded that Fidel Castro was a Soviet client posing a threat
                    to all of Latin America and, after consultations with his advisors, gave his
                    consent for the CIA-planned clandestine invasion of Cuba to proceed. Launched
                    from Guatemala, the attack went wrong almost from the start. Components of
                    Brigade 2506 landed at the Bay of Pigs on April 17, 1961 and were defeated
                    within 2 days by Cuban armed forces under the direct command of Castro.</p>
                <p>The failed invasion strengthened the position of Castro’s administration, which
                    proceeded to openly proclaim its intention to adopt socialism and pursue closer
                    ties with the Soviet Union. It also led to a reassessment of Cuba policy by the
                    Kennedy administration. The President established a committee under former Army
                    Chief of Staff General Maxwell Taylor and Attorney General Robert Kennedy to
                    examine the causes of the defeat suffered at the Bay of Pigs.</p>
                <p>This examination and policy assessment, initiated in May 1961, led in November of
                    that year to a decision to implement a new covert program in Cuba, with the
                    codename of Operation Mongoose. Oversight for Operation Mongoose was provided by
                    the 5412/2 Special Group, under the auspices of the National Security Council,
                    expanded to include General Taylor and Attorney General Kennedy.</p>
                <p>Operation Mongoose was designed to do what the Bay of Pigs invasion failed to do:
                    remove the Communist Castro regime from power in Cuba. Orchestrated by the CIA
                    and Department of Defense under the direction of Edward Lansdale, Operation
                    Mongoose constituted a multiplicity of plans with wide-ranging purpose and
                    scope. Lansdale presented the Project’s six-phase schedule to Attorney General
                    Kennedy on February 20, 1962, and President Kennedy received a briefing on the
                    operation’s components on March 16, 1962. Lansdale outlined the coordinated
                    program of political, psychological, military, sabotage, and intelligence
                    operations, as well as proposed assassination attempts on key political leaders,
                    including Castro. Monthly components of the operation were to be set in place to
                    destabilize the communist regime, including the publication of Anti-Castro
                    propaganda, provision of armaments for militant opposition groups, and
                    establishment of guerilla bases throughout the country, all leading up to
                    preparations for an October 1962 military intervention in Cuba. Some (though not
                    all) of the planned Operation Mongoose actions were deployed during 1962, but
                    the military intervention did not occur, and the Castro regime remained in
                    power.</p>
                <p>Although not considered as significant a U.S. foreign policy failure and
                    embarrassment as the Bay of Pigs invasion, Operation Mongoose failed to achieve
                    its most important goals. Meanwhile, throughout the spring and summer of 1962,
                    U.S. intelligence reports indicated expanded arms shipments from the Soviet
                    Union to Cuba. Amidst growing concern in Washington over whether the Soviet
                    weapons being introduced into Cuba included ballistic missiles with nuclear
                    warheads, in October 1962 the Kennedy administration suspended Operation
                    Mongoose in the face of this far more serious threat—one that resulted in the
                    most dangerous confrontation between the United States and the Soviet Union
                    during the Cold War.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="cuban-missile-crisis"
                ana="kennedy-john-f russia turkey cuba united-nations national-security-council quarantine-blockade cuban-missile-crisis">
                <head>The Cuban Missile Crisis, October 1962 </head>
                <p>The Cuban Missile Crisis of October 1962 was a direct and dangerous confrontation
                    between the United States and the Soviet Union during the Cold War and was the
                    moment when the two superpowers came closest to nuclear conflict. The crisis was
                    unique in a number of ways, featuring calculations and miscalculations as well
                    as direct and secret communications and miscommunications between the two sides.
                    The dramatic crisis was also characterized by the fact that it was primarily
                    played out at the White House and the Kremlin level with relatively little input
                    from the respective bureaucracies typically involved in the foreign policy
                    process.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="cuban-missile-crisis.jpg" height="450px" width="378px"/>
                    <head>Aerial view of missile launch site at San Cristobal, Cuba. (John F.
                        Kennedy Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After the failed U.S. attempt to overthrow the Castro regime in Cuba with the Bay
                    of Pigs invasion, and while the Kennedy administration planned Operation
                    Mongoose, in July 1962 Soviet premier <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName>
                    reached a secret agreement with Cuban premier <persName>Fidel Castro</persName>
                    to place Soviet nuclear missiles in Cuba to deter any future invasion attempt.
                    Construction of several missile sites began in the late summer, but U.S.
                    intelligence discovered evidence of a general Soviet arms build-up on Cuba,
                    including Soviet IL–28 bombers, during routine surveillance flights, and on
                    September 4, 1962, President <persName>Kennedy</persName> issued a public
                    warning against the introduction of offensive weapons into Cuba. Despite the
                    warning, on October 14 a U.S. U–2 aircraft took several pictures clearly showing
                    sites for medium-range and intermediate-range ballistic nuclear missiles (MRBMs
                    and IRBMs) under construction in Cuba. These images were processed and presented
                    to the White House the next day, thus precipitating the onset of the Cuban
                    Missile Crisis.</p>
                <p>Kennedy summoned his closest advisers to consider options and direct a course of
                    action for the United States that would resolve the crisis. Some
                    advisers—including all the Joint Chiefs of Staff—argued for an air strike to
                    destroy the missiles, followed by a U.S. invasion of Cuba; others favored stern
                    warnings to Cuba and the Soviet Union. The President decided upon a middle
                    course. On October 22, he ordered a naval “quarantine” of Cuba. The use of
                    “quarantine” legally distinguished this action from a blockade, which assumed a
                    state of war existed; the use of “quarantine” instead of “blockade” also enabled
                    the United States to receive the support of the Organization of American
                    States.</p>
                <p>That same day, Kennedy sent a letter to Khrushchev declaring that the United
                    States would not permit offensive weapons to be delivered to Cuba, and demanded
                    that the Soviets dismantle the missile bases already under construction or
                    completed, and return all offensive weapons to the U.S.S.R. The letter was the
                    first in a series of direct and indirect communications between the White House
                    and the Kremlin throughout the remainder of the crisis.</p>
                <p>The President also went on national television that evening to inform the public
                    of the developments in Cuba, his decision to initiate and enforce a
                    “quarantine,” and the potential global consequences if the crisis continued to
                    escalate. The tone of the President’s remarks was stern, and the message
                    unmistakable and evocative of the Monroe Doctrine: “It shall be the policy of
                    this nation to regard any nuclear missile launched from Cuba against any nation
                    in the Western Hemisphere as an attack by the Soviet Union on the United States,
                    requiring a full retaliatory response upon the Soviet Union.” The Joint Chiefs
                    of Staff announced a military readiness status of DEFCON 3 as U.S. naval forces
                    began implementation of the quarantine and plans accelerated for a military
                    strike on Cuba.</p>
                <p>On October 24, Khrushchev responded to Kennedy’s message with a statement that
                    the U.S. “blockade” was an “act of aggression” and that Soviet ships bound for
                    Cuba would be ordered to proceed. Nevertheless, during October 24 and 25, some
                    ships turned back from the quarantine line; others were stopped by U.S. naval
                    forces, but they contained no offensive weapons and so were allowed to proceed.
                    Meanwhile, U.S. reconnaissance flights over Cuba indicated the Soviet missile
                    sites were nearing operational readiness. With no apparent end to the crisis in
                    sight, U.S. forces were placed at DEFCON 2—meaning war involving the Strategic
                    Air Command was imminent. On October 26, Kennedy told his advisors it appeared
                    that only a U.S. attack on Cuba would remove the missiles, but he insisted on
                    giving the diplomatic channel a little more time. The crisis had reached a
                    virtual stalemate.</p>
                <p>That afternoon, however, the crisis took a dramatic turn. ABC News correspondent
                    John Scali reported to the White House that he had been approached by a Soviet
                    agent suggesting that an agreement could be reached in which the Soviets would
                    remove their missiles from Cuba if the United States promised not to invade the
                    island. While White House staff scrambled to assess the validity of this “back
                    channel” offer, Khrushchev sent Kennedy a message the evening of October 26,
                    which meant it was sent in the middle of the night Moscow time. It was a long,
                    emotional message that raised the specter of nuclear holocaust, and presented a
                    proposed resolution that remarkably resembled what Scali reported earlier that
                    day. “If there is no intention,” he said, “to doom the world to the catastrophe
                    of thermonuclear war, then let us not only relax the forces pulling on the ends
                    of the rope, let us take measures to untie that knot. We are ready for
                    this.”</p>
                <p>Although U.S. experts were convinced the message from Khrushchev was authentic,
                    hope for a resolution was short-lived. The next day, October 27, Khrushchev sent
                    another message indicating that any proposed deal must include the removal of
                    U.S. Jupiter missiles from Turkey. That same day a U.S. U–2 reconnaissance jet
                    was shot down over Cuba. Kennedy and his advisors prepared for an attack on Cuba
                    within days as they searched for any remaining diplomatic resolution. It was
                    determined that Kennedy would ignore the second Khrushchev message and respond
                    to the first one. That night, Kennedy set forth in his message to the Soviet
                    leader proposed steps for the removal of Soviet missiles from Cuba under
                    supervision of the United Nations, and a guarantee that the United States would
                    not attack Cuba.</p>
                <p>It was a risky move to ignore the second Khrushchev message. Attorney General
                    Robert Kennedy then met secretly with Soviet Ambassador to the United States,
                    Anatoly Dobrynin, and indicated that the United States was planning to remove
                    the Jupiter missiles from Turkey anyway, and that it would do so soon, but this
                    could not be part of any public resolution of the missile crisis. The next
                    morning, October 28, Khrushchev issued a public statement that Soviet missiles
                    would be dismantled and removed from Cuba.</p>
                <p>The crisis was over but the naval quarantine continued until the Soviets agreed
                    to remove their IL–28 bombers from Cuba and, on November 20, 1962, the United
                    States ended its quarantine. U.S. Jupiter missiles were removed from Turkey in
                    April 1963. </p>
                <p>The Cuban missile crisis stands as a singular event during the Cold War and
                    strengthened Kennedy’s image domestically and internationally. It also may have
                    helped mitigate negative world opinion regarding the failed Bay of Pigs
                    invasion. Two other important results of the crisis came in unique forms. First,
                    despite the flurry of direct and indirect communications between the White House
                    and the Kremlin—perhaps because of it—Kennedy and Khrushchev, and their
                    advisers, struggled throughout the crisis to clearly understand each others’
                    true intentions, while the world hung on the brink of possible nuclear war. In
                    an effort to prevent this from happening again, a direct telephone link between
                    the White House and the Kremlin was established; it became known as the
                    “Hotline.” Second, having approached the brink of nuclear conflict, both
                    superpowers began to reconsider the nuclear arms race and took the first steps
                    in agreeing to a nuclear Test Ban Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="alliance-for-progress" ana="johnson-lyndon-b">
                <head>Alliance for Progress and Peace Corps, <date from="1961" to="1969"
                        >1961–1969</date>
                </head>
                <p>Growing out of the fear of increased Soviet and Cuban influence in Latin America,
                    the 1961–1969 Alliance for Progress was in essence a <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall Plan</ref> for
                        <placeName>Latin America</placeName>. The United States pledged $20 billion
                    in assistance (grants and loans) and called upon the Latin American governments
                    to provide $80 billion in investment funds for their economies. It was the
                    biggest U.S. aid program toward the developing world up to that point—and called
                    for substantial reform of Latin American institutions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="peace-corps.jpg" height="450px" width="400px"/>
                    <head>President John F. Kennedy greeting Peace Corps volunteers. (John F.
                        Kennedy Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Washington policymakers saw the Alliance as a means of bulwarking capitalist
                    economic growth, funding social reforms to help the poorest Latin Americans,
                    promoting democracy—and strengthening ties between the United States and its
                    neighbors. A key element of the Alliance was U.S. military assistance to
                    friendly regimes in the region, an aspect that gained prominence with the
                    ascension of President <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> to power in late
                    1963 (as the other components of the Alliance were downplayed). The Alliance did
                    not achieve all its lofty goals. According to one study, only 2 percent of
                    economic growth in 1960s Latin America directly benefited the poor; and there
                    was a general deterioration of United States-Latin American relations by the end
                    of the 1960s. </p>
                <p>Although derided as “Kennedy’s Kiddie Corps” by some when it was established in
                    1961, the Peace Corps proved over time to be an important foreign policymaking
                    institution. By sending intelligent, hard-working, and idealistic young
                    Americans to do economic and social development work (on 2-year tours) in the
                    areas of greatest need in the Third World, the Peace Corps provided a means by
                    which young Americans could not only learn about the world, but promote positive
                    change. A significant number of Peace Corps Volunteers went on to work as
                    officials in the U.S. Government.</p>
                <p>The Peace Corps remains an important, vibrant foreign policy institution. Since
                    the Peace Corps’ founding, more than 187,000 men and women have joined the Peace
                    Corps and served in 139 countries. There are 7,749 Peace Corps Volunteers
                    currently serving 73 countries around the world. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="limited-ban"
                ana="nuclear-weapons russia arms-control-and-disarmament united-kingdom kennedy-john-f">
                <head>The Limited Test Ban Treaty, <date when="1963">1963</date>
                </head>
                <p>In the early 1960s, U.S. President <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> and
                    Soviet Premier <persName>Nikita Khrushchev</persName> each expressed deep
                    concern about the strength of their respective nations’ nuclear arms forces.
                    This concern led them to complete the first arms control agreement of the Cold
                    War, the Limited Test Ban Treaty of 1963.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="test-ban-treaty.jpg" height="450px" width="411px"/>
                    <head>President signing the Limited Test Ban Treaty. (John F. Kennedy
                        Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>This treaty did not have much practical effect on the development and
                    proliferation of nuclear weapons, but it established an important precedent for
                    future arms control. Both superpowers entered the 1960s determined to build or
                    maintain nuclear superiority. The Soviet Union had led the way in the
                    development of intercontinental ballistic missiles after its launch of the first
                    man-made satellite, <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/sputnik">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sputnik</hi>
                    </ref>, in 1957. In just a few years, it had developed an arsenal of long and
                    medium range missiles that had raised alarm in Washington. President Kennedy had
                    even campaigned for office on a claim that President Dwight Eisenhower had
                    allowed the Soviet Union to far out-produce the United States in nuclear
                    technology, creating a “missile gap.” However, soon after he took office, the
                    Kennedy Administration determined that the balance of nuclear power remained in
                    favor of the United States. </p>
                <p>With both sides working to develop new and better nuclear technology over the
                    course of the late 1950s and early 1960s, each engaged in a series of test
                    explosions. These nuclear tests received worldwide scrutiny, not only for what
                    they meant for the arms race but also for what they meant for human life. As the
                    United States, Soviet Union and United Kingdom tested new nuclear technologies
                    in the earth’s atmosphere, concerns emerged worldwide about the potential
                    effects of radioactive fallout on the people exposed to it. This led to the
                    formation of activist groups and public discussion of the issue. </p>
                <p>The three countries entered into negotiations for a comprehensive test ban treaty
                    in 1958. Having recently completed rounds of tests, at that time all three
                    entered into a voluntary moratorium on all forms of testing, initiated first by
                    the Soviet Union but later adhered to by the United States and Great Britain. In
                    spite of this willingness to self-restrict testing, one of the most difficult
                    issues preventing the conclusion of a formal treaty was the question of
                    verification. The United States and Great Britain, in particular, pushed for
                    on-site inspections of Soviet facilities as without them, it was impossible to
                    determine whether the Soviets were continuing underground nuclear tests or just
                    experiencing the frequent seismic activity to which its geographic area was
                    prone. However, the Soviets were hesitant to permit such onsite inspections of
                    its nuclear facilities, interpreting U.S. insistence on these inspections as a
                    ruse to facilitate U.S. efforts to spy on Soviet advancements. After the Soviet
                    military shot down an American U-2 spy plane over Russia in 1960, the prospects
                    for reaching an agreement on the inspections issue all but disappeared.
                    Khrushchev also rejected the idea of having the United Nations conduct
                    inspections after observing what he believed was the organization’s mishandling
                    of the Congo crisis. Instead, in the wake of these incidents both the United
                    States and the Soviet Union resumed testing. </p>
                <p>In 1961, Kennedy established an Arms Control and Disarmament Agency within the
                    U.S. Department of State, and the new organization reopened talks with the
                    Soviet Union. That year, however, neither side was ready to make major
                    concessions. As long as it remained difficult to verify that the other side was
                    not engaging in clandestine testing, there was little incentive to form an
                    agreement. </p>
                <p>Over the course of the next year, however, the situation changed dramatically for
                    a number of reasons. Concerns about nuclear proliferation increased interest in
                    the testing ban, as France exploded its first weapon in 1960 and the People’s
                    Republic of China appeared close to successfully building its own atom bomb.
                    However, it was the rapid escalation of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Cuban Missile
                        Crisis</ref> in October of 1962 that compelled leaders in both the United
                    States and the Soviet Union to pursue more aggressively an agreement that could
                    help them avoid the devastating destruction that nuclear warfare would bring.
                    Although the crisis provided the impetus for an agreement, its final negotiation
                    was made possible by the decision to step back from the original idea of a
                    comprehensive test ban treaty and work instead on a more limited arrangement.
                    Atmospheric and underground tests proved equally effective for scientific
                    purposes, so there was no reason to insist that access to both types of testing
                    remain available. In past negotiations, the inability to detect underground
                    explosions and agree on provisions for inspections to ensure such explosions
                    were not taking place became a problem that prevented an agreement. Once the
                    Soviet Union and the United States decided that underground testing would not be
                    included in this first treaty, the two sides very quickly reached terms they
                    could agree upon. </p>
                <p>The Limited Test Ban Treaty was signed by the United States, the Soviet Union,
                    and Great Britain in 1963, and it banned all nuclear tests in the atmosphere, in
                    space, or underwater. Because it stopped the spread of radioactive nuclear
                    material through atmospheric testing and set the precedent for a new wave of
                    arms control agreements, the Treaty was hailed as a success. The Treaty was the
                    first of several Cold War agreements on nuclear arms, including the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/npt">Non-Proliferation Treaty</ref> that was
                    signed in 1968 and the <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/salt">SALT I
                        agreements of 1972</ref>. In 1974, the Threshold Test Ban Treaty returned to
                    the question of nuclear testing by limiting underground testing of bombs with a
                    yield greater than 150 kilotons. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="gulf-of-tonkin"
                ana="vietnam vietnam-conflict johnson-lyndon-b">
                <head>U.S. Involvement in the Vietnam War: the Gulf of Tonkin and Escalation, <date
                        when="1964">1964</date>
                </head>
                <p>In early August 1964, two U.S. destroyers stationed in the <placeName>Gulf of
                        Tonkin</placeName> in <placeName>Vietnam</placeName> radioed that they had
                    been fired upon by North Vietnamese forces. In response to these reported
                    incidents, President <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> requested permission
                    from the U.S. Congress to increase the U.S. military presence in Indochina. On
                    August 7, 1964, Congress passed the Gulf of Tonkin Resolution, authorizing
                    President Johnson to take any measures he believed were necessary to retaliate
                    and to promote the maintenance of international peace and security in southeast
                    Asia. This resolution became the legal basis for the Johnson and Nixon
                    Administrations prosecution of the Vietnam War.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="gulf-of-tonkin.jpg" width="450px" height="410px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of Defense Robert S. McNamara points out action in Gulf of
                        Tonkin during a briefing at the Pentagon. (AP Photo/Bob Schutz)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After the end of the First Indochina War and the Viet Minh defeat of the French
                    at <placeName>Dien Bien Phu</placeName> in 1954, the countries meeting at the
                    Geneva Conference divided Vietnam into northern and southern halves, ruled by
                    separate regimes, and scheduled elections to reunite the country under a unified
                    government. The communists seemed likely to win those elections, thanks mostly
                    to their superior organization and greater appeal in the countryside. The United
                    States, however, was dedicated to containing the spread of communist regimes
                    and, invoking the charter of the Southeast Asia Treaty Organization (1954),
                    supported the South Vietnamese leader, <persName>Ngo Dinh Diem</persName>, when
                    he refused to hold the elections. Diem held control of the South Vietnamese
                    Government, but he could not halt the communist infiltration of the South. By
                    1959, the Viet Cong, South Vietnamese communist guerillas, and the Viet Minh,
                    began a large scale insurgency in the South that marked the opening of the
                    Second Indochina War.</p>
                <p>Ngo Dinh Diem failed to capture the loyalties of the people of South Vietnam the
                    way that <persName>Ho Chi Minh</persName> had done among the population of North
                    Vietnam. Despite U.S. support, Diem’s rural policies and ambivalent attitude
                    toward necessary changes like land reform only bolstered support for the Viet
                    Cong in the southern countryside. By 1963, Diem’s rule had so deteriorated that
                    he was overthrown and assassinated by several of his generals with the tacit
                    approval of the Kennedy Administration. Three weeks later, U.S. President
                        <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName> was also assassinated, and the war
                    continued under new leadership in both countries. Before his death, Kennedy had
                    increased the U.S. advisory presence in South Vietnam in the hopes that a
                    U.S.-supported program of “nation-building” would strengthen the new South
                    Vietnamese government. However, South Vietnam continued to experience political
                    instability and military losses to North Vietnam.</p>

                <p>By August, 1964, the Johnson Administration believed that escalation of the U.S.
                    presence in Vietnam was the only solution. The post-Diem South proved no more
                    stable than it had been before his ouster, and South Vietnamese troops were
                    generally ineffective. In addition to supporting on-going South Vietnamese raids
                    in the countryside and implementing a U.S. program of bombing the Lao border to
                    disrupt supply lines, the U.S. military began backing South Vietnamese raids of
                    the North Vietnamese coast. The U.S. Navy stationed two destroyers, the Maddox
                    and the Turner Joy, in the Gulf of Tonkin to bolster these actions. They
                    reported an attack by North Vietnamese patrol boats on August 2, and a second
                    attack on August 4. Doubts later emerged as to whether or not the attack against
                    the Turner Joy had taken place. </p>
                <p>Immediately after reports of the second attack, Johnson asked the U.S. Congress
                    for permission to defend U.S. forces in Southeast Asia. The Senate passed the
                    Gulf of Tonkin Resolution with only two opposing votes, and the House of
                    Representatives passed it unanimously. Congress supported the resolution with
                    the assumption that the president would return and seek their support before
                    engaging in additional escalations of the war. </p>
                <p>The Gulf of Tonkin incident and the subsequent Gulf of Tonkin resolution provided
                    the justification for further U.S. escalation of the conflict in Vietnam. Acting
                    on the belief that Hanoi would eventually weaken when faced with stepped up
                    bombing raids, Johnson and his advisers ordered the U.S. military to launch
                    Operation Rolling Thunder, a bombing campaign against the North. Operation
                    Rolling Thunder commenced on February 13, 1965 and continued through the spring
                    of 1967. Johnson also authorized the first of many deployments of regular ground
                    combat troops to Vietnam to fight the Viet Cong in the countryside. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="india-pakistan-war" ana="india pakistan">
                <head>The India-Pakistan War of <date when="1965">1965</date>
                </head>
                <p>The 1965 war between <placeName>India</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> was the second conflict between the two
                    countries over the status of the state of Jammu and Kashmir. The clash did not
                    resolve this dispute, but it did engage the United States and the Soviet Union
                    in ways that would have important implications for subsequent superpower
                    involvement in the region. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="india-pakistan.jpg" height="450px" width="291px"/>
                    <head>A patrol walks in the Haji Pir pass sector of Kashmir region. (AP
                        Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The dispute over this region originated in the process of decolonization in South
                    Asia. When the British colony of India gained its independence in 1947, it was
                    partitioned into two separate entities: the secular nation of India and the
                    predominantly Muslim nation of Pakistan. Pakistan was composed of two
                    noncontiguous regions, East Pakistan and West Pakistan, separated by Indian
                    territory. The state of Jammu and Kashmir, which had a predominantly Muslim
                    population but a Hindu leader, shared borders with both India and West Pakistan.
                    The argument over which nation would incorporate the state led to the first
                    India-Pakistan War in 1947–48 and ended with UN mediation. Jammu and Kashmir,
                    also known as “Indian Kashmir” or just “Kashmir,” joined the Republic of India,
                    but the Pakistani Government continued to believe that the majority Muslim state
                    rightfully belonged to Pakistan. </p>
                <p>Conflict resumed again in early 1965, when Pakistani and Indian forces clashed
                    over disputed territory along the border between the two nations. Hostilities
                    intensified that August when the Pakistani Army attempted to take Kashmir by
                    force. The attempt to seize the state was unsuccessful, and the second
                    India-Pakistan War reached a stalemate. This time, the international politics of
                    the Cold War affected the nature of the conflict. </p>
                <p>The United States had a history of ambivalent relations with India. During the
                    1950s, U.S. officials regarded Indian leadership with some caution due to
                    India’s involvement in the nonaligned movement, particularly its prominent role
                    at the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/bandung-conf">Bandung Conference of
                        1955</ref>. The United States hoped to maintain a regional balance of power,
                    which meant not allowing India to influence the political development of other
                    states. However, a 1962 border conflict between India and China ended with a
                    decisive Chinese victory, which motivated the United States and the United
                    Kingdom to provide military supplies to the Indian Army. After the clash with
                    China, India also turned to the Soviet Union for assistance, which placed some
                    strains on U.S.-Indian relations. However, the United States also provided India
                    with considerable development assistance throughout the 1960s and 1970s. </p>
                <p>U.S.-Pakistani relations had been more consistently positive. The U.S. Government
                    looked to Pakistan as an example of a moderate Muslim state and appreciated
                    Pakistani assistance in holding the line against communist expansion by joining
                    the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/seato">Southeast Asia Treaty Organization
                        (SEATO)</ref> in 1954 and the Baghdad Pact (later renamed the Central Treaty Organization, or
                        CENTO) in 1955. Pakistan’s interest in these pacts stemmed from its
                    desire to develop its military and defensive capabilities, which were
                    substantially weaker than those of India. Both the United States and the United
                    Kingdom supplied arms to Pakistan in these years. </p>
                <p>After Pakistani troops invaded Kashmir, India moved quickly to internationalize
                    the regional dispute. It asked the United Nations to reprise its role in the
                    First India-Pakistan War and end the current conflict. The Security Council
                    passed Resolution 211 on September 20 calling for an end to the fighting and
                    negotiations on the settlement of the Kashmir problem, and the United States and
                    the United Kingdom supported the UN decision by cutting off arms supplies to
                    both belligerents. This ban affected both belligerents, but Pakistan felt the
                    effects more keenly since it had a much weaker military in comparison to India.
                    The UN resolution and the halting of arms sales had an immediate impact. India
                    accepted the ceasefire on September 21 and Pakistan on September 22. </p>
                <p>The ceasefire alone did not resolve the status of Kashmir, and both sides
                    accepted the Soviet Union as a third-party mediator. Negotiations in Tashkent
                    concluded in January 1966, with both sides giving up territorial claims,
                    withdrawing their armies from the disputed territory. Nevertheless, although the
                    Tashkent agreement achieved its short-term aims, conflict in South Asia would
                    reignite a few years later.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="arab-israeli-war-1967"
                ana="johnson-lyndon-b egypt israel jordan syria palestine peace united-nations terrorism arab-israeli-dispute">
                <head>The 1967 Arab-Israeli War</head>
                <p>The 1967 Arab-Israeli War marked the failure of the Eisenhower, Kennedy, and
                    Johnson administrations’ efforts to prevent renewed Arab-Israeli conflict
                    following the 1956 Suez War. Unwilling to return to what National Security
                    Advisor Walter Rostow called the “tenuous chewing gum and string arrangements”
                    established after Suez, the Johnson administration sought Israel’s withdrawal
                    from the territories it had occupied in exchange for peace settlements with its
                    Arab neighbors. This formula has remained the basis of all U.S. Middle East
                    peacemaking efforts into the present.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="six-day-war.jpg" height="450px" width="295px"/>
                    <head>President Lyndon Johnson and his advisors meet with Israeli Foreign
                        Minister Abba Eban to discuss the developing crisis in the Middle East, May
                        26, 1967. (LBJ Library photo by Yoichi Okamoto)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Johnson Administration and the Arab-Israeli Conflict,
                        1963–1967</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Lyndon Johnson’s presidency witnessed the transformation of the American role in
                    the Arab-Israeli conflict. Until the early 1960s, the United States had adhered
                    to the terms of the Tripartite Declaration of 1950, wherein the United States,
                    United Kingdom, and France had pledged to prevent aggression by Middle Eastern
                    states and oppose a regional arms race. The United States had pressed Israel to
                    withdraw from the Sinai Peninsula and Gaza Strip after Suez, and rejected
                    Israeli requests for all but limited quantities of defensive weapons. By the
                    time Johnson took office, however, U.S. policymakers concluded that this policy
                    was no longer sustainable. Soviet arms sales to left-leaning Arab states,
                    especially Egypt, threatened to erode Israel’s military superiority. Johnson’s
                    advisors worried that if the United States did not offset this shift in the
                    balance of power, Israel’s leaders might launch a preventive war or develop
                    nuclear weapons.</p>
                <p>Initially, the Johnson administration sought to convince Egyptian President Gamal
                    Abdul Nasser and the Soviet leadership to work toward a regional arms control
                    regime, but neither party proved receptive. Thus, in 1965, Johnson agreed to
                    sell Israel M48A3 tanks, followed by A–4 Skyhawk aircraft in 1966. The rationale
                    behind these sales, as National Security Council staffer Robert Komer put it,
                    was that “Arab knowledge that they could not win an arms race against Israel
                    should contribute long-term to the damping down of the Arab-Israeli
                    dispute.”</p>
                <p>However, U.S. efforts to preserve the regional balance of power were soon
                    undermined by Fatah and other Palestinian guerilla organizations, which began
                    attacking targets inside Israel. The Johnson administration tried to intercede
                    with Fatah’s Syrian patrons and to prevent Israeli retaliation against Jordan,
                    from which most Palestinian raids were launched. U.S. officials worried that
                    Israeli reprisals could undermine Jordan’s King Hussein, who had secretly agreed
                    to keep Jordan’s strategically crucial West Bank a buffer zone. In November
                    1966, when the Israelis attacked the West Bank town of Samu‘ , the Johnson
                    administration voted for a United Nations Resolution condemning Israel,
                    admonished Israeli officials, and authorized an emergency airlift of military
                    equipment to Jordan.</p>
                <p>While the administration’s response to Samu‘ helped prevent further Israeli
                    reprisals against Jordan, it failed to address the underlying problem of
                    Palestinian cross-border attacks. By the spring of 1967, the Israelis were
                    retaliating forcefully against Syria, whose leaders demanded that Egypt
                    intervene on their behalf.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Prewar Crisis</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On May 13, 1967, Soviet officials informed the Syrian and Egyptian Governments
                    that Israel had massed troops on Syria’s border. Though the report was false,
                    Nasser sent large numbers of Egyptian soldiers into the Sinai anyway. On May 16,
                    Egypt demanded that the United Nations Emergency Force (UNEF), which had been
                    deployed in the Sinai Peninsula and the Gaza Strip since 1957, withdraw from
                    Israel’s border. Secretary-General U Thant replied that he would have to
                    withdraw UNEF from all its positions, including Sharm al-Shaykh, which would put
                    political pressure on Nasser to close the Straits of Tiran to Israeli shipping.
                    Nasser remained adamant, and on May 22, after UNEF withdrew, he announced that
                    he would close the Straits. In 1957, President Dwight D. Eisenhower had promised
                    that the United States would treat the closure of the Straits as an act of war.
                    Johnson now had three unwelcome options: to renege on Eisenhower’s promise,
                    acquiesce in an Israeli attack on Egypt, or order U.S. forces to reopen the
                    waterway.</p>
                <p>Instead, the President played for time. He sought international and Congressional
                    support for Operation Red Sea Regatta, which called for a coalition of maritime
                    nations to send a “probing force” through the Straits if Egypt refused to grant
                    all nations free passage through them. Simultaneously, Johnson implored the
                    Soviets to intercede with Nasser and urged Israeli restraint. “Israel,” Johnson
                    told Israeli Foreign Minister Abba Eban on May 26, “will not be alone unless it
                    decides to go it alone.” Yet over the following week, the administration failed
                    to gain domestic or foreign backing for “Regatta.” Meanwhile, Jordan joined the
                    Arab coalition, heightening the pressure for an Israeli strike. Though Johnson
                    continued to caution Israel against preemption, a number of the President’s
                    advisors had concluded that U.S. interests would be best served by Israel “going
                    it alone” by the time the Israelis actually did so.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The War and its Aftermath</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Between June 5 and June 10, Israel defeated Egypt, Jordan, and Syria and occupied
                    the Sinai Peninsula, the Gaza Strip, the West Bank, East Jerusalem, and the
                    Golan Heights. From the beginning, the United States sought a ceasefire in order
                    to prevent an Arab defeat bad enough to force the Soviet Union to intervene.
                    U.S. officials were also concerned about alienating pro-Western Arab regimes,
                    especially after Egypt and several other Arab states accused the United States
                    of helping Israel and broke diplomatic relations. Yet after June 5, the
                    administration did not also demand an immediate Israeli pullback from the
                    territories it had occupied. U.S. officials believed that in light of the
                    tenuous nature of the prewar armistice regime, they should not force Israel to
                    withdraw unless peace settlements were put into place.</p>
                <p>The administration’s concept of “land-for-peace” solidified following the war.
                    “Certainly,” Johnson proclaimed, “troops must be withdrawn; but there must also
                    be recognized rights of national life, progress in solving the refugee problem,
                    freedom of innocent maritime passage, limitation of the arms race, and respect
                    for political independence and territorial integrity.” Yet after the Arab states
                    rejected a Latin American UN resolution calling for full withdrawal in exchange
                    for recognition of “the right of all states in the area to live in peace and
                    security” and a similar U.S.-Soviet draft, the Johnson administration scaled
                    back its efforts to promote a settlement. Though alarmed by Israeli decisions to
                    absorb East Jerusalem and establish Jewish settlements in the occupied
                    territories, U.S. officials believed that the Arabs remained too inflexible to
                    justify pressing Israel to withdraw. </p>
                <p>The Johnson administration did not re-enter the diplomatic fray until October,
                    when the Soviets began to circulate a new version of the resolution that they
                    had promoted that summer. Knowing that Israel would reject the Soviet draft, the
                    administration encouraged the United Kingdom to introduce an alternative
                    resolution devised by UN Ambassador Arthur Goldberg. Security Council Resolution
                    242, adopted on November 22, called for Israel’s withdrawal from “territories
                    occupied in the recent conflict” in exchange for “termination of all claims or
                    states of belligerency and respect for and acknowledgment of the sovereignty,
                    territorial integrity and political independence of every State in the area and
                    their right to live in peace within secure and recognized boundaries free from
                    threats or acts of force.” Interpreted differently by Israelis and Arabs, this
                    resolution would nonetheless remain the bedrock of all subsequent U.S. efforts
                    to resolve the Arab-Israeli dispute.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="tet" ana="vietnam vietnam-conflict">
                <head>U.S. Involvement in the Vietnam War: The Tet Offensive, <date when="1968"
                        >1968</date>
                </head>
                <p>In late January, 1968, during the lunar new year (or “Tet”) holiday, North
                    Vietnamese and communist Viet Cong forces launched a coordinated attack against
                    a number of targets in <placeName>South Vietnam</placeName>. The U.S. and South
                    Vietnamese militaries sustained heavy losses before finally repelling the
                    communist assault. The Tet Offensive played an important role in weakening U.S.
                    public support for the war in Vietnam. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tet.jpg" height="200px" width="200px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Captain Franklin Eller coordinates with military command during the
                        Tet Offensive</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Ho Chi Minh and leaders in <placeName>Hanoi</placeName> planned the Tet Offensive
                    in the hopes of achieving a decisive victory that would end the grinding
                    conflict that frustrated military leaders on both sides. A successful attack on
                    major cities might force the United States to negotiate or perhaps even to
                    withdraw. At the very least, the North Vietnamese hoped it would serve to stop
                    the ongoing escalation of guerilla attacks and bombing in the North. Hanoi
                    selected the Tet holiday to strike because it was traditionally a time of truce,
                    and because Vietnamese traveling to spend the festival with their relatives
                    provided cover for the movement of <orgName>South Vietnamese National Liberation
                        Forces (NLF)</orgName> who supported the communist forces.</p>
                <p>The first phase of the assault began on January 30 and 31, when NLF forces
                    simultaneously attacked a number of targets, mostly populated areas and places
                    with heavy U.S. troop presence. The strikes on the major cities of
                        <placeName>Huế</placeName> and <placeName>Saigon</placeName> had a strong
                    psychological impact, as they showed that the NLF troops were not as weak as the
                        <persName>Johnson</persName> Administration had previously claimed. The NLF
                    even managed to breach the outer walls of the U.S. Embassy in Saigon. Although
                    the first phase of the offensive became the most famous, a second phase also
                    launched simultaneous assaults on smaller cities and towns on May 4 and
                    stretched into June. A third phase began in August and lasted six weeks. In the
                    months that followed, U.S. and South Vietnamese forces retook the towns that the
                    NLF had secured over the course of the offensive, but they incurred heavy
                    military and civilian casualties in the process.</p>
                <p>At the end of the Tet Offensive, both sides had endured losses, and both sides
                    claimed victory. The U.S. and South Vietnamese military response almost
                    completely eliminated the NLF forces and regained all of the lost territory. At
                    the same time, the Tet Offensive weakened domestic support for the Johnson
                    Administration as the vivid reporting on the Tet Offensive by the U.S. media
                    made clear to the American public that an overall victory in Vietnam was not
                    imminent. </p>
                <p>The aftermath of Tet brought public discussions about de-escalation, but not
                    before U.S. generals asked for additional troops for a wide-scale “accelerated
                    pacification program.” Believing that the U.S. was in a position to defeat the
                    North, these military leaders sought to press for a U.S.-South Vietnam
                    offensive. Johnson and others, however, read the situation differently. Johnson
                    announced that the bombing of <placeName>North Vietnam</placeName> would cease
                    above the 20th parallel and placed a limit on U.S. troops in <placeName>South
                        Vietnam</placeName>. Johnson also attempted to set parameters for peace
                    talks, but it would be several more years before these came to fruition. Within
                    the United States, protests against continued involvement in Vietnam
                    intensified. On March 31, 1968, Johnson announced that he would not seek a
                    second term as president. The job of finding a way out of Vietnam was left to
                    the next U.S. president, <persName>Richard Nixon</persName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="soviet-invasion-czechoslavkia"
                ana="czech-republic slovakia russia johnson-lyndon-b">
                <head>Soviet Invasion of Czechoslovakia, <date when="1968">1968</date>
                </head>
                <p>On <date when="1968-08-20">August 20, 1968</date>, the Soviet Union led <ref
                        target="/milestones/1953-1960/warsaw-treaty">Warsaw Pact</ref> troops in an
                    invasion of <placeName>Czechoslovakia</placeName> to crack down on reformist
                    trends in <placeName>Prague</placeName>. Although the Soviet Union’s action
                    successfully halted the pace of reform in Czechoslovakia, it had unintended
                    consequences for the unity of the communist bloc.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="prague.jpg" width="450px" height="333px"/>
                    <head>Czech youths holding Czechoslovakian ﬂags stand atop of an overturned
                        truck as other Prague residents surround Soviet tanks in downtown Prague on
                        Aug. 21, 1968. (AP Photo/Libor Hajsky/CTK)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Before the <ref target="/milestones/1937-1945">Second World War</ref>, the nation
                    of Czechoslovakia had been a strong democracy in <placeName>Central
                        Europe</placeName>, but beginning in the mid 1930s it faced challenges from
                    both the West and the East. In 1938, the leadership in <placeName>Great
                        Britain</placeName> and <placeName>France</placeName> conceded the German
                    right to takeover the <placeName>Sudetenland</placeName> in the Munich
                    Agreement, but the Czech government condemned this German occupation of its
                    western-most territory as a betrayal. In 1948, Czech attempts to join the
                    U.S.-sponsored <ref target="/milestones/1945-1952/marshall-plan">Marshall
                        Plan</ref> to aid postwar rebuilding were thwarted by Soviet takeover and
                    the installation of a new communist government in Prague. For the next twenty
                    years, Czechoslovakia remained a stable state within the Soviet sphere of
                    influence; unlike in Hungary or Poland, even the rise of de-Stalinization after
                    1953 did not lead to liberalization by the fundamentally conservative Czech
                    government.</p>
                <p>In the 1960s, however, changes in the leadership in <placeName>Prague</placeName>
                    led to a series of reforms to soften or humanize the application of communist
                    doctrines within Czech borders. The Czech economy had been slowing since the
                    early 1960s, and cracks were emerging in the communist consensus as workers
                    struggled against new challenges. The government responded with reforms designed
                    to improve the economy. In early 1968, conservative leader <persName>Antonin
                        Novotny</persName> was ousted as the head of the Communist Party of
                    Czechoslovakia, and he was replaced by <persName>Alexander Dubcek</persName>.
                    The Dubcek government ended censorship in early 1968, and the acquisition of
                    this freedom resulted in a public expression of broad-based support for reform
                    and a public sphere in which government and party policies could be debated
                    openly. In April, the Czech Government issued a formal plan for further reforms,
                    although it tried to liberalize within the existing framework of the
                    Marxist-Leninist State and did not propose a revolutionary overhaul of the
                    political and economic systems. As conflicts emerged between those calling for
                    further reforms and conservatives alarmed by how far the liberalization process
                    had gone, Dubcek struggled to maintain control. </p>
                <p>Soviet leaders were concerned over these recent developments in Czechoslovakia.
                    Recalling the 1956 uprising in Hungary, leaders in <placeName>Moscow</placeName>
                    worried that if Czechoslovakia carried reforms too far, other satellite states
                    in <placeName>Eastern Europe</placeName> might follow, leading to a widespread
                    rebellion against Moscow’s leadership of the Eastern Bloc. There was also a
                    danger that the Soviet Republics in the East, such as the
                        <placeName>Ukraine</placeName>, <placeName>Lithuania</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Latvia</placeName>, and <placeName>Estonia</placeName> might make
                    their own demands for more liberal policies. After much debate, the Communist
                    Party leadership in Moscow decided to intervene to establish a more conservative
                    and pro-Soviet government in Prague.</p>
                <p>The Warsaw Pact invasion of <date when="1968-08-20">August 20–21</date> caught
                    Czechoslovakia and much of the Western world by surprise. In anticipation of the
                    invasion, the Soviet Union had moved troops from the Soviet Union, along with
                    limited numbers of troops from <placeName>Hungary</placeName>,
                        <placeName>Poland</placeName>, <placeName>East Germany</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Bulgaria</placeName> into place by announcing Warsaw Pact
                    military exercises. When these forces did invade, they swiftly took control of
                    Prague, other major cities, and communication and transportation links. Given
                    the escalating U.S. involvement in the conflict in Vietnam as well as past U.S.
                    pronouncements on non-intervention in the East Bloc, the Soviets guessed
                    correctly that the United States would condemn the invasion but refrain from
                    intervening. Although the Soviet crackdown on Czechoslovakia was swift and
                    successful, small-scale resistance continued throughout early 1969 while the
                    Soviets struggled to install a stable government. Finally, in April of 1969, the
                    Soviets forced Dubcek from power in favor of a more conservative administrator.
                    In the years that followed, the new leadership reestablished government
                    censorship and controls preventing freedom of movement, but it also improved
                    economic conditions, eliminating one of the sources for revolutionary fervor.
                    Czechoslovakia once again became a cooperative member of the Warsaw Pact.</p>
                <p>The Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia was significant in the sense that it
                    delayed the splintering of Eastern European Communism and was concluded without
                    provoking any direct intervention from the West. Repeated efforts in the UN
                    Security Council to pass a resolution condemning the attacks met with opposition
                    from the Soviet Union, and the effort finally died away. The invasion did,
                    however, temporarily derail progress toward détente between the Soviet Union and
                    the United States. The NATO allies valued the idea of a lessening of tensions,
                    and as a result they were determined not to intervene. Still, the invasion
                    forced U.S. President <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> to cancel a summit
                    meeting with Soviet leader <persName>Leonid Brezhnev</persName>. Although
                    Brezhnev knew this was the most likely outcome of the invasion, he considered
                    maintaining Soviet control in the East Bloc a higher priority in the short-term
                    than pursuing détente with the West. As it turned out, the progress on arms
                    control agreements were only delayed by a few years in the aftermath of the
                    Prague Spring. </p>
                <p>There were also long-term consequences. After the invasion, the Soviet leadership
                    justified the use of force in Prague under what would become known as the
                    Brezhnev Doctrine, which stated that Moscow had the right to intervene in any
                    country where a communist government had been threatened. This doctrine,
                    established to justify Soviet action in Czechoslovakia, also became the primary
                    justification for the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in 1979, and even before
                    that it helped to finalize the Sino-Soviet split, as Beijing feared that the
                    Soviet Union would use the doctrine as a justification to invade or interfere
                    with Chinese communism. Because the United States interpreted the Brezhnev
                    Doctrine and the history of Soviet interventions in Europe as defending
                    established territory, not expanding Soviet power, the aftermath of the Czech
                    crisis also lent support to voices in the U.S. Congress calling for a reduction
                    in U.S. military forces in Europe. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="npt"
                ana="arms-control-and-disarmament nuclear-weapons nuclear-nonproliferation international-atomic-energy-agency">
                <head>The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT), <date when="1968">1968</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty was an agreement signed in 1968 by several
                    of the major nuclear and non-nuclear powers that pledged their cooperation in
                    stemming the spread of nuclear technology. Although the NPT did not ultimately
                    prevent nuclear proliferation, in the context of the Cold War arms race and
                    mounting international concern about the consequences of nuclear war, the treaty
                    was a major success for advocates of arms control because it set a precedent for
                    international cooperation between nuclear and non-nuclear states to prevent
                    proliferation.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="test-ban.jpg" height="450px" width="304px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Ambassador Llewellyn E. Thompson, signs nuclear non-proliferation
                        treaty as Soviet Foreign Minister Andrei A. Gromyko watches in Moscow,
                        Russia, on July 1, 1968. (AP Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p> After the <placeName>United States</placeName> and the <placeName>Soviet
                        Union</placeName> signed the Limited Test Ban Treaty in 1963, leaders of
                    both nations hoped that other, more comprehensive agreements on arms control
                    would be forthcoming. Given the excessive costs involved in the development and
                    deployment of new and more technologically advanced nuclear weapons, both powers
                    had an interest in negotiating agreements that would help to slow the pace of
                    the arms race and limit competition in strategic weapons development. Four years
                    after the first treaty, the two sides agreed to an Outer Space Treaty that
                    prevented the deployment of nuclear weapons systems as satellites in space. Of
                    far greater import, Soviet and U.S. negotiators also reached a settlement on
                    concluding an international non-proliferation treaty. </p>
                <p>By the beginning of the 1960s, nuclear weapons technology had the potential to
                    become widespread. The science of exploding and fusing atoms had entered into
                    public literature via academic journals, and nuclear technology was no longer
                    pursued only by governments, but by private companies as well. Plutonium, the
                    core of nuclear weapons, was becoming easier to obtain and cheaper to process.
                    As a result of these changes, by 1964 there were five nuclear powers in the
                    world: in addition to the United States, the Soviet Union, and the United
                    Kingdom, all of which obtained nuclear capability during or shortly after the
                    Second World War, France exploded its first nuclear bomb in 1960, and the
                    People’s Republic of China was not far behind in 1964. There were many other
                    countries that had not yet tested weapons, but which were technologically
                    advanced enough that should they decide to build them, it was likely that they
                    could do so before long. </p>
                <p>The spread of nuclear weapons technology meant several things for international
                    lawmakers. While the only countries that were capable of nuclear strike were the
                    United States, its close ally Britain, and the Soviet Union, the doctrine of
                    deterrence could be reasonably maintained. Because both sides of the Cold War
                    had vast stocks of weapons and the capability of striking back after being
                    attacked, any strike would likely have led to mutually assured destruction, and
                    thus there remained a strong incentive for any power to avoid starting a nuclear
                    war. However, if more nations, particularly developing nations that lay on the
                    periphery of the balance of power between the two Cold War superpowers, achieved
                    nuclear capability, this balance risked being disrupted and the system of
                    deterrence would be threatened. Moreover, if countries with volatile border
                    disputes became capable of attacking with nuclear weapons, then the odds of a
                    nuclear war with truly global repercussions increased. This also caused the
                    nuclear states to hesitate in sharing nuclear technology with developing
                    nations, even technology that could be used for peaceful applications. All of
                    these concerns led to international interest in a nuclear non-proliferation
                    treaty that would help prevent the spread of nuclear weapons. </p>
                <p>Although the benefits to be derived from such a treaty were clear, its
                    development was not without controversy. A ban on the distribution of nuclear
                    technology was first proposed by Ireland in a meeting of the General Assembly of
                    the United Nations in 1961. Although the members approved the resolution, it
                    took until 1965 for negotiations to begin in earnest at the Geneva disarmament
                    conference. At that time, U.S. negotiators worked to strike a delicate balance
                    between the interest in preventing further transfer of the technology that it
                    shared with the Soviet Union and the desire to strengthen its NATO allies by
                    giving several Western European nations some measure of control over nuclear
                    weapons. The plan for a nuclear NATO threatened to scuttle the talks altogether,
                    and the United States eventually abandoned it in favor of reaching a workable
                    treaty. A more difficult problem involved the question of bringing non-nuclear
                    nations into line with the planned treaty. Nations that had not yet developed
                    nuclear weapons technology were essentially being asked to give up all
                    intentions to ever develop the weapons. Without this agreement on the part of
                    the non-nuclear powers, having the nuclear powers vow never to transfer the
                    technology would likely not result in any real limitation on the number of
                    worldwide nuclear powers. After two years of negotiations, the nuclear powers
                    managed to make enough concessions to induce many non-nuclear powers to sign. </p>
                <p>The final treaty involved a number of provisions all aimed at limiting the spread
                    of nuclear weapons technology. First, the nuclear signatories agreed not to
                    transfer either nuclear weapons or nuclear weapons technology to any other
                    state. Second, the non-nuclear states agreed that they would not receive,
                    develop or otherwise acquire nuclear weapons. All of the signatories agreed to
                    submit to the safeguards against proliferation established by the International
                    Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA). Parties to the treaty also agreed to cooperate in
                    the development of peaceful nuclear technology and to continue negotiations to
                    help end the nuclear arms race and limit the spread of the technology. The
                    treaty was given a 25-year time limit, with the agreement that it would be
                    reviewed every 5 years.</p>
                <p>The Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty was, and continues to be, heralded as an
                    important step in the ongoing efforts to reduce or prevent the spread of nuclear
                    weapons. Still, it had one major drawback in that two nuclear powers, France and
                    the People’s Republic of China, did not sign the agreement, nor did a number of
                    non-nuclear states. Of the non-nuclear states refusing to adhere, and thereby
                    limit their own future nuclear programs, of particular importance were
                    Argentina, Brazil, India, Israel, Pakistan, Saudi Arabia and South Africa,
                    because these powers were close to being capable of the technology. In fact, in
                    1974, India joined the “nuclear club” by exploding its first weapon. Pakistan
                    tested its first atomic bomb in 1983.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
