<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1969–1976</title>
                <title type="short">1969–1976</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#foreword #nixon-shock #salt #rapprochement-china #arab-israeli-war-1973 #oil-embargo #ending-vietnam #shuttle-diplomacy"
                />
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword" ana="nixon-richard ford-gerald vietnam-conflict">
                <head>1969–1976: The Presidencies of Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford</head>
                <p>President Richard M. Nixon assumed office on January 20, 1969, as an experienced
                    practitioner of foreign policy. He came into the presidency with clear views on
                    the broad objectives of his administration in foreign relations, and with a
                    determination to control major foreign policy initiatives from the White House.
                    During the post-election transition period, Nixon selected Dr. Henry A.
                    Kissinger as his National Security Advisor, and approved a proposal drafted by
                    Kissinger concentrating the interagency policymaking process in the National
                    Security Council. Nixon selected William P. Rogers as the Secretary of State and
                    Melvin R. Laird as the Secretary of Defense. General Earle G. Wheeler served as
                    Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (CJCS) until July 1970, when he was
                    replaced by Admiral Thomas H. Moorer. The Director of the Central Intelligence
                    Agency, Richard M. Helms, continued in that position, which he had held since
                    1966.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="nixon-ford.jpg" height="450px" width="299px"/>
                    <head>Kissinger, Nixon, Ford, and Haig meet in the Oval Office, October 13,
                        1973. (Richard Nixon Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Nixon was a realist, convinced that power was the core dynamic of the
                    international system; while willing to take advantage of summit meetings for
                    political and diplomatic purposes, he was highly skeptical about personal
                    diplomacy. His central concern through his presidency lay in managing great
                    power relationships in the bipolar international system. As the relationship
                    between Nixon and Kissinger matured, they evolved into a close partnership,
                    generally with Nixon laying out the broad outlines of policy and Kissinger
                    helping Nixon work out his thoughts then tirelessly executing the detailed
                    actions necessary to implement broad policy. While Nixon’s major foreign policy
                    initiatives tended to come as great surprises when announced, they had a
                    long-standing basis in his thought and had been worked out well before his
                    inauguration. During the summer of 1967, for example, he spoke at the Bohemian
                    Club in San Francisco, taking the opportunity to outline his thoughts on U.S.
                    relations with the Soviet Union. Similarly, in an article published in <hi
                        rend="italic">Foreign Affairs</hi> in October 1967, he emphasized the
                    importance of bringing China into the community of nations. </p>
                <p>But the achievement of any of these larger visions, he believed, rested on his
                    ability to reach an honorable end to the Vietnam War. Nixon thought that defeat
                    in that conflict would prolong and deepen the division in the United States, and
                    place the United States in a position of weakness in dealing with the Soviets.
                    He and Kissinger projected that the appearance of American weakness would
                    encourage the Soviet Union to adopt a more aggressive foreign policy, in the end
                    creating the risk of war between the superpowers.</p>
                <p>Nixon expected to end American involvement in the Vietnam War within a year, but
                    this hope was dashed when his initial strategy—increasing diplomatic and
                    military pressure on North Vietnam, while offering conciliatory negotiating
                    terms—failed to yield a settlement. He and Kissinger turned to a dual strategy:
                    pursuing a negotiated settlement, while building up South Vietnamese forces and
                    withdrawing U.S. troops, a process known as “Vietnamization” of the war.</p>
                <p>The policymaking process became increasingly concentrated and acrimonious through
                    Nixon’s first administration, with Kissinger and Rogers repeatedly clashing over
                    organizational and personal roles. These clashes generally occurred at times of
                    crisis, imposing a cost on Nixon and on the policy process in general.
                    Kissinger’s deputy, General Al Haig, became an increasingly influential advisor
                    to Nixon, especially on issues related to the war in Southeast Asia.</p>
                <p>Nixon’s major policy initiatives came to fruition during 1972 and early 1973: the
                    “opening to China” with the Beijing Summit in February, the dawn of détente with
                    the Moscow Summit in May, and the end of American involvement in the Vietnam War
                    in January 1973. By that time, the Watergate scandals had begun to envelope
                    Nixon’s presidency, with increasing costs in distraction, stress, and political
                    weakness during Nixon’s remaining time in office. The Nixon administration also
                    grappled with the consequences of the Arab-Israeli War of October 1973, namely
                    the energy crisis precipitated by the Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting
                    Countries (OAPEC) oil embargo against the United States.</p>
                <p>Nixon’s resignation in August 1974 brought Gerald R. Ford to the presidency. Ford
                    inherited Nixon’s second-term foreign policy team, which had undergone
                    considerable turmoil in previous months. Kissinger succeeded Rogers as Secretary
                    of State on September 21, 1973, and served as both Secretary of State and
                    National Security Advisor. Elliott L. Richardson succeeded Laird as Secretary of
                    Defense in January 1973, and then moved to become the Attorney General in late
                    May. James R. Schlesinger served as Director of the Central Intelligence Agency
                    for six months at the outset of the administration, replacing Helms; he then
                    replaced Richardson as the Secretary of Defense. William E. Colby followed
                    Schlesinger as the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency. General George
                    S. Brown replaced Moorer as the CJCS in July 1974.</p>
                <p>Ford emphasized continuity in foreign policy, continuing Nixon’s policy of
                    détente with the Soviet Union and the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT),
                    reaching broad agreement on the SALT II framework in Vladivostok in November
                    1974. Along that same line, he continued to develop U.S. relations with the
                    People’s Republic of China, conducting a summit in Beijing in December 1975. He
                    also worked with Kissinger in securing the Helsinki Accords, which were signed
                    in August 1975, and a second Egyptian-Israeli Disengagement Agreement, which was
                    signed in September 1975. The first months of his presidency saw the invasion
                    and conquest of South Vietnam by North Vietnam in March–April 1975, followed
                    quickly by the <hi rend="italic">Mayaguez</hi> incident. </p>
                <p>Dissatisfied with the performance of his foreign policy team, Ford reshaped it on
                    November 3, 1975. On that day he named Lt. Gen. Brent Scowcroft his National
                    Security Advisor, with Kissinger continuing in his responsibilities as Secretary
                    of State, and Donald R. Rumsfeld replacing James Schlesinger as the Secretary of
                    Defense. Colby was removed as the Director of the Central Intelligence Agency,
                    replaced by George H.W. Bush.</p>
                <p>During the last year of Ford’s presidency, Senator Henry Jackson led critics of
                    détente who viewed it as an amoral foreign policy. That criticism fueled a
                    significant challenge to his presidential candidacy from Ronald Reagan. In
                    response, Ford slowed the momentum both toward an arms control agreement, and
                    toward an agreement in the protracted negotiations on the Panama Canal. Ford was
                    defeated by Jimmy Carter in the 1976 election and left office on January 20,
                    1977.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="allende"
                ana="nixon-richard kissinger-henry-a rogers-william-pierce chile foreign-investment covert-actions">
                <head>The Allende Years and the Pinochet Coup, 1969–1973</head>
                <p>Relations between the United States and Chile deteriorated in the 1960s due to
                    U.S. concerns regarding the Chilean Left and the rise of Chilean nationalization
                    of certain industries, especially copper. The Alliance for Progress, signed in
                    1961 by President <persName>John F. Kennedy</persName>, was designed to prevent
                    the spread of socialism throughout the hemisphere. The Alliance allowed for
                    monetary investment in Latin American countries that would help bolster
                    infrastructure, education, and champion democratic governments, and Chile was
                    one of the primary recipients of aid. The prospect of the nationalization of two
                    of the leading Chilean copper companies, Anaconda and Kennicott—both owned by
                    corporations based in the United States—along with the growth of socialist
                    sentiment throughout the hemisphere led the United States to overtly and
                    covertly send aid and assistance to the Chilean Government, as well as to
                    political parties such as the Christian Democratic Party (PDC).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="chile-allende.jpg" height="450px" width="293px"/>
                    <head>A crowd of marchers show their support for Allende. (U.S. News &amp; World
                        Report Magazine Photograph Collection, Library of Congress Prints and
                        Photographs Division)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In September 1964, PDC candidate <persName>Eduardo Frei</persName> was elected
                    President of Chile, beating out third-time candidate <persName>Salvador
                        Allende</persName> from the Front for Popular Action (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Frente de Acción Popular</hi> or FRAP) party. Frei’s campaign received
                    funds from the U.S. Government to help ensure his election. His administration
                    focused on improving housing, agrarian reform, and increasing access to
                    education. Frei also negotiated an agreement with the Anaconda copper company on
                    the nationalization of copper mines. There were many critics of the Anaconda
                    agreement, even within Frei’s PDC, and nationalization became an important issue
                    in the 1970 presidential election.</p>
                <p>The three candidates for the presidency in the 1970 elections were
                        <persName>Radomiro Tomic</persName> for the PDC, former president
                        <persName>Jorge Alessandri</persName> representing the National Party (PN),
                    and Salvador Allende, candidate of the Popular Unity (<hi rend="italic">Unidad
                        Popular</hi> or UP) party, a leftist coalition which had replaced FRAP. The
                    U.S. Government used covert funds in Chile during this election period, not for
                    any one candidate’s use but to prevent Allende’s election. U.S. support had some
                    impact on the election, but Allende still received over one third of the popular
                    vote. Alessandri also garnered over one third of the vote, trailing Allende by
                    only one percentage point. A run-off election in the Chilean Congress was
                    scheduled for October 24, 1970.</p>
                <p>Neither the Richard Nixon administration, nor the current Chilean Government, nor
                    U.S. companies with businesses in Chile (Anaconda,&#160;International Telephone
                    &amp; Telegraph, Kennicott) wished to see an Allende presidency, fearing his
                    Communist sympathies. The 40 Committee, the U.S. National Security Council
                    committee that reviewed proposals for covert actions, held numerous meetings
                    leading up to the October run-off elections. The debate over whether and how to
                    engage in covert actions in order to prevent an Allende victory was vigorous. At
                    the same time, the Chilean military leadership had splintered into two distinct
                    camps regarding the viability of a military coup: those who were willing to
                    stage a military coup, represented by two factions under General Roberto Viaux
                    and General Camilo Valenzuela, and those (personified by General René Schneider)
                    who believed that any attempt by the military to influence the election was
                    unconstitutional. After two failed attempts by Valenzuela’s supporters to kidnap
                    Schneider, a third attempt was made by Viaux on October 22. The kidnapping
                    attempt went horribly wrong and Schneider was shot. He died several days later.
                    There were no further attempts by the Chilean military to influence the upcoming
                    run-off election.</p>
                <p>On October 24 the Chilean Congress voted to elect Allende president by a large
                    margin, and on November 3 he was officially sworn in as President of Chile.
                    After Allende’s inauguration, Nixon stated that U.S. relations with Chile would
                    continue, but would be cooler than during previous administrations. The
                    administration feared that Allende would create a Communist government in Chile.
                    U.S. policymakers also took steps to severely limit further credits or aid to
                    Chile. </p>
                <p>On December 21, 1970, Allende proposed an amendment to the Chilean constitution
                    that would authorize the expropriation of the mining companies. The Chilean
                    Congress passed the nationalization amendment on July 11, 1971, and it became
                    law five days later. This plan was unique in Latin America because of a clause
                    that Allende had introduced that cited “excessive profit-taking.” This
                    maintained that foreign-owned mining companies made exponentially more in Chile
                    than other similar companies. While expropriation of U.S. assets was usually
                    based upon a percentage of market value, in this case U.S. companies received
                    little or no money at all for the nationalized mines. At the same time, Chile
                    also gained control of the Chilean telephone company, of which ITT owned a
                    majority. Relations between the two countries soured as the battles over the
                    nationalization continued throughout the entirety of the Allende administration. </p>
                <p>Allende wanted to reform health care, agriculture, and education, and was
                    invested in further nationalization of businesses. He increased the percentage
                    of farms and businesses that were nationalized. Wages increased throughout the
                    administration, and for the first few months, inflation was held at bay. On the
                    surface, the reforms appeared to be successful. It became clear, however, that
                    the successes were not balancing out the problems. Rising wages produced a boom
                    in consumerism, and Chile had to rely on imports to meet demand. The price of
                    copper dropped, which severely affected the country’s balance of payments. In
                    addition, the Chilean Government was running out of foreign sources of aid. </p>
                <p>These issues led to a series of demonstrations and strikes from 1971 to 1973. On
                    June 29, 1973, in the midst of widespread protests and strikes, Lieutenant
                    Colonel Roberto Souper led a failed coup attempt against Allende. In a radio
                    address Allende called for the people to support his administration and help
                    defeat the unlawful coup, and called in General Carlos Prats to deal with the
                    rebel forces. Prats, like Schneider, believed that the military should remain
                    apolitical, and the coup was aborted by late morning. Although Prats was key in
                    stopping the coup, by August he lost the support of much of the army. Prats was
                    succeeded as Defense Minister and Army Commander by General Augusto Pinochet on
                    August 24, 1973.</p>
                <p>Between June and September 1973, more protests and strikes crippled Chile. On
                    August 22, the Chamber of Deputies charged the Allende government with breaching
                    numerous sections of the Constitution. Allende refuted the allegations, stating
                    that his actions were constitutional. By this time, it was clear that dissent in
                    the military was rampant and that a coup would be successful if supported fully
                    by the military.</p>
                <p>On the morning of September 11, 1973, the military launched another coup against
                    the Allende government. At 9:10 a.m., Allende made his final broadcast from the
                    presidential palace, announcing that he would not resign the presidency and
                    rallying his supporters with the cry, “Long live Chile! Long live the people!
                    Long live the workers!” After the address, Allende purportedly joined in
                    defending the palace, which was under heavy attack. Once it became clear that
                    the military would take the palace, Allende told the defenders to surrender.
                    Allende died during the final events of the coup: his death is now widely
                    regarded a suicide.</p>
                <p>On September 13, Pinochet was named President of Chile, whereupon he dismantled
                    Congress and outlawed many Chilean leftist political parties. The takeover of
                    the government ended a 46-year history of democratic rule in Chile. In June
                    1975, Pinochet announced that there would be no future elections in the country.
                    Although the U.S. Government was initially pleased by the coup, concerns mounted
                    about the new regime’s reported violations of human rights.</p>
                <p>Debate continues on whether the United States provided direct support for
                    Pinochet’s coup. The United States had a long history of engaging in covert
                    actions in Chile; it had provided funds in support of electoral candidates, run
                    anti-Allende propaganda campaigns, and had discussed the merits of supporting a
                    military coup in 1970. A Senate committee was convened in 1975 to investigate
                    U.S. covert involvement in Chile during the 1960s and 1970s. The report found
                    that the United States had carried out covert actions in Chile during these
                    years and had even considered a proposal for Track II, a covert action meant to
                    organize a military coup to prevent Allende coming to power. However, it
                    concluded that there was little evidence to link the U.S. Government to covert
                    support of Pinochet’s coup.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="detente" ana="russia arms-control-and-disarmament">
                <head>Détente and Arms Control, <date from="1969" to="1979">1969–1979</date>
                </head>
                <p>Between the late 1960s and the late 1970s, there was a thawing of the ongoing
                    Cold War between the United States and the Soviet Union. This détente took
                    several forms, including increased discussion on arms control. Although the
                    decade began with vast improvements in bilateral relations, by the end of the
                    decade events had brought the two superpowers back to the brink of
                    confrontation. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="detente.jpg" height="450px" width="338px"/>
                    <head>Conference on Security and Co-operation in Europe, 1975. (Deutsches
                        Bundesarchiv)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Two decades after the Second World War, Soviet-American tension had become a way
                    of life. Fears of nuclear conflict between the two superpowers peaked in 1962 in
                    the wake of the <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/cuban-missile-crisis">Cuban
                        Missile Crisis</ref>, paving the way for some of the earliest agreements on
                    nuclear arms control, including the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/limited-ban">Limited Test Ban Treaty</ref> in
                    1963. Although these agreements acted as important precedents, the U.S.
                    escalation of the war in Vietnam increased tensions again and served to derail
                    any efforts in the mid-1960s to pursue further arms agreements. By the late
                    1960s, however, both countries had several concrete reasons for resuming arms
                    talks. The ongoing nuclear arms race was incredibly expensive, and both nations
                    faced domestic economic difficulties as a result of the diversion of resources
                    to military research. The emergence of the Sino-Soviet split also made the idea
                    of generally improving relations with the United States more appealing to the
                    USSR. The United States faced an increasingly difficult war in Vietnam, and
                    improved relations with the Soviet Union were thought to be helpful in limiting
                    future conflicts. With both sides willing to explore accommodation, the early
                    1970s saw a general warming of relations that was conducive to progress in arms
                    control talks.</p>
                <p>In practical terms, détente led to formal agreements on arms control and the
                    security of Europe. A clear sign that a détente was emerging was found in the
                    signing of the <ref target="/milestones/1961-1968/npt">Nuclear Nonproliferation
                        Treaty</ref> in 1968. Then, in 1972, the first round of <ref
                        target="/milestones/1969-1976/salt">Strategic Arms Limitations Talks</ref>
                    yielded the Antiballistic Missile Treaty along with an interim agreement setting
                    caps on the number of intercontinental ballistic missiles each side could
                    develop. At mid-decade, in 1975, the Conference on Security and Cooperation in
                    Europe emerged from two years of intense negotiations to sign the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1969-1976/helsinki">Helsinki Final Act</ref>, which
                    recognized political borders, established military confidence building measures,
                    created opportunities for trade and cultural exchange, and promoted human
                    rights. By the end of the decade, however, cracks had begun to form in the
                    precarious U.S.-Soviet relationship. The leadership of the two countries signed
                    a second SALT agreement but did not ratify it, although both nations voluntarily
                    adhered to the provisions for reduced limits on strategic weapons for years
                    thereafter.</p>
                <p>The breakdown of détente in the late 1970s stalled progress on arms control.
                    Ultimately, the United States and the Soviet Union had different visions of what
                    détente meant and what its pursuit would entail. Overblown expectations that the
                    warming of relations in the era of détente would translate into an end to the
                    Cold War also created public dissatisfaction with the increasing manifestations
                    of continued competition and the interventions in the Third World. By the time
                    the Soviet Union invaded Afghanistan in 1979, the spirit of cooperation had been
                    replaced with renewed competition and formal implementation of the SALT II
                    agreement stalled. Arms control talks ceased in the early 1980s and only
                    restarted when <persName>Mikhail Gorbachev</persName> came to power in the
                    Soviet Union.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="south-asia" ana="pakistan india bangladesh nixon-richard">
                <head>The South Asia Crisis and the Founding of Bangladesh, <date when="1971"
                        >1971</date>
                </head>
                <p>In 1971, an internal crisis in Pakistan resulted in a third war between
                        <placeName>India</placeName> and <placeName>Pakistan</placeName> and the
                    secession of East Pakistan, creating the independent state of
                        <placeName>Bangladesh</placeName>. These events altered the relationship
                    between the United States and the region. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="south-asia-crisis.jpg" height="350px" width="528px"/>
                    <head>Last President of a united Pakistan Yahya Khan with President Richard
                        Nixon. (Richard Nixon Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p> The partition of India in 1947 created West and East Pakistan, two noncontiguous
                    territories that shared a dominant religion of Islam but were very different in
                    terms of language, ethnicity and culture. In the 1970 parliamentary elections,
                    an overwhelming number of East Pakistanis voted for a political party that
                    advocated autonomy for the East, but it was blocked from governing by the Army
                    and the existing Pakistani government, and its leader was jailed. The resulting
                    mass protests in the East were brutally suppressed by the Pakistani Army, which
                    caused a massive refugee movement into neighboring India. East Pakistani
                    guerilla forces, supported by India, fought with the Pakistani Army in the late
                    autumn of 1971. West Pakistan responded with air attacks on India, resulting in
                    open war between the two powers beginning on December 3.</p>
                <p>The United States faced several dilemmas in how to respond to the crisis. The
                    regional situation was already complex. India signed a treaty of mutual
                    assistance with the Soviet Union in August, 1971, and the People’s Republic of
                    China was friendly to Pakistan and had fought a war with India in 1962. However,
                    Pakistan was a valuable diplomatic partner, and its government helped the United
                    States achieve a rapprochement with the People’s Republic of China in the early
                    1970s. After President <persName>Richard Nixon</persName>’s visit in 1969, the
                    U.S. Government had resumed selling Pakistan military equipment, a process that
                    had been disrupted by the previous <ref
                        target="/milestones/1961-1968/india-pakistan-war">1965 India-Pakistan
                        War</ref>. Washington wished to avoid a second war between Pakistan and
                    India, but also feared that Pakistan would be greatly weakened if its eastern
                    province seceded, and so supported Pakistan initially. However, the action
                    against the mass protests in East Pakistan was well-publicized and widely
                    condemned, which limited the extent to which the U.S. Government was willing to
                    help the Pakistani Government prevent the division of its country. </p>
                <p>In the end, the United States acted in a somewhat ambiguous manner during the
                    brief 1971 war. The U.S.S. <hi rend="italic">Enterprise</hi> carrier group from
                    Vietnam moved toward the Bay of Bengal, stopping in Singapore and eventually
                    reaching Sri Lanka. This action signaled to the Soviet Union and China that it
                    was possible that the United States would assist Pakistan. However, by not
                    ordering direct intervention, the United States also conveyed to both India and
                    Pakistan the message that the U.S. commitment to intervention in South Asia had
                    limits. This ambiguity would produce negative results for U.S. influence in the
                    region. </p>
                <p>India’s relationship with the Soviet Union ensured that the United Nations would
                    not intervene, and helped deter China from opening a second conflict on India’s
                    northern border. Defeated on both fronts, Pakistan was forced to accede to the
                    establishment of an independent Bangladesh in place of East Pakistan. Bangladesh
                    was admitted to the United Nations in 1974. </p>
                <p>These developments resulted in a decline in U.S. influence in South Asia and
                    India’s emergence as the most significant power on the subcontinent. U.S.
                    prestige was damaged in both nations, in Pakistan for failing to help prevent
                    the loss of East Pakistan and in India for supporting the brutality of the
                    Pakistani regime’s actions in what became Bangladesh. In contrast, the Soviet
                    relationship with India became stronger, a fact that took on greater
                    significance with India’s rise to prominence in the region. In the long run, the
                    1971 war increased competition between India and Pakistan, forcing the United
                    States to maintain its focus on regional developments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="nixon-shock"
                ana="nixon-richard financial-and-monetary-policy trade-and-commercial-policy-agreements">
                <head>Nixon and the End of the Bretton Woods System, 1971–1973</head>
                <p>On August 15, 1971, President <persName>Richard M. Nixon</persName> announced his
                    New Economic Policy, a program “to create a new prosperity without war.” Known
                    colloquially as the “Nixon shock,” the initiative marked the beginning of the
                    end for the Bretton Woods system of fixed exchange rates established at the end
                    of World War II.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="gold-window.jpg" height="350px" width="532px"/>
                    <head>Secretary of the Treasury John Connally on the day that President Richard
                        Nixon announced his New Economic Policy, August 15, 1971. (Nixon
                        Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Under the Bretton Woods system, the external values of foreign currencies were
                    fixed in relation to the U.S. dollar, whose value was in turn expressed in gold
                    at the congressionally-set price of $35 per ounce. By the 1960s, a surplus of
                    U.S. dollars caused by foreign aid, military spending, and foreign investment
                    threatened this system, as the United States did not have enough gold to cover
                    the volume of dollars in worldwide circulation at the rate of $35 per ounce; as
                    a result, the dollar was overvalued. Presidents <persName>John F.
                        Kennedy</persName> and <persName>Lyndon B. Johnson</persName> adopted a
                    series of measures to support the dollar and sustain Bretton Woods: foreign
                    investment disincentives; restrictions on foreign lending; efforts to stem the
                    official outflow of dollars; international monetary reform; and cooperation with
                    other countries. Nothing worked. Meanwhile, traders in foreign exchange markets,
                    believing that the dollar’s overvaluation would one day compel the U.S.
                    government to devalue it, proved increasingly inclined to sell dollars. This
                    resulted in periodic runs on the dollar.</p>
                <p>It was just such a run on the dollar, along with mounting evidence that the
                    overvalued dollar was undermining the nation’s foreign trading position, which
                    prompted President Richard M. Nixon to act. On August 13, 1971, Nixon convened a
                    meeting of his top economic advisers, including Secretary of the Treasury John
                    Connally and Office of Management and Budget Director George Shultz, at the Camp
                    David presidential retreat to consider a program of action. Notably absent from
                    the meeting were Secretary of State William Rogers and President’s Assistant for
                    National Security Affairs Henry Kissinger. After two days of talks, on the
                    evening of August 15, Nixon announced his New Economic Policy in an address to
                    the nation on “The Challenge of Peace.” Asserting that progress in bringing an
                    end to U.S. involvement in the war in Vietnam meant that it was time for
                    Americans to turn their minds to the challenges of a post-Vietnam world, Nixon
                    identified a three-fold task: “We must create more and better jobs; we must stop
                    the rise in the cost of living; we must protect the dollar from the attacks of
                    international money speculators.” To achieve the first two goals, he proposed
                    tax cuts and a 90-day freeze on prices and wages; to achieve the third, Nixon
                    directed the suspension of the dollar’s convertibility into gold. He also
                    ordered that an extra 10 percent tariff be levied on all dutiable imports; like
                    the suspension of the dollar’s gold convertibility, this measure was intended to
                    induce the United States’ major trading partners to adjust the value of their
                    currencies upward and the level of their trade barriers downward so as to allow
                    for more imports from the United States.</p>
                <p>A success at home, Nixon’s speech shocked many abroad, who saw it as an act of
                    worrisome unilateralism; the assertive manner in which Connally conducted the
                    ensuing exchange rate negotiations with his foreign counterparts did little to
                    allay such concerns. Nevertheless, after months of negotiations, the Group of
                    Ten (G–10) industrialized democracies agreed to a new set of fixed exchange
                    rates centered on a devalued dollar in the December 1971 Smithsonian Agreement.
                    Although characterized by Nixon as “the most significant monetary agreement in
                    the history of the world,” the exchange rates established in the Smithsonian
                    Agreement did not last long. Fifteen months later, in February 1973, speculative
                    market pressure led to a further devaluation of the dollar and another set of
                    exchange parities. Several weeks later, the dollar was yet again subjected to
                    heavy pressure in financial markets; however, this time there would be no
                    attempt to shore up Bretton Woods. In March 1973, the G–10 approved an
                    arrangement wherein six members of the European Community tied their currencies
                    together and jointly floated against the U.S. dollar, a decision that
                    effectively signaled the abandonment of the Bretton Woods fixed exchange rate
                    system in favor of the current system of floating exchange rates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="salt"
                ana="johnson-lyndon-b nixon-richard ford-gerald carter-jimmy reagan-ronald russia arms-control-and-disarmament politico-military-issues">
                <head>Strategic Arms Limitations Talks/Treaty (SALT) I and II</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">SALT I</hi>
                </p>
                <p>During the late 1960s, the United States learned that the Soviet Union had
                    embarked upon a massive Intercontinental Ballistic Missile (ICBM) buildup
                    designed to reach parity with the United States. In January 1967, President
                        <persName>Lyndon Johnson</persName> announced that the Soviet Union had
                    begun to construct a limited Anti-Ballistic Missile (ABM) defense system around
                    Moscow. The development of an ABM system could allow one side to launch a first
                    strike and then prevent the other from retaliating by shooting down incoming
                    missiles.</p>
                <p>Johnson therefore called for strategic arms limitations talks (SALT), and in
                    1967, he and Soviet Premier <persName>Alexei Kosygin</persName> met at Glassboro
                    State College in New Jersey. Johnson said they must gain “control of the ABM
                    race,” and Secretary of Defense <persName>Robert McNamara</persName> argued that
                    the more each reacted to the other’s escalation, the more they had chosen “an
                    insane road to follow.” While abolition of nuclear weapons would be impossible,
                    limiting the development of both offensive and defensive strategic systems would
                    stabilize U.S.-Soviet relations. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="salt.jpg" height="450px" width="305px"/>
                    <head>Nixon and Brezhnev during the latter’s visit to the U.S. in 1973. (Nixon
                        Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Johnson’s successor, <persName>Richard Nixon</persName>, also believed in SALT,
                    and on November 17, 1969, the formal SALT talks began in Helsinki, Finland. Over
                    the next two and a half years, the two sides haggled over whether or not each
                    nation should complete their plans for ABMs; verification of a treaty; and U.S.
                    concern that the Soviets continued to build more Submarine-Launched Ballistic
                    Missiles (SLBMs). Nixon and Soviet General Secretary Leonid Brezhnev signed the
                    ABM Treaty and interim SALT agreement on May 26, 1972, in Moscow.</p>
                <p>For the first time during the Cold War, the United States and Soviet Union had
                    agreed to limit the number of nuclear missiles in their arsenals. SALT I is
                    considered the crowning achievement of the Nixon-Kissinger strategy of détente.
                    The ABM Treaty limited strategic missile defenses to 200 interceptors each and
                    allowed each side to construct two missile defense sites, one to protect the
                    national capital, the other to protect one ICBM field. (For financial and
                    strategic reasons, the United States stopped construction of each by the end of
                    the decade.)</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">SALT II</hi>
                </p>
                <p>Negotiations for a second round of SALT began in late 1972. Since SALT I did not
                    prevent each side from enlarging their forces through the deployment of Multiple
                    Independently Targeted Re-Entry Vehicles (MIRVs) onto their ICBMs and SLBMs,
                    SALT II initially focused on limiting, and then ultimately reducing, the number
                    of MIRVs. Negotiations also sought to prevent both sides from making qualitative
                    breakthroughs that would again destabilize the strategic relationship. The
                    negotiations spanned the Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Jimmy Carter
                    administrations.</p>
                <p>At the November 1974 Vladivostok Summit, Ford and Brezhnev agreed on the basic
                    framework of a SALT II agreement. This included a 2,400 limit on strategic
                    nuclear delivery vehicles (ICBMs, SLBMs, and heavy bombers) for each side; a
                    1,320 limit on MIRV systems; a ban on new land-based ICBM launchers; and limits
                    on deployment of new types of strategic offensive arms.</p>
                <p>Even after the Vladivostok agreements, the two nations could not resolve the two
                    other outstanding issues from SALT I: the number of strategic bombers and the
                    total number of warheads in each nation’s arsenal. The first was complicated by
                    the Soviet Backfire bomber, which U.S. negotiators believed could reach the
                    United States but which the Soviets refused to include in the SALT negotiations.
                    Meanwhile, the Soviets attempted unsuccessfully to limit American deployment of
                    Air-Launched Cruise Missiles (ALCMs). Verification also divided the two nations,
                    but eventually they agreed on using National Technical Means (NTM), including
                    the collection of electronic signals known as telemetry and the use of
                    photo-reconnaissance satellites. On June 17, 1979, Carter and Brezhnev signed
                    the SALT II Treaty in Vienna. SALT II limited the total of both nations’ nuclear
                    forces to 2,250 delivery vehicles and placed a variety of other restrictions on
                    deployed strategic nuclear forces, including MIRVs.</p>
                <p>However, a broad coalition of Republicans and conservative Democrats grew
                    increasingly skeptical of the Soviet Union’s crackdown on internal dissent, its
                    increasingly interventionist foreign policies, and the verification process
                    delineated in the Treaty. On December 17, 1979, 19 Senators wrote Carter that
                    “Ratification of a SALT II Treaty will not reverse trends in the military
                    balance adverse to the United States.” On December 25, the Soviets invaded
                    Afghanistan, and on January 3, 1980, Carter asked the Senate not to consider
                    SALT II for its advice and consent, and it was never ratified. Both Washington
                    and Moscow subsequently pledged to adhere to the agreement’s terms despite its
                    failure to enter into force. Carter’s successor Ronald Reagan, a vehement critic
                    of SALT II during the 1980 presidential campaign, agreed to abide by SALT II
                    until its expiration on December 31, 1985, while he pursued the Strategic Arms
                    Reduction Treaty (START) and argued that research into the Strategic Defense
                    Initiative (SDI) adhered to the 1972 ABM Treaty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="rapprochement-china"
                ana="nixon-richard kissinger-henry-a east-asia-and-pacific china taiwan pakistan united-nations">
                <head>Rapprochement with China, 1972</head>
                <p>In 1972, U.S. President <persName>Richard Nixon</persName> traveled to the
                    People’s Republic of China (PRC) and met with <persName>Mao Zedong</persName>,
                    the Chairman of the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party, and
                        <persName>Zhou Enlai</persName>, the PRC Premier. Over the course of this
                    visit, the two governments negotiated the Shanghai Communiqué, an important step
                    toward improving relations between the United States and the PRC after many
                    years of hostility.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="rapproachment-china.jpg" height="450px" width="351px"/>
                    <head>Chairman of the Chinese Communist Party Mao Zedong shakes hands with U.S.
                        President Richard Nixon in Beijing, February 21, 1972. (Nixon Presidential
                        Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Diplomatic estrangement between the two countries went back to the 1940s. After
                    the Chinese civil war ended in 1949, the Communists established the People’s
                    Republic of China on the Chinese mainland while many soldiers and officials of
                    the defeated Republic of China (ROC) evacuated to the island of Taiwan. For the
                    30 years that followed, the United States recognized the Republic of China as
                    the legitimate government of China and had no official diplomatic relations with
                    Communist China.</p>
                <p>In the late 1960s and early 1970s, there were indications that the United States
                    and the People’s Republic of China were considering rapprochement. The
                    escalating war in Vietnam led U.S. officials to look for ways to improve
                    relations with Communist governments in Asia in the hopes that such a policy
                    might lessen future conflict, undermine alliances between Communist countries,
                    diplomatically isolate North Vietnam, and increase U.S. leverage against the
                    Soviet Union. Likewise, Sino-Soviet tension contributed to the Chinese
                    leadership’s desire for a rapprochement with the United States. Nixon signaled
                    his interest in improved relations by easing the travel and trade restrictions
                    against China that dated from the Korean War in the early 1950s. Although the
                    Sino-U.S. Ambassadorial Talks, which began in 1955 and continued intermittently
                    over the years that followed, had reached a hiatus, the two sides agreed to
                    reopen them in 1969. Of greater significance, Nixon established a secret channel
                    to the PRC’s leadership through Pakistani President Yahya Khan. In Nixon’s view,
                    Khan was an attractive intermediary since he had good relations with the leaders
                    of both the United States and the PRC, and he also provided a means to
                    circumvent the U.S. Department of State, which Nixon feared might oppose or
                    publicize his initiative.</p>
                <p>By late 1970, the pace of rapprochement was accelerating. Through the Pakistani
                    channel, the PRC government expressed interest in high level discussions with
                    the United States aimed at improving relations. Mao likewise told U.S.
                    journalist Edgar Snow that he would be happy to talk with Nixon. In 1971, Nixon
                    removed the last remaining restrictions preventing Americans from traveling to
                    mainland China. Following well-publicized fraternization between U.S. and PRC
                    table tennis players during an international competition in Japan, the PRC
                    issued an invitation in April 1971 for the U.S. ping pong team to play a match
                    in Communist China. In April 1972, the PRC ping pong team visited the United
                    States on a good-will tour. This informal “Ping Pong Diplomacy” provided a
                    public face for more serious diplomatic negotiations.</p>
                <p>
                    <persName>Henry Kissinger</persName>, the Assistant to the President for
                    National Security Affairs, traveled to Beijing twice during 1971 to discuss the
                    conditions under which each side would consider a normalization of relations.
                    The first of these trips was conducted in great secrecy and only revealed to the
                    American public during a dramatic speech by President Nixon. Kissinger’s second
                    trip to the PRC, in October 1971, coincided with a vote on Chinese
                    representation in the United Nations. The United States advocated that the
                    United Nations seat delegations from both Communist China and Taiwan. This
                    proposal failed and, instead, the member states of the United Nations voted to
                    seat the PRC delegation in place of the Taiwan delegation. Although the United
                    States unsuccessfully opposed Taiwan’s expulsion from the General Assembly, it
                    supported Communist China’s entrance and assumption of a seat on the Security
                    Council; this contributed to a major diplomatic triumph for the People’s
                    Republic of China.</p>
                <p>Nixon travelled to Communist China February 21–28, 1972, becoming the first U.S.
                    President to visit mainland China while in office. Near the end of the trip, the
                    two governments issued the Shanghai Communiqué, in which each articulated its
                    position on a crucial obstacle to normalization, the Taiwan issue. The People’s
                    Republic of China affirmed that Taiwan was a part of China, and that it opposed
                    all attempts to create two Chinas, one China and one Taiwan, or an independent
                    Taiwan. The United States declared that it “acknowledges that all Chinese on
                    either side of the Taiwan Strait maintain that there is but one China and that
                    Taiwan is a part of China,” and that it did not challenge that position. The
                    United States also noted the importance of finding a peaceful resolution to the
                    Taiwan issue and that it intended to withdraw remaining U.S. troops from Taiwan.
                    Over the course of the talks, Mao and Zhou made clear to Nixon that their
                    country would not normalize relations with the United States as long as
                    Washington continued formal diplomatic relations with Taiwan; Nixon stated that
                    the United States did not support Taiwanese independence. The principles
                    established in the Shanghai Communiqué provided the basis for the establishment
                    of formal diplomatic relations [Carter normalization milestone] between the two
                    countries in 1979. On a global scale, rapprochement fundamentally altered the
                    context of the Cold War and influenced the subsequent movement towards détente
                    between the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="arab-israeli-war-1973"
                ana="nixon-richard rogers-william-pierce kissinger-henry-a egypt israel syria peace united-nations arab-israeli-dispute">
                <head>The 1973 Arab-Israeli War</head>
                <p>The 1973 Arab-Israeli War was a watershed for U.S. foreign policy toward the
                    Middle East. It forced the Nixon administration to realize that Arab frustration
                    over Israel’s unwillingness to withdraw from the territories it had occupied in
                    1967 could have major strategic consequences for the United States. The war thus
                    paved the way for Secretary of State <persName>Henry Kissinger’s</persName>
                    “shuttle diplomacy” and ultimately, the Israeli-Egyptian peace treaty of
                    1979.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="73-war.jpg" height="450px" width="284px"/>
                    <head>President Richard Nixon, Secretary of State Henry Kissinger, and Israeli
                        Prime Minister Golda Meir, November 1973. (U.S. News &amp; World Report
                        Magazine Photograph Collection, Library of Congress)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Nixon Administration and the Arab-Israeli Conflict,
                        1969–1973</hi>
                </p>
                <p>President <persName>Richard Nixon</persName> came into office convinced that the
                    Arab-Israeli standoff over the fate of the occupied territories could damage
                    America’s standing in the Arab world and undermine prospects for U.S.-Soviet
                    détente. In attempt to break the deadlock, he ordered Secretary of State William
                    Rogers to negotiate with the Soviets on the parameters of a Middle East
                    settlement, with the goal of reaching an agreement that each superpower could
                    sell to its regional clients. By December 1969, however, the Soviet Union,
                    Egypt, and Israel had all rejected the so-called “Rogers Plan,” which called for
                    Israeli to withdraw to the 1949 armistice lines, with “insubstantial
                    alterations,” in return for peace.</p>
                <p>The failure of the Rogers Plan led Nixon to suspend efforts to reach a settlement
                    with the Soviets and lent credence to National Security Advisor Henry
                    Kissinger’s argument that the United States should not push Israel for
                    concessions so long as Egypt, the leading Arab state, remained aligned with the
                    Soviets. In the summer of 1970, Nixon broke with Kissinger and allowed Rogers to
                    present a more limited initiative to halt the Israeli-Egyptian “War of
                    Attrition” along the Suez Canal, in which the Soviets had become militarily
                    involved. “Rogers II,” which called for Israel and Egypt to agree to a three
                    month ceasefire and negotiations under the auspices of U.N. mediator
                        <persName>Gunnar Jarring</persName>, was accepted by both parties, who
                    stopped fighting on August 7. Yet Nixon’s appetite for diplomacy was spoiled by
                    Egyptian and Soviet efforts to move anti-aircraft missiles closer to the Canal
                    and Syrian intervention in Jordan’s civil war. Until February 1971, Kissinger’s
                    arguments against prematurely rewarding Soviet clients again held sway.</p>
                <p>In February 1971, however, Egyptian President <persName>Anwar Sadat</persName>
                    presented the Nixon administration with a new opportunity for Arab-Israeli
                    peacemaking. Sadat proposed that Egypt would reopen the Suez Canal if the Israel
                    Defense Forces (IDF) pulled back from the Canal’s east bank and later agreed to
                    a timetable for further withdrawals. He also indicated that he would renounce
                    all claims of belligerency against Israel if the IDF withdrew to the
                    international border. Rogers’ efforts to capitalize on Sadat’s statements by
                    working toward an interim settlement, however, were opposed by the Israelis, and
                    received little support from Kissinger and Nixon. Kissinger believed that
                    Egyptian proposals for an interim settlement, along with a Soviet peace plan
                    tabled that September, would be rejected by the Israelis, and did not want
                    discord over the Middle East to undermine efforts at détente before the Moscow
                    summit of May 1972. For Nixon, such reasoning was reinforced by a desire to
                    avoid a crisis in U.S.-Israeli relations before the 1972 presidential elections. </p>
                <p>In the wake of the Moscow summit, where the Americans and the Soviets
                    deliberately avoided discussing the Middle East, Sadat made two more moves to
                    get the Nixon administration to break the Arab-Israeli stalemate. In July 1972,
                    he decided to expel Soviet military advisors from Egypt, and opened a
                    backchannel to Kissinger through Hafiz Isma‘il, his national security advisor.
                    In February 1973, Isma‘il met with Kissinger and informed him that Egypt would
                    be willing to sign a separate peace agreement with Israel that could involve
                    demilitarized zones on both sides of the international border and peacekeepers
                    in sensitive locations like Sharm al-Shaykh. However, Egyptian-Israeli
                    normalization would have to wait until Israel withdrew from all the territories
                    it had conquered in 1967. The Israelis responded haltingly, and Nixon and
                    Kissinger made little effort to change their minds. Despite Sadat’s public
                    displays of frustration, as well as warnings from Jordan’s King Hussein and
                    Soviet Secretary-General Leonid Brezhnev, Nixon and Kissinger believed that
                    given the military balance, Egypt and Syria would not attack Israel, a view
                    supported by much of the U.S. intelligence community. Until the fall of 1973,
                    the President and Kissinger held that any American diplomatic initiative would
                    have to wait until after Israel’s elections that October.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The War and its Consequences</hi>
                </p>
                <p>On October 6, 1973, Egypt and Syria attacked Israel’s forces in the Sinai
                    Peninsula and the Golan Heights. Despite initial Israeli setbacks, Kissinger,
                    now both Secretary of State and National Security Advisor, believed that Israel
                    would win quickly. He feared that a rout of the Arabs could force the Soviets to
                    intervene, raising their prestige in the Arab world and damaging détente. Thus,
                    he proposed that the United States and the Soviet Union call for an end to the
                    fighting and a return to the 1967 ceasefire lines. The Soviets, who were uneager
                    to intervene on behalf of their clients, agreed, but the Egyptians rejected the
                    ceasefire proposal. Wanting to avoid both an Arab defeat and military
                    intervention, the Soviets then began to resupply Egypt and Syria with weapons.
                    By October 9, following a failed IDF counter-attack against Egypt’s forces, the
                    Israelis requested that America do the same for them. Not wanting to see Israel
                    defeated, Nixon agreed, and American planes carrying weapons began arriving in
                    Israel on October 14.</p>
                <p>With the American airlift underway, the fighting turned against the Arabs. On
                    October 16, IDF units crossed the Suez Canal. Sadat began to show interest in a
                    ceasefire, leading Brezhnev to invite Kissinger to Moscow to negotiate an
                    agreement. A U.S.-Soviet proposal for a ceasefire followed by peace talks was
                    adopted by the UN Security Council as Resolution 338 on October 22. Afterward,
                    however, Kissinger flew to Tel Aviv, where he told the Israelis that the United
                    States would not object if the IDF continued to advance while he flew back to
                    Washington. When Kissinger returned to the United States, he agreed to a Soviet
                    request to seek another ceasefire resolution, which the Security Council adopted
                    on October 23. Yet the Israelis still refused to stop. On October 24, Brezhnev
                    sent Nixon a hotline message suggesting that the United States and the Soviet
                    Union send troops to Egypt to “implement” the ceasefire. If Nixon chose not to
                    do so, Brezhnev threatened, “We should be faced with the necessity urgently to
                    consider the question of taking appropriate steps unilaterally.” The United
                    States responded by putting its nuclear forces on worldwide alert on October 25.
                    By the end of the day, the crisis abated when the Security Council adopted
                    Resolution 340, which called for a ceasefire, the withdrawal of all forces to
                    their October 22 positions, and U.N. observers and peacekeepers to monitor the
                    ceasefire. This time, the Israelis accepted the resolution. </p>
                <p> The 1973 war thus ended in an Israeli victory, but at great cost to the United
                    States. Though the war did not scuttle détente, it nevertheless brought the
                    United States closer to a nuclear confrontation with the Soviet Union than at
                    any point since the Cuban missile crisis. The American military airlift to
                    Israel, moreover, had led Arab oil producers to embargo oil shipments to the
                    United States and some Western European countries, causing international
                    economic upheaval. The stage was set for Kissinger to make a major effort at
                    Arab-Israeli peacemaking.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="oil-embargo"
                ana="israel foreign-economic-policy nixon-richard kissinger-henry-a organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries">
                <head>Oil Embargo, 1973–1974</head>
                <p>During the 1973 Arab-Israeli War, Arab members of the Organization of Petroleum
                    Exporting Countries (OPEC) imposed an embargo against the United States in
                    retaliation for the U.S. decision to re-supply the Israeli military and to gain
                    leverage in the post-war peace negotiations. Arab OPEC members also extended the
                    embargo to other countries that supported Israel including the Netherlands,
                    Portugal, and South Africa. The embargo both banned petroleum exports to the
                    targeted nations and introduced cuts in oil production. Several years of
                    negotiations between oil-producing nations and oil companies had already
                    destabilized a decades-old pricing system, which exacerbated the embargo’s
                    effects.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="oil-embargo.jpg" height="450px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>Cars wait in long lines during the gas shortage. (Library of Congress
                        Prints and Photographs Division, U.S. News &amp; World Report Magazine
                        Photograph Collection, Warren K. Leffler)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The 1973 Oil Embargo acutely strained a U.S. economy that had grown increasingly
                    dependent on foreign oil. The efforts of President Richard M. Nixon’s
                    administration to end the embargo signaled a complex shift in the global
                    financial balance of power to oil-producing states and triggered a slew of U.S.
                    attempts to address the foreign policy challenges emanating from long-term
                    dependence on foreign oil.</p>
                <p>By 1973, OPEC had demanded that foreign oil corporations increase prices and cede
                    greater shares of revenue to their local subsidiaries. In April, the Nixon
                    administration announced a new energy strategy to boost domestic production to
                    reduce U.S. vulnerability to oil imports and ease the strain of nationwide fuel
                    shortages. That vulnerability would become overtly clear in the fall of that
                    year. </p>
                <p>The onset of the embargo contributed to an upward spiral in oil prices with
                    global implications. The price of oil per barrel first doubled, then quadrupled,
                    imposing skyrocketing costs on consumers and structural challenges to the
                    stability of whole national economies. Since the embargo coincided with a
                    devaluation of the dollar, a global recession seemed imminent. U.S. allies in
                    Europe and Japan had stockpiled oil supplies, and thereby secured for themselves
                    a short-term cushion, but the long-term possibility of high oil prices and
                    recession precipitated a rift within the Atlantic Alliance. European nations and
                    Japan found themselves in the uncomfortable position of needing U.S. assistance
                    to secure energy sources, even as they sought to disassociate themselves from
                    U.S. Middle East policy. The United States, which faced a growing dependence on
                    oil consumption and dwindling domestic reserves, found itself more reliant on
                    imported oil than ever before, having to negotiate an end to the embargo under
                    harsh domestic economic circumstances that served to diminish its international
                    leverage. To complicate matters, the embargo’s organizers linked its end to
                    successful U.S. efforts to bring about peace between Israel and its Arab
                    neighbors.</p>
                <p>Partly in response to these developments, on November 7 the Nixon administration
                    announced Project Independence to promote domestic energy independence. It also
                    engaged in intensive diplomatic efforts among its allies, promoting a consumers’
                    union that would provide strategic depth and a consumers’ cartel to control oil
                    pricing. Both of these efforts were only partially successful. </p>
                <p>President Nixon and Secretary of State Henry Kissinger recognized the constraints
                    inherent in peace talks to end the war that were coupled with negotiations with
                    Arab OPEC members to end the embargo and increase production. But they also
                    recognized the linkage between the issues in the minds of Arab leaders. The
                    Nixon administration began parallel negotiations with key oil producers to end
                    the embargo, and with Egypt, Syria, and Israel to arrange an Israeli pullout
                    from the Sinai and the Golan Heights. Initial discussions between Kissinger and
                    Arab leaders began in November 1973 and culminated with the First
                    Egyptian-Israeli Disengagement Agreement on January 18, 1974. Though a finalized
                    peace deal failed to materialize, the prospect of a negotiated end to
                    hostilities between Israel and Syria proved sufficient to convince the relevant
                    parties to lift the embargo in March 1974.</p>
                <p>The embargo laid bare one of the foremost challenges confronting U.S. policy in
                    the Middle East, that of balancing the contradictory demands of unflinching
                    support for Israel and the preservation of close ties to the Arab oil-producing
                    monarchies. The strains on U.S. bilateral relations with Saudi Arabia revealed
                    the difficulty of reconciling those demands. The U.S. response to the events of
                    1973–1974 also clarified the need to reconcile U.S. support for Israel to
                    counterbalance Soviet influence in the Arab world with both foreign and domestic
                    economic policies.</p>
                <p>The full impact of the embargo, including high inflation and stagnation in oil
                    importers, resulted from a complex set of factors beyond the proximate actions
                    taken by the Arab members of OPEC. The declining leverage of the U.S. and
                    European oil corporations (the “Seven Sisters”) that had hitherto stabilized the
                    global oil market, the erosion of excess capacity of East Texas oil fields, and
                    the recent decision to allow the U.S. dollar to float freely in the
                    international exchange all played a role in exacerbating the crisis. Once the
                    broader impact of these factors set in throughout the United States, it
                    triggered new measures beyond the April and November 1973 efforts that focused
                    on energy conservation and development of domestic energy sources. These
                    measures included the creation of the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, a national
                    55-mile-per-hour speed limit on U.S. highways, and later, President Gerald R.
                    Ford’s administration’s imposition of fuel economy standards. It also prompted
                    the creation of the International Energy Agency proposed by Kissinger.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="ending-vietnam"
                ana="vietnam-conflict nixon-richard kissinger-henry-a cambodia laos vietnam">
                <head>Ending the Vietnam War, 1969–1973 </head>
                <p>President <persName>Richard M. Nixon</persName> assumed responsibility for the
                    Vietnam War as he swore the oath of office on January 20, 1969. He knew that
                    ending this war honorably was essential to his success in the presidency. He
                    expected that the American people would give him a year to end U.S. involvement
                    in the war, and he expected to succeed during that time—believing that his
                    experience in foreign relations, his toughness, and his willingness to bring to
                    bear military and political pressure on North Vietnam would yield a settlement
                    in the public negotiations just opening in Paris.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="end-vietnam-war.jpg" height="400px" width="266px"/>
                    <head>President Richard M. Nixon and President Thieu at Midway, June 1969.
                        (Nixon Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In his first months in office, Nixon directed the U.S. military to increase its
                    pressure on the battlefield, while ordering the secret B–52 bombings of North
                    Vietnamese base camps in Cambodia—the “Menu bombings”—as a signal of his
                    willingness to further escalate the war. He expected to complement this military
                    pressure with conciliatory negotiating terms in the newly begun negotiations,
                    and with diplomatic pressure on the Soviet Union, hoping the Soviet Union would
                    encourage their North Vietnamese allies to engage in serious negotiations. These
                    forms of pressure, however, brought him no closer to ending the war. In order to
                    buy time with the American people, Nixon began to withdraw forces from Vietnam,
                    meeting with South Vietnam’s President <persName>Nguyen Van Thieu</persName> on
                    Midway Island on June 8 to announce the first increment of redeployment. From
                    that point on, the U.S. troop withdrawal never ceased. As U.S. troop strength
                    and capabilities declined, the United States worked toward building South
                    Vietnam’s military capacity through a program known as “Vietnamization.” It
                    would remain a constant question over the remaining years of the administration,
                    whether the South Vietnamese could build the combat capability, logistics and
                    planning capacity, and leadership at the national and military levels to face
                    the North Vietnamese on their own.</p>
                <p>It quickly became apparent that the public peace talks in Paris were being used
                    as propaganda theater by both sides, and that any productive negotiations would
                    have to be done in private. On August 4, the President’s Assistant for National
                    Security Affairs <persName>Henry Kissinger</persName> conducted his first
                    private session with the North Vietnamese leadership. He would meet with North
                    Vietnamese Politburo member Le Duc Tho intermittently over the following months,
                    with no apparent progress toward a settlement.</p>
                <p>In the fall of 1969, disappointed with the lack of any visible results from this
                    strategy, Nixon and Kissinger directed an extensive planning effort assessing
                    the possibility of coercing the North Vietnamese into negotiations through a
                    series of “short, sharp blows” inflicted by air and naval forces. The
                    political-military planning included a cell of National Security Council staff
                    members examining strategic issues, and a military planning team comprised of
                    Joint Staff, Pacific Command (PACOM), and Military Assistance Command Vietnam
                    (MACV) officers working at MACV Headquarters in Saigon. Nixon met with the Joint
                    Chiefs of Staff (JCS) on October 11, and it became clear that the planning had
                    satisfied neither the White House nor the JCS. With American casualties on the
                    decline, the anti-war movement still a powerful force, and no satisfactory
                    political-military solution in sight, Nixon turned away from that option to
                    deliver the “silent majority” speech on November 3, 1969, rallying the American
                    people toward patient support for a protracted war. The administration would
                    continue its dual strategy of Vietnamization and negotiation.</p>
                <p>In March 1970 the fall of Prince <persName>Norodom Sihanouk</persName> in
                    Cambodia destroyed the fragile neutrality of that state, as his successor
                        <persName>Lon Nol</persName> demanded the North Vietnamese withdraw from
                    their base camps along the South Vietnamese border. The North Vietnamese reacted
                    by extending their presence toward the west. Nixon responded by ordering a
                    US-South Vietnamese “incursion” into Cambodia on April 30. Limited by Nixon to a
                    30-kilometer strip along the border, and limited in time to the end of June,
                    this action sparked violent protests on campuses across the United States. These
                    culminated in the deaths of four students at Kent State University on May 4. The
                    incursion into the North Vietnamese Army (NVA) base camps yielded a great
                    quantity of rice, weapons, and ammunition, and disrupted the North Vietnamese
                    command and logistics structures for months, buying time for Vietnamization and
                    further U.S. troop withdrawals. </p>
                <p>The following spring, Nixon ordered a theater-wide offensive, seeking to seize
                    the initiative in the war. South Vietnamese forces crossed into Cambodia and
                    Laos in early February 1971. The North Vietnamese had anticipated the incursion
                    into Laos, known as Lam Son 719, and massed their forces in an attempt to
                    annihilate the South Vietnamese. The South Vietnamese withdrawal disintegrated
                    into a disorderly retreat.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile, Nixon and Kissinger sought to reshape the international context of the
                    war through building relationships with North Vietnam’s superpower allies in
                    Moscow and Beijing. Nixon wanted to create a dilemma for the Soviet and
                    Chinese—give them “bigger fish to fry,” in his phrase—in choosing between their
                    support of North Vietnam, and a closer relationship with the United States. The
                    1972 summits in Beijing and Moscow reflected this strategy, though the Communist
                    powers continued their material support of Hanoi.</p>
                <p>The North Vietnamese opened a three-pronged offensive in South Vietnam, known in
                    the United States as the Easter Offensive, in late March 1972, expecting that a
                    victory on the battlefield would translate into a triumph at the negotiating
                    table. Rather than accept the prospect of defeat, Nixon sent massive air force
                    and naval reinforcements to bases in Indochina and Guam. On May 4 he decided to
                    mine North Vietnam’s harbors and open a sustained air offensive, Operation
                    Linebacker, against North Vietnam. These actions, along with intensive air
                    attacks in the battle areas and improved South Vietnamese defenses, stymied
                    North Vietnam’s offensive, leading the Politburo, for the first time, to engage
                    in serious negotiations.</p>
                <p>On October 11–12 Kissinger and <persName>Le Duc Tho</persName> reached agreement
                    on a peace settlement, both sides working to reach that end before the U.S.
                    presidential election on November 7. President Thieu rejected the settlement,
                    refusing to accept a peace that left North Vietnamese forces in South Vietnam,
                    and legitimized the Hanoi-controlled Communist shadow government, the
                    Provisional Revolutionary Government. His rejection forced Kissinger to resume
                    negotiations with Le Duc Tho. </p>
                <p>Kissinger was unable to find any common ground acceptable to both Vietnamese
                    parties in two renewed rounds of negotiations. Finally, in order to break the
                    deadlock, on December 14 Nixon ordered massive B–52 attacks on the North
                    Vietnamese heartland—the “Christmas Bombing.” Meanwhile he continued to exert
                    intense pressure on Thieu, threatening to cut off U.S. economic, military, and
                    political support of South Vietnam if Thieu refused to accept the agreement.
                    Negotiations resumed on January 8, 1973, and the United States and the
                    Democratic Republic of Vietnam initialed the agreement on January 23. Thieu
                    reluctantly accepted the settlement despite his continued misgivings, and the
                    peace agreement was signed on January 27.</p>
                <p>The peace settlement enabled the United States to withdraw from the war and
                    welcome the American prisoners of war back home. Neither of the Vietnamese
                    parties abided by the settlement, however, and the war continued.</p>
                <p>Nixon had gained Thieu’s adherence to the agreement through a series of letters
                    and envoys, all promising U.S. military support in the event of a North
                    Vietnamese violation of the accords. On November 14, 1972, for example, Nixon
                    wrote Thieu that “I repeat my personal assurances to you that the United States
                    will react very strongly and rapidly to any violation of the agreement.” Both
                    sides understood this to mean the recommitment of B–52s to combat. In the end,
                    these commitments were not upheld due to a combination of factors—domestic and
                    Congressional reluctance to re-engage in the war, economic constraints, and
                    finally the Watergate scandal, which weakened and distracted Nixon. Having
                    rebuilt their forces and upgraded their logistics system, North Vietnamese
                    forces triggered a major offensive in the Central Highlands in March 1975. On
                    April 30, 1975, NVA tanks rolled through the gate of the Presidential Palace in
                    Saigon, effectively ending the war.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="angola" ana="angola cuba ford-gerald">
                <head>The Angola Crisis <date from="1974" to="1975">1974–75</date>
                </head>
                <p>After a successful military coup in Portugal that toppled a long-standing
                    authoritarian regime on April 25, 1974, the new rulers in
                        <placeName>Lisbon</placeName> sought to divest the country of its costly
                    colonial empire. The impending independence of one of those colonies,
                        <placeName>Angola</placeName>, led to the Angolan civil war that grew into a
                    Cold War competition. The Angola crisis of 1974–1975 ultimately contributed to
                    straining relations between the United States and the Soviet Union.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="angola.jpg" height="450px" width="299px"/>
                    <head>Cuban and Angolan soldiers are shown during a weapon practice session at a
                        training center. (AP Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Three main military movements had been fighting for Angolan independence since
                    the 1960s. The Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola (MPLA) was a
                    Marxist organization centered in the capital, Luanda, and led by
                        <persName>Agostinho Neto</persName>. The National Front for the Liberation
                    of Angola (FNLA), led by <persName>Holden Roberto</persName>, was based in the
                    north of the country and had strong ties to the U.S. ally, Mobutu Sese Seko, in
                    neighboring Zaire. The National Union for the Total Independence of Angola
                    (UNITA), an offshoot of the FNLA, was led by Jonas Savimbi and supported by the
                    country’s largest ethnic group, the Ovimbundu. Following the Portuguese coup,
                    these three revolutionaries met with representatives of the new Portuguese
                    Government in January 1975 and signed the Alvor Agreement that granted Angolan
                    independence and provided for a three-way power sharing government. However,
                    trust quickly broke down among the three groups, and the country descended into
                    civil war as each vied for sole power. </p>
                <p>The crisis in Angola developed into a Cold War battleground as the superpowers
                    and their allies delivered military assistance to their preferred clients. The
                    United States supplied aid and training for both the FNLA and UNITA while troops
                    from Zaire assisted Holden Roberto and his fighters. China, also, sent military
                    instructors to train the FNLA. The Soviet Union provided military training and
                    equipment for the MPLA. During the summer of 1975, the Soviet-supported MPLA was
                    able to consolidate power in Luanda and oust the U.S.-supported FNLA from the
                    capital, but the FNLA continued to attack. The remaining Portuguese troops
                    failed to stem the violence. When MPLA leader Neto announced November 11, 1975
                    as the day of Angolan independence, Lisbon decided to withdraw its troops on
                    that day. </p>
                <p>The MPLA also had long-established relations with <persName>Fidel
                        Castro</persName>’s Cuba. Before November 11, the MPLA had negotiated with
                    Castro for Cuban assistance. At the same time, UNITA, which enjoyed U.S.
                    support, approached the Apartheid government in South Africa for military
                    reinforcement. Pretoria, with the aim to end the use of Angola as a base for
                    rebels fighting for the independence of South Africa-occupied Namibia,
                    contributed forces that entered southern Angola in October and made rapid
                    progress toward the capital. In response, Castro sent Cuban Special Forces to
                    halt the South African advance and succeeded in drawing attention to the fact
                    that the United States had provided support to a group that now accepted
                    assistance from an Apartheid government. </p>
                <p>The U.S. Government had encouraged the South African intervention, but preferred
                    to downplay its connection with the Apartheid regime. However, once Pretoria’s
                    involvement became widely known, the Chinese withdrew its advisers from the
                    region, and the Ford Administration was faced with domestic resistance to the
                    U.S. role in the Angolan conflict. President Gerald Ford had requested
                    Congressional approval for more money to fund the operation in Angola. However,
                    many members of Congress were wary of intervening abroad after the struggle in
                    Vietnam, others wished to avoid the South Africa connection, and still others
                    did not believe the issue was important. In the end, Congress rejected the
                    President’s request for additional funds. South Africa withdrew its forces in
                    the spring of 1976 and the MPLA remained as the official government of Angola.
                    Still, Jonas Savimbi and UNITA continued an insurgency until his death in 2002. </p>
                <p>During the period of the Angolan crisis, the United States and the Soviet Union
                    were still enjoying a brief thaw in their relations, in an era referred to as
                        <ref target="/milestones/1969-1976/detente">détente</ref>. During this time,
                    Washington and Moscow had reached a series of agreements that aimed to reduce
                    tensions between the two superpowers. However, by 1974, strains on bilateral
                    relations had already compromised U.S. support for détente and the crisis in
                    Angola served to accelerate this trend. From the U.S. point of view, one of the
                    aims of détente was to draw the Soviet Union further into the international
                    system so that Washington could induce Moscow to show restraint in its dealings
                    with the Third World. The Ford Administration believed that Cuba had intervened
                    in Angola as a Soviet proxy and as such, the general view in Washington was that
                    Moscow was breaking the rules of détente. The appearance of a Soviet success and
                    a U.S. loss in Angola on the heels of a victory by Soviet-supported North
                    Vietnam over U.S.-supported South Vietnam continued to erode U.S. faith in
                    détente as an effective Cold War foreign policy. </p>
                <p>The U.S. failure to achieve its desired outcome in Angola raised the stakes of
                    the superpower competition in the Third World. Subsequent disagreements over the
                    Horn of Africa, and Afghanistan contributed to undoing the period of détente
                    between the Soviet Union and the United States. Additionally, the Angola crisis
                    also ended a recent thaw in U.S.-Cuban relations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="shuttle-diplomacy"
                ana="nixon-richard kissinger-henry-a egypt israel syria peace">
                <head>Shuttle Diplomacy and the Arab-Israeli Dispute, 1974–1975 </head>
                <p>In January and May 1974, Secretary of State <persName>Henry Kissinger</persName>
                    engaged in “shuttle diplomacy,” a term coined by the members of the media who
                    followed Kissinger on his various short flights among Middle East capitals as he
                    sought to deal with the fallout of the October 1973 war. After three weeks of
                    fighting, a ceasefire found Israeli forces entangled with the Egyptian and
                    Syrian forces. This presented President Richard Nixon and Kissinger with an
                    opportunity to play a lead role in disengaging these armies from one another and
                    possibly laying the groundwork for further steps to peacefully resolve the
                    25-year conflict. In January 1974, Kissinger helped negotiate the first
                    Egyptian-Israeli disengagement agreement in eight days, and in May, he arranged
                    a Syrian-Israeli disengagement after a month of intense negotiations.
                    Kissinger’s shuttle diplomacy secured one last deal in September 1975 with the
                    conclusion of a second Egyptian-Israeli disengagement agreement.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="shuttle-diplomacy.jpg" height="450px" width="501px"/>
                    <head>The map of the second disengagement agreement between Egypt and Israel in
                        1975. (Office of the Geographer, U.S. Department of State)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The origins of the first shuttle started with Israel’s proposals for
                    disengagement with the Egyptians on January 4 and 5, 1974. Israel’s proposals
                    demonstrated to Kissinger that the two sides were close enough for him to engage
                    in intensive diplomacy between Jerusalem and Cairo to find a way to negotiate a
                    solution. Nixon, who had become severely distracted by the growing Watergate
                    crisis, encouraged Kissinger to make the trip, but Nixon’s involvement in this
                    negotiation and the ones to follow before his resignation was minimal.</p>
                <p>On January 11, Kissinger arrived in Aswan, Egypt where President <persName>Anwar
                        Sadat</persName> worked during the winter. The negotiations would center
                    around three key items: first, where the forward line of each army would be
                    located; second, the size of the zones where armor was to be limited; and third,
                    the types of armor to be limited in these zones. The Israelis also wanted the
                    Egyptians to reopen the Suez Canal and sought assurances guaranteeing Israeli
                    passage through the Suez Canal, the Straits of Tiran, and Bab el-Madeb.
                    Furthermore, Israel desired Egypt to reconstruct cities along the Suez Canal so
                    as to ensure that the danger to Egyptian civilian populations would deter Egypt
                    from starting another war. Kissinger shuttled between Israel and Egypt for a
                    week, reaching an agreement on January 18. The highlights of the agreement
                    included limited Egyptian and Israeli forces divided by a U.N. buffer zone on
                    the east bank of the Suez Canal. Egypt also agreed to most of the assurances
                    that Israel had requested.</p>
                <p>Following the conclusion of this Egyptian-Israeli disengagement agreement,
                    commonly known as Sinai I, U.S. attention moved to Syria, the other country with
                    armies entangled with Israel’s forces. Kissinger hoped moving on the
                    Syrian-Israeli front would lead the Arab members of the Organization of
                    Petroleum Exporting Countries (OAPEC) to lift the oil embargo they had imposed
                    on the United States in retaliation for American assistance to Israel during the
                    war.</p>
                <p>Unlike the relatively short negotiations that led to the Egyptian-Israeli
                    disengagement agreement, negotiations for a Syrian-Israeli disengagement proved
                    far more arduous and took much longer. By March 18, OPEC lifted the oil embargo,
                    but it would be subject to review on June I. With a need to show progress in
                    negotiations between Israel and Syria before then, Kissinger moved forward in
                    laying the groundwork for another shuttle. Through the end of March and most of
                    April, Kissinger met separately in Washington with Israeli officials and a
                    senior- level Syrian emissary to discuss the groundwork for negotiations.</p>
                <p>By the end of April, Kissinger decided the time was right to begin his second
                    shuttle in the Middle East. On May 1, he left for Jerusalem to begin nearly a
                    month of intense negotiations between the Israelis and Syrians. The negotiation
                    centered on the town of Quneitra in the Golan Heights, three kilometers within
                    the zone Israel had captured during the June 1967 Arab-Israeli War. Since
                    Quneitra did not include any Israeli settlements, the Syrians wanted the town
                    returned as part of any agreement, as well as the territory taken during the
                    October war. After the first week of negotiations, the Syrians and Israelis had
                    shared with Kissinger their views of a line of disengagement. They were close to
                    one another; however, control of Quneitra and three hills that surrounded the
                    town remained the key stumbling block. By mid-May, both sides had agreed to
                    compromises that put their proposals within a few hundred meters of each other,
                    and Israel had assented to a civilian Syrian presence in Quneitra. Despite the
                    progress, neither side would close the gap needed to complete an agreement. On
                    May 16, Kissinger offered an American proposal that sought to find the common
                    ground necessary to reach a compromise. Both sides wanted modifications to this
                    American proposal, however, and negotiations dragged on for another two weeks
                    with Kissinger almost ceasing the negotiations on three separate occasions.
                    Finally, on May 31, Syria and Israel signed a disengagement agreement.</p>
                <p>On August 9, Nixon resigned the presidency, and Vice-President <persName>Gerald
                        Ford</persName> assumed the office while keeping Kissinger on board as both
                    Secretary of State and National Security Adviser. During the fall, much to the
                    U.S. Government’s disappointment, an Arab summit in Rabat, Morocco virtually
                    eliminated any hopes of a Jordanian-Israeli agreement. The Arab representatives
                    announced a resolution on October 28 that recognized the Palestine Liberation
                    Organization (PLO) as the sole representative of the Palestinian people and
                    affirmed its right “to establish an independent national authority over all
                    liberated territory.” Despite previous Jordanian efforts during the year to
                    engage the Israelis in negotiations over the West Bank and Jerusalem, this
                    resolution forced King Hussein to defer to the PLO in future negotiations with
                    Israel over the West Bank and East Jerusalem.</p>
                <p>With Jordan no longer in a position to press the United States for a negotiation
                    with Israel, and Israel unwilling to talk with the PLO, Sadat convinced
                    President Ford and Kissinger that they should spend 1975 pushing for a second
                    agreement between Israel and Egypt over the Sinai. Unlike Sinai I, however,
                    negotiations for this second agreement proved far more challenging and lasted
                    several months. After initial discussions with the Egyptians and Israelis, Ford
                    concluded that the Israelis were not as forthcoming as Egypt, and in March, he
                    called for a reassessment of U.S. policy towards Israel. This sparked an outcry
                    from the U.S. Senate, and Ford backtracked during the early summer. Ultimately,
                    by August, an agreement was within sight, and Kissinger finished the second
                    Egyptian-Israeli disengagement agreement, known as the Sinai Interim Agreement
                    or Sinai II, which Egypt and Israel signed on September 4. This agreement led to
                    the withdrawal of Israeli forces further east in the Sinai and a U.N. buffer
                    zone put in the place of the Israelis. The agreement also committed major U.S.
                    resources through the establishment of three manned stations and three unmanned
                    electronic sensor fields in the Sinai.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="helsinki"
                ana="russia conference-on-security-and-cooperation-in-europe">
                <head>Helsinki Final Act, <date when="1975">1975</date>
                </head>
                <p>The Helsinki Final Act was an agreement signed by 35 nations that concluded the
                    Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe, held in <placeName>Helsinki,
                        Finland</placeName>. The multifaceted Act addressed a range of prominent
                    global issues and in so doing had a far-reaching effect on the Cold War and
                    U.S.-Soviet relations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="helsinki.jpg" height="450px" width="344px"/>
                    <head>President Ford adresses the European Security Conference in Helsinki. (AP
                        Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Helsinki Conference had its origins in early Cold War discussions. The Soviet
                    Union first sought a European conference on security issues in 1954 at the
                    Geneva Conference in the hopes that such a meeting would result in formal
                    recognition of the political boundaries in Eastern Europe that had been
                    established after World War II. At that time, the United States and the other
                    Western nations were reluctant to engage in such a discussion because they
                    feared that it might strengthen the Soviet position and lead to an expansion of
                    communism. As a result, no progress was made through the 1950s and 1960s. </p>
                <p>However, the shift towards détente during the early 1970s encouraged Western
                    leaders to reconsider the negotiations. Discussions started with the Helsinki
                    Consultations in 1972 and continued until the opening of the formal Conference
                    on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE) in July of 1973. From the summer of
                    1973 to the summer of 1975, intensive negotiations continued in Geneva, until
                    the participants finally met again in Helsinki on August 1, 1975 to sign the
                    Helsinki Final Act. Every European country except Albania signed the Act, in
                    addition to the United States and Canada.</p>
                <p>The Helsinki Final Act dealt with a variety of issues divided into four
                    “baskets.” The first basket included ten principles covering political and
                    military issues, territorial integrity, the definition of borders, peaceful
                    settlement of disputes and the implementation of confidence building measures
                    between opposing militaries. The second basket focused on economic issues like
                    trade and scientific cooperation. The third basket emphasized human rights,
                    including freedom of emigration and reunification of families divided by
                    international borders, cultural exchanges and freedom of the press. Finally, the
                    fourth basket formalized the details for follow-up meetings and implementation
                    procedures. The CSCE held further meetings in Belgrade in 1977–78, Madrid in
                    1980–83, and Vienna in 1986–89.</p>
                <p>Although initially unpopular in the West, the Helsinki Final Act proved important
                    at the end of the Cold War. Some activists opposed the Western concession on
                    boundaries that resulted in a formal acceptance of the Soviet annexation of
                    Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania, effectively acknowledging Soviet domination of
                    Eastern Europe. In spite of such criticism, the third basket on human rights and
                    freedoms ultimately proved to be important to dissidents in Eastern Europe and
                    the Soviet Union. To follow the progress of the USSR in implementing the human
                    rights stipulations established in the Act, human rights activists set up
                    Helsinki Monitoring Groups in the Soviet Union and across Europe. These groups
                    tracked violations of the Act and drew international attention to human rights
                    violations. Furthermore, the Belgrade follow-up meeting introduced a review
                    process to track violators of the Helsinki Final Act and hold them accountable.
                    Together these measures enabled dissidents to act and speak more openly than
                    would otherwise have been possible.</p>
                <p>The Helsinki Process, including the review meetings, led to greater cooperation
                    between Eastern and Western Europe. Representatives from non-aligned countries
                    acted as intermediaries, helping to broker deals between members of the <ref
                        target="/milestones/1945-1952/nato">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</ref>
                    and the <ref target="/milestones/1953-1960/warsaw-treaty">Warsaw Pact</ref>. The
                    Vienna Review Meeting introduced recognition of the rights of emigration and
                    religious freedom, which helped to open ties between Eastern and Western Europe.
                    In addition, the Vienna meetings launched a new series of CSCE conferences on
                    the Human Dimension that took place concurrently with, and contributed to,
                    widespread political and social changes in Europe. These shifts helped bring an
                    end to Soviet dominance in Eastern Europe and the end of the Cold War.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
