<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1977–1980</title>
                <title type="short">1977–1980</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#foreword #horn-of-africa #central-america-carter #human-rights #us-western-europe #non-proliferation #china-policy #camp-david #panama-canal #soviet-invasion-afghanistan"
                />
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword"
                ana="johnson-lyndon-b nixon-richard carter-jimmy reagan-ronald bush-george-h-w kissinger-henry-a vance-cyrus-roberts muskie-edmund-sixtus china russia egypt iran israel afghanistan panama arms-control-and-disarmament human-rights">
                <head>1977–1981: The Presidency of Jimmy Carter</head>
                <p>President <persName>Jimmy Carter</persName> took office in January 1977 as a
                    Washington outsider, pledging to restore a sense a morality to both domestic and
                    foreign policy following the traumas of the Vietnam War and Watergate. Morality,
                    he believed, existed as the best foundation for exerting U.S. power and
                    influence. Carter envisioned that his foreign policy, “derived from a longer
                    view of global change,” would move the United States away from operating within
                    a bipolar or tripolar context to one taking into account an increasingly
                    complicated and interdependent world. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="carter-admin.jpg" height="450px" width="303px"/>
                    <head>Carter and Brzezinski, April 19, 1977. (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although the former Governor of Georgia had limited foreign policy experience,
                    Carter had engaged in international trade issues and had been invited to join
                    the Trilateral Commission, a consortium of business executives, government
                    officials, and academics from North America, Japan, and Europe. These activities
                    broadened his understanding of global issues and brought him into contact with
                    individuals who had spent much of their careers in Washington, including
                        <persName>Zbigniew Brzezinski</persName> and <persName>Cyrus
                        Vance</persName>, both of whom had served in various capacities during the
                    Lyndon B. Johnson administration. Carter relied on Brzezinski and Vance to
                    advise him during the 1976 presidential campaign and offered them the positions
                    of National Security Adviser and Secretary of State, respectively, after he won
                    election in November 1976. Carter’s foreign policy team also included former
                    Senator Walter F. Mondale (DFL-Minnesota), whom Carter would select as his vice
                    presidential running mate and former California Institute of Technology
                    President Harold Brown, whom Carter would nominate for Secretary of Defense.
                    These principals, later including Secretary of State <persName>Edmund
                        Muskie</persName>, established a collegial working relationship,
                    characterized by their weekly foreign policy breakfasts. Vance, Brzezinski, and
                    Brown also met weekly for an informal V–B–B luncheon to discuss decisions that
                    did not rise to the level of a formal interagency meeting. Although Vance and
                    Brzezinski respected one another, they differed over the administration’s
                    approach to certain issues, notably relations with the Soviet Union. This
                    tension became more pronounced and visible by the midpoint of the
                    administration.</p>
                <p>Carter’s management of foreign policy reflected his preference for simplifying
                    the structures established by his predecessors. In two Presidential Directives
                    issued on January 20, 1977, Carter stated the direction of the work of the
                    National Security Council and participating agencies and the reorganization of
                    the National Security Council. PD/NSC–1 established both the Presidential Review
                    Memorandum, designed to structure the reviews and analyses of foreign policy
                    issues undertaken by agencies, and the Presidential Directive, the statement of
                    presidential decisions on national security matters. PD/NSC–2 reaffirmed the
                    functions, membership, and responsibilities of the National Security Council, as
                    set out in the National Security Act of 1947 and also created the NSC Policy
                    Review Committee (PRC) and the NSC Special Coordination Committee (SCC). The
                    Policy Review Committee formulated policy for presidential decision on cases
                    where responsibilities fell within a particular agency but had implications for
                    other departments or agencies. Issues such as defense or international economic
                    policy fell within the scope of the PRC; Brzezinski had the latitude to choose a
                    particular PRC chair based on the subject matter under consideration. The
                    Special Coordination Committee dealt with the coordination and implementation of
                    foreign policy related to specific issues such as arms control, intelligence,
                    and crisis management; Brzezinski chaired the SCC. Carter also retained the
                    flexibility of appointing NSC ad hoc groups to advise him on issues
                    “transcending” departmental boundaries. Within the National Security Council,
                    Brzezinski trimmed the staff and reorganized it along geographical and
                    functional “clusters,” including ones for global issues, international
                    economics, defense coordination, intelligence coordination, and science. </p>
                <p>During the 1976 presidential campaign, Carter articulated many of the
                    philosophical roots of his foreign policy. His approach emphasized the
                    maintenance of peace, the pursuit of human rights, the achievement of nuclear
                    non-proliferation, the necessity of international cooperation, and a focus on
                    the developing world rather than on East-West concerns. In defining this policy,
                    Carter admitted that the United States did not alone possess the answers to the
                    world’s problems. It should not impose unilateral solutions, although it could
                    take the lead in advancing policies designed to create a “just and stable”
                    international order. In doing so, the United States would maintain its strategic
                    interests.</p>
                <p>Carter enjoyed some early successes in pursuit of his foreign policy objectives.
                    He devoted energy and skill in negotiating and concluding, in 1977 and 1978, two
                    agreements with Panama over the Panama Canal that allowed for joint operations
                    and Panamanian sole control of the Canal by 1999, permanent neutrality and the
                    U.S. right to defend the Canal. Carter also mediated framework discussions
                    between Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin and Egyptian President Anwar Sadat
                    in September 1978, resulting in a formal peace agreement between Egypt and
                    Israel in 1979. Carter elevated and institutionalized human rights as a
                    component of foreign-policy decision making and brought increased attention to
                    global human rights abuses. The administration also completed the normalization
                    of relations with China in 1979, initiated during the Nixon administration. In
                    pursuit of global economic cooperation, Carter promoted multilateral efforts
                    such as an expanded and equitable trading system, food reserves, and an
                    international health program.</p>
                <p>Regardless of Carter’s desire to substitute world order politics for a bipolar
                    foreign policy, he and his advisers had to engage with the Soviet leadership on
                    a number of crucial issues. Although Carter supported détente, he rejected the
                    Nixon-Kissinger concept of “linkage,” believing that he could speak out against
                    human rights abuses in the Soviet Union, while negotiating arms reductions with
                    Soviet General Secretary <persName>Leonid Brezhnev</persName>. Although Carter
                    and Brezhnev, in 1979, signed the SALT II Treaty, which limited the total of
                    both nations’ nuclear forces and placed other restrictions on strategic nuclear
                    forces, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in December 1979 forced Carter to
                    delay Senate consideration of the treaty. Ultimately, the Senate failed to
                    ratify SALT II.</p>
                <p>The Soviet invasion of Afghanistan took place a month after Iranian militants
                    stormed the U.S. Embassy in Tehran and took Americans hostage. In addition to
                    these crises, Carter faced a mounting series of domestic economic problems,
                    including increases in gasoline prices, rising inflation, and rising
                    unemployment. Carter responded to the Soviet invasion by embargoing grain sales,
                    banning technology exports, and prohibiting U.S. participation in the upcoming
                    1980 Moscow Summer Olympics. He also used his January 1980 State of the Union
                    address to issue a warning that if outside forces interfered in the Persian
                    Gulf, the United States would respond, reserving the right to use military
                    force. This harder stance could not overcome public disillusionment with the
                    Carter administration, made worse by the administration’s inability to secure
                    the release of the hostages. Republican presidential candidate <persName>Ronald
                        Reagan</persName> and his vice presidential running mate <persName>George
                        H.W. Bush</persName> capitalized upon this dissatisfaction and, in November
                    1980, defeated Carter and Mondale.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="horn-of-africa"
                ana="carter-jimmy vance-cyrus-roberts ethiopia somalia russia afghanistan cuba">
                <head>“Buried in the Sands of the Ogaden”: The Horn of Africa and SALT II,
                    1977–1979</head>
                <p>In the summer of 1977, Somalia, a poverty -stricken country in the Horn of
                    Africa, invaded its equally poor neighbor, Ethiopia, in hopes of conquering the
                    Ogaden Desert region, which was populated by ethnic Somalis. What began as a
                    local conflict in a far-flung region of the world grew into a Cold War hotspot
                    as the United States and the Soviet Union took sides.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ogaden.jpg" height="450px" width="433px"/>
                    <head>Map of the Ogaden region. (Central Intelligence Agency)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States had supported the long-ruling Emperor Haile Selassie in
                    Ethiopia. The Emperor enjoyed great status as an international statesman, but
                    ultimately failed to deliver basic services to his impoverished people. Several
                    famines in the 1960s and early 1970s finally brought about a revolution in 1973
                    that upended the formerly feudal societal structure. The revolution was
                    originally led by urbanites such as laborers, students, and taxi drivers, but
                    soon a group of mid-level Army officers filled the leadership void and
                    eventually arrested and deposed Haile Selassie in September 1974. The
                    ideological direction of the revolution was not clear at first, and the United
                    States attempted to maintain relations with the new leadership. However, after
                    Mengistu Haile Miriam had his rivals killed and became the dominant leader of
                    Ethiopia, the revolution took a communist turn, and he reached out to the Soviet
                    Union to replace U.S. military aid. The Soviet Union agreed to fund its new ally
                    and hoped that Ethiopia and Somalia could form a communist federation.</p>
                <p>In Somalia, Mohammed Siad Barre had seized power in a coup in 1969 and had
                    declared Somalia a socialist republic. The Soviet Union and Somalia had then
                    signed a Treaty of Friendship and Cooperation in 1974. However, Siad Barre had
                    designs on the Ogaden region of Ethiopia and resented the growing closeness
                    between Ethiopia and the Soviet Union. In response, the Somali dictator reached
                    out to the United States in hopes of securing military aid and eventually
                    expelled the Soviets from the country. The Soviets chose to support Addis Ababa,
                    keeping the bigger prize in the zero sum game of the Cold War. The United States
                    was actively considering aid to Mogadishu when Somalia invaded Ethiopia,
                    completing the total flip in the alliances.</p>
                <p>Siad Barre wanted to take advantage of Ethiopia’s fragmented society when he
                    invaded. The leadership in Addis Ababa faced a long-running rebellion in Eritrea
                    as well as insurgency by the ethnic Somalis in the Ogaden and Mengistu was still
                    focused on consolidating his own power. Somalia, therefore, had the upper hand
                    in the early phase of the war and advanced toward the major Ethiopian cities in
                    the region. However, the Soviet Union began a massive airlift that autumn of
                    Soviet military advisors and supplies, and also Cuban troops to aid the
                    beleaguered Marxist regime, turning the tide of the war.</p>
                <p>The United States was alarmed at such a large scale Soviet and Cuban intervention
                    in Africa. Since this occurred on the heels of the communist countries’
                    involvement in Angola, the administration of President Jimmy Carter feared that
                    a pattern was emerging. The conflict in the Horn and the Soviet intervention
                    also occurred in an era of détente between the United States and the Soviet
                    Union. Détente was a series of agreements between the two superpowers that were
                    meant to reduce tensions. For Moscow, détente represented a chance to be
                    recognized as an equal power to Washington. Washington, on the other hand, saw
                    détente as a way to draw the Soviet Union further into the international system
                    and exercise some influence over Soviet behavior in the Third World. The United
                    States, therefore, used the Horn of Africa conflict as a test case for its
                    understanding of détente.</p>
                <p>The members of the Carter administration’s National Security Council (NSC)
                    disagreed on an appropriate response to the Soviet intervention and they divided
                    into two main camps. In particular, Carter’s National Security Advisor, Zbigniew
                    Brzezinski, argued that the United States needed a bold response and that the
                    administration could not let the Soviets get away with intervention in the Horn
                    or else they would become emboldened elsewhere in Africa. Another faction of the
                    NSC, led by Secretary of State Cyrus Vance, argued that the Soviets were just
                    taking advantage of an opportunity and a hard stance against the Soviets
                    vis-à-vis their Africa policy would jeopardize progress on more important
                    bilateral relations.</p>
                <p>While Vance won the initial arguments and the United States refrained from
                    sending a carrier task force to the region as Brzezinski proposed, members of
                    the administration continued to raise their concerns with their Soviet
                    counterparts. Brzezinski and later Carter himself began to speculate publicly
                    that the Soviet behavior in the Horn of Africa was undermining Congressional
                    willingness to ratify a new agreement on the Strategic Arms Limitation Talks
                    (SALT), the lynchpin of détente. Vance, on the other hand, feared that
                    Brzezinski’s rhetoric was what was causing members of Congress to link the two
                    issues. The Soviets could not understand why the United States attached such
                    importance to their intervention in the Horn and made no attempt to come to an
                    understanding on the issue.</p>
                <p>The Horn of Africa crisis turned out to be the first in a series of disagreements
                    between the superpowers over the Third World that occurred during the Carter
                    years. Events on the Horn were followed by problems in Zaire, Yemen, Cuba and
                    finally, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in December 1979. After the
                    invasion, President Carter withdrew the SALT II treaty from Congressional
                    consideration, leading Brzezinski to claim that “SALT lies buried in the sands
                    of the Ogaden.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="central-america-carter"
                ana="carter-jimmy vance-cyrus-roberts costa-rica el-salvador nicaragua human-rights organization-of-american-states diplomatic-recognition">
                <head>Central America, 1977–1980</head>
                <p>The Carter administration’s preferred policy toward Latin America—stressing human
                    rights and non-interventionism—was severely tested by events in Central America.
                    In July 1979 the revolutionary Sandinista movement prevailed over Nicaraguan
                    President Anastasio Somoza who had been a close U.S. ally. Facing the possible
                    threat of a Marxist tide sweeping through the region, the Carter White House
                    undertook multiple initiatives to moderate the revolution in Nicaragua.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="carter-central-america.jpg" height="350px" width="519px"/>
                    <head>A statue of Anastasio Somoza is pulled from its base by Sandinista
                        guerrillas on July 10, 1979. (AP Photo)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In a series of speeches in 1977 President Jimmy Carter outlined his vision of a
                    foreign policy based on protecting human rights, pledged to end the tradition of
                    U.S. interventionism in Latin America, and offered to support the development of
                    democracy through multilateral cooperation. Widespread poverty, a growing reform
                    movement, and a corrupt and violent military dictatorship made Nicaragua a clear
                    focus for Carter’s new approach. Somoza controlled Nicaragua’s politics,
                    military, and much of its economy. Following his brother Luis Somoza’s direct
                    and indirect rule of the country from 1956 to 1966, Somoza re-established a
                    military dictatorship in the mold of his father Anastasio Somoza García’s
                    two-decades of control from 1936 to 1956. Public outcry over Somoza’s abuses
                    exploded after a devastating earthquake hit the capital city of Managua in 1972
                    and Somoza’s businesses, political cronies, and military subordinates embezzled
                    most of the international relief donations.</p>
                <p>The geo-politics of the Cold War transformed Carter’s policies toward Nicaragua
                    from what might have been straightforward support for democratic reform to a
                    torturous balancing act. While the middle-class, the business community, and the
                    local Catholic leadership became increasingly critical of Somoza in the
                    mid-1970s, a committed group of revolutionaries had already been fighting for
                    decades to overthrow him. Inspired by the 1959 Cuban revolution and advised by
                    the new Cuban leader Fidel Castro, Nicaraguan revolutionaries joined efforts to
                    found the Sandinista National Liberation Front (FSLN). The name honored Augusto
                    Sandino, who had fought against the U.S. Marines in the 1920s and opposed the
                    creation of the Nicaraguan National Guard. In fact the Guard, headed by Somoza’s
                    father, executed Sandino despite a surrender agreement in 1934. The Sandinista
                    guerrillas had limited influence, but the growing public opposition to the
                    Somoza regime in the later 1970s presented the opportunity for a breakthrough.
                    Carter criticized Somoza’s abuses but carefully avoided any encouragement of the
                    FSLN because of its Cuban ties and the Marxist orientation of its leaders. The
                    assassination of Pedro Joaquín Chamorro, the publisher of the opposition
                    newspaper <hi rend="italic">La Prensa</hi>, in January 1978 served as a catalyst
                    for civil war. Though Somoza’s role in the crime was unproven, major
                    demonstrations erupted. In August 1978, Sandinista guerrillas captured the
                    National Palace and exchanged several hundred hostages for the release of
                    prisoners, money, and safe passage out of country. The moderate opposition
                    organized a general strike and in September 1978 the Sandinistas launched a
                    series of coordinated attacks in major cities.</p>
                <p>Carter sought solutions that would cool the boiling forces of revolution in
                    Nicaragua and establish a path to democratic transition. The 17th Meeting of
                    Consultation of Ministers of Foreign Affairs of the Organization of American
                    States (OAS) agreed to a U.S. proposal for a political mediation in Nicaragua.
                    Somoza and the moderate opposition accepted the mediation proposal and an
                    International Commission of Friendly Cooperation and Conciliation, comprised of
                    representatives of the Dominican Republic, Guatemala, and the United States,
                    arrived in October 1978. William G. Bowdler, the U.S. representative, was
                    ultimately unable to convince Somoza to join with the moderates in a transition
                    to free elections. Carter next opted to explore the possibility of a plebiscite
                    on Somoza’s rule. In January 1979, Somoza rejected the idea of international
                    supervision of a plebiscite vote and the mediation effort ended. That February,
                    Carter terminated military assistance to the National Guard and asked that other
                    countries cease assistance to the Sandinistas.</p>
                <p>Events in Nicaragua soon outpaced Carter’s efforts to shape them. The Sandinista
                    leadership joined with selected representatives from the moderate opposition to
                    form a Provisional Government (PG), established in Costa Rica on June 16. On
                    June 21, Secretary of State Cyrus Vance called for the replacement of Somoza
                    with a broadly based transition government of national reconciliation, the
                    negotiation of a cease-fire, humanitarian aid, and an OAS peacekeeping force.
                    Two days later the OAS passed a resolution calling for the replacement of the
                    Somoza regime. In Managua, Ambassador Lawrence Pezzullo pushed for an elaborate
                    plan under which Somoza would resign and the Nicaraguan Congress would elect an
                    interim successor. The successor would appoint a new head of the National Guard,
                    call for a cease-fire, negotiate the gradual merger of the National Guard with
                    FSLN forces, and finally transfer power to the PG within 72 hours. Following the
                    script, Pezzullo informed Somoza on July 12 that his departure would minimize
                    bloodshed and help to salvage the National Guard. Somoza departed for the United
                    States on July 17. The Nicaraguan Congress then elected Francisco Urcuyo.
                    Pezzullo’s plan collapsed when Urcuyo announced his intention to remain in power
                    until the end of Somoza’s presidential term in 1981 and obstructed the
                    cease-fire negotiations. On July 18 Pezzullo departed, the National Guard
                    evaporated, and the PG declared itself the legitimate government of Nicaragua.
                    Sandinista forces entered Managua on July 19 and oversaw the installment of the
                    PG, renamed the Government of National Reconstruction (GNR), the next day. </p>
                <p>Still aiming for influence, President Carter met with members of the GNR in the
                    White House in September 1979 and encouraged moderation and respect for
                    democratic values and human rights. That November, Carter asked Congress for $80
                    million in new supplemental aid funds ($75 million for Nicaragua and $5 million
                    for other Central American states), in addition to the $50 to $70 million of
                    fiscal year 1980 funds that he requested be reprogrammed for Nicaragua. A heated
                    and lengthy congressional debate ended in May 1980 with an act authorizing $80
                    million in assistance to Central America for fiscal year 1980. The act required
                    reports every six months from the Secretary of State on the status of human
                    rights in Nicaragua and stipulated that the aid would be terminated if foreign
                    forces in Nicaragua threatened the security of the United States or any of its
                    Latin American allies.</p>
                <p>The Nicaraguan revolution threatened to worsen an already unstable and violent
                    situation in neighboring El Salvador. Autocratic military governments had
                    prevailed in disputed elections in 1972 and 1977, and by 1979 the President,
                    retired General Carlos Humberto Romero, had increased the repression against the
                    leftist opposition. Convinced that Romero’s rejection of reform strengthened the
                    prospects for revolution and the destruction of their institution, as had
                    transpired in Nicaragua, a group of young military officers overthrew Romero in
                    October 1979. The group established a five-man civilian military junta that was
                    committed to reform and free elections but faced a violent landscape with
                    frequent attacks by both left and right wing terror groups. The United States
                    recognized the new government and provided security assistance and advisers, but
                    the junta collapsed in January 1980 when the civilian members resigned after the
                    junta failed to stem violence by the military and right wing groups. The
                    Christian Democrats, the major reformist political party led by Jose Napoleon
                    Duarte, joined with the military in a new junta government. By March 1980, with
                    Duarte assuming a leadership role, the new junta undertook wide-ranging agrarian
                    and financial reform and received increased U.S. security and economic
                    assistance. Yet, the violence spiked with the murder of the archbishop of San
                    Salvador, Oscar Romero, who had lamented the abuses of the military and
                    criticized U.S. military aid to El Salvador. In December 1980, the abduction and
                    murder of four U.S. churchwomen in El Salvador convinced President Carter to
                    suspended assistance to the country. A Presidential mission sent by Carter to
                    investigate the crime found complicity of the Salvadoran security forces either
                    in the crime or in evading the investigation. In January 1981 guerrillas of the
                    leftist Farabundo Martí National Liberation Front (FMLN), named to honor the
                    executed communist leader of the 1932 peasant uprising, launched a major
                    offensive. The United States responded by providing military aid to the junta,
                    citing progress in the investigation of the murders of the churchwomen and
                    concern about external support for the guerrillas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="human-rights"
                ana="ford-gerald carter-jimmy vance-cyrus-roberts foreign-aid human-rights">
                <head>Carter and Human Rights, 1977–1981</head>
                <p>
                    <persName>Jimmy Carter</persName> campaigned for the presidency in 1976
                    promising substantial changes in the conduct of U.S. foreign policy. He intended
                    to infuse a new morality in American diplomacy, one grounded in the pursuit of
                    human rights.Carter made this cause explicit in his January 20, 1977, inaugural
                    address: “Because we are free, we can never be indifferent to the fate of
                    freedom elsewhere. Our moral sense dictates a clear-cut preference for those
                    societies which share with us an abiding respect for individual human rights.”
                    The Carter administration thus articulated, devised, and implemented a human
                    rights strategy that would serve as the cornerstone of Carter’s foreign
                    policy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="human-rights.jpg" height="450px" width="298px"/>
                    <head>Carter address delivered before the U.N. General Assembly, October 4,
                        1977. (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Criticism of human rights abuses in other nations served as an early indication
                    that Carter’s inaugural address marked an ideological shift in U.S. foreign
                    policy. During the early weeks of the administration, officials spoke out
                    against harassment and human rights violations in Czechoslovakia, the Soviet
                    Union, and Uganda.When asked at a January 31, 1977, press conference if the
                    administration would continue to address specific human rights issues or exert
                    quiet diplomatic pressure, Secretary of State <persName>Cyrus Vance</persName>
                    explained that the United States “will speak frankly about injustice, both at
                    home and abroad,” while avoiding strident and polemical language. Vance
                    cautioned, though, that the administration would not “comment on each and every
                    issue” but would comment “when we see a threat to human rights” and when it was
                    “constructive to do so.” The administration also linked human rights concerns
                    directly to the conduct of foreign policy, including support for a bill halting
                    importation of Rhodesian chrome and the reduction of foreign aid to other
                    nations that did not display sufficient respect for human rights.</p>
                <p>Carter further defined these efforts in a series of public addresses delivered in
                    early 1977. These speeches also afforded Carter the opportunity to explain why
                    and how his administration promoted human rights. Speaking before the United
                    Nations General Assembly on March 17, 1977, the President asserted that the
                    United States had a “historical birthright” to be associated with human rights.
                    While the United States had not always lived up to this ideal, Carter identified
                    several steps to rectify U.S. shortcomings “quickly and openly,” including the
                    liberalization of travel policies and the signing and ratification of
                    international human rights covenants. In his May 22, 1977, commencement address,
                    delivered at Notre Dame University, Carter drew a distinction between his policy
                    and the policies of his predecessors, noting that they had pursued the “flawed
                    and erroneous principles and tactics of our adversaries.” As a result, the
                    United States had moved away from its core values. The interdependent world of
                    the 1970s required a “new American foreign policy” grounded in cardinal
                    principles, including the “commitment to human rights as a fundamental tenet of
                    our foreign policy.” The Notre Dame address served as a comprehensive statement
                    and justification of Carter’s human rights policy.</p>
                <p>Vance refined the policy in an April 30, 1977, address at the University of
                    Georgia Law School. He promoted adherence to three human rights categories—the
                    right to be free from government violation of the integrity of the person; the
                    right to fulfill vital needs such as food, shelter, and education; and civil and
                    political rights. Vance explained flexibility characterized implementation of
                    policy, depending on the details of particular cases. The United States had to
                    accept limits in pursuing human rights; a rigid approach to imposing U.S. values
                    on other nations would not allow the United States to achieve its objectives in
                    this area.</p>
                <p>These public declarations coincided with and guided the administration’s effort
                    to translate Carter’s commitment into a broader strategy. In May 1977, the
                    administration issued Presidential Review Memorandum/NSC 28, which directed a
                    review of U.S. human rights policy in order to define policy objectives,
                    evaluate actions designed to improve rights, review national security
                    considerations, and propose implementing actions. The completed PRM/NSC 28
                    study’s recommendations formed the basis for Presidential Directive 30, issued
                    in February 1978. Noting that a major objective of U.S. foreign policy should be
                    the observance of global human rights, Presidential Directive 30 outlined
                    specific guidelines for U.S. human rights policy and indicated the types of
                    rights the United States would protect. The United States would use “the full
                    range of diplomatic tools,” including public statements, consultations with
                    allies, and cooperation with non-governmental actors and international
                    organizations. The directive linked economic and military assistance to the
                    human rights records of the recipients; countries with good or improving records
                    would receive favorable consideration, while those nations with poor or
                    deteriorating records would not. Presidential Directive 30 thus formally defined
                    U.S. policy on human rights.</p>
                <p>Implementing the administration’s human rights strategy required the Department
                    of State to modify existing institutional structures. Legislation enacted during
                    the Gerald R. Ford administration created the position of Coordinator for Human
                    Rights and Humanitarian Affairs, located within the Deputy Secretary of State’s
                    office. The Office of Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs also included a
                    Deputy Coordinator for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs and coordinators
                    for Refugee and Migration Affairs and POW/MIA Affairs.Carter selected Patricia
                    Murphy Derian, a civil rights activist, to serve as Coordinator, upon the
                    retirement of Coordinator James Wilson. By the end of 1977, the Department of
                    State established the Bureau of Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs and
                    elevated Derian to Assistant Secretary for Human Rights and Humanitarian
                    Affairs. Foreign Service officers with regional and topical expertise staffed
                    the Bureau, which, over time, added additional offices for country reports,
                    asylum, and refugee and migration affairs. Managing the human rights country
                    reports process existed as one of the main responsibilities of the Bureau of
                    Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs. These reports on the status of human
                    rights practices were initially limited to countries receiving security and
                    economic assistance but later extended to apply to all countries. The Department
                    of State released the annual reports to the public, and Derian testified before
                    Congress concerning the administration’s views of the human rights record of
                    particular countries.</p>
                <p>Managing human rights policy also required the administration to establish new
                    coordinating and evaluation mechanisms. To ensure that all bureaus engaged on
                    human rights issues, Vance tasked Deputy Secretary of State Warren Christopher
                    with creating a Human Rights Coordinating Group (HRCG), consisting of Department
                    of State officials at the deputy assistant secretary level, to serve as an
                    “internal mechanism” for decision-making. Recognizing that the United States
                    could not examine economic and security assistance decisions in a vacuum,
                    Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs <persName>Zbigniew
                        Brzezinski</persName> directed Vance and Secretary of the Treasury
                        <persName>W. Michael Blumenthal</persName> to establish a group—the
                    Interagency Working Group on Human Rights and Foreign Assistance—to evaluate, on
                    a case-by-case basis, bilateral and multilateral aid decisions as they related
                    to human rights and to provide guidance to ensure a unified government position
                    on aid decisions. Brzezinski had also established within the National Security
                    Council (NSC) a Global Issues Cluster responsible for overseeing issues such as
                    human rights and arms control.</p>
                <p>The Carter administration raised greater awareness of human rights concerns by
                    connecting human rights to the execution of U.S. foreign policy. During 1977 and
                    1978 the administration articulated the policy in various public statements,
                    devised guidelines for its application, strengthened existing structures for
                    managing human rights, and created new institutional arrangements for applying
                    human rights considerations to economic and military aid. These efforts
                    continued to influence the administration’s pursuit of human rights, even as the
                    foreign policy crises of 1979 and 1980 required more of Carter’s attention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="us-western-europe"
                ana="carter-jimmy belgium france germany italy luxembourg malta netherlands portugal spain united-kingdom iran afghanistan arms-control-and-disarmament human-rights north-atlantic-treaty-organization united-nations terrorism">
                <head>Political and Security Relations between the United States and Western Europe,
                    1977–1981 </head>
                <p>Relations between the United States and Western Europe were mixed during the
                    presidency of Jimmy Carter. Western European capitals greeted the November 1976
                    election of President Carter with optimism, but tensions soon developed between
                    Washington and Western Europe over how to best manage relations with the Soviet
                    Union. Opposition on the part of the European public to European political
                    leadership’s approach on how to deal with this issue also complicated matters.
                    Nevertheless, changes in the political landscape of Western Europe provided
                    opportunities for improved cooperation and understanding between the United
                    States and Europe. Washington learned to live with Eurocommunism, nurtured
                    closer ties to new democracies in southern Europe, and worked more closely with
                    its European partners on counterterrorism measures. Despite these positive
                    developments, conflicting ideas over how to address the 1979 U.S. hostage crisis
                    in Tehran and the Soviet intervention in Afghanistan negatively impacted the
                    U.S.-Western Europe partnership. When Carter left the White House in 1981, U.S.
                    relations with Western Europe remained close yet strained.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="western-europe.jpg" height="450px" width="302px"/>
                    <head>Jimmy Carter and leaders of Western Europe Helmut Schmidt, Valery Giscard
                        d’Estaing, and James Callaghan pose while meeting in Guadeloupe, January
                        1979. (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Many European government officials and members of the public supported the policy
                    of détente undertaken by the administrations of Presidents Richard M. Nixon and
                    Gerald R. Ford as a pragmatic approach to reducing the Soviet threat. The Carter
                    administration’s renewed attention to human rights violations in the Soviet
                    Union and Eastern Europe, along with its opposition to Soviet interventions in
                    the Third World, triggered anxieties in countries such as West Germany that
                    détente might be undermined.</p>
                <p>Regional security issues played a major role in the U.S.-Western Europe
                    relationship during this period. Despite arms control agreements such as
                    Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) I, the Soviet Union continued to expand
                    its conventional forces; in 1977, the Soviet Union began to deploy new
                    intermediate-range ballistic missiles (IRBMs) in Eastern Europe. Many Western
                    Europeans looked to the United States to lead efforts to respond to the
                    continued Soviet military build-up.</p>
                <p>Starting in the summer of 1977, the subject of enhanced radiation weapons (ERWs)
                    created new tensions between Washington and Western European nations. Often
                    referred to as neutron bombs, ERWs were designed to cause a greater share of
                    casualties from radiation rather than explosive force. In June 1977, when the
                    U.S. press reported that the United States would develop ERWs, public reaction
                    was largely negative, particularly in Europe. Some decried the neutron bomb as
                    the “perfect” capitalist weapon that would limit damage to buildings but could
                    expose civilians to greater danger. Many European political leaders supported
                    deployment of the neutron bombs and invested intense effort to convince their
                    citizens of the weapon’s necessity. However, in April 1978 President Carter
                    decided to defer production of ERWs. Carter’s decision frustrated European
                    leaders who had spent political capital to support the deployment of a weapons
                    system that would not be produced.</p>
                <p>While the United States negotiated bilaterally with the Soviet Union on the SALT
                    II agreement, the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) countries sought to
                    counter the IRBM threat to Western Europe. In December 1979, NATO approved a
                    “dual-track” response: deploying Pershing II and cruise missiles while
                    simultaneously seeking to negotiate reductions in theatre nuclear forces with
                    the Soviet Union. The planned missile deployment was a contentious issue in some
                    capitals. European public opinion trends showed resistance to the stationing of
                    new missiles on Western European soil motivated by concerns that it would make
                    Western Europe more vulnerable to Soviet attacks. Despite public resistance,
                    West Germany and Italy approved deployment of the missiles on their territories
                    without conditions. Other governments, such as Belgium and the Netherlands,
                    hesitated or initially resisted the move, which put pressure on their bilateral
                    relationships with Washington.</p>
                <p>The changing political landscape in Western Europe also had a significant impact
                    on U.S.-Western European relations during this time. In the 1970s, communist
                    parties in Western Europe, particularly in Italy, became more independent from
                    policy set in Moscow. Communist groups throughout the region worked more closely
                    within their national systems, and in some cases even entered into ruling
                    coalition governments. This movement, known as Eurocommunism, altered how
                    Washington and its overseas representatives worked with European policymakers.
                    Previously U.S. policy limited the United States to working only with anti- or
                    non-communist groups and politicians. In response to the trend toward
                    Eurocommunism, the Carter administration decided that U.S. diplomats should
                    engage with a broader cross-section of politicians, opinion makers, and the
                    public.</p>
                <p>In southern Europe, fears about the rise of communism were also put to rest.
                    During the Ford administration, the Carnation Revolution (1974) and the death of
                    Spanish Head of State General Francisco Franco (1975) that ended authoritarian
                    regimes in Portugal and Spain respectively, provoked anxiety in Washington about
                    a possible communist takeover of the Iberian Peninsula. By the Carter years it
                    became clear that both Spain and Portugal were peacefully transitioning to
                    democracy. Frequent visits by high-level U.S. officials helped reaffirm
                    Washington’s solidarity with these countries and support for the fledgling
                    democracies in Lisbon and Madrid. Renegotiations of U.S. rights to use military
                    bases in Spain and Portugal further underlined the strengthened relationship
                    between Iberia and the United States. Likewise, by late 1978, the Italian
                    Communist Party’s efforts to participate in government had been frustrated and
                    the party suffered electoral losses, thus reducing concerns about communist
                    influence in Italy.</p>
                <p>The European political scene was also affected by a sharp uptick in domestic
                    terrorism in Western Europe. Leftist and separatist terrorist groups, such as
                    the Baader Meinhof Group (West Germany), Red Brigades (Italy), and <hi
                        rend="italic">Euzkadi ta Azkatasuna</hi>(ETA; Spain) operated throughout the
                    region. While their targets were most often European soldiers, officials, and
                    business leaders, by the late 1970s, these groups also threatened U.S.
                    diplomats, and U.S. representatives in the region were forced to tighten
                    security. In response, the United States and its Western European partners began
                    to coordinate their efforts to limit terrorism. European authorities and their
                    U.S. counterparts worked together more closely to combat terrorism on European
                    soil.</p>
                <p>Despite these areas of increased cooperation between Western European nations and
                    the United States, the events of late 1979 cast a pall over the transatlantic
                    relationship. Differences emerged over how to best handle relations with Iran
                    after Iranian militants stormed the U.S. Embassy in Tehran and took over 60 U.S.
                    diplomats hostage. U.S. and European leaders disagreed over the appropriate
                    response to the hostage crisis, including economic and diplomatic sanctions.
                    Similar tensions emerged over how to confront Moscow after the Soviet Union’s
                    December 1979 intervention in Afghanistan. Carter reacted with a series of
                    measures designed to pressure the Soviets to withdraw, but the Europeans did not
                    agree with all aspects of his decisions. The invasion of Afghanistan led to an
                    escalation of tensions between the Soviet Union and the United States and
                    ultimately drew Carter’s attention away from Europe. The re-intensification of
                    the Cold War chagrined many in Western Europe, who advocated a <hi rend="italic"
                        >rapprochement</hi>between Washington and Moscow as a means to reduce the
                    security threat posed to their region.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="north-south-dialogue"
                ana="foreign-economic-policy foreign-aid carter-jimmy ">
                <head>The North-South Dialogue and Economic Diplomacy</head>
                <p>The North-South Dialogue refers to the process through which the developing and
                    newly independent nations of the “third world,” predominantly in Asia, Africa,
                    and Latin America, engaged the industrialized countries of North America and
                    Western Europe in negotiations over changes to the international economic system
                    during the 1970s.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="unctad.jpg" height="450px" width="298px"/>
                    <head>World Bank President Robert McNamara gives his address at the Fifth
                        Session of the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development on
                        Thursday, May 10, 1979 in Manila.(AP Photo) </head>
                </figure>
                <p>After World War II, many nations of <placeName>Latin America</placeName> became
                    increasingly frustrated with U.S. trade and tariff policies. At the same time,
                    nationalist movements in <placeName>Asia</placeName> and
                        <placeName>Africa</placeName> helped lead to widespread decolonization.
                    Membership in the United Nations had risen from 51 countries in 1945 to 100 in
                    1960 and 150 by 1979. The sudden influx of new countries changed the balance of
                    power in the General Assembly and made possible the establishment of the United
                    Nations Conference on Trade and Development, or UNCTAD, in 1964. UNCTAD created
                    a forum through which the “southern” or “third world” nations could propose
                    economic policies, engaging industrial democracies of the “north.” The term
                    “North-South Dialogue” was used to distinguish this dynamic from the East-West
                    conflict of the Cold War, and to stress the point that development issues were
                    just as pressing as the ideological conflict between communists and
                    capitalists.</p>
                <p>Several factors increased the willingness of the industrialized nations to
                    negotiate. One was the rising power of oil-producing countries in the Arab
                    world, and another was the U.S. loss in the war in
                        <placeName>Vietnam</placeName>, which demonstrated to both the world and the
                    industrialized North that not even wealth and power were enough to guarantee
                    military victory. Both of these issues drew Western attention toward the global
                    balance of economic power. Additionally, the dialogue began in a period of
                    relaxed East-West tensions, which meant that the industrialized world could give
                    more attention to issues like development. The Newly Industrializing Economies,
                    meanwhile, believed the entrenched international economic system benefited
                    developed countries at the expense of the developing world. They hoped to
                    facilitate a reorganization of the international economic system to rectify this
                    imbalance.</p>
                <p>The North-South Dialogue addressed issues pertaining to trade and tariffs,
                    international finance, foreign aid, and the governance of multinational
                    companies and institutions. During the era of détente in the 1970s, when
                    East-West tensions were more relaxed, there was a willingness among
                    industrialized nations to cooperate. Even as détente began to falter in the
                    mid-1970s, the parties to the North-South Dialogue continued their
                    discussions.</p>
                <p>U.S. policies and relations with the other Northern powers inevitably served to
                    help or hinder progress in the dialogue. For example, changes in trade policies
                    between the United States and Western Europe could serve to distract these
                    countries from their negotiations with the industrializing countries or cause
                    them to extend new levels of control over their interactions within their
                    respective spheres of influence in the developing world. Late in the 1970s, the
                    increasing conflicts between the United States and the Soviet Union finally
                    served to sour the prospects for continuing North-South discussions, as the
                    industrialized nations renewed their focus and redirected their resources to the
                    Cold War and paid less attention to development issues. By September of 1980,
                    the discussions in the United Nations that had characterized this dialogue had
                    lost their momentum. Although some dialogue on these issues continued, it
                    remained a series of discussions on economic issues and never presented the
                    workable solution that its proponents had hoped it would.</p>
                <p>There are many ways to interpret the high point of the North-South Dialogue in
                    the 1970s. Some economists have reviewed the southern proposals for broad
                    changes in world economic policy and concluded that they were either
                    fundamentally unworkable or designed to benefit only certain segments of the
                    Third World; others counter that the proposals were necessarily extreme in order
                    to establish a firm position from which to open negotiations with the
                    industrialized North. Either way, the exact implementation of the proposals
                    presented through UNCTAD was always unlikely, because they centered on the
                    Southern ideal and would have required the economically-powerful North to
                    concede every point. The North-South Dialogue can also be viewed as a political
                    struggle between the world’s “haves” and “have-nots.” In this view, the
                    discussions became a vehicle through which the South could unite and assert
                    power within the United Nations and other international organizations to counter
                    the ability of the North to dictate the course of world affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="non-proliferation"
                ana="nixon-richard ford-gerald carter-jimmy russia arms-control-and-disarmament politico-military-issues">
                <head>Counter-Proliferation During the Carter Administration</head>
                <p>During his run for the presidency in 1976, former Governor Jimmy Carter made the
                    non-proliferation of nuclear, chemical, biological, and conventional arms a key
                    part of his foreign policy platform.Carter, in a departure from former
                    Presidents Richard Nixon and Gerald Ford, also tried to link his arms control
                    ideas to his emphasis on human rights. After his January 1977 inauguration,
                    Carter immediately began to pursue his counter-proliferation objectives. He also
                    announced that he would link arms control to the human rights records of U.S.
                    allies, in particular in Latin America.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="carter-nonproliferation.jpg" height="450px" width="295px"/>
                    <head>Carter, Vance, and Brzezinski in the Oval Office. (Jimmy Carter
                        Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Carter focused on five areas: anti-satellite (ASAT) space systems; chemical and
                    biological weapons (CBW); a comprehensive nuclear testing ban (CTB), even if
                    such tests were used for “peaceful” purposes; the ratification of the Treaty of
                    Tlatelolco by Latin American nations; and the global reduction of conventional
                    arms sales/transfers. The Carter administration’s main negotiating partner in
                    the first three areas was the Soviet Union. Carter’s negotiating partners in the
                    last two areas were the Federal Republic of Germany (FRG), the Soviet Union, and
                    the Latin American allies.</p>
                <p>It became quickly apparent that the two superpowers fundamentally diverged on two
                    key points. First was the issue of verification, which also hampered the
                    Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) negotiations that were occurring
                    simultaneously. Like Nixon and Ford, Carter wanted each side to have the ability
                    to perform on-site inspections (OSIs) and employ National Technical Means (NTM)
                    such as photo reconnaissance flights to verify compliance with agreements. The
                    Soviets, however, rejected both means of verification in the ASAT, CTB, and CBW
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>The second area of disagreement involved definitions of weapons systems. The
                    Soviets demanded that the space shuttle, currently being developed by the United
                    States, be subject to an ASAT treaty. Carter, however, categorically rejected
                    this demand. The ASAT negotiations ended after the Soviet Union invaded
                    Afghanistan in December 1979.</p>
                <p>Chemical weapons negotiations bogged down over whether pesticides and other
                    defoliants would be subjected to an arms control agreement, and the Soviet Union
                    and the United States could not agree whether or not binary chemical weapons
                    (those weapons requiring a chemical reaction to activate the toxin) would be
                    included in a potential treaty. These roadblocks had also been a problem during
                    the Nixon and Ford years.</p>
                <p>Biological weapons did not become an issue until the spring of 1980, when the
                    United States learned that an outbreak of pulmonary anthrax had killed hundreds,
                    possibly thousands, in Sverdlovsk, the site of a suspected Soviet biological
                    weapons factory. The factory had ostensibly been closed after former President
                    Nixon and Soviet General Secretary Leonid Brezhnev signed the 1972 Biological
                    Weapons Convention that banned the use and production of biological weapons.
                    This apparent violation of the Convention, coming shortly after the Soviet
                    invasion of Afghanistan and Carter’s decision to boycott the Moscow Summer
                    Olympics, further poisoned U.S.-Soviet relations, and the CBW talks
                    languished.</p>
                <p>The CTB discussions were the most intense and long-lasting arms control
                    discussions of the Carter years. These negotiations also bogged down over
                    whether Peaceful Nuclear Explosions (PNEs) should be included in an agreement.
                    Carter wanted a comprehensive ban, but the Soviets wanted the ability to perform
                    PNEs, especially to divert the course of a river in Siberia to the desert areas
                    of Central Asia. Like the ASAT and CBW negotiations, the CTB talks were
                    threatened after the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan and the Sverdlovsk
                    incident.When the United States began detecting signs in the summer of 1980 that
                    the Soviets had resumed high-yield testing that violated the 1976 Threshold Test
                    Ban Treaty, Carter abandoned the negotiations.</p>
                <p>Talks over nuclear non-proliferation in Latin America also began as soon as
                    Carter took office. Carter had publicly criticized the 1975 sale of a nuclear
                    reactor by the Federal Republic of Germany to Brazil because he worried that the
                    Brazilians would be able to produce weapons-grade uranium. If Brazil developed
                    nuclear weapons it would violate the 1968 Treaty of Ttlatelolco, which had
                    created a Latin American nuclear-free zone. Brazil had signed and ratified the
                    Treaty, but reserved the right not to be bound by all the Treaty's provisions.
                    Only three days into his presidency, Carter learned from the U.S. Department of
                    State that Brazilian-American and German-American relations would be severely
                    jeopardized if he continued to criticize the sale. Meanwhile, Argentina,
                    Brazil’s principal regional rival, refused to ratify the Treaty and began the
                    process of purchasing a nuclear reactor of its own. The Carter administration
                    asked the Mexican Government, which had provided the impetus for the signing of
                    the Treaty, to convince Brazil, Argentina, as well as Cuba, to sign and/or
                    ratify the Treaty without conditions. Washington’s and Mexico City’s efforts
                    failed, and when Carter left office in 1981 the status quo remained.</p>
                <p>As noted above, Carter wanted to link his arms control initiatives to human
                    rights, particularly in the area of conventional arms sales. However, Carter
                    found that his human rights rhetoric collided with U.S. security interests. If
                    the United States wished to counterbalance Soviet power, then it could not
                    easily stop selling or transferring conventional arms to its Latin American (and
                    Asian) allies even if their commitment to human rights was suspect. Meanwhile,
                    the Soviet Union increased its arms sales, especially to the developing world.
                    Ultimately, Carter’s National Security Advisor, Zbigniew Brzezinski,
                    successfully convinced Carter that the rise of Cuban and Soviet activity in
                    Central and South America and instability in East Asia meant that the United
                    States must support its anti-communist allies with conventional weapons, despite
                    their human rights records. By the time Carter left office, U.S. conventional
                    arms sales had actually increased.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="china-policy"
                ana="carter-jimmy vance-cyrus-roberts muskie-edmund-sixtus east-asia-and-pacific china taiwan">
                <head>China Policy</head>
                <p>During Jimmy Carter’s presidency, the most dramatic moment in Sino-American
                    relations occurred on December 15, 1978, when, following months of secret
                    negotiations, the United States and the People’s Republic of China (PRC)
                    announced that they would recognize one another and establish official
                    diplomatic relations. As part of the agreement, the United States recognized the
                    Government of the People’s Republic of China as the sole legal government of
                    China, and declared it would withdraw diplomatic recognition from Taiwan (also
                    known as the Republic of China [ROC]).</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="prc-normalization.jpg" height="450px" width="307px"/>
                    <head>Jimmy Carter, Richard Nixon, and Deng Xiaoping during the state dinner for
                        the Vice Premier of China, January 29, 1979. (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Prior to 1979, the United States and the People’s Republic of China had never
                    established formal diplomatic relations. In 1949, Chinese Communist Party forces
                    defeated the Government of the Republic of China in the Chinese Civil War and
                    founded the People’s Republic of China, eliminating ROC authority from mainland
                    China. Nonetheless, for the next thirty years, the U.S. Government continued to
                    recognize the Republic of China on Taiwan as the sole legal government over all
                    of China. During that period, the U.S. and PRC Governments had only intermittent
                    contact through forums such as the Sino-U.S. Ambassadorial talks in Warsaw,
                    which began in 1955.</p>
                <p>A new era began with a rapprochement during Richard Nixon’s presidency. Nixon and
                    his aide, Henry Kissinger, found ready partners in Mao Zedong, the Chairman of
                    the Chinese Communist Party, and Zhou Enlai, the Chinese Premier, who also
                    wanted to improve Sino-U.S. relations. Their efforts resulted in the Shanghai
                    Communiqué, which laid the basis for future cooperation between the two
                    countries even while acknowledging continuing disagreements on the subject of
                    Taiwan. As part of this rapprochement, the two countries opened liaison offices
                    in one another’s capitals in 1973, a time when Taiwan still had an Embassy in
                    Washington. The liaison offices, which in many ways operated as de facto
                    embassies, represented a significant concession by the People’s Republic of
                    China, which opposed the acceptance of “two Chinas” because that implied both
                    were legitimate governments. The U.S. Government placated the People’s Republic
                    of China, and helped set the stage for normalization, by gradually removing
                    military personnel from Taiwan and scaling back its official contact with the
                    ROC Government.</p>
                <p>When Carter took office in January 1977, a significant improvement in relations
                    between Communist China and the United States seemed far from inevitable.
                    Presidents before Nixon had failed to make significant progress in improving
                    relations with the People’s Republic of China. President Nixon’s attempt to
                    normalize relations with China during his second term had been frustrated by the
                    Watergate scandal. The collapse of South Vietnam and the opposition of
                    conservative Republicans created an inhospitable environment for pursuing
                    normalization during Gerald Ford’s presidency; any policy shift that could be
                    depicted as appeasing a longstanding communist enemy and abandoning a loyal,
                    anti-communist ally generated significant political resistance.</p>
                <p>Officials within the Carter administration debated how to normalize relations
                    with China without damaging relations with the Soviet Union, China’s great rival
                    within the international Communist movement. Nevertheless, Carter and his top
                    aides agreed that the opportunity to normalize relations with China might be
                    fleeting and should not be squandered.In the spring of 1978, Carter decided to
                    proceed with normalization. A handful of top U.S. officials agreed upon
                    instructions, which the President approved, that were sent to the U.S.
                    negotiator Leonard Woodcock, the head of the U.S. Liaison Office in Beijing. By
                    the terms of the agreement the two sides reached, the United States acknowledged
                    “the Chinese position that there is but one China and Taiwan is part of China.”
                    The United States declared its intention to abrogate the Mutual Defense Treaty
                    between the United States and the Republic of China, originally signed in
                    December 1954. Simultaneously, however, the United States declared in the Joint
                    Communiqué that it would “maintain cultural, commercial, and other unofficial
                    relations with the people of Taiwan.” In Carter’s address to the nation on
                    December 15, 1978, he announced that in accordance with “the Shanghai
                    communiqué, issued on President Nixon’s historic visit, we will continue to have
                    an interest in the peaceful resolution of the Taiwan issue.” The Joint
                    Communiqué stated that the United States would begin official diplomatic
                    relations with the People’s Republic of China on January 1, 1979, and that the
                    two countries would open Embassies on March 1.</p>
                <p>The exchange of accredited ambassadors and the operation of Embassies enabled
                    both parties to negotiate diplomatic disputes and pursue mutual interests. A
                    number of disagreements arose that required management by both countries. During
                    Chinese Vice-Premier Deng Xiaoping’s goodwill visit to the United States in
                    January 1979, he informed Carter of the People’s Republic of China’s intention
                    to attack Vietnam in response to that country’s invasion of Cambodia. Carter
                    unsuccessfully attempted to dissuade Deng from pursuing this military action.
                    Another point of contention was the legal framework that Congress erected to
                    enable the people of the United States and Taiwan to continue economic and
                    cultural relations following the U.S. decision to break diplomatic relations.
                    PRC leaders repeatedly expressed displeasure with the Taiwan Relations Act
                    (TRA), which became law on April 10, 1979. The TRA was influenced by
                    Congressional supporters of Taiwan and stated that it is the policy of the
                    United States “to provide Taiwan with arms of a defensive character; and to
                    maintain the capacity of the United States to resist any resort to force or
                    other forms of coercion that would jeopardize the security, or the social or
                    economic system, of the people on Taiwan.” In his signing statement, Carter
                    declared that he would use the discretion granted to him by Congress to
                    interpret the TRA “in a manner consistent with our interest in the well-being of
                    the people on Taiwan and with the understandings we reached on the normalization
                    of relations with the People’s Republic of China.” In addition to disagreement
                    over the TRA, U.S.–PRC relations following normalization were impaired by
                    arguments over longstanding financial claims, economic disputes, and the PRC
                    view that the United States was too conciliatory toward the Soviet Union.</p>
                <p>Despite such difficulties, U.S.–PRC relations generally improved as the two
                    countries made progress on economic and security issues. Deng’s 1979 trip was
                    extremely successful as he charismatically wooed Congress, the media, and the
                    American people. Journalists depicted the Chinese leader as personable, famously
                    photographing him at a rodeo wearing a ten-gallon hat. On January 31, the United
                    States and People’s Republic of China concluded agreements on various topics
                    including consular relations, academic exchanges, and cooperation in the fields
                    of space technology, high-energy physics, and science and technology policy. The
                    1979 Soviet invasion of Afghanistan increased Sino-American military
                    cooperation, despite the objections of Secretary of Defense Harold Brown and
                    Secretary of State Cyrus Vance. The United States and People’s Republic of China
                    also coordinated their other responses to the Soviet incursion, such as the
                    boycott of the Olympic Games in Moscow. The normalization of relations provided
                    both sides with the essential diplomatic mechanisms necessary to manage
                    difficulties and promote common objectives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="camp-david"
                ana="carter-jimmy vance-cyrus-roberts egypt israel peace">
                <head>Camp David Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process</head>
                <p>The Camp David Accords, signed by President Jimmy Carter, Egyptian President
                    Anwar Sadat, and Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin in September 1978,
                    established a framework for a historic peace treaty concluded between Israel and
                    Egypt in March 1979. President Carter and the U.S. Government played leading
                    roles in creating the opportunity for this agreement to occur. From the start of
                    his administration, Carter and his Secretary of State, Cyrus Vance, pursued
                    intensive negotiations with Arab and Israeli leaders, hoping to reconvene the
                    Geneva Conference, which had been established in December 1973 to seek an end to
                    the Arab-Israeli dispute.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="camp-david.jpg" height="450px" width="304px"/>
                    <head>President Jimmy Carter with Egyptian President Anwar Sadat and Israeli
                        Prime Minister Menachem Begin at Camp David, Maryland in September 1978.
                        (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>As Carter and Vance met with individual leaders from Arab countries and Israel
                    during the spring of 1977, negotiations for a return to Geneva appeared to gain
                    some momentum. On May 17, 1977, an Israeli election upset stunned the Carter
                    administration as the moderate Israeli Labor Party lost for the first time in
                    Israel’s history. Menachem Begin, the leader of the conservative Likud Party and
                    the new Israeli Prime Minister, appeared intractable on the issue of exchanging
                    land for peace. His party’s commitment to “greater Israel” left Carter with an
                    even more challenging situation during the summer of 1977.</p>
                <p>In addition to the new reality of a Likud government in Israel, long-standing
                    rivalries among Arab leaders also played a role in blocking substantive progress
                    in negotiations for a Geneva conference. By early November, Egyptian President
                    Sadat found himself frustrated by the lack of movement and made a dramatic move,
                    announcing on November 9 that he would be willing to go to Jerusalem. This move
                    stunned the world. Sadat would attempt to break the deadlock and to engage the
                    Israelis directly for a Middle East settlement, eschewing any talk of returning
                    to the Geneva Conference. Sadat’s visit led to direct talks between Egypt and
                    Israel that December, but these talks did not generate substantive progress. By
                    January 1978, the United States returned to a more prominent negotiation
                    role.</p>
                <p>During the spring and early summer of 1978, the United States attempted to find
                    common ground with regard to Israeli withdrawal from the Sinai, West Bank, and
                    Gaza. Egypt insisted on an Israeli withdrawal to June 4, 1967 borders in
                    exchange for security arrangements and minor border modifications. Israel
                    rejected Egypt’s insistence on withdrawal, especially from the West Bank and
                    Gaza. It argued instead for some form of Palestinian autonomy during a five-year
                    interim period followed by the possibility of sovereignty after the interim
                    period expired. The impasse over the West Bank and Gaza led Carter to intercede
                    directly in an attempt to resolve the deadlock.</p>
                <p>By July 30, as Sadat expressed disappointment over the progress of negotiations
                    and a desire to cut direct contacts off with the Israelis, Carter decided to
                    call for a summit meeting. This meeting would bring Sadat, Begin, and Carter
                    together at the presidential retreat in Maryland at Camp David. On August 8, the
                    White House spokesman formally announced the meeting, which both Begin and Sadat
                    agreed to attend in September.</p>
                <p>The Camp David Summit, held from September 5–17, 1978, was a pivotal moment both
                    in the history of the Arab-Israeli dispute and U.S. diplomacy. Rarely had a U.S.
                    President devoted as much sustained attention to a single foreign policy issue
                    as Carter did over the summit’s two-week duration. Carter’s ambitious goals for
                    the talks included breaking the negotiating deadlock and hammering out a
                    detailed Egyptian-Israeli peace agreement. To this end, U.S. Middle East experts
                    produced a draft treaty text, which served as the basis for the negotiations and
                    would be revised numerous times during the Summit. The talks proved extremely
                    challenging, especially when the trilateral format became impossible to sustain.
                    Instead, Carter and Vance met with the Egyptian and Israeli delegations
                    individually over the course of the next twelve days.</p>
                <p>The talks ranged over a number of issues, including the future of Israeli
                    settlements and airbases in the Sinai Peninsula, but it was Gaza and the West
                    Bank that continued to pose the most difficulty. Specifically, the delegations
                    were divided over the applicability of United Nations Security Council
                    Resolution 242 to a long-term agreement in the territories, as well as the
                    status of Israel’s settlements during projected negotiations on Palestinian
                    autonomy that would follow a peace treaty. In the end, while the Summit did not
                    produce a formal peace agreement, it successfully produced the <hi rend="italic"
                        >basis</hi> for an Egyptian-Israeli peace, in the form of two “Framework”
                    documents, which laid out the principles of a bilateral peace agreement as well
                    as a formula for Palestinian self-government in Gaza and the West Bank.</p>
                <p>While the conclusion of the Camp David Accords represented significant progress,
                    the process of translating the Framework documents into a formal peace treaty
                    proved daunting. As with the Summit, Carter’s hopes for rapid progress were
                    high, and the President hoped that a treaty text would be concluded in a matter
                    of days. However, the controversy that developed between the Carter
                    administration and the Begin government over the duration of an agreed freeze in
                    the construction of Israeli settlements was quickly followed by the
                    administration’s failure to win support from Jordan or Saudi Arabia for the
                    Accords. Beginning in October, a series of talks in Washington broke down as a
                    result of Israeli concerns over the timing of their withdrawal and Egyptian
                    reservations regarding the impact of a peace treaty on its obligations to other
                    Arab states. Other regional developments, especially the Iranian Revolution,
                    distracted U.S. policymakers and raised Israeli concerns about its oil supply,
                    resulting in an impasse during the winter of 1978–1979. After Begin’s visit to
                    the White House in early March failed to break the stalemate, Carter traveled to
                    Israel on March 10. Having previously secured Sadat’s consent to negotiate on
                    behalf of Egypt, the President engaged in three days of intensive talks with the
                    Israelis. As a result of a series of compromises, notably a U.S. guarantee of
                    Israel’s oil supply, omitting references to a “special role” for Egypt in Gaza,
                    and Israeli agreement to make a number of unilateral gestures to the
                    Palestinians, the U.S. and Israeli delegations agreed to a treaty text on March
                    13. Sadat quickly assented to the agreement and the Egyptian-Israeli Peace
                    Treaty was formally signed on March 26.</p>
                <p>Although a landmark event, the successful conclusion of the Egyptian-Israeli
                    Treaty represented the high-water mark for the Peace Process during the Carter
                    Presidency. After March 1979, the issue would not receive the same level of U.S.
                    attention due to the competing demands of crises, especially those in Iran and
                    Afghanistan, as well as Carter’s desire to reduce his personal involvement in
                    the next round of negotiations devoted to Palestinian autonomy. For those talks,
                    Carter appointed a “special negotiator” to represent the United States; former
                    Special Trade Representative Robert Strauss served in this role briefly before
                    being replaced in the fall of 1979 by Sol Linowitz, who had previously helped
                    negotiate the Panama Canal treaty. The talks failed to produce much as
                    Palestinian representatives refused to participate, and the gap between Egyptian
                    and Israeli positions on Palestinian self-government, not to mention their
                    respective stances on Israeli settlements in Gaza and the West Bank and the
                    legal status of East Jerusalem, proved unbridgeable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="panama-canal"
                ana="nixon-richard ford-gerald carter-jimmy reagan-ronald kissinger-henry-a vance-cyrus-roberts panama">
                <head>The Panama Canal and the Torrijos-Carter Treaties</head>
                <p>One of President Jimmy Carter’s greatest accomplishments was negotiating the
                    Torrijos-Carter Treaties, which were ratified by the U.S. Senate in 1978. These
                    treaties gave the nation of Panama eventual control of the Panama Canal.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="panama-canal.jpg" height="450px" width="309px"/>
                    <head>Jimmy Carter and Omar Torrijos at the September 7th signing ceremony.
                        (Jimmy Carter Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The United States acquired the rights to build and operate the Panama Canal
                    during the first years of the 20th century. The Hay-Herrán Treaty, negotiated
                    with the nation of Colombia in 1903, allowed the United States rights to the
                    land surrounding the planned canal. The Colombian Senate refused to ratify the
                    treaty, but Panama was in the process of seceding from Colombia. President
                    Theodore Roosevelt therefore supported the cause of Panamanian independence with
                    the Canal in mind. His support paid off, and on November 18, 1903, the United
                    States signed the Hay-Bunau-Varilla Treaty, establishing permanent U.S. rights
                    to a Panama Canal Zone that stretched across the isthmus. Phillippe-Jean
                    Bunau-Varilla, the Panamanian representative, entered the negotiations without
                    formal consent from the Panamanian government, and had not lived in Panama for
                    seventeen years. The Canal opened in 1914, but many Panamanians questioned the
                    validity of the treaty.</p>
                <p>As the 20th century progressed, tensions between the United States and Panama
                    over U.S. control of the Canal grew. In 1964, a riot between U.S. residents and
                    Panamanians, sparked over the right to fly the Panamanian flag in the Canal
                    Zone, led to a brief interruption of diplomatic relations between the two
                    countries. Within months, ties were re-established and both sides recognized the
                    importance of negotiating a new agreement concerning the Canal. In 1967, the
                    United States and Panama reached agreement on three treaties regarding the
                    status of the Canal, however, Panamanian president Marco Robles was defeated by
                    Arnulfo Arias Madrid in the 1968 Panamanian elections. Eleven days into Arias’s
                    term, a coup led by Colonel Omar Torrijos deposed Arias and established a new
                    government. Because of the political uncertainty, the negotiations suffered a
                    major setback.</p>
                <p>Torrijos, like his predecessors, wished to reach an agreement with the United
                    States. U.S. officials wanted a treaty as well. Secretary of State Henry
                    Kissinger set forth his reasoning in a meeting with President Ford in 1975: “If
                    these [Canal] negotiations fail, we will be beaten to death in every
                    international forum and there will be riots all over Latin America.” In 1973,
                    the Nixon administration appointed Ellsworth Bunker, a seasoned U.S. diplomat,
                    to lead the U.S. delegation. Bunker focused on ensuring perpetual U.S. use of
                    the Panama Canal, rather than perpetual U.S. control of the Panama Canal Zone.
                    Between the years of 1973 and 1976, Bunker and his team were able to conclude a
                    series of draft agreements with the government of Panama that formed the
                    foundation of the eventual Torrijos-Carter Treaties.</p>
                <p>The 1976 presidential elections proved to be a perilous time for the
                    negotiations. While President Ford supported a Canal treaty, his primary
                    opponent, Ronald Reagan, did not. The Democratic nominee for president, Jimmy
                    Carter, also seemed to oppose a treaty. In an October debate with Ford, Carter
                    vowed that he would not surrender “practical control of the Panama Canal Zone
                    any time in the foreseeable future.”</p>
                <p>In the weeks after his electoral victory, President-elect Carter’s views on the
                    Canal began to change. One of his closest advisors, Sol Linowitz, supported a
                    treaty, as did Secretary of State-designate Cyrus Vance. The two men were able
                    to convince Carter of the importance of a new treaty, and when he took office,
                    Carter made concluding negotiations with Panama a priority and named Linowitz
                    co-negotiator with Bunker.</p>
                <p>Despite the fact that both Carter and Torrijos were eager to conclude a treaty,
                    many obstacles remained. A treaty must be ratified by the Senate with at least a
                    two-thirds majority in order to take effect. Many Senators were opposed to
                    giving Panama control over the Canal Zone. Most notable of these critics was
                    Strom Thurmond (R–SC). Thurmond, who was born twelve years before the Canal was
                    built, had a different perspective than the Carter administration. “The loss of
                    this canal would contribute to the encirclement of the United States,” he stated
                    in a 1978 debate. Thurmond and other conservatives also distrusted Torrijos,
                    whom they considered to be pro-communist. Because of the strong opposition in
                    the Senate, Carter’s consultations with Congress amounted to a second set of
                    treaty negotiations.</p>
                <p>The Carter administration formulated a strategy to conclude debate over the Canal
                    and to gain Senate ratification. Carter officials worked on selling the treaty
                    to the public, holding hundreds of forums where policymakers explained the
                    administration’s rationale for completing a treaty. Torrijos hosted U.S.
                    Senators in Panama, where he stressed that he was neither an enemy of the United
                    States nor a communist. Actor John Wayne, both a conservative and a friend of
                    Torrijos, also endorsed the negotiations. The negotiators decided that their
                    best chance for ratification was to submit two treaties to the U.S. Senate. The
                    first, called <hi rend="italic">The Treaty Concerning the Permanent Neutrality
                        and Operation of the Panama Canal, </hi>or the <hi rend="italic">Neutrality
                        Treaty, </hi>stated that the United States could use its military to defend
                    the Panama Canal against any threat to its neutrality, thus allowing perpetual
                    U.S. usage of the Canal. The second, called The<hi rend="italic"> Panama Canal
                        Treaty, </hi>stated that the Panama Canal Zone would cease to exist on
                    October 1, 1979, and the Canal itself would be turned over to the Panamanians on
                    December 31, 1999. These two treaties were signed on September 7, 1977.</p>
                <p>It took more than six months before the Senate voted. Many Senators who opposed
                    the treaties tried to add amendments that would make it harder for other
                    Senators to vote in favor of them. In the end, the Carter administration
                    succeeded—but just barely. The Senate ratified the <hi rend="italic">Neutrality
                        Treaty </hi>on March 16, 1978 by a vote of 68 to 32. On April 18, they
                    ratified <hi rend="italic">The Panama Canal Treaty</hi> by an identical margin.
                    The Carter administration revisited many of these issues with Congress when it
                    negotiated the implementation legislation for the Torrijos-Carter Treaties.
                    Carter signed the implementation legislation into law on September 27, 1979.</p>
                <p>The Torrijos-Carter Treaties allowed the United States to defend itself from
                    charges of imperialism made by Soviet-aligned states. While the treaties
                    represented a great moment of cooperation between the United States and Panama,
                    relations between the two countries grew contentious after the death of Torrijos
                    in 1981. In December of 1989, President George H.W. Bush ordered an invasion of
                    Panama to remove Panamanian leader Manuel Noreiga from power. By 1999, however,
                    relations had grown more peaceful and the Canal was turned over to the
                    Panamanians who have administered it ever since.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="soviet-invasion-afghanistan"
                ana="carter-jimmy russia afghanistan pakistan economic-sanctions foreign-aid covert-actions diplomatic-recognition">
                <head>The Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan and the U.S. Response, 1978–1980</head>
                <p>At the end of December 1979, the Soviet Union sent thousands of troops into
                        <placeName>Afghanistan</placeName> and immediately assumed complete military
                    and political control of <placeName>Kabul</placeName> and large portions of the
                    country. This event began a brutal, decade-long attempt by Moscow to subdue the
                    Afghan civil war and maintain a friendly and socialist government on its border.
                    It was a watershed event of the Cold War, marking the only time the Soviet Union
                    invaded a country outside the Eastern Bloc—a strategic decision met by nearly
                    worldwide condemnation. While the massive, lightning-fast military maneuvers and
                    brazenness of Soviet political objectives constituted an “invasion” of
                    Afghanistan, the word “intervention” more accurately describes these events as
                    the culmination of growing Soviet domination going back to 1973. Undoubtedly,
                    leaders in the Kremlin had hoped that a rapid and complete military takeover
                    would secure Afghanistan’s place as an exemplar of the Brezhnev Doctrine, which
                    held that once a country became socialist Moscow would never permit it to return
                    to the capitalist camp. The United States and its European allies, guided by
                    their own doctrine of containment, sharply criticized the Soviet move into
                    Afghanistan and devised numerous measures to compel Moscow to withdraw.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="afghanistan.jpg" height="450px" width="263px"/>
                    <head>Soviet combat vehicles move through Afghanistan. (Department of
                        Defense)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In the summer of 1973, <persName>Mohammed Daoud</persName>, the former Afghan
                    Prime Minister, launched a successful coup against King Zahir. Although Daoud
                    himself was more nationalist than socialist, his coup was dependent on
                    pro-Soviet military and political factions. Since 1955 Moscow had provided
                    military training and materiel to Afghanistan; by 1973, a third of active troops
                    had trained on Soviet soil. Additionally, Daoud enjoyed the support of the
                    People’s Democratic Party of Afghanistan (PDPA), founded in 1965 upon Marxist
                    ideology and allegiance to Moscow. In 1967 the PDPA split into two factions: the
                    Parchamists, led by <persName>Babrak Karmal</persName> (who supported Daoud),
                    and the “Khalqis” led by Noor Taraki. For the next five years, Daoud attempted
                    the impossible task of governing Afganistan’s Islamic tribal regions, while also
                    struggling to reconcile the PDPA split. But the more radical Khalq faction never
                    fully recognized Daoud’s leadership, while Karmal viewed the coup largely as a
                    means to consolidate his own power. In response, Daoud hoped to mitigate both of
                    these threats by steering Afghanistan away from Soviet influence and improving
                    U.S. relations, while decreasing the influence of radical elements in the
                    government and military.</p>
                <p>Daoud’s middle course ended in disaster. On April 28, 1978, soldiers aligned with
                    Taraki’s “Khalq” faction assaulted the presidential palace, where troops
                    executed Daoud and his family. In the following days Taraki became the Prime
                    Minister, and, in an attempt to end the PDPA’s divisions, Karmal became Deputy
                    Prime Minister. In Washington, this Communist revolution was met with alarm. The
                    Carter administration recognized that Taraki would undo Daoud’s attempt to steer
                    Afghanistan away from Moscow, and it debated whether to cut ties with
                    Afghanistan or recognize Taraki in the hopes that Soviet influence could be
                    contained. Although the President’s Assistant for National Security Affairs
                    Zbigniew Brzezinski advocated the former course, Carter supported the Department
                    of State’s advocacy of recognition. Shortly after the revolution, Washington
                    recognized the new government and soon named Adolph Dubs its Ambassador to
                    Afghanistan. Until his kidnapping and death at the hands of Afghan Shia
                    dissidents in February 1979, Dubs strongly pursued good relations with the
                    Taraki regime in the hopes that U.S. support would keep Soviet influence at
                    bay.</p>
                <p>Once again, the tumult of internal Afghan politics complicated both U.S. and
                    Soviet jockeying. In the summer of 1979, <persName>Hafizullah Amin</persName>, a
                    longtime ally of Taraki who became Deputy Prime Minister following the April
                    Revolution, received word that Babrak Karmal (Daoud’s early supporter) was
                    leading a Parcham plot to overthrow the Taraki regime. Amin took the opportunity
                    to purge and execute many Parchamists and consolidate his own power.
                    Complicating matters further, this internal strife damaged the Kabul
                    Government’s major national program, namely, to bring the Communist revolution
                    to the Islamic tribal areas beyond Kabul. By the winter of 1978, this program
                    was met by armed revolt throughout the country. In response, Amin and Taraki
                    traveled to Moscow to sign a friendship treaty which included a provision that
                    would allow direct Soviet military assistance should the Islamic insurgency
                    threaten the regime. This insurrection intensified over the next year and it
                    became increasingly obvious to the Soviets that Taraki could not prevent all-out
                    civil war and the prospect of a hostile Islamic government taking control. By
                    mid-1979 Moscow was searching to replace Taraki and Amin, and dispatched combat
                    troops to Bagram Air Base outside of Kabul. This move prompted the Carter
                    administration to begin supplying non-lethal aid to Afghan <hi rend="italic"
                        >mujahedeen</hi>, or Islamic insurgents. In August, a high-ranking Soviet
                    military delegation arrived in Kabul to assess the situation. U.S. officials
                    interpreted this mission as one last Soviet attempt to shore up the Taraki
                    regime, and also an opportunity to devise a military takeover. Regarding the
                    latter, most analysts in Washington believed that such a move remained possible
                    but unlikely.</p>
                <p>But this calculus was bound to change. Amin sensed the Soviet mission was
                    designed to strengthen Taraki at his expense. In response, forces loyal to Amin
                    executed Taraki in October—a move that infuriated Moscow, which began amassing
                    combat units along its border. At this juncture Washington was still unsure how
                    to interpret the Soviet maneuvers: was the Soviet Union planning a full takeover
                    or did it remain committed to preserving the April Revolution? Analysts remained
                    skeptical that Moscow would occupy the country given the political and economic
                    costs. By the winter of 1979, faced with mutinies and an uncertain leadership,
                    the Afghan Army was unable to provide basic security to the government against
                    the onslaught of Islamic fighters nearing Kabul. By that point the Soviets were
                    sending in motorized divisions and Special Forces. Washington demanded an
                    explanation, which the Soviets ignored. Finally, on Christmas Eve, the invasion
                    began. Soviet troops killed Amin and installed Babrak Karmal as the Soviet’s
                    puppet head of government.</p>
                <p>Although the Carter administration had closely watched this buildup from the
                    outset, its reaction following the invasion revealed that, until the end, it
                    clung to the hope that the Soviets would not invade, based on the unjustified
                    assumption that Moscow would conclude that the costs of invasion were too high.
                    In response, Carter wrote a sharply-worded letter to Brezhnev denouncing Soviet
                    aggression, and during his State of the Union address he announced his own
                    doctrine vowing to protect Middle Eastern oil supplies from encroaching Soviet
                    power. The administration also enacted economic sanctions and trade embargoes
                    against the Soviet Union, called for a boycott of the 1980 Moscow Olympics, and
                    stepped up its aid to the Afghan insurgents. In sum, these actions were
                    Washington’s collective attempt to make the Soviets’ “adventure” in Afghanistan
                    as painful and brief as possible. Instead, it took ten years of grinding
                    insurgency before Moscow finally withdrew, at the cost of millions of lives and
                    billions of dollars. In their wake, the Soviets left a shattered country in
                    which the Taliban, an Islamic fundamentalist group, seized control, later
                    providing <persName>Osama bin Laden</persName> with a training base from which
                    to launch terrorist operations worldwide.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
