<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1981–1988</title>
                <title type="short">1981–1988</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#foreword #u.s.-soviet-relations #central-america #south-atlantic"/>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword"
                ana="reagan-ronald haig-alexander-meigs shultz-george-pratt lebanon afghanistan falkland-islands-islas-malvinas arms-control-and-disarmament">
                <head>
                    <date from="1981" to="1988">1981–1988</date>: The Presidency of Ronald W.
                    Reagan</head>
                <p>The principal foreign policy framework for the <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName>
                    administration rejected acquiescence in the Cold War status quo that had emerged
                    during the Nixon, Ford, and Carter presidencies. Reagan objected to the implied
                    moral equivalency of détente, insisting instead on the superiority of
                    representative government, free-market capitalism, and freedom of conscience
                    over what he viewed as godless, collectivist, Communism. This more
                    confrontational approach eventually came to be labeled the “Reagan Doctrine,”
                    which advocated opposition to Communist-supported regimes wherever they existed,
                    as well as a willingness to directly challenge the Soviet Union on a variety of
                    fronts.</p>
                <p>Often referred to as “the great communicator,” Reagan utilized his rhetorical
                    skills to frame the Cold War contest as a fundamental clash between good and
                    evil. In his first inaugural address on January 20, 1981, the new President
                    contrasted the “enemies of freedom” as doomed to fail when faced with the “will
                    and moral courage of free men and women.” Later that year in an address at Notre
                    Dame University he stated that “the West won’t contain Communism, it will
                    transcend Communism.” In 1983, he famously characterized the Soviet Union as an
                    “evil empire.” In 1987, standing in front of the Berlin Wall constructed by the
                    East German communist regime a quarter-century earlier to stem the flow of East
                    Germans to the West, Reagan challenged the patron of the East German regime,
                    Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev, to “tear down this wall.” Reagan’s many
                    memorable public addresses served as an important tool to galvanize support for
                    policies that often sparked considerable controversy.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="reagan-admin.jpg" height="450px" width="301px"/>
                    <head>Arrival of General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev of the USSR for his first
                        meeting with President Reagan for the Geneva Summit at Fleur D’Eau in
                        Switzerland, November 19, 1985. (Ronald Reagan Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Reagan administration advocated a wide array of initiatives that heightened
                    confrontation with the U.S.S.R. and its allies. Reagan engineered a significant
                    increase in U.S. defense spending designed to modernize existing forces and
                    achieve technological advances the Soviet Union could not match. For example,
                    the administration advocated building a much larger navy with enhanced technical
                    capabilities, deployment of intermediate-range nuclear missiles in Europe,
                    development of terrain-hugging cruise missiles difficult both to detect and to
                    shoot down, and the Strategic Defense Initiative, which held out the prospect of
                    seizing the ultimate “high ground”—outer space—by preventing intercontinental
                    nuclear missile warheads from reaching their targets. During his two terms in
                    office, Reagan successfully advocated increasing the Defense Department budget
                    by 35%. The United States supported Afghan resistance organizations opposing the
                    Soviet-backed regime in Kabul, anti-communist forces in Angola, and the Contras
                    in Nicaragua. In 1983 American forces invaded Grenada to forestall installation
                    of a Marxist regime. The administration also greatly increased spending on the
                    U.S. Information Agency, especially Voice of America and Radio Free Europe/Radio
                    Liberty, signaling the importance placed on challenging Soviet ideology
                    throughout the world.</p>
                <p>Conversely, heightened tensions also led Reagan administration officials to
                    attempt conciliatory measures designed to reduce the threat of direct
                    confrontation, especially nuclear war. In 1982, Reagan broached the idea of
                    substantially decreasing nuclear weapon stockpiles, which eventually resulted in
                    the landmark Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty (START). The emergence of Mikhail
                    Gorbachev as the principal Soviet leader provided Reagan with a partner willing
                    to engage in substantive negotiations. A series of summit meetings ensued which
                    reduced tensions and produced concrete results, such as the 1987
                    Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty (INF) that eliminated the deployment of
                    theater-level nuclear missiles in Europe.</p>
                <p>The Reagan administration dealt with many other foreign policy issues as well.
                    Affairs in and around Southwest Asia continued to present multiple challenges,
                    including a Lebanese civil war, strained relations with Iran, and increasing
                    tensions after the bombing of Libya in retaliation for a state-sanctioned
                    terrorist attack in Berlin. A (third) joint communiqué with the Peoples’
                    Republic of China reiterated both parties’ commitment to improved relations,
                    while not resolving all issues related to Taiwan. Trade disputes with Japan
                    required constant attention. The United States had to determine what course to
                    steer amid hostilities between allies during the Falklands Crisis. A variety of
                    global issues also rose to prominence. After a decade of negotiation, the
                    administration opted not to support Senate ratification of a comprehensive Law
                    of the Sea treaty out of concerns about the potential for the internationalizing
                    of seabed mining operations and potential impingement on U.S. Navy prerogatives.
                    The United States increasingly promoted its enforcement preferences regarding
                    drug trafficking, resulting in a landmark 1988 treaty. It became apparent that
                    the AIDS crisis represented an international public health issue of consequence.
                    With the increasing rapidity of international communications, enhanced global
                    trade, and the rising world-wide movement of people, many issues previously
                    considered “domestic” became subject to diplomatic negotiation.</p>
                <p>The Secretary of State occupied a prominent position in Reagan’s approach to
                    creating and implementing foreign policy. <persName>Alexander Haig</persName>
                    first occupied the chair, but an inability to exert as much influence as he
                    desired caused him to resign after only 18 months in office. <persName>George
                        Shultz</persName> served as Secretary for the remainder of Reagan’s two
                    terms, and is generally regarded as an effective bureaucratic manager and
                    influential policy leader. <persName>Caspar Weinberger</persName> served as
                    Secretary of Defense for almost seven years and <persName>William
                        Casey</persName> as Director of Central Intelligence for six years. Both
                    played key roles in the foreign policy arena. The position of National Security
                    Adviser was downgraded somewhat during the Reagan administration. The six
                    individuals who occupied the position exercised relatively less influence than
                    predecessors in the Carter, Ford, or Nixon White House.</p>
                <p>Perhaps to an unusual degree, the accomplishments of this administration are
                    viewed in the light of events that occurred after Ronald Reagan left office in
                    January 1989. Within a year, the Berlin Wall fell, and by the end of 1991 the
                    Soviet Union had collapsed, signaling the end of the Cold War. Historians and
                    other analysts continue to debate the extent of their influence, but there is no
                    question that Ronald Reagan and his foreign policy advisers played key roles in
                    this remarkable turn of events.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="u.s.-soviet-relations"
                ana="reagan-ronald bush-george-h-w shultz-george-pratt baker-james-addison russia arms-control-and-disarmament nuclear-weapons">
                <head>U.S.-Soviet Relations, 1981–1991</head>
                <p>The period 1981–1991 witnessed a dramatic transformation in the relationship
                    between the United States and the Soviet Union. During these years the specter
                    of a nuclear war between the superpowers receded as the Cold War ended swiftly,
                    nearly entirely peacefully, and on U.S. terms.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="us-soviet.jpg" height="450px" width="298px"/>
                    <head>Gorbachev, Reagan, and Bush in New York City, December 1988. (Ronald
                        Reagan Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>When Ronald Reagan became president in January 1981, such outcomes were
                    inconceivable. The Soviets had invaded Afghanistan, causing President Jimmy
                    Carter to withdraw a strategic arms limitation treaty (SALT II) from Senate
                    ratification, boycott the 1980 Olympics Games in Moscow, and ban U.S. grain
                    sales to Moscow. Détente—or, “relaxation of tensions”—yielded to
                    confrontation.</p>
                <p>Committed to restoring U.S. strength and reversing strategic imbalances real and
                    perceived, President Reagan pursued a comprehensive modernization of U.S.
                    nuclear and conventional forces and attempted to roll back communism in South
                    America, Africa, and South Asia. At the same time, he wrote to Soviet leaders
                    Leonid Brezhnev, Yuri Andropov, and Konstantin Chernenko, imploring them to
                    alleviate Cold War tensions and negotiate arms reductions. He lifted the grain
                    embargo as a show of good faith, but the crackdown on Solidarity and declaration
                    of martial law in Poland in December 1981 led the President to declare further
                    economic sanctions against Moscow and curtail U.S.-Soviet academic
                    exchanges.</p>
                <p>Although formal nuclear arms control talks resumed, the relationship between
                    Washington and Moscow remained tense throughout Reagan’s first term. The
                    President spoke of leaving “Marxism-Leninism on the ash-heap of history;”
                    labeled the Soviet Union an “evil empire;” and introduced the Strategic Defense
                    Initiative (“Star Wars”), which Soviet leaders found highly threatening. The
                    nadir of this time period was the fall of 1983, when the Soviets shot down
                    Korean Airlines Flight 007 over the Sea of Japan, NATO deployed a new generation
                    of intermediate-range nuclear missiles in Western Europe, and Soviet negotiators
                    walked out of arms control talks in Geneva.</p>
                <p>Reagan’s top advisers disagreed about Soviet strategies. Secretary of Defense
                    Caspar Weinberger was deeply skeptical of arms control. Secretary of State
                    George Shultz believed that agreements would enhance U.S. security. The
                    President seldom intervened to resolve such disputes, yet he shared Shultz’s
                    enthusiasm for establishing a dialogue on human rights—in particular, the plight
                    of religious and political dissidents—as a central focus of U.S.-Soviet
                    negotiations. In January 1984, he delivered an eloquent speech, drafted by his
                    Soviet aide Jack Matlock, which imagined the human connections that fictional
                    American and Soviet couples could forge if left to their own devices.</p>
                <p>The March 1985 appointment of Mikhail Gorbachev as General Secretary of the
                    Communist Party of the Soviet Union provided Reagan with a viable negotiating
                    partner. A series of summits and high-profile encounters followed. At Reykjavik
                    in October 1986, Reagan and Gorbachev discussed the prospect of abolishing all
                    nuclear weapons. In December 1987 they signed the Intermediate-Range Nuclear
                    Forces Treaty, which eliminated an entire class of missiles. In May 1988,
                    standing in the middle of Red Square in Moscow, Reagan declared that the term
                    “evil empire” belonged to “another era.”</p>
                <p>Fearful that Reagan had moved too quickly to accept Gorbachev’s good intentions
                    and the feasibility of his economic and political agenda (“Perestroika” and
                    “Glasnost”), President George H.W. Bush ordered a strategic review to reassess
                    U.S. objectives toward the Soviet Union in the first months of 1989.
                    Simultaneously, Assistant to the President for National Security Affairs Brent
                    Scowcroft reiterated that the Cold War was not over, and Secretary of Defense
                    Richard Cheney publicly stated that Gorbachev’s reforms were destined to
                    fail.</p>
                <p>These statements aggravated Gorbachev, yet the pause did not derail the
                    constructive relationship between Washington and Moscow. Gorbachev accommodated
                    as revolutions occurred in Central and Eastern Europe that fall. After Bush met
                    with his Soviet counterpart off the coast of Malta in December 1989, one month
                    after the fall of the Berlin Wall, Gorbachev’s spokesman declared, “We buried
                    the Cold War at the bottom of the Mediterranean Sea.” In the months that
                    followed, Bush worked with the Soviet leader to allow for the peaceful
                    reunification of Germany within NATO, to sign the Conventional Forces in Europe
                    (CFE) treaty and the Strategic Arms Reduction Treaty (START), and to enable the
                    transition to democratically-elected governments in countries emerging from
                    Communist rule.</p>
                <p>The starkest example of the improvement in U.S.-Soviet relations came after
                    Saddam Hussein invaded Kuwait in August 1990. The Iraqi regime had previously
                    been a Soviet client and Gorbachev vigorously opposed the use of force to turn
                    back Saddam; yet Gorbachev did not stand in Washington’s way. Secretary of State
                    James Baker, who had been Reagan’s chief of staff in 1981, recalled the fall of
                    1990 as “the world turned upside down.”</p>
                <p>As Gorbachev’s economic reforms foundered and his political base crumbled in
                    1991, the Bush administration increasingly engaged Russian President Boris
                    Yeltsin. Yeltsin turned back a coup against Gorbachev in August 1991, but in
                    subsequent months consolidated authority over political and military
                    institutions, and increasingly supported Russian independence and dissolution of
                    the Soviet Union. On the evening of December 25, after speaking to Gorbachev on
                    the telephone, Bush addressed the nation from the Oval Office to announce that
                    the Soviet Union had ceased to exist.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="central-america"
                ana="reagan-ronald bush-george-h-w haig-alexander-meigs costa-rica cuba el-salvador guatemala honduras nicaragua panama narcotics organization-of-american-states">
                <head>Central America, 1981–1993</head>
                <p>Following his electoral victory in November 1980, President <persName>Ronald
                        Reagan</persName> amplified the concerns expressed by President Carter and
                    Congress about foreign support of Central American leftist guerrilla forces. In
                    February 1981, a month after the leftist <hi rend="italic">Farabundo Martí
                        National Liberation Front</hi> (FMLN) launched a major offensive against the
                    Salvadoran military, the Department of State issued a White Paper stating that
                    Cuba and other Communist countries had played a central role in the political
                    unification, military direction, and arming of the Salvadoran insurgents.
                    Secretary of State <persName>Alexander Haig</persName> accused the Sandinista
                    government of exporting terrorism to El Salvador and in April 1981, Reagan
                    terminated economic assistance to Nicaragua citing its involvement in supporting
                    Salvadoran rebels. After several failed diplomatic attempts to dissuade Managua
                    from supporting FMLN activities, Reagan opted to support a clandestine guerrilla
                    force to quash the Sandinista training and arming of Salvadoran guerillas. These
                    “Contras,” as in “counterrevolutionaries,” were primarily ex-Nicaraguan National
                    Guard members who had gathered in Honduran territory. The Contras launched their
                    first major attack against the Sandinistas in March 1982. In response, the
                    Sandinistas undertook a dramatic build-up of military manpower assisted by
                    Soviet and Cuban advisers and weaponry, mostly from the Soviet bloc.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="reagan-central-america.jpg" height="450px" width="296px"/>
                    <head>Supporters of the Nicaraguan Contra rebels outside a protest against the
                        Contras at Hurlburt Field, Florida.(Department of Defense)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Reagan’s efforts to strengthen the Contras met with opposition from a divided
                    Congress and resistance in Nicaragua. Concerns about the ultimate goals of the
                    Contras and the possibility of direct U.S. military involvement prompted
                    Representative <persName>Edward Boland</persName>, Chairman of the House
                    Intelligence Committee, to sponsor legislation in December 1982 that prohibited
                    the use of U.S. funds for the purpose of overthrowing the Sandinista government.
                    The bill, signed into law by Reagan later that December, allowed assistance to
                    the Contras for other purposes. Reagan continued to advocate increases in
                    support for the Contras. He addressed a joint session of Congress in April 1983
                    asserting that the Sandinista government presented a threat to Central America
                    and U.S. national security. American military exercises off the Nicaraguan coast
                    and the invasion of Grenada in October 1983 demonstrated Reagan’s commitment to
                    countering Communist threats in the region. Consequently, the Sandinistas
                    decided to participate in the Contadora peace negotiations that had begun in
                    January 1983 at the initiative of Mexico, Venezuela, Colombia, and Panama.
                    Claiming success in rolling back Communism in Grenada, Reagan gained
                    congressional increases of up to $100 million in non-military aid to the
                    Contras. In October 1984, however, Congress ended the support after learning
                    about the mining of Nicaraguan harbors and the destruction of an oil facility.
                    In November 1984 Reagan’s re-election and Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega’s
                    elevation to president in a controversial national election set the tone for
                    additional confrontation.</p>
                <p>Reagan redoubled his commitment to the Contras in his second term. In his 1985
                    State of the Union address he called them “freedom-fighters” who were risking
                    their lives to “defy Soviet-supported aggression.” In June 1985 Congress agreed
                    to $27 million in humanitarian aid for the Contras, but no military support.
                    Sandinista victories against the Contra fighters, heavy Presidential lobbying,
                    and an incursion into Honduran territory by Nicaraguan forces helped to sway
                    Congress into approving $100 million for the Contras, with seventy percent
                    allocated for military aid to be delivered in October 1986. However, the
                    Iran-Contra scandal broke the next month. The Tower Commission reported that
                    White House staff members had been using extralegal funds raised from arms sales
                    to Iran and foreign donors to arm the Contras prior to October 1986.</p>
                <p>Following the deaths of hundreds of thousands and a decade of economic
                    devastation, peace initiatives eventually gained traction in Central America.
                    Numerous efforts to establish a peace plan by regional leaders, the United
                    Nations, and the Organization of American States had continued in the wake of
                    the 1983 Contadora initiative. In August 1987, Central American leaders signed a
                    peace accord at Esquipulas, Guatemala that had been shaped and promoted
                    primarily by Costa Rican President Óscar Arias. The plan focused on
                    democratization and regional security, backed with a system of verification.
                    Meeting in Costa Rica in January 1988, Central American leaders cemented their
                    commitment to implement the Guatemala peace accord. Nicaraguan President Ortega
                    entered into negotiations with the Contras and the United States began to shift
                    aid to humanitarian purposes. Nicaragua implemented the accord and held
                    internationally supervised elections in 1990. <persName>Violeta
                        Chamorro</persName>, former member of the revolutionary Provisional
                    Government and widow of <persName>Pedro Joaquín Chamorro</persName>, the
                    journalist and hero of the opposition who had been slain in 1978, was elected
                    president and the Contras disbanded. The civil war in El Salvador lasted until
                    1991, when the FMLN reached a peace accord with the Salvadoran Government under
                    United Nations supervision. In Guatemala, fighting between leftist groups and
                    the military continued into the mid-1990s.</p>
                <p>Washington continued to perceive threats in Central America after the end of the
                    Cold War. On December 20, 1989, President <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName>
                    dispatched over twenty thousand troops to invade Panama and arrest its head of
                    state, <persName>Manuel Noriega</persName>. Noriega had nullified a presidential
                    election won by opposition candidate <persName>Guillermo Endara</persName> that
                    May. In addition, Bush had become opposed to Noriega's continued leadership of
                    Panama due to Noriega’s connections with drug smuggling and money laundering, as
                    well as the declining security situation around the Panama Canal. In the months
                    leading up to the invasion, the Bush administration implemented economic
                    sanctions and increased local troop levels. The Panamanian legislature declared
                    that a state of war existed with the United States on December 15 due to the
                    escalating tension between the two countries. A U.S. serviceman was killed in
                    Panama the following day; this and other events, including the harassment of a
                    U.S. officer and his wife, precipitated U.S. action. Code-named Operation Just
                    Cause, the fighting lasted for five days. After taking refuge in the Vatican
                    Embassy, Noriega eventually surrendered to U.S. authorities and Endara regained
                    his presidency. Noriega was tried in a United States court and convicted on
                    charges of drug trafficking, money laundering, and racketeering.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="lebanon"
                ana="reagan-ronald haig-alexander-meigs shultz-george-pratt israel lebanon syria palestine peace military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal terrorism arab-israeli-dispute">
                <head>The Reagan Administration and Lebanon, 1981–1984</head>
                <p>From 1981 onward, the Reagan administration feared that conflict between Lebanese
                    factions backed by Syria and Israel, along with clashes between Israel and the
                    Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), could escalate into an Arab-Israeli
                    war. Yet American policymakers differed over how to prevent such a conflict,
                    especially over whether to commit troops for that purpose. Following Israel’s
                    1982 invasion of Lebanon, the advocates of military intervention won out. But by
                    1984, terrorist attacks, a lack of diplomatic progress, and congressional
                    opposition led President <persName>Ronald Reagan</persName> to withdraw U.S.
                    forces from Lebanon.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="lebanon.jpg" height="350px" width="533px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Marines on patrol in Beirut, April 1983. (Department of
                        Defense)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>In April 1981, the Israeli Air Force attacked Syrian forces in Lebanon to prevent
                    them from seizing the strategic Sannin ridge. Syria responded by deploying
                    surface-to-air missiles into the Biqa‘ Valley, threatening Israel’s ability to
                    monitor PLO forces in Lebanon. To avert war, Reagan sent emissary
                        <persName>Philip Habib</persName> to the Middle East, but he failed to
                    persuade the Syrians to withdraw the missiles. When fighting escalated between
                    Israel and the PLO that July, the Reagan administration feared that Israel would
                    invade Lebanon. Ultimately, Habib managed to negotiate a de facto ceasefire
                    between Israel and the PLO.</p>
                <p>The ceasefire, however, merely postponed a larger crisis. The Lebanese remained
                    at odds, Syria refused to withdraw its missiles, and Israel chafed under the
                    restrictions of the ceasefire, which allowed the PLO to strengthen itself and
                    did not prevent terrorist attacks from the West Bank and Gaza Strip or against
                    Israeli and Jewish targets in Europe. In London on June 3, 1982, Palestinian
                    assailants shot Shlomo Argov, Israel’s ambassador to the United Kingdom. The
                    Israel Defense Forces (IDF) invaded Lebanon on June 6.</p>
                <p>The Reagan administration was divided over how to respond to Israel’s invasion.
                    Secretary of State <persName>Alexander Haig</persName> argued that the United
                    States should not pressure Israel to withdraw without demanding that the PLO and
                    Syria do likewise. Secretary of Defense <persName>Caspar Weinberger</persName>,
                    Vice President <persName>George Bush</persName>, and National Security Advisor
                        <persName>William Clark</persName> wanted the IDF to withdraw immediately
                    and to sanction Israel if they did not. The debate sharpened when the IDF
                    destroyed Syria’s missiles in the Biqa‘ on June 9, raising the specter of a
                    wider war. President Reagan sent Habib to Israel to demand a ceasefire. The IDF
                    halted its advance into the Biqa‘ but continued to the outskirts of
                    PLO-controlled West Beirut.</p>
                <p>With the Israeli-Syrian confrontation defused, Reagan adopted Haig’s strategy of
                    helping the Lebanese Government take over West Beirut, then negotiating Israeli
                    and Syrian withdrawal. By July, the PLO informed Habib that they would leave
                    Beirut if an international force deployed to protect Palestinian civilians.
                    Against Weinberger’s advice, Reagan agreed to contribute Marines to a
                    multinational force (MNF), alongside French and Italian troops. However, the
                    Palestinian withdrawal did not begin until August 21. The United States could
                    not convince any Arab country to receive all PLO fighters from Beirut; they were
                    ultimately dispersed to several states. Initially, the Israelis refused to let
                    the MNF deploy until the PLO left, instead intensifying their attacks on Beirut.
                    The PLO completed its withdrawal by September 1. Though the MNF was supposed to
                    remain for thirty days, Weinberger announced that the Marines would leave on
                    September 10.</p>
                <p>On September 14, Lebanese President-elect <persName>Bashir Gemayel</persName>,
                    whose election had been backed by the Israelis, was assassinated. Citing a need
                    to prevent civil disorder, the IDF entered West Beirut. By September 18, it
                    became clear that the Israelis had allowed Maronite militiamen to enter the
                    Sabra and Shatilla camps and massacre Palestinian civilians. An international
                    outcry ensued, and Reagan decided to commit Marines to a new MNF. On October 28,
                    Reagan signed National Security Decision Directive (NSDD) 64, calling for the
                    United States to work toward the withdrawal of foreign forces from Lebanon, help
                    rebuild the Lebanese Army, and contribute to an expanded MNF if necessary. In
                    April–May 1983, Secretary of State George Shultz helped Israel and Lebanon
                    negotiate an agreement that ended the hostilities between the two countries and
                    provided a basis for normal relations once Israel withdrew. For Israel to
                    withdraw, however, Syrian and Palestinian forces would also need to leave
                    Lebanon. </p>
                <p>The Israeli-Lebanese agreement was opposed by Syrian President <persName>Hafiz
                        al-Asad</persName>, who claimed that it would enable Israel to dominate
                    Lebanon. Asad refused to remove his troops and encouraged Lebanese opposition to
                    President <persName>Amin Gemayel</persName>. Meanwhile, the Israelis, facing
                    guerilla attacks in the Shuf, decided that they would unilaterally withdraw from
                    the area.</p>
                <p>The Reagan administration feared that an Israeli pullback could lead to the
                    partition of Lebanon and expose the MNF to shelling from the Shuf. New emissary
                        <persName>Robert McFarlane</persName> attempted to soften Syria’s position,
                    delay Israeli withdrawal, and help Gemayel and his opponents reconcile, but
                    without success. The IDF pulled back on September 3, and fighting erupted
                    between Maronite Lebanese Forces and pro-Syrian militias led by <persName>Walid
                        Jumblatt’s</persName> Popular Socialist Party. To prevent Lebanese troops
                    from intervening, Jumblatt and his allies attacked them as well, leading
                    McFarlane to warn that they might reach Beirut and topple Gemayel’s
                    government.</p>
                <p>Reagan responded by authorizing the Marines to engage in “aggressive
                    self-defense,” dispatching the battleship <hi rend="italic">New Jersey</hi>to
                    Lebanon, and authorizing naval gunfire and airstrikes to prevent hostile forces
                    from seizing Suq al-Gharb, which overlooked the Marine barracks. But by the time
                    a ceasefire took hold on September 25, the fighting had provoked significant
                    opposition to Reagan’s Lebanon policy. On September 29, Congress passed
                    legislation invoking the War Powers Act and authorizing the Marines to remain in
                    Lebanon for 18 months, the first time constraint placed on their presence.
                    Weinberger now proposed withdrawing U.S. forces offshore.</p>
                <p>On October 23, suicide bombers attacked the barracks of the U.S. and French
                    contingents of the MNF, killing 241 American servicemen. The administration
                    believed that the bombings, like the attack on the U.S. Embassy in Beirut that
                    April, were perpetrated by Shi‘i militants linked to Syria’s ally Iran. Reagan
                    responded by adopting a tough policy championed by Shultz and McFarlane, now
                    National Security Advisor. On October 28, he signed NSDD 111, which called for
                    broadening strategic cooperation with Israel and Arab opponents of Syria,
                    reducing Syrian influence over Lebanon’s Druze and Shi‘a, and expanded rules of
                    engagement regarding naval and air support for the Lebanese Army.</p>
                <p>The implementation of NSDD 111, however, was marred by disagreements between
                    Reagan’s advisors, Syrian intransigence, a lack of progress toward Lebanese
                    reconciliation, and major public relations setbacks. Though Reagan publicly
                    proclaimed that the perpetrators of the October 23 bombings “must be dealt
                    justice,” U.S. forces did not join their French counterparts in attacking an
                    Iranian Revolutionary Guards barrack in the Biqa‘ that November. McFarlane later
                    contended that Reagan had authorized U.S. participation in the strikes, but
                    Weinberger refused to follow through on his order. On December 4, the Syrians
                    shot down two U.S. planes, and held one of the pilots, Lt. Robert Goodman,
                    prisoner until releasing him to Democratic presidential candidate Jesse Jackson.
                    Even more damaging to the administration’s prestige were press leaks regarding
                    the Department of Defense’s Long Commission report, which harshly criticized the
                    Marines’ deployment. On February 1, 1984, amidst mounting congressional
                    criticism, Reagan approved the idea of redeploying the Marines but did not set a
                    date for doing so. Almost immediately afterward, however, pro-Syrian militias
                    overran West Beirut, and on February 7, Reagan announced that the Marines would
                    withdraw offshore.</p>
                <p>Reagan’s decision to withdraw the Marines remains controversial. Supporters argue
                    that it did not make sense to sacrifice American lives and resources to help
                    resolve a conflict where the parties involved showed little interest in working
                    toward U.S. goals. Critics, however, claim that Reagan failed to stand firm
                    against terrorism and demonstrated that the United States was an undependable
                    ally.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="south-atlantic"
                ana="reagan-ronald haig-alexander-meigs united-kingdom argentina falkland-islands-islas-malvinas south-georgia-and-the-south-sandwich-islands warfare">
                <head>Crisis in the South Atlantic: The Reagan Administration and the
                    Anglo-Argentine War of 1982</head>
                <p>Early on the morning of April 2, 1982, Argentine military forces landed on the
                    Falkland Islands (Spanish: <hi rend="italic">Islas Malvinas</hi>) in the
                    southern Atlantic Ocean. Argentina had maintained a claim to the islands dating
                    to its independence from Spain in 1816; beginning in 1833, however, the United
                    Kingdom had established a presence on the islands and developed them as a
                    British colony. The issue of the islands’ future sovereignty had been the
                    subject of intermittent and inconclusive negotiations between the two countries
                    since the 1960s. Within hours of the invasion, the Argentines overwhelmed the
                    small British garrison, forcing its surrender. In subsequent days, the military
                    junta led by General Leopoldo Galtieri formalized Argentine control over the
                    territory (as well as over other British South Atlantic possessions in South
                    Georgia and the South Sandwich Islands) and expelled the British administration.
                    British Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher condemned the landings as an act of
                    aggression against the wishes of the islands’ inhabitants who, she argued,
                    favored overwhelmingly continued association with the United Kingdom. She
                    ordered the deployment of a naval task force to the region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="falklands.jpg" height="450px" width="296px"/>
                    <head>Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of England is welcomed by Secretary of
                        State Alexander Haig upon arrival for a visit to the United States.
                        (Department of Defense)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Amidst a situation that initially struck some U.S. policy makers as an
                    anachronistic “Gilbert and Sullivan battle,” this crisis presented the Ronald
                    Reagan administration with a formidable foreign policy dilemma. Although the
                    United States had proclaimed its neutrality on the question of the islands’
                    sovereignty since the mid-nineteenth century, the clash between Argentina and
                    the United Kingdom created conflicts among Reagan’s foreign policy team.
                    Ambassador to the United Nations Jeane Kirkpatrick did not want to alienate the
                    Argentines, regarded by the administration as key partners in halting the
                    perceived expansion of Soviet-directed communist influence in the Western
                    Hemisphere. Secretary of Defense Caspar Weinberger argued strongly to support
                    the British. The United Kingdom was one of Washington’s closest allies and
                    Weinberger feared the administration’s failure to vigorously support the
                    Thatcher government would tacitly condone the Argentines’ actions and encourage
                    other countries to employ similarly aggressive methods. Secretary of State
                    Alexander M. Haig, Jr., argued that Cuba and the Soviet Union stood poised to
                    exploit the crisis and expand their influence in South America if the United
                    States failed to prevent an escalation of hostilities. In such an environment,
                    he advocated an even-handed “honest broker” approach toward both sides.</p>
                <p>Containing the crisis and preserving Washington’s relationships with both
                    governments hinged upon the conclusion of a negotiated settlement. Having failed
                    to persuade Galtieri to refrain from landing on the islands, after much internal
                    debate, Reagan dispatched Haig to the United Kingdom and Argentina for talks
                    with Thatcher and Galtieri on April 7. The backdrop to Haig’s mission was
                    ominous: in addition to an increasingly bellicose war of words between the
                    Argentine and British governments, Britain’s mounting military buildup in the
                    region raised the possibility of actual hostilities.</p>
                <p>Haig shuttled between London and Buenos Aires for two rounds of intensive
                    discussions over the next fortnight, but failed to broker a peaceful solution.
                    Supported by most Britons, Thatcher insisted on a return to the <hi
                        rend="italic">status quo ante</hi>. Any other result would, she believed,
                    imply moral equivalence between the British and Argentine positions, validate
                    Argentina’s aggression, and diminish the islanders’ right to self-determination.
                    Moreover, Thatcher stipulated that no negotiation over sovereignty could occur
                    until Argentine forces withdrew. The Argentine Junta held its own suspicions
                    about U.S. impartiality, refused to make concessions that might prejudice its
                    claims to sovereignty over the islands, and viewed the dispute as a matter
                    national honor. A series of detailed proposals and counterproposals failed to
                    break the diplomatic impasse. Following a successful British operation to retake
                    South Georgia and with growing indications of the Thatcher government’s
                    readiness to seek a military solution, Argentina officially rejected Haig’s
                    final peace proposal on April 29.</p>
                <p>The following day, after a meeting of the National Security Council, Haig
                    announced the breakdown of negotiations, administration support for the British
                    position, and the suspension of military and economic aid to Argentina. On May
                    5, Weinberger met with British Defense Secretary John Nott to finalize
                    arrangements for the fulfillment of British requests for military materiel as
                    part of a broad range of political, diplomatic, and military measures undertaken
                    by the United States in support of the Thatcher government.</p>
                <p>Despite this public tilt toward the British position, the Reagan administration
                    continued its efforts to control the conflict and to mitigate the fighting’s
                    impact upon U.S. interests. Indeed, most Latin American countries viewed U.S.
                    support for Britain as a betrayal of the hemispheric solidarity embodied in the
                    1947 Inter-American Treaty of Reciprocal Assistance (the Rio Treaty). In
                    addition to offering broad support for peace initiatives undertaken by the
                    Peruvian president and U.N. General Secretary Javier Pérez de Cuéllar, the
                    administration pressed the belligerents to draw down their military engagement.
                    Ambassador-at-Large General Vernon Walters met secretly with the Argentine
                    Junta, while Reagan attempted to personally intercede with Prime Minister
                    Thatcher. Over the course of two tense telephone conversations in late May,
                    Reagan failed to persuade Thatcher to refrain from “scoring total victory” in
                    the South Atlantic in order to avoid toppling the Junta.</p>
                <p>British victory in the field brought an end to the 1982 Falklands/Malvinas
                    crisis. Following a three-week ground campaign, British forces re-captured the
                    islands’ capital, Port Stanley, on June 14, forcing the surrender of all
                    Argentine troops. Three days later, Galtieri resigned as Argentine president,
                    the first step in the eventual return of civilian government to Argentina.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="china-communique"
                ana="reagan-ronald bush-george-h-w east-asia-and-pacific china taiwan arms-transfers">
                <head>The August 17, 1982 U.S.-China Communiqué on Arms Sales to Taiwan</head>
                <p>On August 17, 1982, after eight months of contentious negotiations, the United
                    States and the People’s Republic of China (PRC) issued the United States-China
                    Joint Communiqué on United States Arms Sales to Taiwan, more commonly known as
                    the August 17 Communiqué. The Communiqué addressed the troublesome issue of U.S.
                    arms sales to Taiwan in an effort to prevent the collapse of U.S.–PRC
                    relations.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="china-communique-1982.jpg" height="350px" width="515px"/>
                    <head>President and Nancy Reagan at the Great Wall of China, April 1984. (Ronald
                        Reagan Presidential Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The administration of President Jimmy Carter formally normalized relations with
                    the People’s Republic of China on January 1, 1979, but the perpetually divisive
                    issue of U.S. arms sales to Taiwan remained unresolved. On the one hand,
                    officials in the Carter administration and the incoming administration of
                    President Ronald Reagan, along with majorities in Congress, agreed that the
                    United States should not end arms sales to Taiwan. On the other hand, PRC
                    officials insisted that the continuation of such sales was a violation of their
                    country’s sovereignty and justification for downgrading relations with the
                    United States. Making matters more contentious, the Taiwan Relations Act of
                    April 1979 required the United States to continue to sell defensive arms to
                    Taiwan; PRC officials saw the law as a direct challenge to the normalization
                    agreement finalized a few months earlier. U.S. and PRC officials both recognized
                    that if the two sides could not establish a <hi rend="italic">modus vivendi</hi>
                    on the future of U.S. arms sales, U.S.–PRC relations could retrogress or
                    collapse entirely.</p>
                <p>In January 1982, the United States and the People’s Republic of China commenced
                    official discussions on U.S. arms sales to Taiwan. As the two sides began
                    exchanging drafts of a potential communiqué, two major disagreements were
                    immediately apparent. The first area of discord was the nature of future U.S.
                    arms sales to Taiwan. The People’s Republic of China insisted that the United
                    States eventually, and relatively quickly, end all arms sales. While the Reagan
                    administration was prepared to place qualitative and quantitative limits on its
                    future arms sales, and gradually to reduce those sales over time, it was
                    unwilling to commit itself to the termination of such transactions. The second
                    dispute centered on the nature of PRC policy toward Taiwan. The Reagan
                    administration stated that arms sales reductions were contingent on a PRC policy
                    of maintaining peaceful relations with Taiwan. PRC officials, however, refused
                    to make any official commitments to the United States on their future policy
                    toward Taiwan, arguing that doing so would be a challenge to their country’s
                    sovereignty.</p>
                <p>In May 1982, with negotiations largely stalled due to these significant
                    disagreements, Reagan suggested that Vice President George H.W. Bush travel to
                    Beijing to meet with high-level officials. Bush was not traveling to China to
                    engage in detailed communiqué negotiations, but U.S. officials hoped that his
                    visit would, nonetheless, jumpstart the languishing talks and convince PRC
                    officials that the United States was committed to reaching an agreement. Bush
                    met with several high-level Chinese officials, including the leader of the
                    People’s Republic of China, Deng Xiaoping, and discussed a wide range of issues
                    affecting U.S.–PRC relations. In addition, during Bush’s trip the White House
                    publicized three letters from President Reagan—to Deng, Premier Zhao Ziyang, and
                    Communist Party Chairman Hu Yaobang—that stressed the importance of U.S.–PRC
                    relations, recognized the significance of the People’s Republic of China’s
                    peaceful approach to the Taiwan issue, and reinforced Reagan’s willingness to
                    reduce U.S. arms sales to Taiwan if the People’s Republic of China maintained
                    its peaceful policy. The visit marked a turning point in the communiqué
                    negotiations, largely because it confirmed the personal involvement of both Deng
                    and Reagan in the ongoing talks. Both leaders, it was clear, wanted and
                    anticipated a speedy and successful conclusion to the communiqué
                    negotiations.</p>
                <p>By the end of July, after several weeks of intense internal discussions in both
                    Washington and Beijing, U.S. and PRC officials had worked out many of the
                    communiqué’s most vexing problems. Chinese officials dropped their insistence
                    that the United States agree to a “date certain” for the termination of all arms
                    sales to Taiwan and the two sides found agreeable language that combined the
                    People’s Republic of China’s commitment to maintaining peaceful relations toward
                    Taiwan with the United States’ respect for China’s sovereignty.</p>
                <p>On August 17, 1982, the People’s Republic of China and United States announced
                    the agreement of the Communiqué. Agreement on the Communiqué did not, however,
                    signal consensus between the United States and the People’s Republic of China on
                    the issue of arms sales to Taiwan. In describing it, U.S. and PRC officials
                    purposefully highlighted different aspects of the Communiqué and offered
                    significantly different interpretations of the language. U.S. officials, for
                    example, focused on the correlation between reduction of arms sales to Taiwan
                    and the People’s Republic of China’s peaceful policy toward Taiwan. PRC
                    officials chose instead to focus on the U.S. pledges to respect PRC sovereignty
                    and gradually reduce arms sales to Taiwan. The malleability of the Communiqué
                    was intentional and, in fact, allowed it to be successful. Though the Communiqué
                    did not put an end to differences over U.S. arms sales to Taiwan, U.S. and PRC
                    officials were able to embrace it as it provided each nation a reasonable
                    platform from which to pursue its own policy while simultaneously challenging
                    that of the other side. This understanding, however tenuous, allowed the United
                    States and the People’s Republic of China to move beyond the divisive and
                    restrictive issue of arms sales to Taiwan and take up other bilateral
                    issues.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
