<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1989–1992</title>
                <title type="short">1989–1992</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#foreword #fall-of-communism #collapse-soviet-union #breakup-yugoslavia #tiananmen-square #gulf-war #madrid-conference"
                />
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword"
                ana="bush-george-h-w baker-james-addison rice-condoleezza russia">
                <head>
                    <date from="1989" to="1992">1989–1992</date>: The Presidency of George H.W.
                    Bush</head>
                <p>The collapse of the <placeName>Soviet Union</placeName> in 1991 created a massive
                    shift in the international balance of power and left the United States as the
                    sole remaining superpower.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="ghw-bush.jpg" height="450px" width="315px"/>
                    <head>President Bush examines papers with Sec. Cheney and Gen. Scowcroft in the
                        Oval Office of the White House. (George Bush Presidential Library and
                        Museum)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>President George H.W. Bush took the oath of office with foreign policy on his
                    mind. He brought to the White House strong credentials: Congressman, Ambassador
                    to the United Nations, Permanent Representative to the People’s Republic of
                    China, Director of the Central Intelligence Agency, and Vice President of the
                    United States. He started his career in military service in 1942, enlisting in
                    the Navy on his 18th birthday and earning a commission as an ensign several days
                    before his 19th birthday. He later served as a torpedo bomber pilot, earning a
                    Distinguished Flying Cross; he was the last veteran of World War II to serve as
                    president.</p>
                <p>Patrician and self-effacing, President Bush engaged foreign dignitaries with
                    ease. He already knew most world leaders on a first-name basis. Former President
                    Ronald Reagan’s physical grace and soaring rhetoric led to unkind comparisons in
                    the lead-up to the 1988 campaign. The October 19, 1987, edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">Newsweek </hi>featured Bush on the cover with the caption:
                    “Fighting the ‘Wimp Factor.’” Whether from this portrayal of him or merely his
                    highly competitive instincts, Bush overwhelmed his opponents in Republican
                    primary debates and ran a highly aggressive general election campaign against
                    Massachusetts Governor Michael Dukakis. While a majority of Americans voted for
                    him, Bush was a Burkean conservative in a burgeoning Information Age, and he did
                    not always connect with the average man on the street.</p>
                <p>Democrats who comprised a majority in the U.S. House of Representatives and the
                    U.S. Senate bore lingering resentment from the 1988 campaign, while
                    conservatives such as House Minority Whip Newt Gingrich recalled Bush’s track
                    record as a political moderate. There were few coattails to President Bush’s
                    electoral triumph, in other words, and neither a “Bush Revolution” in 1988 nor a
                    class of “Bush Democrats” in the 101st Congress. In contrast, the so-called
                    foreign policy establishment held him in high regard. Former Assistant to the
                    President for National Security Affairs Zbigniew Brzezinski endorsed him for
                    president—even though Brzezinski had mentored most of Bush’s opponent’s foreign
                    policy advisers.</p>
                <p>President Bush faced additional constraints. The massive tax cuts he himself had
                    termed “voodoo economics” in the 1980 Republican primary had stimulated the U.S.
                    economy but failed to increase tax revenues, while the 1985 Gramm-Rudman Deficit
                    Reduction Act triggered automatic spending cuts. Concern over the national debt
                    was the chief substantive issue of the 1988 campaign, and Bush had vowed to
                    reduce it without raising taxes. Inflation was tame and unemployment relatively
                    low, yet the transition to a post-industrial economy and the influx of
                    high-technology consumer products from Japan raised the specter of a decline in
                    America’s economic and technological leadership. The shock of the October 1987
                    stock market crash persisted, coming as it did in a year of two bestsellers,
                    Paul Kennedy’s <hi rend="italic">The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers</hi> and
                    Allan Bloom’s <hi rend="italic">Closing of the American Mind</hi>, which
                    predicted a gloomy future for the West.</p>
                <p>Bush rejected such pessimism, as it contrasted with developments in the
                    international political system. Soviet General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev’s
                    comprehensive reforms spoke to mankind’s universal yearning to live in an open
                    society. Chinese Chairman Deng Xiaoping’s economic reforms demonstrated the
                    intellectual bankruptcy of communism. The ascent of democratic governments in
                    the Philippines and Chile indicated that right-wing authoritarian regimes—as
                    opposed to left-wing totalitarian ones—could in fact evolve into democracies.
                    And the stirrings of liberty in Poland and Hungary offered tremendous
                    opportunity to pierce the Iron Curtain.</p>
                <p>Bush appointed as Secretary of State his best friend, James A. Baker, who in turn
                    chose career foreign service officer Lawrence Eagleburger as his deputy. Another
                    close associate, Lieutenant General Brent Scowcroft, became Assistant to the
                    President for National Security Affairs, a position he had held in the
                    administration of President Gerald Ford. Scowcroft chose as his deputy Robert
                    Gates, a career employee of the Central Intelligence Agency who had served on
                    the National Security Council (NSC) under both Scowcroft and Brzezinski. Yet
                    another veteran of the Ford administration, Congressman Richard Cheney, became
                    Secretary of Defense after the Tower nomination debacle. With the addition of
                    General Colin Powell, Reagan’s last national security adviser who became
                    Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff in October 1989, these individuals formed
                    the core of the Bush foreign policy team and would all serve in some capacity
                    for the entirety of the administration. They, in turn, assembled a roster of
                    staffers who prided themselves on working in relative harmony with
                    interdepartmental counterparts. These included Robert Blackwill, Condoleezza
                    Rice, Philip Zelikow, Robert Hutchings, and Richard Haass at the NSC; Robert
                    Zoellick, Dennis Ross, Robert Kimmett, and William Burns at the Department of
                    State; and Paul Wolfowitz at the Department of Defense.</p>
                <p>Presiding over this operation, Bush valued teamwork and loyalty. He extolled
                    prudence and pragmatism, and did not entertain romantic visions such as a shield
                    that could make nuclear weapons obsolete. Over time, he and his administration
                    would strive to build what he termed in his September 11, 1991, address before a
                    joint session of congress on the Persian Gulf Crisis and federal budget deficit,
                    a “new world order,” one “freer from the threat of terror, stronger in the
                    pursuit of justice, and more secure in the quest for peace.”</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="apartheid" ana="south-africa">
                <head>The End of Apartheid</head>
                <p>Apartheid, the Afrikaans name given by the white-ruled <placeName>South
                        Africa</placeName>’s Nationalist Party in 1948 to the country’s harsh,
                    institutionalized system of racial segregation, came to an end in the early
                    1990s in a series of steps that led to the formation of a democratic government
                    in 1994. Years of violent internal protest, weakening white commitment,
                    international economic and cultural sanctions, economic struggles, and the end
                    of the Cold War brought down white minority rule in Pretoria. U.S. policy toward
                    the regime underwent a gradual but complete transformation that played an
                    important conflicting role in Apartheid’s initial survival and eventual
                    downfall.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="apartheid.jpg" height="450px" width="317px"/>
                    <head>F.W. de Klerk shakes hands with Nelson Mandela at the end of the talks
                        between the Government and anti-apartheid groups to end white-minority rule.
                        (AP Photo/ John Parkin)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Although many of the segregationist policies dated back to the early decades of
                    the twentieth century, it was the election of the Nationalist Party in 1948 that
                    marked the beginning of legalized racism’s harshest features called Apartheid.
                    The Cold War then was in its early stages. U.S. President Harry Truman’s
                    foremost foreign policy goal was to limit Soviet expansion. Despite supporting a
                    domestic civil rights agenda to further the rights of black people in the United
                    States, the Truman Administration chose not to protest the anti-communist South
                    African government’s system of Apartheid in an effort to maintain an ally
                    against the Soviet Union in southern Africa. This set the stage for successive
                    administrations to quietly support the Apartheid regime as a stalwart ally
                    against the spread of communism.</p>
                <p>Inside South Africa, riots, boycotts, and protests by black South Africans
                    against white rule had occurred since the inception of independent white rule in
                    1910. Opposition intensified when the Nationalist Party, assuming power in 1948,
                    effectively blocked all legal and non-violent means of political protest by
                    non-whites. The African National Congress (ANC) and its offshoot, the Pan
                    Africanist Congress (PAC), both of which envisioned a vastly different form of
                    government based on majority rule, were outlawed in 1960 and many of its leaders
                    imprisoned. The most famous prisoner was a leader of the ANC, <persName>Nelson
                        Mandela</persName>, who had become a symbol of the anti-Apartheid struggle.
                    While Mandela and many political prisoners remained incarcerated in South
                    Africa, other anti-Apartheid leaders fled South Africa and set up headquarters
                    in a succession of supportive, independent African countries, including Guinea,
                    Tanzania, Zambia, and neighboring Mozambique where they continued the fight to
                    end Apartheid. It was not until the 1980s, however, that this turmoil
                    effectively cost the South African state significant losses in revenue,
                    security, and international reputation.</p>
                <p>The international community had begun to take notice of the brutality of the
                    Apartheid regime after white South African police opened fire on unarmed black
                    protesters in the town of Sharpeville in 1960, killing 69 people and wounding
                    186 others. The United Nations led the call for sanctions against the South
                    African Government. Fearful of losing friends in Africa as de-colonization
                    transformed the continent, powerful members of the Security Council, including
                    Great Britain, France, and the United States, succeeded in watering down the
                    proposals. However, by the late 1970s, grassroots movements in Europe and the
                    United States succeeded in pressuring their governments into imposing economic
                    and cultural sanctions on Pretoria. After the U.S. Congress passed the
                    Comprehensive Anti-Apartheid Act in 1986, many large multinational companies
                    withdrew from South Africa. By the late 1980s, the South African economy was
                    struggling with the effects of the internal and external boycotts as well as the
                    burden of its military commitment in occupying Namibia.</p>
                <p>Defenders of the Apartheid regime, both inside and outside South Africa, had
                    promoted it as a bulwark against communism. However, the end of the Cold War
                    rendered this argument obsolete. South Africa had illegally occupied neighboring
                    Namibia at the end of World War II, and since the mid-1970s, Pretoria had used
                    it as a base to fight the communist party in Angola. The United States had even
                    supported the South African Defense Force’s efforts in Angola. In the 1980s,
                    hard-line anti-communists in Washington continued to promote relations with the
                    Apartheid government despite economic sanctions levied by the U.S. Congress.
                    However, the relaxation of Cold War tensions led to negotiations to settle the
                    Cold War conflict in Angola. Pretoria’s economic struggles gave the Apartheid
                    leaders strong incentive to participate. When South Africa reached a
                    multilateral agreement in 1988 to end its occupation of Namibia in return for a
                    Cuban withdrawal from Angola, even the most ardent anti-communists in the United
                    States lost their justification for support of the Apartheid regime.</p>
                <p>The effects of the internal unrest and international condemnation led to dramatic
                    changes beginning in 1989. South African Prime Minister <persName>P.W.
                        Botha</persName> resigned after it became clear that he had lost the faith
                    of the ruling National Party (NP) for his failure to bring order to the country.
                    His successor, <persName>F W de Klerk</persName>, in a move that surprised
                    observers, announced in his opening address to Parliament in February 1990 that
                    he was lifting the ban on the ANC and other black liberation parties, allowing
                    freedom of the press, and releasing political prisoners. The country waited in
                    anticipation for the release of Nelson Mandela who walked out of prison after 27
                    years on February 11, 1990.</p>
                <p>The impact of Mandela’s release reverberated throughout South Africa and the
                    world. After speaking to throngs of supporters in Cape Town where he pledged to
                    continue the struggle, but advocated peaceful change, Mandela took his message
                    to the international media. He embarked on a world tour culminating in a visit
                    to the United States where he spoke before a joint session of Congress.</p>
                <p>After Prime Minister de Klerk agreed to democratic elections for the country, the
                    United States lifted sanctions and increased foreign aid, and many of the U.S.
                    companies who disinvested in the 1980s returned with new investments and joint
                    ventures. In April 1994, <persName>Nelson Mandela</persName> was elected as
                    South Africa’s first black president.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="apec" ana="clinton-bill australia">
                <head>Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC), <date when="1989">1989</date>
                </head>
                <p>Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation, or APEC, was formed in 1989 in Australia as an
                    informal forum in which member nations could discuss free trade and economic
                    cooperation along the Pacific Rim. From the perspective of the United States, it
                    has been a crucial institution for economic engagement within the region.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="apec.jpg" height="450px" width="284px"/>
                    <head>On the red carpet at the garden of the Osaka Guest House, leaders of the
                        18-nation Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation forum line up for a group photo
                        session. (AP Photo/Koji Sasahara)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>APEC was one of many multilateral trade organizations that emerged in the
                    post-Cold War era. As the bipolarity of the Cold War came to an end, the new
                    world order was marked in part by increasing globalization and the growth of
                    regional trading blocs. The <placeName>United States</placeName> took a leading
                    role in defining this new world order in which free trade and multilateral
                    organizations played an essential role. Although it assisted in the formation of
                    APEC, the U.S. Government played an even greater role in the creation of the
                    North American Free Trade Association (NAFTA) and the World Trade Organization
                    (WTO). All these organizations were based on identifying shared economic goals
                    and methods, but did not rely upon binding agreements, so states could continue
                    to act in their own interests. These entities aimed to eliminate trade barriers
                    and help states consider regional issues when making economic policy.</p>
                <p>Although the countries bordering the Pacific Ocean were extremely diverse in
                    terms of linguistic, cultural and ethnic backgrounds, they shared rapidly
                    developing economic power and common economic interests. Recognizing this, a
                    number of countries in the region began to discuss the creation of a regional
                    organization that would promote free trade and further economic integration in
                    the hope that such a move would benefit the entire region. The resulting
                    organization, APEC, brought together developed and developing economies and
                    promoted the idea of a regional Pacific Rim identity in an effort to increase
                    Pacific-wide cooperation.</p>
                <p>Since 1989, APEC has expanded from its original 12 members to include 21 member
                    economies. The founding members were Australia, Brunei Darussalam, Canada,
                    Indonesia, Japan, the Republic of Korea, Malaysia, New Zealand, the Philippines,
                    Singapore, Thailand and the United States. In 1991, the <placeName>People’s
                        Republic of China</placeName>, <placeName>Hong Kong</placeName> and Chinese
                    Taipei joined the forum. Over the course of the 1990s, Chile, Mexico, Papua New
                    Guinea, Peru and Russia entered the organization. Together, the member economies
                    of APEC account for a substantial proportion of world economic activity.</p>
                <p>During its first five years of operation, APEC established its core objectives.
                    In the 1991 Seoul Declaration, APEC member economies proclaimed the creation of
                    a liberalized free trade area around the Pacific Rim as the principle objective
                    of the organization. A 1994 meeting held in Bogor, Indonesia set as the
                    organization’s goal the achievement of “free and open trade and investment” for
                    the region, establishing 2010 as the target date for developed economies and
                    2020 for developing ones. Each subsequent annual meeting has addressed the
                    implementation of the Bogor Goals along with pertinent issues for the economic
                    and security interests of the member economies. The topics that may be addressed
                    at annual meetings are not proscribed, but the focus tends to be on trade
                    liberalization, promoting business, and economic cooperation.</p>
                <p>The United States has long been an active participant in the activities of APEC.
                    In 1993 in Seattle, Washington, President <persName>Bill Clinton</persName>
                    hosted what became the first annual meeting of member economies—ministers and
                    economic leaders. This act displayed the U.S. commitment to working with APEC
                    member economies to achieve freer trade in the region. Since that time the
                    United States has maintained a high level of engagement with this key
                    organization.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="fall-of-communism"
                ana="bush-george-h-w baker-james-addison eagleburger-lawrence-sidney bulgaria czech-republic germany hungary malta poland romania russia border-administration elections self-determination diplomatic-recognition">
                <head>Fall of Communism in Eastern Europe, <date when="1989">1989</date>
                </head>
                <p>On November 9, 1989, thousands of jubilant Germans brought down the most visible
                    symbol of division at the heart of Europe—the Berlin Wall. For two generations,
                    the Wall was the physical representation of the Iron Curtain, and East German
                    border guards had standing shoot-to-kill orders against those who tried to
                    escape. But just as the Wall had come to represent the division of Europe, its
                    fall came to represent the end of the Cold War. In the White House, President
                    George H. W. Bush and his National Security Advisor, Brent Scowcroft, watched
                    the unfolding scene on a television in the study, aware of both the historical
                    significance of the moment and of the challenges for U.S. foreign policy that
                    lay ahead.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="berlin-wall.jpg" height="400px" width="401px"/>
                    <head>Germans celebrating the fall of the Berlin Wall on November 10, 1989. (AP
                        Photo/File) </head>
                </figure>
                <p>Not even the most optimistic observer of President’s Ronald Reagan’s 1987 Berlin
                    speech calling on Soviet General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev to “tear down this
                    wall” would have imagined that two years later the communist regimes of Eastern
                    Europe would collapse like dominoes. By 1990, the former communist leaders were
                    out of power, free elections were held, and Germany was whole again.</p>
                <p>The peaceful collapse of the regimes was by no means pre-ordained. Soviet tanks
                    crushed demonstrators in East Berlin in June 1953, in Hungary in 1956, and again
                    in Czechoslovakia in 1968. Soviet military planners were intimately involved in
                    the Polish planning for martial law in 1980, and Soviet troops remained
                    stationed throughout Eastern Europe, as much a guarantee for Soviet security as
                    an ominous reminder to Eastern European peoples of Soviet dominance over their
                    countries. </p>
                <p>The Reagan administration’s strong rhetoric in support of the political
                    aspirations of Eastern European and Soviet citizens was met, following 1985,
                    with a new type of leader in the Soviet Union. Mikhail Gorbachev’s policies of
                        <hi rend="italic">perestroika</hi> (restructuring) and <hi rend="italic"
                        >glasnost</hi> (transparency) further legitimized popular calls for reform
                    from within. Gorbachev also made clear—at first secretly to the Eastern European
                    leaders, then increasingly more public—that the Soviet Union had abandoned the
                    policy of military intervention in support of communist regimes (the Brezhnev
                    Doctrine).</p>
                <p>On February 6, 1989, negotiations between the Polish Government and members of
                    the underground labor union Solidarity opened officially in Warsaw. Solidarity
                    was formed in August 1980 following a series of strikes that paralyzed the
                    Polish economy. The 1981 Soviet-inspired imposition of martial law drove the
                    organization underground, where it survived due to support from Western labor
                    organizations and Polish émigré groups. The results of the “Round Table Talks,”
                    signed by government and Solidarity representatives on April 4, included free
                    elections for 35% of the Parliament (<hi rend="italic">Sejm</hi>), free
                    elections for the newly created Senate, a new office of the President, and the
                    recognition of Solidarity as a political party. On June 4, as Chinese tanks
                    crushed student-led protests in Beijing, Solidarity delivered a crushing
                    electoral victory. By August 24, ten years after Solidarity emerged on the
                    scene, Tadeusz Mazowiecki became the first non-communist Prime Minister in
                    Eastern Europe.</p>
                <p>In Hungary, drastic changes were also under way. The government, already the most
                    liberal of the communist governments, allowed free association and assembly and
                    ordered opening of the country’s border with the West. In doing so, it provided
                    an avenue to escape for an ever-increasing number of East Germans. The Hungarian
                    Party removed its long-time leader, Janos Kadar, agreed to its own version of
                    the Round Table talks with the opposition, and, on June 16, ceremoniously
                    re-interred Imre Nagy, the reformist communist leader of the 1956 Hungarian
                    Revolution. By October 23, ten months after political reforms began, Hungary
                    adopted a new constitution allowing a multi-party system and competitive
                    elections.</p>
                <p>The economic collapse of East Germany led increasing numbers of East Germans to
                    seek to emigrate to the West. Thousands sought refuge in West German embassies
                    in other communist countries, eventually forcing the government to allow them to
                    emigrate via special trains. Visiting Berlin in early October, Gorbachev
                    cautioned the East German leadership of the need to reform, and confided in his
                    advisors that East German leader Erich Honecker had to be replaced. Two weeks
                    later, Honecker was forced to resign, while hundreds of thousands marched in
                    protest throughout major East German cities. On November 9, as the world watched
                    on television, the East German Government announced the opening of all East
                    German borders. In a fluid situation, the Berlin Wall came down when an
                    obviously ill-prepared East German spokesman told reporters that the new travel
                    regulations also applied to Berlin. Before the end of the month, West German
                    Chancellor Helmut Kohl unveiled a plan for reunification of the two
                    Germanies.</p>
                <p>As the Wall came down and the fears of a Soviet reaction receded, the dominoes
                    started falling at a quickened pace. In October, riot police arrested hundreds
                    in Prague after an unsanctioned demonstration; only weeks later, hundreds of
                    thousands gathered in Prague to protest the government. Alexander Dubcek, the
                    reformist communist who led the Prague Spring in 1968, made his first public
                    appearance in over two decades. A new, non-communist government took the
                    country’s reins on December 5, and on December 29, Vaclav Havel, the famed
                    playwright and dissident, was elected President. In Bulgaria, protests lead to
                    the removal of Todor Zhivkov, the long-time leader of the Bulgarian Communist
                    Party, and his replacement with reformist communist, Petar Mladenov. The new
                    government quickly announced that the government would hold free elections in
                    1990.</p>
                <p>Only in Romania did the events turn violent. Nicolae Ceausescu, an increasingly
                    idiosyncratic relic of Stalinist times, refused any reforms. On December 17 in
                    Timisoara, the army and police fired into crowds protesting government policies,
                    killing dozens. Protests spread to other cities, with hundreds killed when
                    Ceausescu ordered the violent repression of demonstrations on December 21. By
                    the next day, Ceausescu was forced to flee Bucharest and was arrested by Army
                    units in the countryside. The interim government, led by a reformist communist
                    Ion Iliescu, held a quick mock trial and Ceausescu and his wife were executed on
                    December 25.</p>
                <p>By the summer of 1990, all of the former communist regimes of Eastern Europe were
                    replaced by democratically elected governments. In Poland, Hungary, East Germany
                    and Czechoslovakia, newly formed center-right parties took power for the first
                    time since the end of World War II. In Bulgaria and Romania, reformed communists
                    retained control of the governments, but new center-right parties entered
                    Parliaments and became active on the political scene. The course was set for the
                    reintegration of Eastern Europe into Western economic, political, and security
                    frameworks. Writing in his journal on November 10, 1989, Anatoly Chernyaev,
                    foreign policy advisor to Gorbachev noted that the fall of the wall represented
                    “a shift in the world balance of forces” and the end of Yalta.</p>
                <p>Meeting in Malta on December 2, Bush and Gorbachev “buried the Cold War at the
                    bottom of the Mediterranean” as one of Gorbachev’s staffers later described. In
                    his memoirs, Bush noted that the rapport he built with Gorbachev at that meeting
                    would prove beneficial later on. And while Scowcroft did not yet feel the Cold
                    War was over, he noted that U.S. policy at the time evolved, “from quietly
                    supporting the transformations to cultivating Soviet acquiescence, even
                    collaboration, in them.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="collapse-soviet-union"
                ana="bush-george-h-w baker-james-addison estonia georgia latvia lithuania russia ukraine arms-control-and-disarmament nuclear-nonproliferation nuclear-weapons">
                <head>The Collapse of the Soviet Union</head>
                <p>After his inauguration in January 1989, <persName>George H.W. Bush</persName> did
                    not automatically follow the policy of his predecessor, <persName>Ronald
                        Reagan</persName>, in dealing with <persName>Mikhail Gorbachev</persName>
                    and the Soviet Union. Instead, he ordered a strategic policy re-evaluation in
                    order to establish his own plan and methods for dealing with the Soviet Union
                    and arms control.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="collapse-soviet-union.jpg" height="450px" width="361px"/>
                    <head>Boris Yeltsin makes a speech from atop a tank in front of the Russian
                        parliament building in Moscow, U.S.S.R., Monday, Aug. 19, 1991. (AP Photo)
                    </head>
                </figure>
                <p>Conditions in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, however, changed rapidly.
                    Gorbachev’s decision to loosen the Soviet yoke on the countries of Eastern
                    Europe created an independent, democratic momentum that led to the collapse of
                    the Berlin Wall in November 1989, and then the overthrow of Communist rule
                    throughout Eastern Europe. While Bush supported these independence movements,
                    U.S. policy was reactive. Bush chose to let events unfold organically, careful
                    not to do anything to worsen Gorbachev’s position.</p>
                <p>With the policy review complete, and taking into account unfolding events in
                    Europe, Bush met with Gorbachev at Malta in early December 1989. They laid the
                    groundwork for finalizing START negotiations, completing the Conventional Forces
                    in Europe treaty, and they discussed the rapid changes in Eastern Europe. Bush
                    encouraged Gorbachev’s reform efforts, hoping that the Soviet leader would
                    succeed in shifting the USSR toward a democratic system and a market oriented
                    economy.</p>
                <p>Gorbachev’s decision to allow elections with a multi-party system and create a
                    presidency for the Soviet Union began a slow process of democratization that
                    eventually destabilized Communist control and contributed to the collapse of the
                    Soviet Union. Following the May 1990 elections, Gorbachev faced conflicting
                    internal political pressures: Boris Yeltsin and the pluralist movement advocated
                    democratization and rapid economic reforms while the hard-line Communist elite
                    wanted to thwart Gorbachev’s reform agenda.</p>
                <p>Facing a growing schism between Yeltsin and Gorbachev, the Bush administration
                    opted to work primarily with Gorbachev because they viewed him as the more
                    reliable partner and because he made numerous concessions that promoted U.S.
                    interests. Plans proceeded to sign the START agreement. With the withdrawal of
                    Red Army troops from East Germany, Gorbachev agreed to German reunification and
                    acquiesced when a newly reunited Germany joined NATO. When Saddam Hussein
                    invaded Kuwait, the United States and the Soviet leadership worked together
                    diplomatically to repel this attack.</p>
                <p>Yet for all of those positive steps on the international stage, Gorbachev’s
                    domestic problems continued to mount. Additional challenges to Moscow’s control
                    placed pressure on Gorbachev and the Communist party to retain power in order to
                    keep the Soviet Union intact. After the demise of Communist regimes in Eastern
                    Europe, the Baltic States and the Caucasus demanded independence from Moscow. In
                    January 1991, violence erupted in Lithuania and Latvia. Soviet tanks intervened
                    to halt the democratic uprisings, a move that Bush resolutely condemned.</p>
                <p>By 1991, the Bush administration reconsidered policy options in light of the
                    growing level of turmoil within the Soviet Union. Three basic options presented
                    themselves. The administration could continue to support Gorbachev in hopes of
                    preventing Soviet disintegration. Alternately, the United States could shift
                    support to Yeltsin and the leaders of the Republics and provide support for a
                    controlled restructuring or possible breakup of the Soviet Union. The final
                    option consisted of lending conditional support to Gorbachev, leveraging aid and
                    assistance in return for more rapid and radical political and economic reforms. </p>
                <p>Unsure about how much political capital Gorbachev retained, Bush combined
                    elements of the second and third options. The Soviet nuclear arsenal was vast,
                    as were Soviet conventional forces, and further weakening of Gorbachev could
                    derail further arms control negotiations. To balance U.S. interests in relation
                    to events in the Soviet Union, and in order to demonstrate support for
                    Gorbachev, Bush signed the START treaty at the Moscow Summit in July 1991. Bush
                    administration officials also, however, increased contact with Yeltsin.</p>
                <p>The unsuccessful August 1991 coup against Gorbachev sealed the fate of the Soviet
                    Union. Planned by hard-line Communists, the coup diminished Gorbachev’s power
                    and propelled Yeltsin and the democratic forces to the forefront of Soviet and
                    Russian politics. Bush publicly condemned the coup as “extra-constitutional,”
                    but Gorbachev’s weakened position became obvious to all. He resigned his
                    leadership as head of the Communist party shortly thereafter—separating the
                    power of the party from that of the presidency of the Soviet Union. The Central
                    Committee was dissolved and Yeltsin banned party activities. A few days after
                    the coup, Ukraine and Belarus declared their independence from the Soviet Union.
                    The Baltic States, which had earlier declared their independence, sought
                    international recognition.</p>
                <p>Amidst quick, dramatic changes across the landscape of the Soviet Union, Bush
                    administration officials prioritized the prevention of nuclear catastrophe, the
                    curbing of ethnic violence, and the stable transition to new political orders.
                    On September 4, 1991, Secretary of State James Baker articulated five basic
                    principles that would guide U.S. policy toward the emerging republics:
                    self-determination consistent with democratic principles, recognition of
                    existing borders, support for democracy and rule of law, preservation of human
                    rights and rights of national minorities, and respect for international law and
                    obligations. The basic message was clear—if the new republics could follow these
                    principles, they could expect cooperation and assistance from the United States.
                    Baker met with Gorbachev and Yeltsin in an attempt to shore up the economic
                    situation and develop some formula for economic cooperation between the
                    republics and Russia, as well as to determine ways to allow political reforms to
                    occur in a regulated and peaceful manner. In early December, Yeltsin and the
                    leaders of Ukraine and Belarus met in Brest to form the Commonwealth of
                    Independent States (CIS), effectively declaring the demise of the Soviet
                    Union.</p>
                <p>On December 25, 1991, the Soviet hammer and sickle flag lowered for the last time
                    over the Kremlin, thereafter replaced by the Russian tricolor. Earlier in the
                    day, Mikhail Gorbachev resigned his post as president of the Soviet Union,
                    leaving Boris Yeltsin as president of the newly independent Russian state.
                    People all over the world watched in amazement at this relatively peaceful
                    transition from former Communist monolith into multiple separate nations.</p>
                <p>With the dissolution of Soviet Union, the main goal of the Bush administration
                    was economic and political stability and security for Russia, the Baltics, and
                    the states of the former Soviet Union. Bush recognized all 12 independent
                    republics and established diplomatic relations with Russia, Ukraine, Belarus,
                    Kazakhstan, Armenia and Kyrgyzstan. In February 1992, Baker visited the
                    remaining republics and diplomatic relations were established with Uzbekistan,
                    Moldova, Azerbaijan, Turkmenistan, and Tajikistan. Civil war in Georgia
                    prevented its recognition and the establishment of diplomatic relations with the
                    United States until May 1992. Yeltsin met with Bush at Camp David in February
                    1992, followed by a formal state visit to Washington in June. Leaders from
                    Kazakhstan and Ukraine visited Washington in May 1992.</p>
                <p>During his visits to Washington, politics, economic reforms, and security issues
                    dominated the conversations between Yeltsin and Bush. Of paramount concern was
                    securing the nuclear arsenal of the former Soviet Union and making certain
                    nuclear weapons did not fall into the wrong hands. Baker made it clear that
                    funding was available from the United States to secure nuclear, chemical and
                    biological weapons in the former Soviet Union. The Nunn-Lugar Act established
                    the Cooperative Threat Reduction Program in November 1991 to fund the
                    dismantling of weapons in the former Soviet Union, in accordance with the START
                    and INF Treaties and other agreements. Bush and Baker also worked with Yeltsin
                    and international organizations like the World Bank and IMF to provide financial
                    assistance and hopefully prevent a humanitarian crisis in Russia.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="breakup-yugoslavia"
                ana="bosnia-and-herzegovina croatia kosovo macedonia montenegro serbia slovenia bush-george-h-w baker-james-addison">
                <head>The Breakup of Yugoslavia, 1990–1992</head>
                <p>Issued on October 18, 1990, National Intelligence Estimate (NIE) 15–90 presented
                    a dire warning to the U.S. policy community:</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Yugoslavia will cease to function as a federal state within a
                        year, and will probably dissolve within two. Economic reform will not stave
                        off the breakup. [...] A full-scale interrepublic war is unlikely, but
                        serious intercommunal conflict will accompany the breakup and will continue
                        afterward. The violence will be intractable and bitter. There is little the
                        United States and its European allies can do to preserve Yugoslav
                        unity.</hi>
                </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="yugoslavia.jpg" height="450px" width="469px"/>
                    <head>1993 map of the former Yugoslavia. (Central Intelligence Agency)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The October 1990 judgment of the U.S. intelligence community, as Thomas Shreeve
                    noted in his 2003 study on NIE 15–90 for the National Defense University, “was
                    analytically sound, prescient, and well written. It was also fundamentally
                    inconsistent with what US policymakers wanted to happen in the former
                    Yugoslavia, and it had almost no impact on US policy.” By January 1992, the
                    Socialist Federal Republic of Yugoslavia ceased to exist, having dissolved into
                    its constituent states.</p>
                <p>Yugoslavia—the land of South (i.e. Yugo) Slavs—was created at the end of World
                    War I when Croat, Slovenian, and Bosnian territories that had been part of the
                    Austro-Hungarian Empire united with the Serbian Kingdom. The country broke up
                    under Nazi occupation during World War II with the creation of a Nazi-allied
                    independent Croat state, but was reunified at the end of the war when the
                    communist-dominated partisan force of Josip Broz Tito liberated the country.
                    Following the end of World War II, Yugoslavian unity was a top priority for the
                    U.S. Government. While ostensibly a communist state, Yugoslavia broke away from
                    the Soviet sphere of influence in 1948, became a founding member of the
                    Non-Aligned Movement in 1961, and adopted a more de-centralized and less
                    repressive form of government as compared with other East European communist
                    states during the Cold War.</p>
                <p>The varied reasons for the country’s breakup ranged from the cultural and
                    religious divisions between the ethnic groups making up the nation, to the
                    memories of WWII atrocities committed by all sides, to centrifugal nationalist
                    forces. However, a series of major political events served as the catalyst for
                    exacerbating inherent tensions in the Yugoslav republic. Following the death of
                    Tito in 1980, provisions of the 1974 constitution provided for the effective
                    devolution of all real power away from the federal government to the republics
                    and autonomous provinces in Serbia by establishing a collective presidency of
                    the eight provincial representatives and a federal government with little
                    control over economic, cultural, and political policy. External factors also had
                    a significant impact. The collapse of communism in Eastern Europe in 1989, the
                    unification of Germany one year later, and the imminent collapse of the Soviet
                    Union all served to erode Yugoslavia’s political stability. As Eastern European
                    states moved away from communist government and toward free elections and market
                    economies, the West’s attention focused away from Yugoslavia and undermined the
                    extensive economic and financial support necessary to preserve a Yugoslav
                    economy already close to collapse. The absence of a Soviet threat to the
                    integrity and unity of Yugoslavia and its constituent parts meant that a
                    powerful incentive for unity and cooperation was removed.</p>
                <p>Slobodan Milosevic, Serbia’s president from 1989, took advantage of the vacuum
                    created by a progressively weakening central state and brutally deployed the use
                    of Serbian ultra-nationalism to fan the flames of conflict in the other
                    republics and gain legitimacy at home. Milosevic started as a banker in Belgrade
                    and became involved in politics in the mid-1980s. He rose quickly through the
                    ranks to become head of the Serbian Communist Party in 1986. While attending a
                    party meeting in the Albanian-dominated province of Kosovo in May 1987, Serbians
                    in the province rioted outside the meeting hall. Milosevic spoke with the
                    rioters and listened to their complaints of mistreatment by the Albanian
                    majority. His actions were extensively reported by Serbian-controlled Yugoslav
                    mass media, beginning the process of transforming the former banker into the
                    stalwart symbol of Serbian nationalism. Having found a new source of legitimacy,
                    Milosevic quickly shored up his power in Serbia through control of the party
                    apparatus and the press. He moved to strip the two autonomous provinces of
                    Kosovo and Vojvodina of their constitutionally-guaranteed autonomy within Serbia
                    by using mass rallies to force the local leaderships to resign in favor of his
                    own preferred candidates. By mid-1989 Kosovo and Vojvodina had been reintegrated
                    into Serbia, and the Montenegro leadership was replaced by Milosevic allies.</p>
                <p>The ongoing effects of democratization in Eastern Europe were felt throughout
                    Yugoslavia. As Milosevic worked to consolidate power in Serbia, elections in
                    Slovenia and Croatia in 1990 gave non-communist parties control of the state
                    legislatures and governments. Slovenia was the first to declare “sovereignty” in
                    1990, issuing a parliamentary declaration that Slovenian law took precedence
                    over Yugoslav law. Croatia followed in May, and in August, the Yugoslav republic
                    of Bosnia-Herzegovina also declared itself sovereign. Slovenia and Croatia began
                    a concerted effort to transform Yugoslavia from a federal state to a
                    confederation. With the administration of George H. W. Bush focused primarily on
                    the Soviet Union, Germany, and the crisis in the Persian Gulf, Yugoslavia had
                    lost the geostrategic importance it enjoyed during the Cold War. While
                    Washington attempted during the summer of 1990 to marshal some limited
                    coordination with its Western allies in case the Yugoslav crisis turned bloody,
                    Western European governments maintained a wait-and-see attitude. At the same
                    time, inter-republic relations in Yugoslavia spiraled out of control. Slovenia
                    overwhelmingly voted for independence in December 1990. A Croatian referendum in
                    May 1991 also supported full independence. Secretary of State James Baker
                    traveled to Belgrade to meet with Yugoslav leaders and urge a political solution
                    to no avail. Slovenia and Croatia both declared formal independence on June 25,
                    1991.</p>
                <p>The Yugoslav Army (JNA) briefly intervened in Slovenia, but it withdrew after 10
                    days, effectively confirming Slovenia’s separation. The Serb minority in Croatia
                    declared its own independence from the republic and its desire to join Serbia,
                    sparking violence between armed militias. The JNA intervened in the conflict
                    ostensibly to separate the combatants, but it became quickly apparent that it
                    favored the Croatian-Serbs. The war that followed devastated Croatia, resulting
                    in tens of thousands dead, and hundreds of thousands of people displaced. In
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina, a referendum on independence took place in March 1992, but
                    was boycotted by the Serb minority. The republic declared its independence from
                    Yugoslavia in May 1992, while the Serbs in Bosnia declared their own areas an
                    independent republic. Macedonia itself also declared independence following a
                    September 1991 referendum, and a U.S. peacekeeping and monitoring force was
                    dispatched to the border with Serbia to monitor violence.</p>
                <p>Croatia and Slovenia were internationally recognized in January 1992, with
                    Bosnia’s independence recognized soon thereafter. The three countries joined the
                    United Nations on May 22, 1992. Serbia and Montenegro formed a new Federal
                    Republic of Yugoslavia as a successor state to old Yugoslavia, but the
                    international community did not recognize its successor claim. Over the next
                    three years, the war in Bosnia and Herzegovina claimed hundreds of thousands of
                    lives and displaced millions from their homes, as Europe witnessed the most
                    horrific fighting on its territory since the end of World War II. In 1998–1999,
                    violence erupted again in Kosovo, with the province’s majority Albanian
                    population calling for independence from Serbia. A NATO bombing campaign and
                    economic sanctions forced the Milosevic regime to accept a NATO-led
                    international peace keeping force. The province was placed under U.N.
                    administrative mandate. With the economy crumbling, Milosevic lost his grip on
                    power in 2001, was arrested, and turned over to the International Crimes
                    Tribunal in The Hague. He died in prison in 2006, before his trial concluded. In
                    2008, Kosovo declared independence and was recognized by the United States and
                    most European states, despite Russian objections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="tiananmen-square"
                ana="china arms-embargoes economic-sanctions human-rights">
                <head>Tiananmen Square, 1989</head>
                <p>The establishment of formal diplomatic relations between the United States and
                    the People’s Republic of China in 1979, together with Chinese Vice Premier Deng
                    Xiaoping’s economic reforms, inaugurated a decade of vibrant cultural exchange
                    and expanding economic ties between the two countries. However, the Chinese
                    Government’s violent suppression of demonstrations in Tiananmen Square on June
                    4, 1989, cooled U.S.-Chinese relations considerably. To the present day, the
                    Department of State marks the anniversary of the suppression by issuing a
                    statement calling on the Chinese Government to end harassment of those who
                    participated in the protests and to fully account for those killed, detained, or
                    missing.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="tianamen-square.jpg" height="450px" width="292px"/>
                    <head>A Chinese man stands alone to block a line of tanks heading east on
                        Beijing’s Chang’an Blvd. in Tiananmen Square. (AP Photo/Jeff Widener,
                        File)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The demonstrations began on April 15, when Chinese students gathered in Beijing’s
                    Tiananmen Square, where so many student and mass demonstrations had taken place
                    since the early 20th century, to mark the death of the popular pro-reform
                    Chinese leader Hu Yaobang. The demonstration became a forum to protest
                    corruption and inflation, and call for broader political and economic reforms to
                    build on the reforms that had already transformed China considerably in the
                    post-Mao era. </p>
                <p>The Chinese leadership was divided on how to handle the demonstrations. As the
                    numbers of protesters swelled to the tens of thousands, some leaders who saw the
                    protests as a direct challenge to Communist Party rule labeled the demonstrators
                    “counter-revolutionary” in an April 26 editorial in the government-run <hi
                        rend="italic">People’s Daily</hi> newspaper. Other officials sympathetic to
                    the protestors’ demands for political reform favored a conciliatory approach, as
                    represented by General Secretary of the Communist Party Zhao Ziyang’s visit with
                    protestors on May 4 to hear and acknowledge their concerns.</p>
                <p>Soviet General Secretary Mikhail Gorbachev’s impending state visit on May 15
                    invigorated the protests. Some protestors initiated hunger strikes to increase
                    pressure on the government. Foreign media that arrived to cover the visit turned
                    their attention to the protests and heightened international—especially
                    Western—awareness of the protesters and their demands. The crowds in the Square
                    grew beyond students to include a broad segment of Chinese society, from workers
                    to ordinary citizens from Beijing and beyond, and reportedly exceeded one
                    million in number. Gorbachev’s visit occupied Chinese officials’ attention until
                    his departure on May 18. On May 19, Zhao visited the protesters once more to
                    make an emotional appeal for hunger strikes to end. The Chinese leadership
                    imposed martial law in Beijing on May 20. The protests continued.</p>
                <p>On the night of June 3 and 4, the People’s Liberation Army stormed the Square
                    with tanks, crushing the protests with terrible human costs. Estimates of the
                    numbers killed vary. The Chinese Government has asserted that injuries exceeded
                    3,000 and that over 200 individuals, including 36 university students, were
                    killed that night. Western sources, however, are skeptical of the official
                    Chinese report and most frequently cite the toll as hundreds or even thousands
                    killed. Similar protests that had taken place in other Chinese cities were soon
                    suppressed and their leaders imprisoned.</p>
                <p>In the aftermath, President George H.W. Bush denounced the actions in Tiananmen
                    Square and suspended military sales as well as high level exchanges with Chinese
                    officials. Many members of the U.S. Congress, the American public, and
                    international leaders advocated broader economic sanctions, some of which were
                    implemented. U.S. leaders met with Chinese nationals studying in the United
                    States as a symbolic gesture of commitment. Questions of relations with China,
                    in particular the granting of Most-Favored-Nation trading status, were
                    controversial questions for the remainder of President Bush’s term and into the
                    term of President Bill Clinton.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="gulf-war"
                ana="bush-george-h-w iraq kuwait organization-of-petroleum-exporting-countries united-arab-emirates military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">
                <head>The Gulf War, 1991</head>
                <p>At the end of the Iran-Iraq War of 1980–1988, Iraq emerged with its state intact
                    and a reinforced sense of national pride, but laden with massive debts. Iraq had
                    largely financed the war effort through loans, and owed some $37 billion to Gulf
                    creditors in 1990. Iraqi President Saddam Hussein called on the United Arab
                    Emirates and Kuwait to cancel the Iraqi debt they held, arguing that the loans
                    should be considered payments to Iraq for protecting the Arabian Peninsula from
                    Iranian expansionism, but his appeals went unanswered. The Gulf states’ refusal
                    to cancel Iraq’s war debts contributed to Saddam Hussein’s decision to make
                    threats against Iraq’s rich, but militarily weak, neighbor Kuwait.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="desert-storm.jpg" height="450px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>President George Bush speaks to U.S. Military personnel gathered for his
                        Thanksgiving holiday visit during Operation Desert Shield. (Department of
                        Defense/Gerald Johnson)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>After Kuwait rejected Saddam’s debt-forgiveness demands, he threatened to
                    reignite a conflict over the long-standing question of ownership of the Warbah
                    and Bubiyan Islands, to which Iraq ascribed importance because of the secure
                    access they afforded to its ports on the Khawr 'Abd Allah—the waterway to the
                    Persian Gulf that remained the only viable alternative to the closed Shatt
                    Al-'Arab, cluttered with debris from the Iran-Iraq War.</p>
                <p>The dispute over the Bubiyan and Warbah Islands was a key point of contention in
                    the lengthy history of territorial conflict between Iraq and Kuwait. In 1961,
                    when the United Kingdom ended its protectorate over Kuwait, then Iraqi Prime
                    Minister General 'Abd Al-Karim Qasim asserted that Kuwait was an "integral part
                    of Iraq" because it had been part of the former Ottoman province of Al-Basrah.
                    Iraq threatened to exert its sovereignty over Kuwait, but the consequent
                    deployment of British troops to Kuwait forced the Iraqis to back down. Although
                    subsequent regimes relinquished this claim by recognizing Kuwait's independence,
                    Ba’athist Iraq never formally accepted a common boundary between the two
                    countries.</p>
                <p>Still, there had been no major incidents regarding the border dispute until 1990,
                    when Iraq was in the throes of the postwar economic crisis. In July, Saddam
                    accused Kuwait and the United Arab Emirates of breaking with Organization of
                    Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) production quotas and over-producing crude
                    oil for export, which depressed prices, depriving Iraq of critical oil revenues.
                    In addition, Saddam Hussein alleged that Kuwait was stealing oil from the
                    Rumayla oil field that straddled the Iraq-Kuwait border. He also demanded that
                    Kuwait cede control of the Bubiyan and Warbah Islands to Iraq.</p>
                <p>During this period, there was a deterioration of relations between the United
                    States and Iraq. Iraq accused the United States and Israel of deliberately
                    weakening Iraq by encouraging Kuwait to reduce oil prices. When Iraq began to
                    threaten Kuwait early in July 1990, the United States staged maneuvers in the
                    Gulf to warn Iraq against taking military action against the United Arab
                    Emirates and Kuwait. Despite this show of U.S. force, President George H.W. Bush
                    adopted a conciliatory policy toward Saddam Hussein in hopes of moderating the
                    Iraqi regime and policies. The Bush administration tried to maintain economic
                    and political relations with Iraq, and on April 12, 1990, sent a delegation of
                    American senators led by Senator Robert Dole to meet with Hussein. Senator Dole
                    brought a message from the White House suggesting that the United States wanted
                    to improve relations with Iraq. A letter from President Bush to Saddam delivered
                    by U.S. Ambassador April Glaspie on July 27 echoed this sentiment.</p>
                <p>But on August 2, 1990, a force of one hundred thousand Iraqi troops invaded
                    Kuwait and overran the country in a matter of hours. The invasion of Kuwait led
                    to a United Nations Security Council embargo and sanctions on Iraq and a
                    U.S.-led coalition air and ground war, which began on January 16, 1991, and
                    ended with an Iraqi defeat and retreat from Kuwait on February 28, 1991.</p>
                <p>Although the United States was aware of Hussein’s threats to Kuwait, it did not
                    anticipate the Iraqi military incursion. The Iraqi Republican Guard units moved
                    toward Kuwait City while Iraqi Special Forces secured key sites, including the
                    islands of Warba and Bubayan, Kuwaiti air fields, and the palaces of the Emir
                    and the Crown Prince. There was some Kuwaiti resistance to the Iraqi invasion,
                    but the Iraqi forces easily suppressed Kuwait’s defenses. Members of the Kuwaiti
                    royal family escaped to Saudi Arabia where they appealed for international
                    support. On August 28, Iraq declared that Kuwait had become its nineteenth
                    province.</p>
                <p>International condemnation of the Iraqi invasion was widespread and virtually
                    unanimous. Within days, the United States led efforts to organize an
                    international coalition, which, working through the United Nations Security
                    Council, passed Resolution 660 demanding Iraq’s immediate and unconditional
                    withdrawal, Resolution 661 imposing economic sanctions, and Resolution 663
                    declaring the annexation of Kuwait null and void.</p>
                <p>The United States and Saudi Arabia agreed to a deployment of U.S. forces to Saudi
                    Arabia to protect the peninsula. At the same time, the United States and the
                    coalition insisted on Iraq’s unconditional withdrawal from Kuwait, but Iraq
                    refused to withdraw and began looting Kuwait and destroying its
                    infrastructure.</p>
                <p>By October 30, the Bush administration made a decision to push Iraq out of Kuwait
                    by force if necessary. Bush increased the U.S. force presence and petitioned the
                    United Nations for authorization to use force. The result was UN Resolution 678,
                    which authorized the use of force to compel Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait, but
                    gave Iraq a forty-five day grace period to withdraw. Led by the United States,
                    an international coalition of nations amassed forces in the region to help
                    liberate Kuwait.</p>
                <p>After the deadline for withdrawal passed, the coalition led by the United States
                    attacked Iraq by air. Within twenty-four hours, coalition forces controlled the
                    skies and bombarded such strategic sites as the Iraqi command and control
                    facilities, Saddam Hussein’s palaces, the Ba’th Party headquarters, power
                    stations, intelligence and security facilities, hydroelectric stations, oil
                    refineries, military-industrial complexes, and Iraq’s missile facilities.
                    Coalition aircraft subsequently targeted Iraqi troops in Kuwait</p>
                <p>In retaliation, Saddam Hussein launched missile attacks against Israel and on
                    coalition force bases in Saudi Arabia. But Israel refused to retaliate and
                    coalition forces took the offensive by launching a land campaign that began on
                    February 24 and lasted four days. Comprising forces from thirty-four countries,
                    including a number of Arab countries, the coalition forces liberated Kuwait City
                    and drove Iraqi forces into a retreat. On March 2, the United Nations Security
                    Council passed Resolution 686, which set forth conditions for a cease-fire. Iraq
                    was obligated to accept its provisions, which included sanctions and payment of
                    reparations for war damages. Iraq was obligated to return property stolen from
                    Kuwait. The United States continued to put pressure on Iraq through the United
                    Nations, which passed Security Council Resolution 687 establishing the United
                    Nations Special Commission (UNSCOM) to inspect Iraq’s suspected chemical and
                    biological weapons capabilities. The United States subsequently sought to ensure
                    that the trade embargo imposed on Iraq the previous year through Resolution 661
                    remained in place and that Iraq was stripped of chemical weapons and missiles
                    and its nuclear research capabilities. In the chaos following the war,
                    spontaneous Shiite rebellions in the South and Kurdish unrest in northern Iraq
                    broke out but were eventually suppressed by Saddam Hussein and his Revolutionary
                    Guards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="madrid-conference"
                ana="bush-george-h-w baker-james-addison israel jordan palestine peace arab-israeli-dispute">
                <head>The Madrid Conference, 1991</head>
                <p>On March 6, 1991, President <persName>George H. W. Bush</persName> told Congress,
                    “The time has come to put an end to the Arab-Israeli conflict.” Bush’s
                    declaration was followed by eight months of intensive shuttle diplomacy by
                    Secretary of State <persName>James Baker</persName>, culminating in the Madrid
                    Peace Conference in October 1991. The Conference, co-chaired by Bush and Soviet
                    President <persName>Mikhail Gorbachev</persName>, was attended by Israeli,
                    Egyptian, Syrian, and Lebanese delegations, as well as a joint
                    Jordanian-Palestinian delegation. For the first time, all of the parties to the
                    Arab-Israeli conflict had gathered to hold direct negotiations—a historically
                    unprecedented event.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="madrid-conference.jpg" height="350px" width="512px"/>
                    <head>President George H.W. Bush at the Madrid Peace Conference, October 30,
                        1991. (George Bush Presidential Library and Museum)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>The Conference’s long-term impact, however, was more limited than the Bush
                    administration had hoped. Following Madrid, Israeli, Syrian, Jordanian, and
                    Palestinian representatives continued to meet for bilateral talks in Washington,
                    and multilateral talks commenced in Moscow in 1992. Yet by 1993, the Washington
                    talks had become deadlocked and were overtaken by secret Israeli-Palestinian and
                    Israeli-Jordanian negotiations, which produced the Israeli-Palestinian
                    Declaration of Principles (the so-called “Oslo Accord”) of September 1993 and
                    the Israeli-Jordanian peace treaty of October 1994.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">From the <hi rend="italic">Intifada</hi> to Madrid </hi>
                </p>
                <p>The United States began trying to convene an international Middle East peace
                    conference during the final year of <persName>Ronald Reagan’s</persName>
                    Presidency. In December 1987, the Palestinians of the West Bank and the Gaza
                    Strip had risen up against Israeli military rule. Hoping to stop the violence
                    and address Palestinian grievances, Secretary of State <persName>George
                        Shultz</persName> called for an international convention that would serve as
                    a prelude to direct negotiations between Israel, Jordan, and local Palestinians
                    on interim autonomy for the occupied territories, followed by talks on a
                    permanent status agreement. Shultz’s plan, however, went nowhere. Israel
                    rejected the Secretary’s proposals because they did not call for an end to the
                    Palestinian uprising, or <hi rend="italic">intifada</hi>,as a precondition to
                    negotiations. In July 1988, Jordan’s King Hussein rendered the Shultz Plan
                    unworkable when he renounced his kingdom’s links to the West Bank.</p>
                <p>Throughout 1989–1990, U.S. peacemaking efforts centered on a plan put forward by
                    Israeli Prime Minister <persName>Yitzhak Shamir</persName>, which called for the
                    Palestinians of the West Bank and Gaza Strip to elect representatives who would
                    negotiate interim arrangements for self-governance with Israel, followed by a
                    permanent status agreement. U.S. and Egyptian efforts to build on this proposal
                    ultimately faltered over Israel’s insistence on vetting potential Palestinian
                    candidates for ties to the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO). In March
                    1990, controversy over how to proceed with Shamir’s plan led to the fall of
                    Israel’s national unity government, putting diplomacy on hold. The failure of
                    the plan, combined with sharp U.S.-Israeli exchanges over Israeli
                    settlement-building in the occupied territories, strained relations between Bush
                    and Shamir. However, American efforts to bring the PLO into the peace process
                    fared no better. In November 1988, the PLO finally met U.S. demand that it
                    renounce terrorism and accept U.N. Security Council Resolutions 242 and 338,
                    which called for Arab-Israeli peace and mutual recognition accompanied by
                    Israeli withdrawal from “territories” it had occupied in 1967. Nevertheless,
                    diplomatic contacts between the two sides remained at a low level and were cut
                    off in June 1990, when Chairman Yasir Arafat refused to condemn a terrorist
                    attack perpetrated by the Palestine Liberation Front, a PLO faction.</p>
                <p>By March 1991, the Persian Gulf War had created a more favorable context for
                    American peacemaking efforts. The Bush administration’s successful military
                    campaign against Iraq left the President enormously popular at home, and
                    highlighted America’s increasingly dominant role in a post-Cold War Middle East.
                    The Soviet Union had not strongly opposed American intervention, and Arab
                    states, including former Soviet client Syria, joined the coalition against
                    Saddam Hussein. At the same time, the administration felt a need to reward its
                    Arab partners for their support by pushing for progress on the Palestinian
                    issue. Since the PLO backed Iraq during the war, it had alienated Egypt, Syria,
                    and most of the Gulf States, and lost influence over Palestinians in the
                    occupied territories. The Bush administration thus had an opportunity to bring
                    Palestinians into the diplomatic process under conditions that the Israelis
                    might accept.</p>
                <p>Between March and October 1991, Baker succeeded in getting Arab leaders and
                    Palestinian representatives from the occupied territories to drop their demands
                    that PLO officials and Palestinians from East Jerusalem participate in an
                    international peace conference. Instead, the Arab parties agreed that the
                    Palestinians would only be represented by delegates from the occupied
                    territories, and as part of a joint Palestinian-Jordanian delegation.
                    Simultaneously, Baker and Bush put pressure on Shamir to drop Israel’s
                    insistence on bilateral negotiations by withholding $10 billion in loan
                    guarantees that he had requested to help settle Jewish immigrants from the
                    Soviet Union. The President insisted that Shamir would have to promise that the
                    funds would not be used to finance new settlement activity in the occupied
                    territories. Shamir refused to accept Bush’s demand, but it undoubtedly played a
                    role in his decision to come to Madrid.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="strong">The Conference and its Aftermath</hi>
                </p>
                <p>The Madrid Conference opened October 30, 1991, and ended on November 4. Though
                    the parties largely stuck to their traditional positions and did not negotiate
                    seriously with each other, they nevertheless agreed to remain in dialogue.
                    Bilateral talks between Israeli officials and their Arab counterparts would
                    begin in Washington in December 1991, while multilateral negotiations began in
                    Moscow in January 1992. From the beginning, the bilateral talks were generally
                    regarded as the more significant of the two tracks. While these talks acquired
                    greater momentum following the election of Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin
                    in June 1992, they failed to yield results before the Clinton administration
                    took office. Ultimately, the Israeli-Jordanian and Israeli-Palestinian tracks
                    established at Madrid would be circumvented by the parties themselves.
                    Frustrated by the Palestinian delegation’s inability to move forward without
                    Arafat’s approval, the Israelis decided to negotiate directly with the PLO,
                    culminating in the signing of the Declaration of Principles on September 13,
                    1993. King Hussein and the Israelis likewise decided to move forward
                    independently of the Madrid framework, holding direct talks which produced a
                    peace treaty by October 1994.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
