<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="complete">Milestones: 1993–2000</title>
                <title type="short">1993–2000</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Department of State</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Office of the Historian, United States Department of State Publication</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <listChange>
                <change when="2013-10-31"
                    target="#evolution-of-nato #somalia #bosnia #clinton-yeltsin #two-koreas #haiti"
                />
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="section" xml:id="foreword" ana="clinton-william-j">
                <head>
                    <date from="1993" to="2000">1993–2000</date>: The Presidency of William J.
                    Clinton</head>
                <p/>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="clinton-admin.jpg" height="450px" width="301px"/>
                    <head>President Bill Clinton during his second State of the Union address on
                        Tuesday, Jan. 24, 1995. (AP Photo/J. Scott Applewhite)</head>
                </figure>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="section" xml:id="evolution-of-nato"
                ana="bush-george-h-w clinton-william-j russia north-atlantic-treaty-organization">
                <head>The Evolution of NATO, 1988–2001</head>
                <p>The North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) was born at the outset of the Cold
                    War, designed to meet three complementary objectives: deter Soviet expansionism,
                    prevent the revival of nationalist militarism in Europe through a strong North
                    American presence on the continent, and encourage European political
                    integration. Its core function lay in the collective defense of Central and
                    Western Europe against a Soviet attack. The end of the Cold War and the
                    disintegration of the Soviet Union forced the organization and its member states
                    to adapt to a new security environment. This evolution has played out over a
                    protracted series of decisions addressing a series of complex and interrelated
                    issues: the Alliance’s mission in the post-Cold War setting, and the related
                    questions of its force structure, command structure, and decision making
                    processes; NATO’s composition; and its role in the complex system of
                    interlocking European institutions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="nato.jpg" height="450px" width="299px"/>
                    <head>U.S. Army forces cross the Sava River during their deployment into
                        Bosnia-Herzegovina as part of Operation Joint Endeavor, 31 December 1995.
                        (Department of Defense/Senior Airman Edward Littlejohn)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>This process began in the late 1980s, as Soviet leader Mikhail Gorbachev
                    instituted a sweeping series of reforms in the Soviet Union. Gorbachev
                    considered it imperative to reduce the proportion of the Soviet economy devoted
                    to defense spending. That objective quickly manifested itself in a new openness
                    toward arms control, and eventually led to a dramatic reduction of Soviet forces
                    in Eastern Europe and abandonment of the Brezhnev Doctrine. The subsequent
                    collapse of the Warsaw Pact and the reunification of Germany ended the threat of
                    Soviet-led invasion that had been the centerpiece of NATO’s defense posture
                    since its foundation.</p>
                <p>Wary of Soviet intentions and aware of the possibility of a reversal of these
                    reforms, policymakers in the West responded cautiously to Gorbachev and his
                    calls for a “common European home.” NATO’s first formal response to the changes
                    in the security environment came in July 1990, with the “London Declaration on a
                    Transformed North Atlantic Alliance.” Acknowledging the changes in the Soviet
                    Union, NATO’s heads of state agreed on changes to force structure and nuclear
                    posture, directed the Alliance to prepare a new strategic concept and an
                    accompanying defense strategy, and emphasized the importance of the Conference
                    on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE)’s role in the emerging European
                    security architecture. The London Declaration closed, “Today, our Alliance
                    begins a major transformation. Working with all the countries of Europe, we are
                    determined to create enduring peace on this continent.”</p>
                <p>Alliance leaders meeting at the Rome Summit in November 1991 approved a new
                    Strategic Concept outlining NATO’s purpose and missions in the new Europe. The
                    “Rome Declaration on Peace and Cooperation” emphasized the importance of NATO’s
                    traditional collective defense mission, calling for “smaller and more flexible”
                    forces. The Concept outlined NATO’s purpose in providing a “stable security
                    environment in Europe,” a decision that committed the Alliance to sustaining the
                    stability within NATO and areas on its periphery. The Strategic Concept
                    projected NATO’s place in the emerging strategic architecture in Europe, with
                    the maturation of the European Union, an expanded role for the CSCE, and
                    construction of the North Atlantic Cooperation Council as a consultative
                    mechanism for NATO and its former adversaries. The Rome Declaration “welcomed
                    the development of a European security and defence role, reflected in the
                    further strengthening of the European pillar within the Alliance.”</p>
                <p>This program for transformation and new capacity was tested immediately. NATO
                    faced instability on its doorstep with the disintegration of Yugoslavia. The
                    conflict in Bosnia-Herzegovina placed severe stress on the Alliance, as its
                    members struggled to reach a common perspective and an effective response to
                    this complex and vicious war. The Alliance committed forces toward limiting the
                    war, enforcing the arms embargo in Operation Sharp Guard and the no-fly zone
                    through Operation Deny Flight. The Alliance’s involvement increased gradually
                    until September 1995, when NATO air attacks against Bosnian Serb forces in
                    Operation Deliberate Force were among the key factors in enabling the peace
                    talks at Dayton that yielded a negotiated settlement to the war. NATO forces
                    then executed the postwar peacekeeping and stabilization mission in Operation
                    Joint Endeavor.</p>
                <p>The Brussels Summit in January 1994 continued the progressive elaboration of the
                    Alliance’s role in the new Europe, strongly supporting the maturation of the
                    European Security and Defence Identity and confirming the willingness of NATO to
                    “make collective assets of the Alliance available in operations of the Western
                    European Union.” The Brussels Declaration called for the adaptation of the
                    Alliance’s command and control structures to provide for Combined Joint Task
                    Forces, as a flexible “means to facilitate contingency operations, including
                    operations with participating nations outside the Alliance.” Most significantly,
                    the Brussels Summit addressed the issue of enlargement—reconfirming that the
                    Alliance remained open to NATO expansion, and establishing the Partnership for
                    Peace (PfP) to strengthen practical working relations between the Alliance and
                    participating nations from across the CSCE. The Partnership, expected to “play
                    an important role in the evolutionary process of the expansion of NATO,” began
                    operations that same year.</p>
                <p>NATO enlargement was widely debated through the mid-1990s, as policymakers and
                    analysts explored its implications, costs, and likely results. NATO conducted a
                    study of enlargement and established general criteria for new members in
                    September 1995. In December 1996, the Alliance announced its decision to invite
                    new members the following July in a summit to be held in Madrid. The major
                    concern was the effect of enlargement on Russia, with fear that an expansion of
                    NATO to the east would threaten its fragile democracy and any prospects of
                    future cooperation between Russia and the Western democracies. President Bill
                    Clinton addressed that issue with Russia’s President Boris Yeltsin in a March
                    1997 summit conducted in Helsinki. There the leaders agreed to disagree on
                    NATO’s enlargement, but pledged stronger consultation and, where possible, joint
                    decision making in security issues between NATO and Russia. Two months later
                    Yeltsin signed the “Founding Act on Mutual Relations, Cooperation, and Security
                    between NATO and the Russian Federation,” which established the NATO-Russia
                    Permanent Joint Council. With Russia’s concerns somewhat mollified, NATO invited
                    the Czech Republic, Poland, and Hungary to join the Alliance, projecting an
                    accession date in 1999.</p>
                <p>Much work remained, both within the Alliance and across the broader landscape of
                    European security, but this first decade of post-Cold War adaptation established
                    the broad scope of adaptation for NATO. The Alliance had begun its internal
                    transformation, accepted and executed its new missions, recast its relationship
                    with its former adversaries, and begun its enlargement. In doing so, NATO
                    confirmed its utility in the new security environment and its capacity for
                    further change as considered necessary by its member states.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="somalia"
                ana="bush-george-h-w clinton-william-j christopher-warren-minor somalia united-nations military-intervention-presence-and-withdrawal">
                <head>Somalia, 1992–1993</head>
                <p>The United States has long had to face the challenge of determining to what
                    degree it wants to participate in global peacekeeping efforts and whether or not
                    U.S. lives should be put at risk for peacekeeping. Events in Somalia between
                    1992 and 1994 threw that debate into sharp relief.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="somalia.jpg" height="450px" width="300px"/>
                    <head>A Marine sentry prepares to close the gate to the Joint Task Force Somalia
                        headquarters during the multinational relief effort Operation Restore Hope.
                        (Department of Defense/Joe Gawlowicz)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Somalia achieved its independence in 1960 with the union of Somalia, which had
                    been under Italian administration as a United Nations trust territory, and
                    Somaliland, which had been a British protectorate. The United States immediately
                    established diplomatic relations with the new country. In 1969, the Somali Army
                    launched a coup which brought <persName>Mohamed Siad Barre</persName> to power.
                    Barre adopted socialism and became allied with the Soviet Union. The United
                    States was thus wary of Somalia in the period immediately after the coup.</p>
                <p>Barre’s government became increasingly radical in foreign affairs, and in 1977
                    launched a war against Ethiopia in hopes of claiming their territory. Ethiopia
                    received help from the Soviet Union during the war, and so Somalia began to
                    accept assistance from the United States, giving a new level of stability to the
                    U.S.-Somalia relationship. </p>
                <p>Barre’s dictatorship favored members of his own clan. In the 1980s, Somalis in
                    less favored clans began to chafe under the government’s rule. Barre’s
                    ruthlessness could not suppress the opposition, which in 1990 began to unify
                    against him. After joining forces, the combined group of rebels drove Barre from
                    Mogadishu in January 1991. No central government reemerged to take the place of
                    the overthrown government, and the United States closed its embassy that same
                    year, although the two countries never broke off diplomatic relations. The
                    country descended into chaos, and a humanitarian crisis of staggering
                    proportions began to unfold.</p>
                <p>The United Nations attempted to address the crisis with United Nations Operation
                    in Somalia (UNOSOM) to provide humanitarian assistance, created by the United
                    Nations Security Council via Resolution 751 in April 1992. The United States
                    sent food aid via Operation Provide Comfort starting in August 1992. Intense
                    fighting between the warlords impeded the delivery of aid to those who needed it
                    most, and so the United Nations contemplated stronger action. In December 1992,
                    the United States began Operation Restore Hope. President <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName> authorized the dispatch of U.S. troops to Somalia to assist
                    with famine relief as part of the larger United Nations effort. The United
                    Nations’ United Task Force (UNITAF) operated under the authority of Chapter VII
                    of the U.N. Charter. Chapter VII allowed for the use of force to maintain peace
                    and did not require the consent of the states involved. UNITAF transitioned to
                    UNOSOM II in March 1993. UNOSOM II’s efforts to protect aid deliveries were
                    directly challenged by warlord <persName>Muhammad Farah Aideed.</persName>
                </p>
                <p>The most significant of these challenges came on October 3, 1993. Aideed’s forces
                    shot down two Black Hawk helicopters in a battle which lead to the deaths of 18
                    U.S. soldiers and hundreds of Somalis. The deaths turned the tide of public
                    opinion in the United States. President Bill Clinton pulled U.S. troops out of
                    combat four days later, and all U.S. troops left the country in March 1994. The
                    United Nations withdrew from Somalia in March 1995. Fighting continued in the
                    country.</p>
                <p>At the same time the Somalia crisis was unfolding, President Clinton ordered the
                    national security bureaucracy to consider how and when the United States should
                    become involved in peacekeeping operations. The resulting document was
                    Presidential Decision Directive 25, issued on May 3, 1994. The Directive
                    outlined a series of factors which the national security bureaucracy must
                    consider before involving the United States in peacekeeping: eight factors which
                    must be weighed before deciding in favor of peacekeeping in the United Nations,
                    and nine additional factors before becoming involved in a Chapter VII
                    action.</p>
                <p>Although the United Nations’ involvement in Somalia was unable to provide a
                    solution to the country’s political crisis, the United States remained engaged
                    in responding to the humanitarian needs of the Somali people, and continued to
                    be a significant source of bilateral aid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="bosnia"
                ana="bush-george-h-w clinton-william-j serbia bosnia-and-herzegovina">
                <head>The War in Bosnia, 1992–1995</head>
                <p>In 1991 and 1992, Yugoslavia disintegrated under the pressures of ethnic
                    conflict, economic issues, and the demagoguery of Serbian President Slobodan
                    Milosevic. The secessions of Slovenia and Croatia triggered warfare in both new
                    nations, with the United Nations inserting a peacekeeping force, the U.N.
                    Protective Force (UNPROFOR), in mid-1992 to stabilize the situation. The U.N.
                    further imposed an arms embargo on the region, seeking to dry up the flow of
                    arms to the combatants. Serbian forces executed widespread “ethnic cleansing” in
                    occupied areas, creating horrific scenes of refugees and concentration camps
                    that seemed unthinkable in modern Europe.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="balkan-wars.jpg" height="450px" width="525px"/>
                    <head>Bosnia and Herzegovina. (Central Intelligence Agency)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Bosnia’s declaration of independence from Yugoslavia in 1992 raised the violence
                    to a new level, triggering a war that lasted over three years and exemplified
                    the complexities of the “post-Cold War” strategic environment. The population of
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina was comprised of three ethnic groups: Serbian, Croatian, and
                    Muslim. Initially, Croats and Serbs expanded their territorial control at the
                    expense of the Bosnian state, with the Serbs, supported by Serbia and the
                    Yugoslav National Army (JNA), eventually controlling about 70% of
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina. Shifts in territorial control were accompanied by widespread
                    ethnic cleansing.</p>
                <p>While the situation in Yugoslavia was a constant subject of discussion at the
                    highest levels of the Bush Administration, President George H. W. Bush and his
                    advisors considered the situation in the Balkans to be primarily a European
                    issue, to be addressed by the European Union. The lack of U.S. response became
                    an issue in the 1992 presidential campaign, as candidate Bill Clinton advocated
                    a “lift and strike” policy—lifting the arms embargo, which was operating at the
                    disadvantage of the Bosnian Muslims and Croats, and conducting airstrikes
                    against Bosnian Serb forces.</p>
                <p>Following Clinton’s electoral victory, the new administration set to work quickly
                    with Ambassador to the United Nations Madeleine Albright to shape a more active
                    U.N. role in the conflict. In early January 1993, during the final days of the
                    Bush Administration, the United Nations and the European Union had agreed upon
                    the Vance-Owen Peace Plan (VOPP) for Bosnia. A month later, the U.N. Security
                    Council established a war crimes tribunal for the former Yugoslavia and the
                    United States initiated night airdrops of food to the Muslim enclaves. By March
                    the U.N. authorized enforcement of a no-fly zone in Bosnia, implemented by the
                    United States Air Force in Operation Deny Flight, the first armed engagement of
                    U.S. forces in the former Yugoslavia. Following the Bosnian Serbs’ rejection of
                    VOPP, the U.N. declared the Muslim enclaves of Sarajevo, Bihac, Tusla,
                    Srebrenica, Zepa, and Gorazde to be “safe areas.” The Security Council did not,
                    however, provide for the defense of these areas.</p>
                <p>On May 1 President Clinton sent Secretary of State Warren Christopher to consult
                    with the major NATO allies and with Russia in order to gain support for the
                    “lift and strike” strategy. This effort failed, exposing issues that would
                    hamstring NATO’s actions in the conflict for another two years. Alliance members
                    participating in UNPROFOR were concerned that their troops, lightly armed and
                    widely dispersed, were likely to be taken as hostages and did not share
                    Washington’s enthusiasm for an air campaign. Wide divergence between the
                    alliance’s national perspectives on the conflict and very little European
                    domestic support for armed intervention added to the Administration’s problems.
                    NATO’s inability to reach consensus on an effective response to the atrocities
                    called into question the future of the alliance in post-Cold War Europe.</p>
                <p>Gridlock in the alliance was mirrored by gridlock in the U.S. interagency policy
                    process. The Department of Defense was very reluctant to commit to a role in the
                    Balkans, concerned as it was about a protracted occupation or guerrilla warfare.
                    Ambassador Albright was active in promoting a western response but she had
                    little influence on the overall administration policy. There was also little
                    domestic support in the United States for intervention in the Balkans, though
                    the violence, documented by cable television news, kept the issue in the public
                    eye.</p>
                <p>In June 1993, Serb attacks on the Srebrenica “safe area” led the U.N. Security
                    Council to authorize the use of air power “to support UNPROFOR in the
                    performance of its mandate.” The resolution established a “dual key” arrangement
                    between the U.N. and NATO in control of tactical air power responding to Serbian
                    attacks. This arrangement proved difficult for Washington, as the U.N. was
                    extremely reluctant to authorize any effective combat action on the part of
                    NATO.</p>
                <p>On February 5, 1994, a mortar shell exploded in the Markala marketplace in
                    Sarajevo, killing 69 civilians. The attack led to the declaration of a
                    20-kilometer weapons exclusion zone around Sarajevo. A confrontation with the
                    Bosnian Serb forces was averted through Russian mediation.</p>
                <p>In early April, Bosnian Serb forces launched an offensive against Gorazde.
                    Following the killing of a UNPROFOR soldier by Serbian artillery, NATO launched
                    an air strike. In turn, Bosnian Serbs surrounded a contingent of UNPROFOR
                    soldiers, and their commander, Ratko Mladic, threatened that none would survive
                    if NATO repeated the air attacks. In the immediate aftermath, the United States
                    led the formation of a Contact Group to spearhead policy toward the conflict.
                    The group agreed on a set of principles for any peace settlement: Bosnia would
                    remain a single state, comprised of the Muslim-Croat federation and a Serb
                    entity, and these entities would be linked by constitutionally-agreed
                    principles. The group further agreed to a map of Bosnia-Herzegovina where the
                    Muslim-Croat federation controlled 51 percent of the territory and the Serbian
                    entity controlled 49 percent. While the Bosnian Croats and Muslim groups signed
                    a cease fire between their forces under the terms of the 1994 Washington
                    Agreement, the Bosnian Serbs rejected the plan. The military balance also began
                    to equalize, as Serbia cut off support to Bosnian-Serb forces while Croatia and
                    Bosnian-Muslim forces built up via an increasingly porous arms embargo. The year
                    closed with a four-month truce negotiated by former President Jimmy Carter.</p>
                <p>The spring of 1995 brought renewed combat, with Muslim and Croatian forces now on
                    the offensive in western Bosnia-Herzegovina. Without logistical support from
                    Serbia, Bosnian Serb forces retook U.N.-secured weapons, brushing aside UNPROFOR
                    guards. When NATO responded with air strikes, the Serbs took UNPROFOR troops
                    hostage, using them as human shields. NATO deployed a combat-ready Rapid
                    Reaction Force to Bosnia to reduce the vulnerability of the widely scattered
                    UNPROFOR units.</p>
                <p>In July, the Bosnian Serb commanders launched an offensive against the eastern
                    enclaves of Srebrenica and Zepa; they massacred over 7,000 men in Srebrenica.
                    The mass killing served as a tipping point to western resolve to bring a
                    decisive end to the conflict. Convening in London on July 21, NATO agreed on the
                    effective end of the “dual key” policy for controlling air strikes, with
                    authority for strikes delegated to UNPROFOR and NATO commanders in the field.
                    The alliance further agreed that any future attacks on safe areas would result
                    in a sustained air offensive.</p>
                <p>On August 1, Croatian and Bosnian forces launched a powerful offensive, Operation
                    Storm, against Bosnian Serb-held territory in western Bosnia. The offensive
                    rolled eastward, displacing many thousands of Serb refugees and steadily moving
                    the territorial balance toward the 51/49 balance called for by the Contact
                    Group. The new Assistant Secretary of State for Western Europe, Richard
                    Holbrooke, had seized a major role in policy toward the Balkans, and sought to
                    orchestrate a cease-fire and negotiated settlement. When a mortar shell exploded
                    in the Markala marketplace in Sarajevo on August 25, NATO executed Operation
                    Deliberate Force, an intense two-week series of attacks on Serb military
                    positions.</p>
                <p>The combination of the ground offensive, NATO’s air campaign, and Holbrooke’s
                    tireless diplomacy yielded a cease-fire by the end of September. On November 1,
                    negotiations among the three parties opened at Dayton AFB, OH. The parties
                    reached a hard-fought agreement on November 21 and the Dayton Accords, formally
                    the General Framework Agreement for Peace in Bosnia and Herzegovina, were signed
                    in Paris on December 14. The NATO-led Implementation Force (IFOR) deployed into
                    Bosnia-Herzegovina on December 20.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="clinton-yeltsin"
                ana="clinton-william-j russia arms-control-and-disarmament">
                <head>Bill Clinton, Boris Yeltsin, and U.S.-Russian Relations</head>
                <p>Upon his inauguration in January 1993, President <persName>Bill
                        Clinton</persName> became the first president since Franklin Roosevelt who
                    did not need a strategy for the Cold War—and the first since William Howard Taft
                    who did not need a policy for the Soviet Union. In his inaugural address,
                    Clinton saluted the service of his predecessor, <persName>George H.W.
                        Bush</persName>, in the peaceful resolution of the conflict between the
                    superpowers. He also acknowledged that, even without the Soviet Union, the world
                    was still threatened by “ancient hatreds and new plagues.” Planning to focus on
                    domestic affairs, Clinton intended to leave the day-to-day management of foreign
                    policy—including dealing with the “ancient hatreds and new plagues” of the
                    former Soviet sphere of influence—to senior members of his national security
                    team. He also recruited <persName>Strobe Talbott</persName>, a journalist and
                    Russian expert, to assume a portfolio for the region, first as
                    Ambassador-at-Large and then, from February 1994, as Deputy Secretary of State.
                    By appointing Talbott, a close friend since both had served as Rhodes scholars
                    in the late 1960s, Clinton wanted to demonstrate his personal commitment to
                    Russia in the emerging post-Cold War world. Such calculations were soon
                    overtaken by events, however, as the challenges of managing relations between
                    two former adversaries proved too much for his subordinates to handle on their
                    own. “By the spring of his first year in office,” Talbott later recalled,
                    “Clinton had become the U.S. government’s principal Russia hand, and so he
                    remained for the duration of his presidency.”</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="clinton-russia.jpg" height="400px" width="266px"/>
                    <head>Presidents Yeltsin and Clinton, October 23, 1995, during the summit
                        meeting at Hyde Park, New York. (William J. Clinton Presidential
                        Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Like many of his predecessors, Bill Clinton tended to view relations with other
                    countries through the prism of personality. In this case, Russia was personified
                    by its President, <persName>Boris Yeltsin</persName>. Clinton was strongly
                    inclined not only to like Yeltsin but also to support his policies, in
                    particular, his commitment to Russian democracy. During the seven years both
                    were in office, “Bill and Boris” met eighteen times, nearly as often as their
                    predecessors had met throughout the entire Cold War. For his first trip abroad,
                    Clinton met Yeltsin in Vancouver in April 1993. At the time, and periodically
                    throughout his term in office, Yeltsin faced growing opposition at home to his
                    efforts to liberalize the economy and enact democratic reforms in Russia. At
                    Vancouver, Clinton promised Yeltsin strong support in the form of financial
                    assistance to promote various programs, including funds to stabilize the
                    economy, to house decommissioned military officers, and to employ nuclear
                    scientists. The U.S. Congress—including broad, bipartisan majority in the
                    Senate—approved the program in September. Although not always able to deliver
                    such assistance, Clinton also supported Yeltsin and his position on economic and
                    political matters by other means. At Clinton’s behest, and at a meeting he
                    hosted in Denver in June 1997, for instance, Russia became a member of the
                    so-called G–8, the group of leaders representing eight of the world’s leading
                    economies, thus ensuring that Russian interests would be considered at this
                    important annual forum.</p>
                <p>Clinton and Yeltsin also continued the bilateral cooperation, begun by Ronald
                    Reagan and Mikhail Gorbachev, to manage the most tangible, and terrifying,
                    relics of the Cold War. The control of nuclear weapons had always been one of
                    the most difficult issues for the two superpowers to negotiate. The task in the
                    1990s, however, was greatly complicated by the fact that Russia did not maintain
                    control over the entire Soviet inventory; some strategic (long-range) and
                    theater (intermediate range) nuclear weapons were also still based on the
                    territory of at least Ukraine, Belarus, and Kazakhstan. In terms of
                    international law, and as a matter of foreign policy, the United States urged
                    the four former Soviet republics to assume Soviet obligations under three arms
                    control agreements: the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty (NPT) of 1968, the
                    Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty (INF) of 1987, and the Strategic Arms
                    Reduction Talks Treaty of 1991 (START I). Under the Lisbon Protocol of May 1992,
                    Russia, Ukraine, Belarus, and Kazakhstan agreed not only to abide by the NPT and
                    START I, but also to destroy or transfer to Russia all remaining nuclear weapons
                    at their disposal. The Clinton administration soon discovered, however, that
                    political concerns in Kiev and Almaty—in particular, fears of political
                    interference from Moscow—impeded further progress not only in negotiating
                    additional but also in implementing existing agreements. Clinton and Yeltsin
                    managed to address such concerns through a combination of security assurances
                    and economic assistance. In November 1994, Russia, Ukraine, Belarus, and
                    Kazakhstan finally agreed to adhere to INF; then, the following month, the four
                    countries formally ratified START I. After nearly two years of negotiations, the
                    United States thus succeeded in transferring Soviet treaty obligations to reduce
                    or eliminate nuclear weapons to post-Soviet successor states, who, in turn,
                    agreed to transfer the weapons to Russia. Under the Cooperative Threat Reduction
                    program, established by the Nunn-Lugar Act of 1991, the United States—in an
                    unprecedented partnership with the four countries—also became directly involved
                    in the “dirty work” of fulfilling these commitments, providing financial
                    assistance and technical expertise in securing and dismantling the Soviet
                    nuclear arsenal.</p>
                <p>Throughout the Clinton administration, U.S.-Russian relations were embroiled over
                    how to address the challenges of European security. During the Cold War, the two
                    sides organized on opposite sides of the Iron Curtain: in 1949, the United
                    States and its Western European allies established the North Atlantic Treaty
                    Organization (NATO); and in 1955, the Soviet Union and its Eastern European
                    allies established the Warsaw Treaty Organization. When the Warsaw Pact formally
                    disbanded in February 1991, NATO began to debate in earnest how to adapt the
                    alliance to the realities of post-Cold War Europe, including a proposal to
                    expand membership to include countries in the former Soviet sphere of influence.
                    The debate became more urgent with the outbreak of war in the former Yugoslavia,
                    in particular, Bosnia-Herzegovina in April 1992. In an effort to address
                    concerns in Warsaw, Prague, and other capitals—without at the same time unduly
                    raising concerns in Moscow—NATO formally agreed in January 1994 to establish the
                    Partnership for Peace, which in effect created a pathway toward membership for
                    nations joining the organization, without extending the security commitment of
                    the alliance. Russia joined the Partnership in June 1994. Despite this agreement
                    on paper, events on the ground increasingly threatened to undermine bilateral
                    relations. Clinton objected to Russian military intervention in the autonomous
                    region of Chechnya, including the siege of Grozny, which began in January 1995;
                    and Yeltsin objected to U.S. military intervention in Bosnia, including NATO
                    airstrikes in September. The Dayton Agreement, which ended the Bosnian War in
                    December, and the Khasavyurt Accord, which ended the First Chechen War in August
                    1996, did not resolve growing tensions between the two countries. At its meeting
                    in Madrid, July 1997, NATO formally invited three former Soviet
                    satellites—Poland, Hungary, and the Czech Republic—to join the alliance; and in
                    March 1999, less than two weeks after their membership became effective, NATO
                    began to bomb Serbia, Russia’s ally, in an effort to end its military operations
                    in Kosovo. Yeltsin denounced but could not deflect either development. Likewise,
                    Clinton could do little but protest five months later as Russia began a massive
                    bombing campaign in the Second Chechen War. When Yeltsin suddenly resigned from
                    office in December, however, Clinton praised his counterpart for helping to
                    achieve “genuine progress” in U.S.-Russian relations. “Of course, we have also
                    had our differences,” Clinton observed, “but the starting point for our
                    relationship has always been how Russia and America can work together to advance
                    our common interests.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="two-koreas"
                ana="china japan north-korea south-korea russia nuclear-nonproliferation foreign-aid international-atomic-energy-agency united-nations">
                <head>Denuclearization and the Two Koreas, 1993–2001</head>
                <p>The end of the Cold War altered the Korean Peninsula’s diplomatic landscape. The
                    Republic of Korea (South Korea) established diplomatic relations with the
                    longstanding allies of the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (North Korea):
                    the Soviet Union, in 1990, and China, in 1992. In 1991 both Koreas were
                    simultaneously admitted into the U.N. These developments, together with North
                    Korea’s worsening economy and growing need for international aid, opened up the
                    possibility of a thaw in relations, with negotiations over reunification between
                    the two Koreas and normalization of U.S.-North Korean relations.
                    Denuclearization, a key aim of U.S. diplomacy, was at the heart of a series of
                    crises on the Korean Peninsula throughout the Clinton Administration. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="korean-crisis.jpg" height="450px" width="295px"/>
                    <head>Madeleine Albright toasts North Korean leader Kim Jong Il at a dinner in
                        Pyongyang. (AP Photo/Chien-min Chung, Pool)</head>
                </figure>
                <p>There were signs of hope in early steps toward denuclearization. In January 1992,
                    North Korea publicly committed to signing the nuclear safeguards agreement with
                    the U.N.’s International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) and to permitting
                    inspections of its primary nuclear facility at Yongbyon. In April of the same
                    year, the North and South signed the Joint Declaration of the Denuclearization
                    of the Korean Peninsula, which barred the parties from developing or acquiring
                    nuclear weapons and limited them to using nuclear energy for peaceful purposes
                    only.</p>
                <p>However, North Korea’s refusal throughout 1992 and 1993 to cease and disclose its
                    nuclear activities at Yongbyon, in defiance of IAEA agreements and directives,
                    and its threat to withdraw from the Nuclear Non-Proliferation Treaty, initiated
                    a series of crises. With the credibility of this Treaty in question and its
                    forthcoming renewal thrown into question, the United States threatened to call
                    upon the U.N. Security Council to issue an ultimatum threatening North Korea
                    with economic sanctions. Tensions subsided by June 1993, when the United States
                    and North Korea issued a joint statement affirming the principle of respect for
                    each other’s sovereignty and noninterference in each other’s internal
                    affairs.</p>
                <p>The parties returned to negotiations, but these, too, faltered as North Korea
                    resisted IAEA inspections. By March 1994, North Korean diplomats threatened war
                    if the United States and South Korea went to the U.N. In May North Korea
                    withdrew from the IAEA. A last-minute private trip to North Korea by President
                    Jimmy Carter in June 1994 averted war and led to U.S.-North Korean bilateral
                    negotiations and the October 1994 Agreed Framework for the denuclearization of
                    North Korea.</p>
                <p>The Agreed Framework was a staged, multilateral agreement involving the two
                    Koreas, the United States, and Japan. It required Pyongyang to halt its nuclear
                    activities at Yongbyon, allow IAEA monitors in, and eventually dismantle the
                    facility. In exchange, the United States, Japan, and South Korea would provide
                    light water reactors, and the United States would provide interim energy
                    supplies in the form of fuel-oil. Each stage was to build confidence that the
                    parties were willing to continue.</p>
                <p>In carrying out the agreement, however, numerous setbacks eroded trust among the
                    parties. While the United States followed through on its promises to ship
                    fuel-oil, the U.S. Congress delayed the deliveries. The 1997 IMF Crisis limited
                    the ability of South Korea to contribute to the construction of the light water
                    reactors, leading to delays. Meanwhile, North Korea engaged in provocative acts
                    against South Korea and Japan, testing ballistic missiles and pursuing other
                    weapons activities. In 1998, suspected nuclear weapons activities at Kumchang-ri
                    brought the Agreed Framework to the brink of collapse. Once inspectors were
                    finally allowed in, they found no evidence of nuclear activity, but mistrust
                    remained high. The Clinton administration worked to get the Agreed Framework
                    back on track, leading to the visit of a North Korean envoy to the United
                    States, a joint statement of no hostile intent, and a reciprocal visit by
                    Secretary of State Madeleine Albright to Pyongyang in October 2000.</p>
                <p>However, despite these efforts, the nuclear issue was still unresolved. It was
                    not long before the next crisis would arise, requiring the international
                    community to take another approach to addressing the denuclearization issue.
                    North Korea broke out of the 1994 agreement in the winter of 2002, resulting in
                    the opening of the Six-Party Talks the following year, hosted by China.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="oslo"
                ana="clinton-william-j israel jordan syria palestine peace arab-israeli-dispute">
                <head>The Oslo Accords and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process</head>
                <p>On September 13, 1993, Israeli Prime Minister <persName>Yitzhak Rabin</persName>
                    and Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) Negotiator <persName>Mahmoud
                        Abbas</persName> signed a Declaration of Principles on Interim
                    Self-Government Arrangements, commonly referred to as the “Oslo Accord,” at the
                    White House. Israel accepted the PLO as the representative of the Palestinians,
                    and the PLO renounced terrorism and recognized Israel’s right to exist in peace.
                    Both sides agreed that a Palestinian Authority (PA) would be established and
                    assume governing responsibilities in the West Bank and Gaza Strip over a
                    five-year period. Then, permanent status talks on the issues of borders,
                    refugees, and Jerusalem would be held. While President <persName>Bill
                        Clinton’s</persName> administration played a limited role in bringing the
                    Oslo Accord into being, it would invest vast amounts of time and resources in
                    order to help Israel and the Palestinians implement the agreement. By the time
                    Clinton left office, however, the peace process had run aground, and a new round
                    of Israeli-Palestinian violence had begun. </p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="oslo.jpg" height="400px" width="265px"/>
                    <head>President Clinton, Yitzhak Rabin, and Yasir Arafat at the signing ceremony
                        for the Oslo Accord, September 13, 1993. (William J. Clinton Presidential
                        Library)</head>
                </figure>
                <p><hi rend="strong">The Clinton Administration and the Arab-Israeli Peace Process,
                        1993–1996</hi></p>
                <p>The Clinton administration did not initially make Israeli-Palestinian peace a
                    priority. Clinton and his advisors believed that a diplomatic breakthrough on
                    the Israeli-Syrian track would be more likely, and that Israel’s leaders would
                    find it politically easier to pull back from the Golan Heights than to withdraw
                    from the West Bank. An Israeli-Syrian agreement, they reasoned, would also lead
                    to an Israeli-Lebanese agreement, and help isolate Iraq and Iran, the principal
                    regional opponents of the peace process. U.S. officials were briefed on secret
                    negotiations that the Israelis and Palestinians had begun in Oslo in December
                    1992, but made little effort to get involved in them.</p>
                <p>The United States did not play a major role in the negotiations that led to the
                    Israeli-Jordanian peace treaty of October 1994, though Clinton lent his support
                    by hosting King Hussein and Rabin in Washington and urging Congress to forgive
                    Jordan’s debts. Nor did the United States play a critical part in the
                    negotiations leading up to the May 1994 Cairo Agreement, which finalized
                    Israel’s withdrawal from most of Gaza and Jericho, or the Taba (or "Oslo II")
                    Agreement of September 1995. The latter agreement divided the West Bank into
                    separate areas under Israeli control, Palestinian control, and Israeli military
                    responsibility with Palestinian civil administration, respectively. Oslo II aslo
                    spelled out provisions for elections, civil/legal affairs, and other bilateral
                    Israeli-Palestinian cooperation on various issues. Since the Oslo Accord did not
                    give the United States monitoring responsibilities, the Clinton administration
                    found itself largely confined to defusing crises and building up the Palestinian
                    Authority with economic aid and security assistance.</p>
                <p>On the Israeli-Syrian track, the administration exerted itself more forcefully,
                    but with few results. Clinton, Secretary of State <persName>Warren
                        Christopher</persName>, and Special Middle East Coordinator <persName>Dennis
                        Ross</persName> tried to build on Rabin’s August 1993 promise to withdraw
                    fully from the Golan if Syria agreed to full peace and necessary security
                    arrangements. By 1994, these talks stalled over Israel and Syria’s different
                    definitions of “full withdrawal.” The Syrians insisted that the Israelis should
                    withdraw to the line of “June 4, 1967,” when they had controlled a pocket of
                    land on the northeastern shore of the Sea of Galilee, Israel’s principal source
                    of water. The Israelis wanted to pull back to the 1923 international border,
                    which would have left the Sea of Galilee under their sovereignty. That July,
                    Rabin indicated to Christopher that Israel would withdraw to the June 4 line if
                    Syria met its other needs, paving the way for talks between Israeli and Syrian
                    military officers. However, these negotiations eventually bogged down over
                    whether Israel could retain early warning stations on the Golan, and also became
                    politically controversial in Israel. Rabin thus chose to suspend them until
                    after Israel’s elections in 1996.</p>
                <p><hi rend="strong">Oslo’s Collapse, 1996–2000</hi></p>
                <p>In November 1995, Rabin was assassinated by <persName>Yigal Amir</persName>, an
                    Israeli who opposed the Oslo Accords on religious grounds. Rabin’s murder was
                    followed by a string of terrorist attacks by Hamas, which undermined support for
                    the Labor Party in Israel’s May 1996 elections. New Prime Minister
                        <persName>Binyamin Netanyahu</persName> hailed from the Likud Party, which
                    had historically opposed Palestinian statehood and withdrawal from the occupied
                    territories.</p>
                <p>Worried that the peace process might collapse, the Clinton administration
                    involved itself more actively in Israeli-Palestinian negotiations. In January
                    1997, following intensive U.S. mediation, Israel and the PA signed the Hebron
                    Protocol, which provided for the transfer of most of Hebron to Palestinian
                    control. In October 1998, Clinton hosted Netanyahu and Arafat at the Wye River
                    Plantation, where they negotiated an agreement calling for further Israeli
                    withdrawals from the West Bank. Infighting over the implementation of the Wye
                    Memorandum, however, brought down Netanyahu’s government in January 1999.</p>
                <p>In Israel’s May 1999 elections, the Labor Party’s <persName>Ehud Barak</persName>
                    decisively defeated Netanyahu. Barak predicted that he could reach agreements
                    with both Syria and the Palestinians in 12 to 15 months, and pledged to withdraw
                    Israeli troops from southern Lebanon. In September, Barak signed the Sharm
                    al-Shaykh Memorandum with Arafat, which committed both sides to begin permanent
                    status negotiations. An initial round of meetings, however, achieved nothing,
                    and by December the Palestinians suspended talks over settlement-building in the
                    occupied territories. </p>
                <p>Barak then focused on Syria. In January 2000, Israeli, Syrian, and U.S.
                    delegations convened in West Virginia for peace talks. These negotiations
                    foundered when Barak refused to reaffirm Rabin’s pledge to withdraw to the June
                    4, 1967 line, arguing that none of the concessions offered by the Syrian
                    delegation in return could be considered final, since Syrian President
                        <persName>Hafiz al-Asad</persName> was not present. A subsequent meeting
                    between Clinton and Asad in Geneva failed to produce an Israeli-Syrian
                    accord.</p>
                <p>Barak then withdrew Israeli forces unilaterally from Lebanon and returned to the
                    Palestinian track. At the prime minister’s insistence, Clinton convened a summit
                    at Camp David in July 2000, where he, Barak, and Arafat attempted to reach a
                    final agreement on the West Bank and the Gaza Strip. Accounts differ as to why
                    Camp David failed, but it is clear that despite additional concessions by Barak,
                    the Israelis and Palestinians remained strongly at odds over borders, Jerusalem,
                    and whether Israel would recognize Palestinian refugees’ “right of return.” The
                    summit ended without a settlement; Clinton would blame Arafat for its
                    failure.</p>
                <p>On September 28, riots erupted following a visit of Likud Party leader Ariel
                    Sharon to the Temple Mount, and soon escalated into a wave of
                    Israeli-Palestinian violence that became known as the al-Aqsa Intifada. In
                    December 2000, Clinton put forward his own proposals for an Israeli-Palestinian
                    agreement. By this point, however, the president was leaving office, Barak faced
                    electoral defeat, and Israeli-Palestinian violence continued unabated.</p>
                <p>Thus, by the end of 2000, the prospect of ending the Arab-Israeli conflict looked
                    more distant than it had eight years earlier. The Clinton administration had
                    helped facilitate Israeli-Jordanian peace and lay the foundations for
                    Palestinian self-rule. More broadly, the negotiations of the 1990s helped
                    Israel, the Palestinians, and Syria break with numerous diplomatic taboos and
                    establish a basis for what a comprehensive Arab-Israeli peace might look like.
                    But a settlement of the Arab-Israeli conflict remained elusive.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" xml:id="haiti"
                ana="clinton-william-j haiti organization-of-american-states">
                <head>Intervention in Haiti, 1994–1995</head>
                <p>On September 30, 1991, a military coup under the leadership of Lieutenant General
                    Raoul Cedras overthrew the government of Jean-Bertrand Aristide, the first
                    popularly elected president in Haitian history. President George H.W. Bush
                    called for the restoration of democracy, and worked with the Organization of
                    American States (OAS) to impose a trade embargo on all goods except medicine and
                    food. During his 1992 presidential candidacy, Bill Clinton criticized the Bush
                    administration for its policy on refugee return and promised to increase
                    pressure on the military junta by tightening economic sanctions.</p>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="haiti.jpg" height="450px" width="372px"/>
                    <head>USS <hi rend="italic">America</hi> enroute to Haiti in September 1994,
                        with a unique complement of U.S. Army Special Forces and the 160th Army
                        Special Aviation Regiment embarked.</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Unburdened by the Cold War international framework that structured U.S. foreign
                    policy for nearly fifty years, the Clinton administration sought to outline new
                    objectives for U.S. foreign policy, including novel uses for military power.
                    Ambassador to the United Nations Madeleine Albright outlined a U.S. policy of
                    “assertive multilateralism,” with an increased role for the United Nations.
                    National Security Advisor Anthony Lake emphasized the role of economic power in
                    the new world order, and argued for a U.S. role in the “enlargement” of the
                    community of free nations. The new administration, however, faced multiple
                    challenges in the former Yugoslavia, Somalia, North Korea, and Haiti that
                    complicated their attempts to implement the broad strategies and objectives
                    defined by the administration’s leaders.</p>
                <p>Clinton appointed Lawrence Pezzullo as special envoy for Haiti, and as promised
                    in his campaign, worked to increase economic and diplomatic pressure on the
                    junta. On June 16 the United Nations voted to impose a ban on petroleum sales to
                    Haiti. Cedras agreed to participate in talks sponsored by the United Nations and
                    the OAS. The so-called “Governors Island Accord” signed by Aristide and Cedras
                    on July 3 called for Aristide’s return to Haiti by October 30, 1993, an amnesty
                    for the coup leaders, assistance in modernizing the Haitian Army, and the
                    establishment of a new Haitian police force. The agreement provided for the
                    suspension of U.N. sanctions once Aristide had assumed office in Haiti.</p>
                <p>Despite indications that the Haitian military was backing away from the
                    agreement, the United States dispatched the USS <hi rend="italic">Harlan
                        County</hi> with 200 U.S. and Canadian engineers and military police on
                    board to prepare for the return of Aristide. On October 11 the ship was met at
                    the pier in Port-au-Prince by a mob of Haitians, appearing to threaten violence.
                    With the street battle in Mogadishu only a week past, the administration proved
                    unwilling to risk casualties in Port-au-Prince. The ship pulled away the
                    following day and returned to the United States, a significant setback for the
                    Clinton administration.</p>
                <p>Four days later, the United Nations Security Council imposed a naval blockade on
                    Haiti. Through the following months the administration pursued a dual strategy,
                    planning for military intervention while hoping that the threat of a U.S.
                    invasion would coerce the Haitian leaders to surrender power. Pressure toward
                    action continued to build, with Congressional Black Caucus members especially
                    vocal in demanding an end to military rule in Haiti.</p>
                <p>The Clinton administration built the diplomatic foundation for the operation in
                    the summer of 1994, working to secure a United Nations Security Council
                    Resolution (UNSCR) authorizing the removal of the Haitian military regime. On
                    July 31 the Security Council passed UNSCR 940, the first resolution authorizing
                    the use of force to restore democracy for a member nation. It provided for the
                    reinstatement of the Aristide government and a six-month mandate for the United
                    Nations Mission in Haiti (UNMIH), which would maintain order after the
                    operation. The U.N. mandate authorizing the intervention enabled the
                    administration to recruit forces from Caribbean nations to serve in the
                    post-invasion security force.</p>
                <p>In early September planning and preparation for the invasion was completed under
                    the code name Operation Uphold Democracy. The invasion force numbered nearly
                    25,000 military personnel from all services, backed by two aircraft carriers and
                    extensive air support. Although the United States provided the vast majority of
                    the forces, a multinational contingent from Caribbean nations agreed to serve in
                    an operation conducted under U.N. mandate. The addition of these multinational
                    forces shifted the operation from a U.S. military intervention to
                    U.N.-sanctioned multinational action. The operation was scheduled for September
                    19.</p>
                <p>With military action clearly imminent, former President Jimmy Carter led a
                    delegation to Haiti in search of a negotiated settlement. Carter, Senator Sam
                    Nunn, and General Colin Powell flew to Haiti on September 17, well aware that
                    they had little time to reach agreement. President Clinton approved Carter’s
                    mission, but insisted that the military operation would proceed as scheduled.
                    The invasion forces launched with the negotiations in progress, without any
                    certainty whether they would make an opposed or a peaceful entry on to Haitian
                    soil.</p>
                <p>The Haitian leadership capitulated in time to avoid bloodshed. Having launched
                    the operation with the expectation of a forced-entry assault, the forces
                    conducting the operation displayed remarkable discipline and flexibility in
                    adjusting to this new and uncertain environment. General Hugh Shelton, commander
                    of the invasion force, was transformed enroute to Haiti from commander to
                    diplomat, charged with working out a peaceful transition of power. Shelton and
                    Cedras met on September 20, 1994, to begin the process, and Aristide returned to
                    Haiti on October 15. </p>
                <p>Military planners had defined the conditions for hand-off to UNMIH as the
                    restoration of basic order, the return of Aristide, and the conduction of a
                    presidential election and subsequent peaceful transfer of power. The operation
                    ended with the transfer to UNMIH command on March 31, 1995, and a peaceful
                    election and transferal of power occurred on February 7, 1996. The operation
                    yielded important lessons about the complexities involved in managing complex
                    contingency operations, which were captured in PDD/NSC 56, “Managing Complex
                    Contingency Operations,” issued in May 1997.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
